一个叫安德鲁奇奥的佩鲁贾人在那不勒斯的历险故事[1]

据说，在佩鲁贾有位名叫安德鲁奇奥·迪·皮耶特罗的小伙子，靠贩卖马匹为生。听说那不勒斯的马卖得非常实惠，他便带了五百枚佛罗林金币[2]，与其他商贩一起奔赴那不勒斯了。这是他第一次离开家。周日晚上，将近晚祷的时候，安德鲁奇奥到达了目的地。他从旅馆老板那里打听到，第二天早晨就会有一个马市。马市上果真有许多马匹，安德鲁奇奥也看中了好几匹，就上前去跟商贩们讨价还价。为了让对方知道自己能买得起这些马，他就像那些土里土气的乡下人一样，每当有人经过，就把金币从包里掏出来显摆一下。但最终价格并没有谈好，所以他连一匹马都没有买到。

在商量价钱时，他的钱袋子吸引了旁边一位西西里女人的注意。虽然她长得漂亮，但是非常轻浮，为了几个小钱就能把自己随随便便交付给一个男人。趁安德鲁奇奥不注意，她偷偷地靠近了这个小伙子，偷瞄了一眼他的钱袋，心想：“要是我有了这些钱，谁还能比得上我呢？”然后，她就悄悄走开了。有一位老妇陪伴在这个女人的身边，她也是西西里人。当看到安德鲁奇奥后，老妇立刻激动地跑过去拥抱这位同乡，完全没有注意到女主人的离开，原来他们早就相识。安德鲁奇奥转脸看到老妇，热情地和她打了招呼，还邀请她有空去自己下榻的旅馆做客。两人没说几句话就各忙各的去了，但是那个女人却躲在一旁，偷听了这两位同乡的对话。

安德鲁奇奥继续逛马市，但始终没有买到马。那女人见他带了那么多钱，又看到他跟自己手下的老妇如此熟络，就仔仔细细地询问老妇关于安德鲁奇奥的情况：他是谁，从哪里来，到这里做什么，他们是如何认识的，一五一十地统统问了个遍，以便设计陷阱把他的钱弄到手。能把他所有的钱都弄到手自然是好，如果不行，能拿到一部分也是不错的。老妇一五一十地回答了主人的问题，事无巨细，就像是安德鲁奇奥本人在回答似的。老妇之所以如此了解安德鲁奇奥，是因为早年在西西里的时候，她曾在他父亲的手下干活，后来又跟他们一起去了佩鲁贾。她还把安德鲁奇奥住的地方以及他来那不勒斯的原因一并告诉了主人。

那女人掌握了安德鲁奇奥所有的信息，连他家人的名字都一清二楚。如此一来，她就能对安德鲁奇奥行骗，满足自己的贪心了。回家以后，她给老妇安排了很多工作，让她忙得一整天都出不了门，根本没办法找安德鲁奇奥叙旧，她又派手下一名深谙此道的女佣，在晚祷时去安德鲁奇奥住的旅馆找他。

女佣在旅馆门口看到一名男子，便上前打听安德鲁奇奥的情况。碰巧的是，这名男子正是安德鲁奇奥。女佣把他拉到一旁，对他说：“先生，有位美丽的姑娘想见您一面，不知您何时方便。”安德鲁奇奥听了以后，上上下下打量了自己一番，觉得自己的确是个美男子，也许整个那不勒斯再也找不到一位如此英俊的小伙子了。他认为那位姑娘肯定是爱上他了。想到这里，他立刻跟女佣说自己随时都可以过去，便问她那姑娘想什么时候和他交谈。

女佣回答道：“先生，无论您何时过去，她都会在家恭候您。”

安德鲁奇奥一听这话，没有和旅馆打声招呼就对女佣说：“你在前面带路，我现在就跟你去见她。”

那女人家门前的道路叫“魔窟街”，一看这个名字，就知道这条街上的居民有多么“善良”了。但是安德鲁奇奥并不知道真相，也没有半点疑虑。他相信，在这片美好的土地上，他要找的那位姑娘一定天真而纯良。于是他跟着女佣走进了姑娘家。上楼时，女佣对女主人说：“安德鲁奇奥来啦！”安德鲁奇奥也看到了那位在楼梯口等他的姑娘。

她正值青春，身材修长，面容姣好，穿着优雅而得体。看到安德鲁奇奥来了，女人连忙下楼迎接。她张开双臂，紧抱住他的脖子，欲言又止，激动得说不出话来。随后，她潸然泪下，亲吻了他的额头，用近乎沙哑的声音对他说：“我的安德鲁奇奥啊！你知道我有多想见到你吗？！”

安德鲁奇奥没有料到会受到如此热烈的欢迎，一时惊讶不已，只好顺着姑娘的话回应道：“天哪！我也很想见到您！”

于是姑娘走到他身旁，牵起他的手，一句话也没有说，就带他走进了自己的闺房。她的房间里洋溢着玫瑰、橘子花和各种香料散发出的芬芳气息，闺床装饰华丽，床架上挂着许多华美的服装，还有很多精致的摆设。安德鲁奇奥还是第一次看到这些东西，这使他更加相信面前这个女人一定是位出身高贵的小姐。

女人请他坐在床边的一个箱子上，开口说道：“安德鲁奇奥，我知道我的热情和激动肯定吓着你了，毕竟你我从未见过面，你也没有听说过我这个人。但听完我接下来给你讲的这件事，你一定会更加惊讶——我可是你的亲姐姐啊！谢天谢地，让我在死前还能亲眼看到我的弟弟！我是多么想见一见我的亲弟弟啊！不然我死也不会瞑目！你好像不知道这回事，那就让我来告诉你吧。我们的父亲皮耶罗曾在巴勒莫住过很长一段时间，我相信你肯定知道这事吧。他和蔼善良，所以周围的人都十分爱戴他，直到今天也都很惦念他，其中最爱他的那个人就是我的母亲。我的母亲出身高贵，但当时正在守寡。她不顾父兄的威胁恐吓，放弃了自己的尊荣，选择与我们的父亲在一起。后来，我，也就是你面前的这个人，就出生了。再后来，由于突发情况，父亲离开了巴勒莫，去了佩鲁贾。当时我还只是个小女孩，他就抛弃了我们母女二人。我总觉得，他走后就把我们忘得一干二净了！如果他不是我的生身父亲，那我眼看着他如此对待我母亲，一定会怪他冷酷无情！怎奈是他生了我！抛开他辜负了我母亲的一片真情不说，我好歹也是他的女儿啊！更何况我母亲既不是有损他颜面的无知少女，也不是放荡轻浮的风尘女子。她对父亲一片痴心，但却没有看清他的本来面目，就把自己的一切都托付给他了。可是这换回了什么呢？往事说起来容易，但却很难挽回，何况事情已经这样了。他在巴勒莫抛弃我们时，我年龄还小，后来我慢慢长成了现在的模样。我的母亲毕竟是贵族出身，所以把我嫁给了杰尔真蒂[3]那边一位家境富裕的绅士。他深爱着我，也敬重我的母亲，所以搬到了巴勒莫与我们同住。他坚决拥护教皇派[4]，所以和西西里的查理国王交往甚密。但腓特烈国王察觉了这一切，于是我们只好逃离西西里。那时，我马上就要被封为女骑士了，这种事在西西里岛上还是头一遭。于是我们带着不多的行李——即便‘不多’，其实也不少，只是就那时的家境而言‘不多’罢了，我们离开了那片土地，离开了我们的宫殿，逃到了这里。查理国王感念我们的笃诚，在那不勒斯给了我们田地和房产作为补偿，还一直寄很多钱给我丈夫，也就是你姐夫，这你以后就会看到的。就这样，我在这里住了下来。幸亏天主保佑，而不是拜你所赐，我才又见到了你，我的弟弟。”

说完，她又紧紧地抱住了安德鲁奇奥，亲吻他的额头，眼睛里噙满了泪水。

安德鲁奇奥听完这个故事，觉得一切是那么合情合理，而且这个姑娘在讲故事时也没打一个磕巴。他又想起自己的父亲的确在巴勒莫住过一段时间，那时的父亲和自己现在一样年轻，当然也会贪恋女色。再看看面前姑娘眼含热泪，想想她的拥抱和那些真诚的亲吻，安德鲁奇奥将她说的话信以为真。等她不说话了，安德鲁奇奥开口说道：“您应该料到了我会大吃一惊。我的父亲从未提及过你们母女，或者说他曾经提起过，但我没有听到，所以我并不认识您，也不知道您的存在。然而能在那不勒斯找到姐姐，的确出乎我的意料，让我十分开心。没有哪位男士不想与您亲近，无论他的地位有多高，更何况是我这个小商贩。但是请您告诉我一件事情，您是怎么知道我在这里的呢？”

那女人答道：“是今天早上一个经常来我家的穷老太太告诉我的，也是她说起了我们的父亲。她告诉我，父亲在巴勒莫和佩鲁贾时，自己一直在他家里做事。我听了这些话，早就想去找你了，可是我一个女人去陌生男子的住处有失体统，所以就把你叫到了这里。”

说完这些，她又询问起了家人的近况，还说出了他们的名字。安德鲁奇奥一一作答，并且越发相信她说的话了——尽管他不该相信。

他们就这样聊了很久。女人让下人端来了白葡萄酒和蜜饯，请安德鲁奇奥享用。安德鲁奇奥喝完酒，看着晚饭时间快到了，便起身告辞。姑娘却无论如何也不答应，还装作生气的样子，抱住他说：“哎呀！你走吧！我算是明白了，你根本就没把我当亲人！我怎么也想象不到，你刚刚见到了从未谋面的姐姐，还在她的家里，却要回旅馆吃饭！对，我的丈夫是没在家，我也很遗憾他不能陪你用晚餐，但我知道作为一个女人该如何招待你。”

听了这些话，安德鲁奇奥不知该如何回答，只好说：“我是把您当亲人的，就像您对我一样。但是如果我不回去，旅馆的人要等我一晚上才能吃饭，这未免失礼啊。”

女人这时说：“天哪！难道我就不能派家里的用人去趟旅馆，告诉他们不用等你了吗？既然你这么懂得礼数，那就该把旅馆的朋友叫来一起用晚餐。那样吃完饭后，你还可以和他们一起回去。”

安德鲁奇奥说，今晚不想请朋友来，但他非常愿意留下。于是女人假装派人告诉旅馆老板他不回去吃饭的事，又与他聊了很长时间，才吩咐用人上晚餐。晚餐十分丰盛，女人也故意拖延时间。直到夜幕降临，安德鲁奇奥起身告辞时，她仍旧坚持不让他走，说是因为在那不勒斯晚上不能出门随便走动，尤其是一个外地人。她还说，刚刚让人跟旅馆说他不回去吃饭时，也交代过他不回去过夜了。安德鲁奇奥觉得这些话有道理，而且他很想和姑娘在一起，所以就又被她骗了。他们接着聊了好一阵——这当然也是女人故意而为的。夜深了，她让安德鲁奇奥到自己的卧室睡下，又留下了一个侍童伺候，看他不再需要什么了，便带着侍女们去了另一个房间。

天气十分炎热，安德鲁奇奥看房间里只剩他一个人了，就把裤子、袜子和内衣全部脱掉，放在了床头。过了一会儿，他想去方便，就问侍童厕所在哪里。侍童指着一扇门说：“进去吧，这里就是。”安德鲁奇奥毫无戒备地走进了那扇门，不料踏到了一块架空的木板上，连人带板一起摔了下去。幸亏天主保佑，虽然从很高的地方摔下，但他并没有受伤。只是掉下去的地方满是污秽，所以他浑身散发着恶臭。为了让你们明白我刚刚讲的内容，也为了方便你们理解接下来发生的事，我得在这里啰唆几句。他掉下去的那个地方其实在一个小巷子里，就像我们经常可以看到的那样：人们在对着的两个窗户间搭上两根细细的木棍，然后在木棍上架一块木板，人就坐在木板上方便。安德鲁奇奥就是从这样一块木板上掉下去的。

安德鲁奇奥摔得很疼。他发现自己掉到了小巷子里，就连忙喊侍童。然而侍童一听到他掉下去的声响，就跑到女人那里报信去了。那女人赶紧去他房间，看他的衣服在不在。找到衣服后，从里面翻出了安德鲁奇奥的钱。原来他不放心把钱放到别处，都是随身带着。这位“巴勒莫的贵妇”，这位“佩鲁贾小伙子的姐姐”，拿到钱之后，就再也不管安德鲁奇奥的安危，关上了他方才走出去的那扇门。

安德鲁奇奥看侍童没有回答他，就更大声地喊叫，但已然没有用了。这时他才感觉到有些不对，可是为时已晚。安德鲁奇奥翻过一道矮墙，到了大街上。他认识姑娘的家门，便过去不停地敲打，不停地叫喊，但还是没人理睬他。这时他才知道自己被骗了，哭着说：“哎呀！才这么一小会儿，我就丢了五百个金币和一个姐姐啊！”

哭了一阵子后，他又开始敲门喊人。邻居们受不了他的闹腾，纷纷起身。那家的一个女佣装作被吵醒的样子，朝窗外怒吼：“谁在下面敲门呢？”

“喂！”安德鲁奇奥说，“你不认识我了？我是安德鲁奇奥啊，菲奥尔达莉索夫人的弟弟！”

女佣回答他说：“你这个人！如果你喝多了，就先睡一觉，明早再过来吧！我既不认识安德鲁奇奥，也听不懂你说的话。请你走吧，让我们好生休息，拜托了！”

“怎么会？”安德鲁奇奥说，“难道你不知道我说的是什么吗？你绝对知道！就算你们西西里人对待亲戚都是转脸就忘，但至少让我把留在你们家的衣服拿走吧！我拿了衣服会立刻走人！”

女佣快要笑出声来了，说：“我看你这人是在梦游吧！”边说边缩回身子，关上了窗子。

安德鲁奇奥这才恍然大悟，原来自己被骗了，他气得快要发疯。但现在光靠嘴已经拿不回想要的东西了，于是他拿起一块大石头使劲砸门。他的动静更大了，吵醒了更多的邻居，惹得他们十分反感。邻居们相信他就是个骗子，编这些谎话来骚扰那位善良的夫人。于是他们都到窗边责骂安德鲁奇奥，就像是满街的狗对着一只新来的狗狂吠一样。“你这个时候来人家姑娘家，说这些不三不四的话，实在无礼！”“天哪！你走吧，好孩子，让我们睡觉吧，求你了！”“你要是真有事找她，就明天再来吧，今晚就别烦我们了！”

那位“好姑娘”的家里还住着一个恶棍。不过安德鲁奇奥在她家时既没有看到他，也没有听到他说话。听到邻居们这么说，恶棍放心了，于是走到窗前，粗声粗气地吼道：“是谁在下面？”

安德鲁奇奥听到这吓人的声音，抬起头来，隐隐约约地瞧见这个满脸黑胡子的人，看样子很厉害。只见他伸着懒腰，打着呵欠，像刚从床上爬起来似的。安德鲁奇奥见状，不免有些害怕地回答道：“我是这家女主人的弟弟。”

然而那人没等他说完，就打断了他，语气比之前还要凶：“我不知道我为什么还站在这儿，而不是下去给你一通乱棍，把你打到不能动弹为止。你这个醉鬼，你这个烦人的蠢驴，今天晚上因为你谁都睡不成觉了！”说罢便缩回身子，锁上了窗户。

一些邻居知道这个人的脾气，就低声劝安德鲁奇奥说：“求你了，好孩子，走吧！你不想今晚被他打死吧！走吧，这是为你好。”

安德鲁奇奥害怕那个恶棍，又被邻居们这么一劝，觉得他们也是好心，就离开了。一想到自己再也拿不回那些钱，他非常难过。安德鲁奇奥不知道去哪里，只好沿着女佣带他来时走过的路回旅馆。但是他身上很臭，想去海里洗一洗，就在路口往左拐，走进了一条叫作“卡塔拉纳”的街。他顺着坡往上走，突然看见两个提着灯笼的人向自己走来。安德鲁奇奥担心对方是巡警，也害怕又遇到坏人，于是看旁边有个小破屋，就悄悄地躲了进去。然而那两个人像是提前商量好了似的，径直走进了这间破屋子。其中一个人把背在肩上的铁家伙放了下来，和另一个人一起一一查看。

突然，其中一个人说：“怎么回事？我闻见了一股臭味，之前好像从来没在这儿闻见过。”他说完便举起灯笼，看到了可怜的安德鲁奇奥。这人吓了一跳，问道：“谁在那里？”

安德鲁奇奥没有出声，于是那两个人拿着灯笼走近了他，问他一身脏臭的在这里干什么。安德鲁奇奥就把事情的来龙去脉一五一十地告诉了他们。他们想了一下这件事发生的地方，自言自语地说：“那是布塔福科家，就是那个黑社会的小头目。”

其中一个人对安德鲁奇奥说：“可怜的家伙，虽然你把钱丢了，但你还算是万幸，因为你幸亏摔了下来，没再进那座房子。要是你没有摔下去，他们肯定等你一睡着就把你杀了，那样你连钱带命就都丢了。你现在哭有什么用呢？想拿回一分钱，比从天上摘星星还要难呢。而且，他们要是知道你把这件事说了出去，可能还会来杀你。”

他说完后，两个人商量了一会儿，又对安德鲁奇奥说：“你看，我们很同情你。现在我们正要去做点事情，如果你加入我们，那我们保证你能赚到比你丢掉的那五百个金币更多的钱。”

正走投无路的安德鲁奇奥立刻答应了。

原来那天是那不勒斯大主教菲利波·米努托洛神父下葬的日子。他穿的华服上有许多价值连城的饰品，手上还戴着一枚红宝石戒指。光是那块红宝石就值五百多佛罗林，而那两个人想偷的也正是它。就这样，他们把计划告诉了安德鲁奇奥。

安德鲁奇奥的欲望战胜了理智，便和他们一起上路了。在去往主教堂的路上，安德鲁奇奥仍然一身臭气，于是他们中的一人说道：“我们不能找个地方让他稍微洗洗吗？免得他这么臭。”

另一个人回答说：“对，这附近有一口井，井辘轳上一直挂着个大木桶。我们赶紧去那里让他洗一洗吧。”

到了井边，他们发现绳子还在，但是木桶被人拿走了。于是那两人想着用绳子拴住安德鲁奇奥，让他下井清洗一下，洗好了晃绳子，他们再把他拉上来。就这样，安德鲁奇奥下井了。

他刚下去，就来了几个巡警。因为天气炎热，又刚刚追捕了一个犯人，所以他们口渴难耐，就来井边找水喝。那两个人一看到巡警来了，撒腿就跑，所以巡警并没有看到他们。

安德鲁奇奥在井底洗好后晃了绳子。看到绳子晃了，那两个口渴的巡警以为桶里的水满了，就把手里的木盾、武器和披风放在地上，往上拉绳子。安德鲁奇奥看到井沿后，就抓着井沿跳了上来。巡警看到从井里跳出来了一个人，吓得魂飞魄散，立刻松开了绳子，跑得要多快有多快。安德鲁奇奥自己也大吃了一惊，要不是抓住了井沿，他就可能摔到井底，也就可能受伤乃至丢了性命。他又看到了井边的武器，便更加疑惑了，因为他记得那两个同伴并没有带什么武器。

他心存疑虑，不知道发生了什么事情。于是什么都没碰，离开了那个地方，但又不知道去哪里。就这样走着走着，他突然碰见了之前的两个同伴。原来，他们想回去把安德鲁奇奥拉上来。看到安德鲁奇奥后，同伴们也十分惊讶，连忙问是谁把他拉上来的。安德鲁奇奥说自己也不知道，只把从井里上来的经过告诉了他们。两人相视一笑，明白了怎么回事，向安德鲁奇奥解释了他们为什么逃走，又是谁拉他上来的。这时夜已过半，所以大家就没有再多说什么，直接去主教堂了。他们很顺利地进了教堂，来到了大主教的棺材旁。这口棺材很大，而且是用大理石做的。他们用随身带的铁棍撬起了沉重的棺材盖，然后找东西撑住，留出来够一个人出入的空隙。

做好后，他们其中一人说：“谁进去？”

另一个人回答：“我不去。”

“我也不去，”那个人说，“安德鲁奇奥，你去。”

“我不会去的。”安德鲁奇奥说。

听了这话，那两人对安德鲁奇奥说：“你为什么不去？苍天在上，要是你不进去，我们就用这根铁棍打你的头，直到打死你为止。”

安德鲁奇奥很害怕，只好进去。他一边往里爬一边想：“他们让我进来，无非是想骗我。等到我把东西给了他们，要往外爬时，他们就会自顾自地跑了，而我什么也得不到。”因此他决定先把自己那份弄到手。安德鲁奇奥想起他们之前说的话，就把那枚昂贵的戒指从大主教手上摘了下来，戴在了自己手上。然后他把主教的权杖、僧帽、手套给了那两个人，跟他们说里面什么也没有了。的确，当时的主教身上只剩一件衬衣了。那两个人确定里面有一枚戒指，就让安德鲁奇奥再好好找找。安德鲁奇奥假装努力地找，一直跟他们说没有找到，让他们在外面等。谁知那两个人比安德鲁奇奥还要狡猾，不停地说让他再找找，却趁机拿掉了撑着棺盖的东西，逃了出去，把安德鲁奇奥一个人留在了棺材里。我们应该可以想象出安德鲁奇奥当时的心情吧。

他用头和肩膀顶棺盖，尝试了许多次，但始终没有顶开。一阵绝望袭来，安德鲁奇奥昏倒在了大主教的尸体上。要是有人看见这一幕，一定分不清到底哪个是死人，也分不清谁是大主教，谁是安德鲁奇奥。醒来后，安德鲁奇奥不禁号啕大哭。他预料到，自己只会有两种结局：如果没有人来打开棺材，那他只能在这里面，在一堆蛆虫中饿死，或者被尸体腐烂的臭味熏死；如果有人来开棺，那么他就会被当作盗墓贼绞死。

就在悲痛万分地思考这些事情时，安德鲁奇奥突然听到有很多人边说话边走进了教堂。他认为这些人来这里，也要干那两个人干过的勾当。于是他更害怕了。但是等他们打开了棺盖，撑好之后，也遇到了派谁进去的问题。他们谁都不想进去，吵了很长时间以后，一位神父说：“你们有什么好怕的？觉得他能吃了你们？死人是不会吃人的。来，我进去。”说罢，神父把胸脯抵在棺材沿上，脸向外，将腿伸了进去。安德鲁奇奥一看到他，就马上站了起来，抓住他的一条腿，装作要把他拉下来的样子。神父感到有东西在拽自己，吓得大叫起来，立刻爬出棺材逃走了。其他人看到这番情形也都吓坏了，没把棺材盖合上就撒腿跑了，好像身后有千万个魔鬼在追赶他们一样。

安德鲁奇奥看到这些后喜出望外，赶紧爬了出来，沿着来时的路走出了教堂。天快亮了，安德鲁奇奥戴着那枚历经千难万险才得到的戒指，走到了海边，然后回到了旅馆。旅馆的店主和他的朋友们为他担心了整整一宿。安德鲁奇奥把这一夜发生的事情告诉他们后，店主建议他赶紧离开那不勒斯。于是他立刻出发，回佩鲁贾去了。安德鲁奇奥原本打算拿了五百枚金币买马，结果马没买成，却换来了一枚戒指。

[1] 本书中的四个故事均节选自《十日谈》，故事标题为英文译者根据故事内容所起，并非原有标题。本书译文是根据1980年艾奥迪（Einaudi）出版社出版的新版《十日谈》翻译的，主编是维托雷·布兰卡（Vittore Branca）。本篇故事原标题为“第二天第五则故事”。（说明：书中脚注均为译者注。）

[2] 佛罗林是当时在佛罗伦萨流通的金币。

[3] 即今天西西里岛的阿格里琴托城。

[4] 12—13世纪，意大利中部和北部分别支持教皇和神圣罗马帝国，因此分为教皇派与皇帝派两派。双方的纷争在意大利一直持续到15世纪。

里卡尔多·钦齐卡失去了他的妻子[1]

从前，在比萨有一位法官大人，名叫里卡尔多·迪·钦齐卡，虽然体力衰弱，但却十分聪明。法官很富有，想找一位年轻美丽的妻子。他觉得，对待妻子只需要拿出做学问的精力就可以了。他找得很慢，心想，如果帮自己拿主意也像帮别人拿主意一样简单，那他早就选好妻子了。最后，他如愿以偿地找到了一位年轻貌美的妻子——洛托·瓜兰迪先生把自己的女儿许配给了他。这位姑娘叫巴尔托洛梅娅，是比萨最美丽可人的姑娘之一。在比萨，毕竟没有几个人长得比吃虫子的蜥蜴更好看。法官举行了盛大的庆典迎娶姑娘，婚礼豪华而又隆重。新婚之夜，为了遵守惯例，他勉强与妻子做了一次爱，但是很快就招架不住了。第二天早上，本就瘦弱的他已然筋疲力尽，只能靠干白葡萄酒、滋补蜜饯和其他补品来恢复体力。

现在这位法官大人比之前更清楚自己的能力了，于是开始教妻子读一本历书。这本历书好像是在拉文纳出版印制的，很受孩子们的喜爱。[2]根据这本历书上的标注，每一天都会纪念一位圣人，甚至在一天之内要纪念好几位圣人。法官用了很多理由向妻子解释说，为了表示崇敬之心，男女在这些日子里都要禁欲，不能行房事。除了历书上规定的节日以外，他还增加了斋戒日、四季小斋、圣徒斋戒日，还有纪念千余位圣人的斋戒日，又添上了礼拜五、礼拜六和献给天主的礼拜日。除此之外，禁欲的日子还有整个四旬斋期间。里卡尔多还规定了上百个方位，一旦月亮移动到这些位置，男女就不可行房。此外，在其他一些特殊情况下，夫妻也要禁欲。他觉得，对待同床的女人，就像应对法律案件，没什么不同。这么一来，他的太太要吃不少苦头。里卡尔多一个月只碰她一次，而且把她盯得死死的，以防有人像自己教她什么是节假日那样教她什么是工作日。

夏天到了，天气炎热，里卡尔多大人想带妻子一起去蒙特内罗附近的庄园里住几天，避暑消遣。这一天，里卡尔多为了让太太开心，便带她去海上钓鱼。他和渔夫坐在一只船上，妻子和侍女们坐在另一只船上。大家一时兴起，一直驶向了深海，驶出了好几海里还未曾察觉。大家要么专心致志地钓鱼，要么聚精会神地观看。就在这时，突然驶来一艘大船，那是当时远近闻名的海盗帕伽尼诺的船。看到两只小船，帕伽尼诺径直地驶了过去。小船只能拼命地逃，但是海盗还是追上了法官太太坐的船。帕伽尼诺看到船上美丽的夫人，就想也不想地把她掳走了。这时的里卡尔多已经上岸，只能眼睁睁地看着海盗把他夫人带上船，消失在茫茫大海上。法官本就心胸狭窄，连空气都要嫉妒，现在看到这一幕有多恼火，就不必我多言了吧。他到比萨控诉海盗的恶行，又去了其他地方，但最终也没能得知是谁抢走了妻子，又把她带去了哪里。

帕伽尼诺看巴尔托洛梅娅如此美丽，不禁心动。再加上他本就没有妻室，所以就想和她永远生活在一起。巴尔托洛梅娅大哭不止，帕伽尼诺就温柔地安慰她。夜幕降临，他解开了她的腰带。那本历书刚好从腰带上掉了下来，与此同时，每一个节日和休假日都从她的脑海中消失了。帕伽尼诺觉得实际行动比话语有效，就一直用行动安慰她。就这样，还没到摩纳哥，巴尔托洛梅娅就把法官和他的规定忘得一干二净，和帕伽尼诺过上了天下最快活的日子。帕伽尼诺把巴尔托洛梅娅带到摩纳哥后，不仅日夜宽慰她，还像对待妻子一样善待她。

过了一段时间，里卡尔多大人打听到了太太的下落，便迫不及待地想去找她。他觉得没有人知道该怎么做，于是亲自去找夫人，并且决定无论花多少钱都要赎回她。他乘船去了摩纳哥，见到了巴尔托洛梅娅。巴尔托洛梅娅也看到了里卡尔多，当晚就告诉了帕伽尼诺这件事，并且向他表明了自己的想法。第二天早上，里卡尔多看到帕伽尼诺后就过去和他套近乎。没过多长时间，两人就成了亲密的好友。其实帕伽尼诺认识他，并且知道他想做什么，只是没有表现出来。里卡尔多见时机成熟，就委婉地向帕伽尼诺解释了自己来这里的缘由，接着又央求帕伽尼诺，只要把妻子还给他，不管多少赎金他都会照付。

帕伽尼诺和善地回答道：“法官阁下，我很欢迎您的到来，所以我向您简单地解释一下，我家的确有位年轻的姑娘，但我并不知道她是您的太太还是其他人的太太。我不晓得您是谁，对她也不太了解，因为她住在我家没多长时间。我看您是位正直的绅士，就带您去见见她吧。如果真如您所说，那她肯定认识您。如果她说的和您一致，并且想和您回去，看在您如此友善的分儿上，无论您给我多少赎金我都会放她走；如果她说的和您不同，那您就是存心来我这里抢她了。我是个年轻的男子，和其他人一样，也会保护自己的女人，尤其是她，因为我从未见过如此可爱的姑娘。”

里卡尔多说：“她绝对是我的妻子，你只要带我去见她就知道了。她一见我，就会立刻勾住我的脖子。你提的意见很好，我非常同意。”

“那么，”帕伽尼诺说，“我们走吧。”

于是两人来到了帕伽尼诺家，在客厅就座。这时，帕伽尼诺派人叫巴尔托洛梅娅过来。她穿戴整齐，从房里走出，来到了里卡尔多和帕伽尼诺所在的客厅。但她见了里卡尔多后，就像见了帕伽尼诺带回家的一位陌生客人似的，只是打了声招呼，并没有多余的举动。法官原想着巴尔托洛梅娅见了自己会非常开心，所以看到这一幕后十分惊讶，自言自语道：“可能是我失去她后，太过悲伤痛苦，所以面容憔悴，以至于她认不出我了。”

于是他说：“夫人，带你去钓鱼让我付出了多么昂贵的代价啊！我从来没有像失去你之后这样痛苦过，而你却疏远我，好像不认识我了。你没看见吗？我是你的里卡尔多啊！我来这里是要带你回去，不管这家的主人要什么我都会给他。他也很慷慨，无论我付多少赎金都会把你还给我。”

夫人转向他，面带微笑地说：“先生，您是在对我说话吗？您仔细看看，不要把我认成别人了，因为我不记得曾经见过您。”

里卡尔多说：“瞧你说的什么话，你好好看看我，你要是愿意仔细回想一下的话，就会知道我是你的丈夫里卡尔多·迪·钦齐卡。”

夫人说：“先生，请您原谅我，按您说的，我仔细地看了看您，这好像不大礼貌，但不用仔细看，我也知道自己从未见过您。”

里卡尔多又想，她是因为害怕帕伽尼诺，才不敢在他面前承认认识自己。所以过了一会儿，他恳求帕伽尼诺，让他们两人单独在一个房间里谈一谈。帕伽尼诺说可以，前提是里卡尔多不能强行亲吻她。帕伽尼诺让巴尔托洛梅娅跟着里卡尔多去里屋，听听他想说什么，想怎么回答就怎么回答。

于是他们二人单独去了一间屋子里。一坐下来，里卡尔多就说：“啊！我的心肝，我的魂，我活下去的希望啊！现在你不认识爱你胜过爱自己的里卡尔多了吗？怎么能这样呢？我的样子变了那么多吗？啊，你美丽的眼睛啊，看看我吧，哪怕只看一小会儿也行啊。”

巴尔托洛梅娅开始大笑，没有让他再说下去：“您明明知道我没有失忆！我并非不知道您是我的丈夫里卡尔多·迪·钦齐卡大人，但是当我和您在一起时，您没有真正地理解过我。如果您像自己以为的那般聪明，那您就应该明白，我年轻活泼，朝气蓬勃，所以和其他少妇一样，除了吃穿外，还会想要别的东西，尽管我害羞说不出口。而您是怎么做的，您自己清楚。如果比起妻子，您更喜欢研究法律的话，那您就不应该娶亲。但我觉得您根本就不是什么法官，只是那些节日和斋戒日的鼓吹者罢了。我跟您说，如果您也让给您种地的农民们过您规定的那些节日，让他们也像您耕种我这块田地一样种田的话，那您一粒粮食也收获不到。上帝看我年轻，怜悯我，让我遇到了他。我和他就睡在这间房里。在这里，没有人知道节日是什么。我指的节日就是您平时过的那些纪念日。您对上帝的虔诚超越了您对女人的爱。在这扇门里，我们没有礼拜五和礼拜六，没有斋戒日，没有四季小斋，也没有那漫长的四旬斋。相反，我们从早到晚都在‘劳作’，把毯子都扯破了。今天一大早，我还爬到他身上了呢。我愿意和他在一起，趁着年轻好好‘劳作’。那些节日、朝觐和斋戒就留给我的晚年吧。我为您祝福，但请您赶紧离开吧，能多快离开就多快离开。没有我在身旁，您想过多少节日就过多少节日吧。”

里卡尔多听到这些话，感到一阵难以忍受的痛苦，看她停了下来，才说：“啊，我的魂啊！你说的这叫什么话？你现在就不能考虑一下你家人的声望和你的名誉吗？你情愿道德败坏地在这里做他的姘妇，也不想回比萨做我的太太吗？这个男人，当他对你厌烦时，会对你恶语相加，把你赶走的。而我会永远爱你，哪怕我死了，你也会是我家的女主人。为了这点荒淫的肉欲，你就要抛弃你我的名誉，抛弃爱你胜过爱自己生命的我吗？啊，我的亲爱的，我的希望啊！不要再这么说了，跟我回去吧。我知道你的欲望了，从今往后我会努力的。我的美人儿，你就改变主意，跟我走吧！我从来没有像你离开我之后那么伤心。”

巴尔托洛梅娅回答他说：“我的名誉只能把握在我自己手里，容不得他人说三道四。我再也不会像从前那般温柔恭顺了。如果能回到我父母把我嫁给你的那天，该有多好啊！当时他们没有顾及过我的名誉，现在我也不会考虑他们的声望。如果我现在是个罪恶的‘臼’，那您就是个没用的‘捣槌’。我已经不爱您了。我还要告诉您，在这里，我觉得自己是帕伽尼诺的妻子，而在比萨，我却觉得是您的姘妇。我要想着月亮的方位，研究几何学的规则，才能将我们的‘星体’结合在一起。但在这里，帕伽尼诺每晚都搂我入怀，紧紧抱着我，轻轻地咬我。他是怎么对待我的，就请天主替我告诉您吧。您还说您会努力，可您会努力做什么呢？您能在做完三次后，还能随时坚挺得像个鱼竿似的吗？我知道，在我不在您身边的这些日子里，您已经荣升为骑士了。所以您还是走吧，还是努力地活下去吧。我看您体弱多病，觉得您应该活得很累吧。我再跟您多说一句，即便那人离开了我——不过我觉得不会的，只要我想和他在一起的话——我也永远不会回到您的身边，因为不管我怎么挤，也不能从您身上挤出一滴‘汁液’。在您那里，我承受了惨痛的损失，现在我要在另一个地方收获利润。我再向您重申一遍，这里没有节日，也没有斋戒日，所以我想留在这里。您赶紧走吧，不然我就叫了，说您要强暴我。”

里卡尔多看情况不妙，只好痛苦万分地走出了那间屋子。直到那时他才明白自己有多无能，而娶一个年轻的妻子又是一件多么荒唐的事情。他又和帕伽尼诺说了很多话，但却无济于事。最后，他什么事也没做成，只能离开妻子，回比萨去了。由于太过悲痛，他已经神智不清，在比萨街头到处游走。无论谁向他打招呼，或者询问事情，他都只会回答说：“坏人是不过节的。”不久之后，他就一命呜呼了。

帕伽尼诺知道巴尔托洛梅娅对自己的爱，就娶了她，让她做了自己的合法妻子。他们从不理会节日和斋戒日，也不过四旬斋，只要腿还能动，就每夜“劳作”。

[1] 原标题为“第二天第十则故事”。

[2] 据说，一年中有多少天，在拉文纳城中就有多少座教堂。每天都是纪念圣人的节日，都要休假，所以孩子们很喜欢这本历书。

贝尔科洛蕾夫人与神父[1]

正如你们中的一些人知道，或是曾经听说过的那样：在瓦尔隆戈，也就是离这儿不远的村子里，有一个身强体壮的教士，在服务女人时很能干。尽管学识浅薄，他每逢礼拜日都会在村里的榆树下，说很多好听的善言善语，让村民们开心。当男人们不在家时，他就去看望他们的女人，比以往任何一任神父都要热切，给她们带些宗教节日上的礼品，有时还把圣水和蜡烛头带到家里为她们祝祷。人们还从未见过像他这样的教士呢。

事情是这样的。在之前爱慕过的众多农妇中，他最喜欢的那人名叫贝尔科洛蕾，是农民本蒂韦尼亚·德尔·马佐的妻子。贝尔科洛蕾神采奕奕，的确是个讨人喜爱的农妇。她皮肤黝黑，健壮有力，推起磨来比其他女人更有劲。她还会敲铃鼓，唱《水流深谷》，跳力达舞和巴隆基奥舞，兴起时还会从手边拿起一块精致的小手绢舞动，十分俊俏美丽。教士大人喜欢这一切喜欢得不得了，对她着了迷。为了看她，教士整日在村子里逛来逛去。周日早晨，如果见她来了教堂，他就会在唱《慈悲经》和《三圣颂》时特别卖力，来表现自己优秀的歌唱才能，尽管他的声音像驴叫一样难听；如果没有看到她，他就唱得有气无力。尽管知道教士歌声的变化，本蒂韦尼亚·德尔·马佐却丝毫没有察觉到教士对妻子的喜爱，就连他身旁的贝尔科洛蕾也没有意识到这回事。为了和贝尔科洛蕾更亲近些，教士时不时地送她礼物：有时是一把新鲜的大蒜，那是他亲手在菜园里种出来的，也是这片教区中长得最好的蒜；有时是一小筐豆子；有时是一小束五月葱或是一小把斯卡洛尼葱。一有时机，他就用眼神和她打情骂俏。但贝尔科洛蕾对教士很冷漠，举止十分端庄，每次都假装没有看到他，所以教士始终不能如愿以偿。

有一天的正午时分，教士在教区里东走西逛，突然看到本蒂韦尼亚·德尔·马佐赶着一驾驴车迎面而来，车上载满了东西。于是教士过去和他打招呼，问他要去哪里。

本蒂韦尼亚回答他说：“尊敬的神父，我要去城里办点事情，把这些东西送给博纳科里·达·吉内斯特雷托大人。不知道为什么，一位刑事法官让手下的检察官发了张诉状，里面竟然提到了我。这件事刻不容缓，我想请吉内斯特雷托大人帮帮忙。”

教士高兴地说：“孩子，好好做！带上我的祝福出发吧，快去快回。如果碰到拉普乔或者纳尔迪诺，别忘了跟他们说把我打谷棒上的皮带还给我。”

本蒂韦尼亚答应了他，就朝着佛罗伦萨的方向走了。教士想，是时候去找贝尔科洛蕾碰碰运气了，于是大步向她家走去。他边进门边说：“求天主为这家人赐福！家里有人吗？”

贝尔科洛蕾当时在阁楼里，听到教士的声音，答道：“神父，欢迎您！这么大热的天，您来这里做什么呢？”

教士回答说：“天主赐福于我，我看到你丈夫去城里了，所以过来和你待一会儿。”

贝尔科洛蕾从阁楼下来，坐下收拾丈夫刚打下来的卷心菜种子。教士开口说道：“你看，贝尔科洛蕾，你总是这个样子，是想急死我吗？”

贝尔科洛蕾笑了，说：“我对您做什么了呀？”

教士说：“你什么都没做，可是你不让我做我想做的事。那件事也是天主让我做的。”

贝尔科洛蕾说：“啊！您清醒一点，教士还做这种事吗？”

教士答道：“我们也做啊，为什么不做呢？我还告诉你，我们的功夫比别的男人还要好。你知道为什么吗？因为我们很少干这事，所以干起来更有劲。说实话，只要安安静静地让我施展，你是会占便宜的。”

贝尔科洛蕾说：“我能占什么便宜呢？你们这些比小气鬼还小气的人！”

于是教士说道：“我不知道你想要什么，所以你自己说吧。你是想要双鞋呢，还是想要个项圈？或者是一块上好的羊毛料子？你想要什么都可以。”

贝尔科洛蕾回答道：“神父，您说得倒好听！这些东西我都有。但是，如果您真的喜欢我，就帮我个忙吧！帮了我的忙，您想做什么，我就让您做什么。”

于是教士说：“你想让我做什么就直说吧，我很愿意帮你。”

贝尔科洛蕾说：“周六，我要去趟佛罗伦萨，把我织好的羊毛交给别人，还要修一下我的纺车。如果您借我五里拉，我就能从放高利贷的人手里赎回我那件紫黑色的裙子，还有我那条当嫁妆带过来的腰带。要是没有裙子和腰带，我什么好地方都去不了，也不能去教堂了。我知道，您是有这个钱的。您要是借给我钱，让我做什么我都会做的。”

教士回答说：“求天主祝福我！我今天没有带那么多钱，但你相信我，周六之前我会给你的。”

“是吗！”贝尔科洛蕾说，“你们个个都是耍嘴皮子的，却从不履行诺言。您还想用对待毕廖扎的方式对待我，让我所有的期待都落空，然后灰溜溜地离开吗？毕廖扎因为这件事，还沦落成了妓女。我对天发誓，我是不会让您得逞的。所以，如果没有钱，那您就走吧。”

“啊！”教士说，“别让我现在回家拿钱了。你看，我难得那么走运，赶上你家里没人的好时候。要是我回家一趟，等我再回来时，可能就会有人打扰我们了。现在这么好的机会，我不知道要等到什么时候才能再碰上一回。”

贝尔科洛蕾说：“说得好听。如果您想回去拿钱，那就回去，不然您就忍着吧。”

教士看这样子，觉得如果不押给她点东西，她就不会让他做自己想做的事情，于是说道：“你看，你不相信我会给你钱，那我把这件深蓝色的披风押在你这里。这回你相信我了吧。”

贝尔科洛蕾抬头看了一眼说：“哦，这件披风啊。一件披风能值多少钱呢？”

教士说：“值多少钱？我要让你知道，这可是第戎[2]料子，甚至是‘第戎中的第戎料子’，还有人说它是‘特等第戎料子’呢。我从旧货商洛托那里花了整整七里拉才把它买下来，买回家还不到十五天。你知道，洛托最懂这种料子了，他还说我占了五索尔多[3]的便宜呢。”

“哦，这样吗？”贝尔科洛蕾说，“天主保佑，我之前真不敢相信一件披风居然值这么些钱。但是你得先把它给我才行。”

教士大人感到弓已上弦，实在忍不住了，于是急忙把披风脱下来给了她。贝尔科洛蕾把它放好后，对教士说：“大人，请您来棚屋里，这儿不会有人来的。”于是他们去了棚屋。

在屋里，教士给她世上最甜蜜的吻，让她快活得飘飘欲仙。他从贝尔科洛蕾家离开时，像刚为别人主持完婚礼似的，只穿了教士袍，没有穿披风。

回到教堂后，教士想，就算收上整整一年的蜡烛头，连五里拉的一半都赚不到。于是他觉得自己做了件错事，后悔把披风留给了她，开始琢磨该怎么不费分文地把披风要回来。教士这人本来就挺狡猾，所以不一会儿就想出了要回披风的办法。正好第二天是个节日，教士就让邻居家的孩子去贝尔科洛蕾家，问她愿不愿意把石臼借给他，因为宾古焦·达尔·波焦和努托·布列蒂要和他一起用午餐，所以他想用石臼捣些酱汁。于是贝尔科洛蕾把石臼给了那孩子。

到了用午餐的时候，教士偷看到贝尔科洛蕾和丈夫本蒂韦尼亚·德尔·马佐在一起吃饭，便叫来手下的人，对他说：“你把这个石臼还给贝尔科洛蕾，然后跟她说‘大人非常感谢您，请您把那孩子上午押在您这里的披风还给大人。’”那人来到贝尔科洛蕾家，看到她正和丈夫一起吃饭，就放下了石臼，把教士交代的话说了一遍。

那贝尔科洛蕾听完正想回嘴，不料本蒂韦尼亚脸色阴沉地看着她说：“你敢拿神父大人的东西？我向基督发誓，我真想狠狠地揍你一拳。你这个混账娘们儿，赶紧把东西还回去！听着，无论神父大人要什么东西，哪怕是咱们家的驴，你也不能对他说一个‘不’字。”

贝尔科洛蕾嘟哝着站了起来，从床下的箱子里拿出披风，给了那个人，并且对他说：“你替我告诉大人：‘贝尔科洛蕾向天主祈祷，希望您再也不要在她的“臼”里捣“酱汁”了。在这件事上，您已经失去了她的信任。’”

那人带着披风回去了，并且向教士转告了贝尔科洛蕾的话。教士听了后笑着说：“下次你见到她，就跟她说，她不借给我‘臼’，我还不借给她‘捣槌’了呢。一报还一报吧！”

本蒂韦尼亚听了这些话，还以为神父大人在责怪自己，就没往那件事上想，但贝尔科洛蕾对教士却是爱搭不理。直到收获葡萄的季节[4]，教士恐吓她，如果再不理他，她会被魔王撒旦吃掉。贝尔科洛蕾很害怕，就在酿葡萄酒和炒栗子的季节[5]里，表面上与他和好了。后来，他们又一起寻欢作乐了很多次。为了补偿那五里拉，教士给她的铃鼓换了张新皮，又系了一个铃铛。贝尔科洛蕾这才开心了。

[1] 原标题为“第八天第二则故事”。

[2] 第戎是一座法国城市，盛产羊毛制品。

[3] 索尔多是意大利当时的流通货币之一，一里拉等于二十索尔多。

[4] 即夏季。

[5] 即秋季。

耐心的格里赛尔达[1]

很久以前，桑卢佐有一个侯爵世家。家中的主人很年轻，名叫瓜尔蒂耶里，尚未娶亲。而且他每天只管打鸟狩猎，根本没有娶妻生子的念头。尽管人们都十分尊敬侯爵，觉得他机智过人，但他手下的人却颇有微词。他们几次三番求他成家，不然侯爵将后继无人，他们也就没有了主公。此外，他们还给侯爵找了许多与他门当户对的姑娘，希望他能喜欢。

侯爵对下属们说：“朋友们，你们逼我做的事，偏偏是我从来都不想做的事情。你们想一想，娶一位和自己志趣相投的妻子有多困难，而娶一个跟自己合不来的女人却是大有可能。要是娶了这么一个女人，日子该多不好过啊！你们真蠢，竟然以为，只要摸清姑娘父母的品性，就能找到让我满意的妻子。我不知道你们如何认识了她们父亲，也不知道你们如何窥探到了她们母亲的隐私。就算你们明白了姑娘父母的情况，又怎么保证她和父母一模一样呢？但既然你们执意要给我套上这道枷锁，我只能欣然接受。不过，我要自己选择妻子。就算之后事情进展得不顺利，我也用不着怪罪别人。我还要告诉你们，不管我最后选了谁，你们都要尊敬她。要是我按照你们的意愿，娶了一个自己不喜欢的女人，那我有多不爽快，就会让你们吃到多大的苦头。”他那些精明的手下立刻回答说，只要侯爵肯娶亲，无论娶谁，他们都会高兴的。

在附近的村子里，住着一个出身贫寒的姑娘。侯爵欣赏她的品性已经有很长一段时日了。而且他也十分欣赏姑娘的美貌，觉得与她一起生活应该会很开心。于是他就不再物色别人，直接挑明要娶她。侯爵派人把姑娘的父亲叫了过来，向他表明了心意。姑娘的父亲十分贫穷，所以立刻答应了这门婚事。

办完这些事后，瓜尔蒂耶里侯爵把辖区内所有的居民都召集过来，对他们说：“朋友们，我知道你们很想让我娶亲，我也马上就要结婚了。但我成亲，多半是为了让你们开心，并非我自己所想。你们答应过我，无论我娶谁回家都会同意，而且都会尊敬她。现在，是时候让我来履行我对你们许下的诺言，也是时候让你们兑现承诺了。我按照自己的心愿找到了附近的一位姑娘，不日就会和她在府里成婚。所以，你们要想一想，该如何办一场热闹的婚礼，又该如何迎娶她。这样一来，你们让我高兴，我也会让你们满意。”

大家听到这个消息后都很兴奋，回答说，无论侯爵想要娶谁，他们都会欣然接受，并且在任何时候都会尊敬她，视她为自己的女主人。那之后，大伙很快就投入到这一庆典的准备当中，瓜尔蒂耶里本人也参与了筹备过程。侯爵让他们把婚礼办得豪华隆重，还邀请了所有亲朋好友以及周边地区的上层人士来参加庆典。此外，他还找来了一位与新娘身材差不多的姑娘，按照她的尺寸做了很多华丽的衣服，又置办了几条腰带、一枚戒指和一顶漂亮的王冠。总之，只要是新嫁娘会用到的东西，他都准备好了。

到了婚礼那天，瓜尔蒂耶里一大早就上了马，要和他一起迎娶新娘的人也都到齐了。一切安排妥当后，手下人对侯爵说：“大人，是时候去接新娘了。”于是，侯爵在其他人的陪同下，朝着那个小村子出发了。到了之后，他们看到姑娘抬着刚从井里打来的水，急急忙忙地往家赶，周围还有几个同行的姑娘，大概是为了来看一眼侯爵的新娘。瓜尔蒂耶里看到她后，知道她名叫格里塞尔达，就叫了她一声，问她父亲在哪里。姑娘羞答答地回答道：“大人，他在家里呢。”

于是瓜尔蒂耶里下了马，让众人在外面等着，自己一个人走进了那个简陋的房子。见到姑娘的父亲贾努科雷后，侯爵对他说：“我来娶格里塞尔达回府，但是在此之前，我想当着你的面问她几个问题。”于是侯爵问格里塞尔达，结婚之后不管自己说什么话，做什么事，她会不会始终顺从于他，讨好于他。姑娘回答“会”。他又问了很多诸如此类的问题，格里塞尔达都做出了肯定的回答。

听到格里塞尔达的回答后，侯爵便牵起了她的手，把她带到了屋外，吩咐手下的人将她的旧衣裳脱掉，换上他备好的华服。很快，他们就打扮好了新娘，还梳理了她原本蓬乱的头发，为她戴上了王冠。在场的每一个人都为这一幕惊叹不已。于是侯爵说：“诸位，只要这位姑娘同意，她就是我要娶的妻子了。”接着他转过身来问姑娘：“格里塞尔达，你愿意让我做你的丈夫吗？”

格里塞尔达还是那么羞涩，不敢相信这是真的，怯生生地回答道：“大人，我愿意。”

于是侯爵说：“我也愿意让你做我的妻子。”就这样，侯爵在所有人的见证下娶走了她。他将她扶上一匹小马，风风光光地回了侯爵府。在府里，他们举行了盛大的仪式。就算是法国公主出嫁，也不过如此了。

换上新衣服后，年轻的新娘就像变了个人似的。我们刚才说过，她本就貌美如花，温柔贤淑，再经过这么一番打扮，就更加惹人喜爱了。现在的她宛若一位大家闺秀、贵族小姐，根本不像是农民贾努科雷的女儿，更不像是个放羊的姑娘了，这让之前认识她的人都惊讶万分。而且她对丈夫也十分恭顺，时刻让他感到自己是世界上最快乐、最有福气的男人。除此之外，她对丈夫手下的人也非常和蔼宽厚。每个人都衷心地爱戴她，尊敬她，祈祷她身体健康，事事顺意。有些人之前说瓜尔蒂耶里娶这个女人是犯了糊涂，现在就连他们也说，瓜尔蒂耶里料事如神，是天下最聪明的男人，因为再也没有人能像他一样，透过乡下女子的粗布衣衫，窥探到如此高尚的品德。不久，格里塞尔达的名声不仅传遍了整个侯爵领地，还传到了其他各个地方。她证明了自己的价值和品德，也让之前反对侯爵娶她的人改变了主意。

和瓜尔蒂耶里一起住了没多久后，格里塞尔达就怀孕了。几个月后，一个女婴呱呱坠地。瓜尔蒂耶里十分高兴，然而没过多长时间，他心里就萌生了一个奇怪的念头。他想用一些常人无法忍受的事考验妻子的耐心，而且要考验她很长时间。瓜尔蒂耶里先是用语言打击她。他装出心神不宁的样子，对夫人说因为她出身寒微，所以下属们对她很不满意。特别是当她生孩子时，大家一看是个女孩，都很不高兴，一直在嘀咕。

听到这些话后，夫人镇定自若，连一点多余的举动都没有。她说：“大人，您想对我做什么就做什么吧。只要能对您的名誉有利，能令您高兴，那您对我做什么，我都会心甘情愿地接受。我知道，我没有您的下属重要，而且我本就配不上您对我的尊重。”这个回答很合瓜尔蒂耶里的心意，因为他从这些话里听出，妻子并没有因为自己和他人的尊敬而骄傲自大。

没过多长时间，瓜尔蒂耶里又向妻子暗示，下属们容不下她生的这个女儿。然后，他又叫来府上一个仆人，派他去夫人那里做件事。到了格里塞尔达面前，仆人面露难色地对她说：“夫人，我要是不按大人吩咐的做，大人就会杀了我的。他让我把您的女儿带走，让我……”他说到这里，就没再说下去了。

格里塞尔达听了这话，再看看这个仆人的脸色，想起侯爵之前说的话，便明白了丈夫是派他来杀女儿的。尽管心里悲恸欲绝，但她仍然面不改色，立刻把女儿从摇篮里抱了起来，在一番亲吻、祝福之后，把孩子给了仆人，对他说：“带她走吧！既然你的主人要你这么做，那你按他的命令照做就是了。但请你别让鸟兽吃掉孩子的尸身，除非大人命令你必须这么做。”仆人抱着孩子，把夫人说的话重复给了侯爵听。妻子坚强的意志让他感到十分惊讶，于是，他把女儿送到了博洛尼亚的一位亲戚那里，请亲戚悉心照料教导她，但永远不要让孩子知道自己的身世。

不久，夫人又怀孕了，这次生下了一名男婴。瓜尔蒂耶里十分喜欢这个孩子，但觉得之前做的还不够，想用更大的打击来考验妻子。一天，他又装作心绪不定的样子对妻子说：“夫人，自从你生了这个儿子，我手下那些人知道我死以后，贾努科雷的外孙要做他们的主公，就一直闹得不可开交。我实在受不了他们了。要想不被他们推翻，我恐怕还得再对儿子做一次上次对女儿做的事情，不然最后还得离开你，再娶一个女人。”妻子耐心地听他讲完，只是回答说：“大人，请您按自己的意愿行事。您只管让自己开心就好，不用考虑我。因为如果看到您不开心，我做什么事情都不会开心的。”

没过几天，瓜尔蒂耶里又像当年送走女儿一样，送走了儿子。和上次一样，他假装把孩子杀掉，但其实还是送到了博洛尼亚抚养。而夫人也和上次送走女儿时一样，没流露出一丝多余的神情，也没说一句多余的话。瓜尔蒂耶里看到后震惊了，越发确信没有女人可以做到她这般隐忍。如果不是亲眼看到格里塞尔达与自己一样疼爱孩子的话，他还以为妻子根本没把孩子放在心上呢。而格里塞尔达也很聪明，让丈夫看出了自己对孩子的爱。侯爵的下属们以为他真的把两个孩子杀了，于是都强烈地谴责他，觉得他是个残忍无情的人，也都对夫人表现出了极大的同情。别人家的夫人看她失去了孩子，过来安慰她。但她只是说，如果孩子的亲生父亲想这么做，那么她也愿意这么做。

女儿长大后，瓜尔蒂耶里觉得考验妻子忍耐力的最终时刻到了。当着众多下属的面，瓜尔蒂耶里宣称，他再也忍受不了夫人了，还说当初娶她是因为年少无知，所以想请求教皇特许，让他离开格里塞尔达，再娶新人。很多下属反对他，但他却说自己只能这么做。夫人听说这件事后，想到自己要回娘家，像从前那样终日放羊，还要看着另一个女人与自己心爱的丈夫在一起生活，心里十分难过。然而，就像以前接受不公的命运时一样，这次她仍然隐忍不发，听从命运的安排。

没过多久，瓜尔蒂耶里就派人从罗马寄回几封伪造的信，让手下的人看到，教皇已经在信中特许他休掉格里塞尔达，另娶他人。接着，他派人把格里塞尔达叫来，当着众人的面对她说：“夫人，我获得了教皇的特许，可以把你休掉再娶了。我的祖上都是这里的达官贵人，而你家世世代代都是农民，所以我不想让你做我的妻子了，但你可以带着嫁妆回贾努科雷家。我也已经找到了一位适合我的妻子，过几天就会把她娶来。”

夫人听到这些话后，费了好大的劲才克制住女人的天性，把眼泪咽到肚子里，回答道：“大人，我知道自己出身卑微，配不上高贵的您。多亏了上帝的恩赐和您的宠爱，我才能和您在一起。尽管您给了我尊位，但我始终不敢把自己当成侯爵夫人，只觉得自己沾了您的光。既然您想收回送给我的东西，那么我也愿意将它们还给您。这是您娶我时用的戒指，请您收下吧。至于您让我把带过来的嫁妆带走，这既不用您花钱找人来搬，也不用我叫牲口来驮，因为我还没有忘记，我嫁给您时，什么也没有带过来，连身上穿的衣服都是您给的。如果您觉得可行的话，我也可以赤裸着走出去，让大家都看看我这为您生了两个孩子的身子。但我是带着童贞过来的，现在已经带不走了，所以我求求您看在这分儿上，除了本就不存在的嫁妆之外，至少让我再穿走一件衣服吧。”

瓜尔蒂耶里感动得直想哭，但仍然板着脸说：“那你就穿件衣服吧。”

周围的人都求侯爵再给夫人件衣裳，别让相伴十三年的妻子只穿一件内衣，走得那么寒酸，那么不光彩。但他们怎么求侯爵都没有用，夫人还是辞别了众人，摘去头饰，身穿一件单衣，赤足走出了侯爵府，回到了父亲家。所有看到这一幕的人无不痛哭流涕。而贾努科雷从未相信过瓜尔蒂耶里是真心实意要娶女儿为妻，所以每时每刻都在等待这一天的到来。他还一直留着瓜尔蒂耶里娶亲时，女儿脱下来的衣服，等女儿回娘家时再给她继续穿。回家后，格里塞尔达还是像之前一样干些杂务活。尽管命运多舛，她还是凭借顽强的意志忍耐了下来。

瓜尔蒂耶里做完这些事后，便对他手下的人说，自己看中了帕纳戈一位公爵的女儿，让他们好好筹备婚礼，又派人把格里塞尔达叫来。格里塞尔达到了后，侯爵对她说：“我新看中了一个姑娘，想让她第一次进我家门时风光一番。你知道，办这么一场婚礼，需要有人收拾屋子，处理许多杂务，而我府上没有一个女佣能担得起这差事。你比其他任何人都熟悉这些事务，所以我派你来主持工作。除此之外，你还要把这附近该邀请的太太都请过来，最后像迎接女主人一样，迎接我的新婚妻子。办完这些事后，你就可以回娘家了。”

这些话就像刀子一样扎在格里塞尔达心上。曾经的好运让她拥有了深爱丈夫的权利，现在她已然失去了这份权利，但实在不忍心割舍这份感情。然而，她只是回答说：“大人，我准备好了。”于是她穿着粗布衣衫，又走进了那座不久前身穿单衣离开的府第，开始布置房间。她在床头挂上装饰品，给客厅铺好地毯，又收拾了厨房。事无巨细，她都亲自动手，就像一个卑贱的女佣。直到把所有东西都布置妥当，又以侯爵的名义邀请完附近府上的夫人之后，她才停下歇了歇，等待婚礼的到来。到了婚礼那天，她面带笑容，迎接了所有的女宾。尽管穿着破衣旧衫，但她举止大方，谈吐得体，如同一位贵族夫人。

侯爵之前把孩子送给了博洛尼亚的亲戚抚养，而亲戚的丈夫正是帕纳戈的伯爵。现在，瓜尔蒂耶里和格里塞尔达的女儿已经长到了十二岁，出落得亭亭玉立，宛若仙女一般。他们的儿子也已经六岁了。瓜尔蒂耶里写信给亲戚，请他把女儿和儿子送回桑卢佐，还拜托他派阵势浩大的随从护送他们，告诉所有人，女儿将会嫁给瓜尔蒂耶里侯爵，但不要告诉任何人她的真实身份。这位亲戚按照侯爵的请求一一照做，带着姑娘、弟弟和随从们出发了。几天后，他们在午餐时分到达了桑卢佐。当地所有村民，以及附近村子里的人都在桑卢佐等候瓜尔蒂耶里侯爵的新娘。女宾们把姑娘迎到了府上，而在布好筵席的客厅里，格里塞尔达像往常一样，兴高采烈地迎上去说：“欢迎夫人！”其实女宾们早就求瓜尔蒂耶里，让格里塞尔达待在另一个房间里，或者给她些衣物，别让她在客人面前出这么大的丑，但瓜尔蒂耶里不答应。这时，她们只好就座，等待婚礼开始。每个人看了那姑娘后，都说瓜尔蒂耶里换夫人换得好，格里塞尔达也对姑娘和她弟弟赞不绝口。

瓜尔蒂耶里看到所有这些场景，觉得对夫人耐心的考验已经足够了。他看到格里塞尔达从不改变态度，始终恭顺谦卑，又知道她很聪慧，并不是由于智力缺陷才会如此，所以认为是时候解除她所有的痛苦了。他还知道，尽管她没有把这些痛苦表现在脸上，但一定藏在了心里。于是，瓜尔蒂耶里把格里塞尔达叫来，当着所有人的面，微笑着问她：“你觉得我的新娘怎么样？”

“大人”，格里塞尔达回答说，“我觉得她非常好，既美丽又聪慧。我觉得，您和她一起生活，一定会成为世上最快乐的人。但我求求您，不要像对待您上一位妻子一样对待她，叫她受到那么多伤害。您的前妻自小就饱受苦难，所以并无大碍；而她一向被娇生惯养，是忍受不了这些挫折的。”

瓜尔蒂耶里看到格里塞尔达如此坚信自己会娶这姑娘为妻，而且没有一句抱怨的话，于是让她坐在自己身边，对她说：“格里塞尔达，你忍耐了这么长时间，是时候让你得到回报，也是时候让那些说我残酷不义的人知道我这么做的目的了。我之所以这么做，是想要教会你该如何做一个妻子，并且让大家知道该如何对待我的妻子，好让我们的生活永远平安顺利。刚娶你时，我非常害怕你会不听我的话，所以才想方设法地试探你，甚至伤害你。然而，你说的每句话都顺我的心，做的每件事都合我的意。我觉得拥有你，就等于拥有了我期盼的所有宽慰和欣喜。现在，我想一次性弥补之前对你的亏欠，用我全部的温柔抚慰你受伤的心。来，高高兴兴地牵起这姑娘和这男孩的手吧，因为你相信我要娶的这位姑娘就是我们的女儿，而这男孩就是我们的儿子。他们两人就是你们以为被我残忍杀害的孩子。而我，是你的丈夫，我爱你胜过世间万物。我相信，现在我可以自豪地说，没有人能够像我一样，对自己的妻子如此满意。”

说罢，他拥吻了妻子。格里塞尔达喜极而泣，和丈夫一起站起来，向女儿走去。他们的女儿听完这些事情后又惊又喜，在场的众人到这时也才明白了侯爵的所作所为。格里塞尔达温柔地拥抱了女儿，又抱住了儿子。女宾们也非常欣慰，纷纷起身祝贺格里塞尔达，然后和她去里间，帮她脱下了那身粗布衣裳，换上了一身她之前穿的华服，将女主人迎回客厅。其实，就算穿着方才那身衣服，她看起来仍像是府上的女主人。格里塞尔达和孩子们都欣喜若狂，大家也都兴奋不已，于是一连庆祝了好几天。大家虽然觉得瓜尔蒂耶里对妻子做的事不近人情，但都夸他聪明绝顶，对格里塞尔达的智慧更是赞不绝口。

几天后，帕纳戈伯爵回到了博洛尼亚。瓜尔蒂耶里也把丈人贾努科雷接到了府里，让他不必再劳累度日，以安享晚年。他又把自己和格里塞尔达的女儿嫁给了一个富贵人家，而他自己则和格里塞尔达幸福地生活了一辈子。

现在，我们能说什么呢？高尚的灵魂也会降临到穷人家里，正如一些为人主公的贵族子弟只配去喂猪一样。除了格里塞尔达以外，还有谁能像她一样，在自己的丈夫做了那些残忍无比的事情后，不仅可以忍住不哭，还能面带笑意呢？如果换成另一个女人穿着单衣，被瓜尔蒂耶里赶出家门的话，那她就会去找别的男人，让他再给自己一身漂亮的新衣服。这听起来好像也没什么不对的。

[1] 原标题为“第十天第十则故事”。

Andreuccio da Perugia’s Neapolitan adventures

I was told some time ago about a young man from Perugia called Andreuccio, the son of a certain Pietro and a horse- dealer by trade. Having heard that horses were trading well in Naples, he put five- hundred gold florins in his bag and went off there with some other merchants, never having previously been away from home. He arrived on a Sunday evening, about vesper time, got the necessary information from his innkeeper and was in the market square early the next morning. He saw a lot of horses, many of which met with his approval, and did a good deal of bargaining without being able to agree a price for any of them. But he was keen to show that he was there to do some buying and naively and imprudently pulled out his bag of florins several times before the eyes of people coming and going past him. It was while he was negotiating, with his bag in full view, that a young Sicilian woman walked past. She was very beautiful, but ready to give any man what he wanted for a small payment. He didn’t see her, but she saw his bag and immediately said to herself, ‘Wouldn’t I be a lucky one if that money were mine?’ Then she went on her way.

There was old woman with her who was also Sicilian. As soon as she saw Andreuccio, she let the girl go on and hurried over to give him an affectionate hug. The young woman noticed and, without saying anything, stopped and waited for her on one side. Andreuccio, who had turned round and recognized the old woman, greeted her with great warmth. She promised to come and see him at his inn, but didn’t keep him talking for too long just then and soon left. Andreuccio went back to his bargaining, though he made no purchases that morning. After seeing first the bag and then the intimacy with the old servant, the young woman began to wonder if she might get hold of some or all of the money. She asked a few cautious questions about who the young man was, where he was from, what he was doing there and how she came to know him. The old servant gave her all the information she wanted, almost in as much detail as Andreuccio might have supplied himself, being able to do this because she had spent a long time with his father first in Sicily and then in Perugia. She likewise told her where he was lodging and why he had come to Naples.

Once the young woman was fully informed about his family and their names, she had the basis for playing a clever trick that would bring her what she wanted. Back at her house she made sure that the old woman was busy all day so that she couldn’t go and see Andreuccio. She had a much younger servant- girl to whom she had given a very good training in the sort of work she had in mind, and towards evening she sent her to the inn where Andreuccio was staying. When she arrived, she found him by chance standing alone in the doorway. She asked for Andreuccio and he said that he was the very man. At which she drew him to one side.

‘Sir,’ she said, ‘there is a noble lady in this town who would appreciate a conversation with you, if you were so inclined.’

Andreuccio thought carefully for a moment when he heard this. He decided that he was a good- looking lad and deduced that this lady must have fallen for him, as if there were no other fine young men in Naples just then apart from himself. He quickly said that he was up for it, and asked where and when this lady wanted to have a talk with him.

The young servant- girl replied, ‘She’s waiting for you in her house, sir, whenever you feel like coming along.’

‘Well, you lead the way and I’ll follow on,’ said Andreuccio immediately, with no thought of letting anyone in the inn know.

So the girl led him to the Sicilian woman’s house, which was in a district called Malpertugio, a name meaning Bad Passage, which gives a clear idea of just how respectable a district it was. But Andreuccio, knowing nothing of this and quite unsuspecting, thought he was going to a most respectable house to see a lady of some standing, and confidently followed the girl into the house. As they were climbing the stairs, she called out to her mistress, ‘Here’s Andreuccio’, and he saw her appear at the top, waiting for him.

She was still young, with a full figure and a lovely face, and her clothes and jewellery were tastefully ornate. When Andreuccio was closer, she came down three steps towards him, her arms wide, and, flinging them round his neck, stayed like that for a while without saying a word, as if too overcome to speak. Then she tearfully kissed his forehead and said in a broken voice, ‘O my precious Andreuccio, welcome to my house!’

Such a heartfelt reception amazed Andreuccio, and he replied quite dazed, ‘Well, it’s wonderful to meet you, my lady!’

After this she took him by the hand and led him into the main room, and from there, without saying another word, into her private chamber, which was redolent with the scents of roses, orange blossom and other flowers. Andreuccio noticed a splendid curtained bed, and an abundance of beautiful dresses arranged on hangers in the south Italian way, and many other fine and costly items. In his inexperience he was fully convinced by all this that the woman could be nothing but a great lady. Once they were seated together on a chest that was at the foot of her bed, she embarked on the following speech.

‘I am quite certain, Andreuccio, that you are startled at being embraced and wept over by me in this way. After all, you don’t know me and and may never have heard my name mentioned. But in a moment you are going to hear something which will perhaps amaze you even more. The fact is, I am your sister. And I can tell you that, since God has granted me the enormous grace of letting me see one of my brothers before I die – though of course I want to see all of you – I shall not die unconsoled. Perhaps you have never heard a word of this. So I shall happily tell you all about it.

‘As I think you may have been told, Pietro – that is, your father and mine – lived for a long time in Palermo. Thanks to his native goodness and appealing character he gained the affections of those who came to know him and still has a place in their hearts. But, among those most attached to him, there was someone who loved him more than anyone else, and that was my mother, who was a noble lady and recently widowed. She loved him so much that she put aside all fears of her father and brothers and any concern for her honour, and entered into intimate relations with him. As a result I was born into the world and am now the person you see before you.

‘A little later, when a reason arose for Pietro to return to Perugia, he left me, still a very little girl, with my mother. From everything I heard, he never gave me or her another thought. If he had not been my father, I would be very critical of him, considering the ingratitude he showed to my mother – and let’s leave aside the love he should have felt for me his daughter, and not by a servant- girl or some woman of easy virtue either. My mother was inspired by the truest form of love when knowing nothing of who he was, she put herself and everything she had in his hands. But there you are Wrongs of long ago are more easily criticized than pu right.

‘So he left me a little girl in Palermo. When I had grown into more or less the woman you see before you, my mother, who was a rich lady, married me to a man from Agrigento, an upstanding man of noble rank. Out of love for myself and my mother he moved to Palermo, and there, being very much on the Guelf side, he became involved in plotting with our King Charles. King Fred erick got wind of the plot before any of our plans could be acted on, and so we had to flee Sicily just at the moment when I was expecting to become the finest lady there had ever been on the island. We took with us wha few things we could – I mean few in comparison to al the possessions we had – and, leaving our lands and man sions behind, escaped to this city. We found King Charles very grateful. He partially compensated us for the losses we had suffered on his behalf. He gave us lands and houses, and he still gives my husband, your brother- in- law a substantial pension, as you’ll soon be able to see. So that is how I came to be here, and how, thanks to God’s grace, though not at all to you, I now see you before me my sweet brother.’

With this she clasped him to her again and kissed his forehead, still weeping tenderly.

She told her cock- and- bull story in a supremely coherent and convincing way, with not a hesitation or stutter. Andreuccio recalled that his father really had been in Palermo and he knew from his own experience what young men are like, and how prone they are to falling in love. What with the tender tears, embraces and decidedly unamorous kisses, he was convinced that what she said was more than true. When she finished, he made the following reply.

‘My lady, you must not be shocked by my own amazement. To be candid, either my father for some reason of his own never spoke about you and your mother, or if he did speak of you, not a whisper reached my ears. So I had no more knowledge of you than if you had never existed. But it’s all the more precious to me to have found you, my sister, in this place, because I’m here all alone and this was the thing I least expected. And to tell the truth, I can’t imagine your not being precious to the grandest businessman I can think of, let alone to a small- scale merchant like myself. But please, explain one thing for me. How did you come to know I was here?’

‘I was told this morning,’ she replied. ‘And the person who told me is a poor woman who spends a lot of time here with me, the reason being that, from what she says, she was with our father for a long time in both Palermo and Perugia. If it hadn’t seemed to me more honourable for you to come here to what is your house than for me to come and see you at someone else’s, I would have been with you ages ago.’

After this she started putting precise questions to him about his relatives, identifying each one by name Andreuccio told her about them all, becoming more and more willing to believe what he should not have believed at all.

Since they kept on talking for a long time and it was very hot, she called for white wine and sweetmeats, and ensured that Andreuccio was duly served. He made to leave after this since it was now dinnertime, but she wouldn’t allow it. Looking deeply distressed, she flung her arms round him, saying, ‘Oh, poor me, I can tell I don’t really matter to you! To think that you’re here with a sister you’ve never seen before, in her house, where you should have come and stayed when you arrived, and you want to go off and have your dinner in an inn. No, you’l dine with me, and though my husband is not here, I’m very sorry to say, I’ll do what little a lady is capable of to see you are treated with some degree of honour.’

Andreuccio could only come up with one reply.

‘You do matter to me,’ he said, ‘as much as any siste should. But if I don’t go, I shall keep them waiting fo me for dinner all evening, which would be really churlish.’

‘Lord in heaven,’ she said, ‘do you think I’ve nobody in the house I can send to tell them not to expect you? Though you would be doing a finer thing, not to say your duty, if you sent a message to your friends inviting them to come and dine here. Then afterwards, if you were set on leaving, you and all the rest could go off in one big party.’

Andreuccio replied that he had no wish to see his friends that evening, and that, if this was how she felt, she should treat him as she pleased. She then made a show of sending a message to the inn telling them not to expect him for dinner. After this they talked on for a long time before sitting down to eat. They were served in a splendid fashion with a series of dishes, the woman cunningly prolonging the dinner well into the night. When they got up from the table, and Andreuccio expressed a desire to leave, she said that she could not possibly allow it. Naples was not a city for anyone to walk through at night, especially a stranger. She had sent a message to say he should not be expected for dinner and then she had sent another regarding where he was staying. He believed everything she said, and was delighted, in his deluded state, to stay on.

At her instigation conversation after dinner was prolonged and varied. Late into the night she left Andreuccio in her own chamber, with a young servant- boy to show him anything he needed, while she herself went off to another room with her maids.

It was very hot and as soon as he saw he was alone Andreuccio removed his jacket and peeled off his leg gings, which he left over the bedhead. Feeling nature calling him to lighten his stomach of the excess weigh within it, he asked the servant where one did that sort o thing. The boy pointed to a door in a corner of the room

‘Go in there,’ he said.

Andreuccio went insouciantly though the door. By chance he brought one of his feet down on a board, the other end of which was no longer attached to the joist on which it was resting. The result was that the board swung up in the air and then crashed downwards, taking Andreuccio with it. God was kind to him and he did him self no harm in the tumble, although he fell from a considerable height, but he was thoroughly covered in the horrible filth that the place was full of. To explain the arrangement in order to give you a clearer picture of wha I’ve just said and what follows, two narrow beams had been fixed over the sort of narrow alleyway we often see separating two houses, with some boards nailed to them and a place to sit on fitted. It was one of these boards which had fallen with Andreuccio.

When he found himself down below in the alleyway he was extremely upset at what had happened and began calling out to the boy. But, as soon as he had heard him fall, the boy had rushed to tell his mistress. She in he turn rushed into the bedroom, quickly looked to see i his clothes were there and found them. With them was the money, which, crazily, the ever suspicious Andreuccio always carried on his person. The Palermo tart, who now had what she had schemed for by turning into the sister of the visitor from Perugia, couldn’t care less any more about Andreuccio. She went promptly over to the door which Andreuccio had passed through when he fell, and closed it.

When the boy didn’t reply, Andreuccio started calling more loudly, but to no avail. He was now becoming suspicious and beginning, somewhat late in the day, to have an inkling of the trickery. He climbed on to the low wall separating the alleyway from the street and, once down on the other side, found his way to the door of the house, which he easily recognized. He stood there for a long time, vainly calling out and shaking and banging on the door. He could now see the full extent of his misfortune quite clearly, which reduced him to tears.

‘Oh, poor me,’ he began saying. ‘How little time it’s taken for me to lose five- hundred florins and a sister too!’

After a lot more of this he began again beating on the door and calling out. The result was that many people living nearby woke up and then, when the din became unbearable, got themselves out of bed. One of the lady’s female servants appeared at a window, looking all sleepy, and called out in an irritated voice, ‘Who’s banging away down there?’

‘Oh, don’t you know me?’ said Andreuccio. ‘I’m Andreuccio, the brother of Lady Fiordiliso.’

The servant replied, ‘My good man, if you’ve had too much to drink, go and sleep it off and come back in the morning. I don’t know anything about any Andreuccio or anything else you’re gabbling on about. Do us a favour please go away and let us get some sleep.’

‘What?’ said Andreuccio. ‘Don’t you really know wha I’m saying? Oh, you must do. But if family relations in Sicily are like that and get forgotten as quickly as this at least let me have back the clothes I left with you and I’ll be glad to go on my way with only the Lord for company.’

The servant almost broke out laughing.

‘Good man,’ she said, ‘I think you’re dreaming.’

And even before she finished speaking, she was back inside with the window shut.

Andreuccio was now fully aware of his losses and the pain of the realization made him so angry it almost drove him wild. He could not recover what he had lost through words and he resorted to physical violence. He picked up a big stone and began savagely beating at the door again only now with much more force. At this many of the neighbours who had been woken up and were out of thei beds started thinking that he was some no- gooder who was inventing the whole palaver to bother the good woman. When the banging got too much for them, they started calling out from their windows, as if they were the neighbourhood dogs barking all together at some stray intruder.

‘It’s an outrage,’ they said, ‘coming at this hour of night to respectable women’s houses with all this claptrap. Oh, go away, for God’s sake, and please let us sleep. If you have anything to sort out with her, you can come back tomorrow. Just don’t be such a blasted nuisance tonight.’

What they were saying perhaps encouraged the good Sicilian woman’s pimp, who was inside the house, though he had not been seen or heard till now by Andreuccio. He came to the window and in his best horrible and savage voice called out loudly, ‘Who’s that down there?’

Andreuccio looked up when he heard this and saw someone who, so far as he could tell (which was not much), had the air of a man to be taken seriously. He had a thick black beard and was yawning and rubbing his eyes, as if he’d just awoken from deep sleep.

‘I’m a brother of the lady of the house,’ replied Andreuccio nervously.

The man did not wait for him to go on.

‘I can’t think,’ he said in an even more intimidating voice than before, ‘why I’m stopping myself from coming down there and giving you such a thrashing you won’t ever move again. An irritating drunk of a donkey, that’s what you must be, not letting anyone round here get any sleep tonight.’

With that he turned back inside and bolted the window.

Some of the neighbours knew what sort of a man he was and whispered a few fearful words of advice to Andreuccio.

‘For God’s sake,’ they said, ‘go away, good man, don’get yourself murdered down there. Go away for your own good.’

Being already terrified by the ruffian’s voice and appear ance, Andreuccio saw every reason for accepting this advice, which he felt was motivated by simple goodwill He was now as dejected as anyone could be and despaired of recovering his money. He set off towards the part o the city he had come from following the servant- girl ear lier that day, aiming to get back to his inn, but with no idea of the way. Then, since the stench he could smel coming from him was disgusting, he decided to go towards the sea in order to wash himself down. But he turned leftwards and headed up a street called the Ruga Catalana, or Catalan Way. This was taking him to the higher part of the city, when he happened to see in fron two figures coming towards him with a lantern. He was afraid they might be part of the official watch, or else jus up to no good. He noticed an open building nearby and quietly crept in to try to avoid them. But it was as if they had been directed precisely to that spot. They too entered the building. One was carrying various tools round his neck, which he unloaded, and the two of them began looking the tools over and commenting on them.

At a certain point in their conversation, one of them said, ‘What can it be? I can smell the worst stink I’ve eve smelt.’ And then, lifting up the lantern a bit, they saw the miserable Andreuccio.

‘Who’s that there?’ they asked, astounded.

When Andreuccio said nothing, they came over to him with the light and asked him what he was doing there in such a repulsive state. Andreuccio told them the whole story of what had happened to him. They guessed where it could have been and said to each other, ‘It must have all happened at that villain Buttafuoco’s.’

‘My good lad,’ said one of them, turning to Andreuccio,‘you might have lost your money, but you have plenty reason for praising the Lord that you happened to have that fall and then couldn’t get back into the house. If you hadn’t fallen, you can be sure that you’d have been murdered as soon as you dropped off to sleep, and then you’d have lost your life as well as your money. But what’s the point of crying over it at this stage? You’ve as much chance of getting a penny back as of picking stars from the sky. You’re likely to end up dead if that villain hears you’ve been blabbing away.’

Then, after some conferring together, they put a proposal to him.

‘Look, we feel sorry for you,’ they said. ‘So, if you want to join us in a certain project we are en route to perform, we are of the definite opinion that your share of the profits will amount to much more than what you have lost.’

Andreuccio, in his desperate state, replied that he was ready and willing.

That day had seen the burial of a certain Archbishop of Naples called Messer Filippo Minutolo. He had been buried in elaborate finery with a ruby ring on his finge worth over five- hundred gold florins. The two of them had in mind to detach it. They explained the scheme to Andreuccio, who let greed override good sense, and the three of them set off.

Andreuccio was still giving off a strong smell as they proceeded towards the cathedral.

‘Can’t we find a way,’ said one of the two at a certain point, ‘for this companion of ours to have a wash some where to stop him stinking so horribly?’

‘Yes,’ said the other, ‘we’re near to a well now. It’s always had a pulley and a big bucket. Let’s go over and give him a quick wash.’

When they reached the well, they found the rope was there but the bucket had been removed. So they decided to tie Andreuccio to the rope and lower him into the well Once at the bottom, he would wash himself, and then when he had done, he would give the rope a shake and they would pull him up.

So they moved into action and lowered Andreuccio into the well. But it so happened that some of the nigh watch were feeling thirsty because of the heat and also because they had been chasing after someone. They were coming towards the well to get a drink when the othe two saw them, and at once took to their heels, withou any of the company coming after water seeing them Down in the well, Andreuccio, having finished washing, shook the rope a few times. The thirsty watchmen, who had now unstrapped their bucklers, their weapons and their surcoats, began pulling on the rope, believing that it was attached to a big bucketful of water.

As soon as Andreuccio saw he was near the rim of the well, he let go of the rope and grabbed hold of the rim in his hands. The sight was enough to terrify the watchmen, who immediately, without a word, let go of the rope and ran off as fast as they could. Andreuccio was profoundly startled. If he had not kept a firm hold, he would have fallen back into the well and perhaps have hurt himself badly, or even finished up dead. Once he was finally out of the well, he found the abandoned weaponry, which he knew his companions had not been carrying, and was even more amazed. Nervous, unclear what was going on, bemoaning his misfortune, he decided to take himself off without touching anything and wandered away with no idea of where he was heading. He was going along like this when he bumped into his two companions, who were coming back to pull him up out of the well. They were astonished and asked him who had actually done that. Andreuccio replied that he did not know, but gave them a full account of what had occurred and of what he had found by the well.

His companions realized what had happened and explained, laughing, why they had run away and who the people were who had pulled him up. Then, without wasting any more words since it was already midnight they all went off to the cathedral. They got in quite easily and reached the tomb, which was marble and very large They used their irons to lift the cover, which was enor mously heavy, raising it just enough for a single man to get inside, and then they propped it up.

When this was done, one of them asked, ‘Who’s going to go inside?’

‘Not me,’ said the other.

‘Nor me either,’ said the first. ‘But let Andreuccio go in.

‘I’m not doing that,’ said Andreuccio.

Both of them turned on him.

‘What do you mean you won’t go in?’ they said. ‘By God, if you don’t go in, we’ll give you a bashing round the head with one of these iron poles and that’ll be the end of you.’

This put the wind up Andreuccio. He went inside thinking to himself as he did so, ‘These two are making me enter the tomb in order to trick me. When I’ve passed them everything and am getting myself out again, they’l be off and I’ll be left with nothing.’

He decided first and foremost to pocket his own share He remembered the precious ring he had heard them discussing and, as soon as he was in the tomb, he took i off the Archbishop’s finger and put it on his own. Then he passed them the crozier, the mitre and the gloves and stripped the body down to the shirt, passing them each item, saying that was all there was. They protested tha the ring must be somewhere and told him to look everywhere. He replied that he couldn’t find it and pretended to go on looking, keeping them waiting for some time. But they were as canny as he was. They continued telling him to keep looking and then, picking their moment, they pulled away the prop supporting the lid of the tomb and ran off, leaving Andreuccio enclosed within. Anyone can guess how Andreuccio felt when he heard the lid fall.

He tried many times to push up the lid with his head and shoulders, but his efforts were useless. He was so overcome with the anguish of it all that he passed out, collapsing on the Archbishop’s dead body. And anyone who had seen the two of them would have had difficulty deciding which was the more lifeless, the Archbishop or Andreuccio. When he came to his senses, he broke into a flood of tears, foreseeing that he could not avoid one of two ends. If no one came to open the tomb, he was doomed to die of hunger and the stink among the worms from the corpse. Or else, if people came and found him inside the tomb, he would be hung as a thief.

With these bleakly distressing thoughts going round in his head, he heard movement in the church and many people talking. They were, he gathered, going to do what he and his companions had already done. This sharply increased his terror. But when they had opened the tomb and propped up the lid, they began to argue about who should go inside, which none of them wanted to do. At last, after much dispute, a priest said, ‘What are you frightened of? Do you think he’s going to eat you? The dead don’t eat people. I’ll be the one to go in.’ With this he leaned over the edge of the tomb, turned his head outwards and swung his legs inside in order to lower himself down. Andreuccio saw what was going on jumped up and seized the priest by one of his legs and made as if to pull him down inside. When the priest fel himself being pulled, he let out an enormous shriek and scrambled out of the tomb as fast as he could. This ter rified the rest of them. Leaving the tomb open, they took off as if they were being chased by a hundred thousand devils.

Seeing them go, Andreuccio clambered out of the tomb, happier than he could have hoped, and left the church by the way he had come in. It was almost dayligh as he walked off, trusting to luck, with the ring on his finger. But he reached the seafront and finished up some how at his inn, where he discovered that the merchants he had come with and the innkeeper had been worrying about him all night. He told them what had happened to him and they all opined that he should take the inn keeper’s advice and leave Naples immediately. He quickly did so and returned to Perugia, with his funds now invested in a ring, after having set out to do some horse- trading.

Ricciardo da Chinzica loses his wife

There was once a judge in Pisa with more brains than muscle called Messer Ricciardo da Chinzica, who may have thought that what worked well with his studies would satisfy a wife too. Being very rich, he was able to devote considerable time and effort to searching for a good- looking young lady to marry, whereas, if he had been able to give himself the sort of professional counsel he gave to others, good looks and youth were just what he should have run away from. And he managed it: Ser Lotto Gualandi gave him one of his daughters in marriage. She was called Bartolommea and she was one of the best- looking and most fanciable girls in Pisa, though admittedly there aren’t many there who don’t look like hairy spiders. The judge took her home with great razzmatazz, and the marriage- feast was magnificent.

When he finally geared himself up for the actual consummation, he just about brought it off. But being scrawny, wizened and not exactly spunky, next morning he had to have a glass of fortified wine, some sweet biscuits and other pick- me- ups before he could re- enter the world of the living. The experience gave the judge a bette idea of his capabilities than he had had before, and he began teaching his wife a calendar of saints’ days of the kind that schoolboys pore over looking for holidays which might have been made in Ravenna. As he now showed her, there wasn’t a day that wasn’t a saint’s day or rather every day had a multitude of them. Reverence for these demanded, as he demonstrated on various grounds, that man and woman should abstain from acts of congress. Then he threw in fasts, the four Ember days evening vigils for the Apostles and hundreds of othe saints, Fridays, Saturdays, the Lord’s Day, the whole o Lent, certain phases of the moon and endless other specia cases, no doubt assuming that the breaks from court- work he enjoyed from time to time applied just as much to women in bed. So this was how he managed things for a long time, with his wife becoming seriously depressed from being given at best a monthly treat, while he always kept a watchful eye on her just in case someone else gave her lessons about working days like the ones he had given her about saints’ days.

Since the next summer was very hot, Messer Ricciardo found himself wanting to go off to a beautiful property he had near Monte Nero, where he could relax and enjoy the air for a few days. With him he took his lovely wife To give her some entertainment while they were there one day he organized a fishing trip. The two of them sailed out on small boats to watch the spectacle, he on one with the fishermen, she on the other with some ladies. They were so captivated that they drifted several miles along the coast almost without realizing it. But while they were gazing in rapt attention, a sloop suddenly came on the scene, belonging to Paganino da Mare, a celebrated corsair of the time. Once it sighted the boats, it set a course straight for them. They were unable to get away fast enough and Paganino caught up with the boat with the ladies in it. As soon as he laid eyes on Messer Ricciardo’s beautiful wife, he stopped wanting any other booty, and whisked her into his sloop under the eyes of her husband, who was now on shore, and sailed away.

It doesn’t take much to imagine how upset the judge was by the sight, given that he was so jealous he was fearful of the very air she breathed. In Pisa and elsewhere, he started fruitlessly complaining about the criminal behaviour of corsairs, but without discovering who had carried off his wife, or where they had taken her.

When Paganino took in how beautiful she was, he felt that he was on to a good thing. Not having a wife, he thought he might hang on to her permanently and began gently soothing her tears, which were copious. He had long ago thrown away saints’ calendars and forgotten all about feast- days and holidays. That night he consoled her with some action, on the grounds that words had not helped much during the day. His consolations were so effective that the judge and his rules had gone entirely out of her head before they reached Monaco, and she began to have the time of her life with Paganino. And once he had got her there, he not only consoled her day and night, but honoured her as his wife.

After a while Messer Ricciardo got wind of the where abouts of his good lady. Ardently desiring to do something and believing that no one else could manage to do wha needed to be done, he made up his mind to go and ge her himself, being prepared to pay out any amount o money to recover her. So he set to sea and sailed to Monaco. Once there he caught sight of his wife, and she caught sight of him, as she reported back to Paganino that evening, also informing him what his intentions were When Messer Ricciardo saw Paganino the next morning he went up to him and quickly started an easy, friendly conversation with him, while Paganino pretended all the while not to recognize him and waited for him to get to the point. When he judged the moment had arrived deploying his best abilities in the most ingratiating way possible, Messer Ricciardo disclosed the reason why he had come to Monaco, begging Paganino to take as much money as he wanted and give him back the lady.

‘Sir,’ replied Paganino with a cheerful expression on his face, ‘you are very welcome here. My reply in brief is as follows: it is true I have a young woman in my house though I don’t know whether she’s your wife or someone else’s. I don’t know anything about her except what I’ve gathered from her during her stay with me. If you are he husband as you say, I’ll take you to her since you seem to me a likeable gentleman and I’m sure she’ll recognize you very well. If she says that the situation is as you say and wishes to go away with you, then, since I do love a likeable man such as you, you can give me the amount you yourself decide on for a ransom. But if the situation should be different, it would be indecent for you to try to take her from me, since I’ve got youth on my side and can hold a woman in my arms as well as any man, particularly one who is more attractive than any other girl I’ve ever seen.’

‘She certainly is my wife,’ said Messer Ricciardo, ‘as you’ll soon see if you take me to where she is. She’ll fling her arms round my neck straight away. So I won’t ask for the terms to be different from those you’ve thought up yourself.’

‘Let’s go then,’ said Paganino.

So they walked off to Paganino’s house and went into a reception- room, from where Paganino sent for her. She appeared from a chamber properly and neatly dressed and went over where Messer Ricciardo was waiting with Paganino. There she addressed only the sort of remarks to Messer Ricciardo that she might have made to any other stranger who had come with Paganino to his house. The judge, who was expecting to be given a rapturous welcome, was amazed.

‘Could it be,’ he began to wonder, ‘that depression and my protracted sufferings ever since I lost her have altered me so much that she doesn’t recognize me?’

‘Lady,’ he said, ‘taking you fishing has cost me dear No one has suffered as much as I have since I lost you and here you are seeming not to recognize me, given the unfriendly way you’re talking. Can’t you see that I’m your Messer Ricciardo, who’s come here to pay whatever sum is demanded by this fine gentleman in whose house we find ourselves, so that I can have you back and take you away from here? He’s being kind enough to restore you to me for a sum of my own choosing.’

The lady turned to him and gave him a faint smile.

‘Are you addressing me, sir?’ she asked. ‘You should check you’ve not mistaken me for somebody else. As fa as I’m concerned, I don’t recall ever seeing you before.’

‘It’s you who should check what you’re saying,’ said Messer Ricciardo. ‘Look at me properly. If you’re willing to do a little serious recalling, you’re bound to see tha I’m your very own Ricciardo da Chinzica.’

‘Sir, you’ll forgive me,’ said the lady, ‘but it’s not as right and proper as you imagine for me to give you a lengthy looking- over. All the same, I’ve looked at you enough to know that I’ve never seen you before.’

Messer Ricciardo imagined that she was acting in this way out of fear of Paganino and did not want to admi to knowing him in his presence. So, after a few moments he asked Paganino if he would be so kind as to let him speak with the lady alone in her chamber. Paganino said that he was happy to do so, on condition that he didn’start kissing her against her will. Then he told the lady to go with him into the chamber, listen to what he wanted to say and give him whatever reply she felt like.

Once the lady and Messer Ricciardo were in the chamber by themselves and had sat down, Messer Ricciardo began entreating her. ‘Oh, heart of my life, my own sweet soul, my one hope, don’t you recognize your Ricciardo, who loves you more than he loves himself? How can it be? Have I altered so much? Oh, lovely darling girl, at least give me a little look.’

The lady broke out laughing and wouldn’t let him go on. ‘You are very well aware,’ she said, ‘that I’ve not such a bad memory that I don’t know you are Messer Ricciardo da Chinzica, my husband. But you made a poor show of knowing me as long as I was with you. You’re not as wise as you want people to think you are, and you never were. If you had been, you really should have had the wit to see that I was young, fresh and frisky, and then have consequently acknowledged that young ladies require something else apart from food and clothing, though modesty forbids them to spell it out. But you know how you managed all that.

‘You shouldn’t have married, if you liked studying law more than studying your wife. Not that I thought you were much of a judge. You seemed more like a crier calling out holy days and feast- days, you knew them so well, not to mention fast- days and overnight vigils. Let me tell you that if you had given as many days off to the labourers working your lands as you did to the one who should have been working my little plot, you’d not have har vested one grain of corn. By chance I’ve met with this man here, chosen by God, because he shows a compas sionate concern for my young age. And I stay with him in this chamber, where no one knows what a feast- day is I mean those feast- days that you celebrated one afte another, piously serving the Lord in preference to the ladies. Saturdays don’t pass through that door, neithe do Fridays, vigils, Ember days or Lent, which just goes on and on. No, it’s all work, day and night, banging away all the time. As soon as the bell rang for matins this morn ing, there we were back at it, doing the same job again and again, as I know very well. So I intend to stay and work with him while I’m young, and keep feast- days and penances and fasts for when I’m old. Get out of here as soon as you can and good luck to you. Go and keep you saints’ days as much as you like without me.’

Messer Ricciardo’s distress at hearing her speak like this was unbearable.

‘Oh, sweet soul of mine,’ he said, when he realized she had finished, ‘what are you saying? Aren’t you bothered at all about your family’s honour or your own? Do you want to stay here as this fellow’s tart, living in mortal sin rather than be my wife in Pisa? He’ll get fed up with you and throw you out in total disgrace. But I’ll always hold you dear and you’ll always be the lawful mistress of my house, even if I didn’t want to be your husband. Oh please listen. Are you going to let this unbridled, immora lust make you forget your honour and forget me, when I love you more than my very life? Please, my dear love, don’t say things like that any more, just come away with me. Now that I know what you want, I’ll really make an effort from now on. So, sweetheart, change your mind, come away with me. I’ve been so miserable since you were carried off.’

‘Now that there’s nothing to be done about it,’ said the lady, ‘I don’t see how anyone apart from me can be squeamish over my honour. I just wish my family had been a bit more squeamish when they gave me to you! But since they didn’t bother about my honour then, I don’t intend to bother about theirs now. If my sin’s a mortar one, I’ll stay stuck in it like a pestle. So don’t you worry about me. And what’s more, let me tell you that I feel like Paganino’s wife here, while I felt like your tart in Pisa, what with lunar charts and geometric squarings having to align your planet and mine, while here Paganino has me in his arms all night, squeezing me, biting me, and the state he leaves me in God alone can tell you. Then you say you’ll make an effort. Doing what? Waiting for something to happen? Straightening it by hand? I can tell you’ve turned into a redoutable knight since I saw you last! Go on, do your best to come to life. But you can’t manage it. I don’t think you belong in this world, you look such a wasted, miserable little wimp. And another thing. If he leaves me – which I don’t think he’s inclined to do as long I want to stay with him – I’ve no intention of ever coming back to you. Squeeze you til you squeaked, and you still wouldn’t produce a spoonfu of sauce. That meant that when I was with you I just los out and paid out. I’m after better returns somewhere else To go back to where I started, I tell you there are no feast- days and no vigils here, where I intend to stay. So leave as quickly as you can, and the Lord be with you. I you don’t, I’ll start shouting that you’re forcing yoursel on me.’

Messer Ricciardo saw that the game was up, recogniz ing there and then the folly in marrying a young wife without the appropriate wherewithal. He left the chamber in a saddened, suffering state and spoke a lot of waffle to Paganino, which got him nowhere. In the end, he left the lady and returned empty- handed to Pisa. The blow affected his mind and, when he was walking around the city, if someone greeted him or asked him a question, he would only reply, ‘A horrid hole hates a holy day.’

It wasn’t long before he died. When Paganino heard knowing how much the lady loved him, he took her as his lawful wedded wife. Thereafter, with no thought fo holy days or vigils or Lent, they worked their patch as much as their limbs would let them, and had a wonderfu time together.

Mrs Rosie and the Priest

So, to begin, there’s a village not far from here called Varlungo, as every one of you knows or will have heard from other people. It had once a valiant priest, a fine figure of a man who served the ladies well. He was not much of a reader, but every Sunday he would spout wholesome holy verbiage beneath the churchyard elm to refresh the spirits of his parishioners. When the men were off somewhere, he would come visiting their wives more solicitously than any priest they’d had before, sometimes bringing religious bits and pieces, holy water or candle- ends into their houses, and giving them his blessing.

Now among the women of the parish he took a fancy to, there was one he particularly liked, called Mrs Rosie Hues. She was the wife of a labourer by the name of Willy Welcome, and she really was a lovely ripe country- girl, tanned, sturdy, with lots of grinding potential. She was also better than any girl around at playing the tambourine, singing songs like ‘The water’s running down my river’, and dancing reels and jigs, when she had to, waving a pretty little kerchief in her hand. With all these talents, she reduced the good priest to a quivering wreck. He would wander round the village all day trying to catch sight of her. When he realized she was in church on a Sunday morning, he would launch into a Kyrie or a Sanc tus and struggle to come over as a virtuoso singer, though he sounded more like an ass braying, whereas, when he didn’t see her there, he barely bothered to sing at all. Al the same, he was clever enough not to arouse the suspi cions of Willy Welcome or any neighbours of his.

From time to time, he would send Mrs Rosie presents in an effort to win her over. Sometimes it was a bunch o fresh garlic, since he grew the best in the region in a vege table garden he worked with his own hands, sometimes it was a basket of berries, and now and then a bunch o shallots or spring onions. When he saw his chance, he would give her a hurt look and mutter a few gentle reproaches, while she acted cold, pretending not to notice and looking all supercilious. So the estimable priest was left getting nowhere.

Now it happened one day that the priest was kicking his heels in the noontime heat out in the countryside with nothing much to do, when he bumped into Willy Wel come driving an ass loaded up with a pile of things on it back. He greeted him and asked him where he was going

‘To tell the truth, Father sir,’ replied Willy, ‘I’m off to town on a bit of business. I’m transporting these materials to Mr Notary Bonaccorri da Ginestreto to get him to aid and assist with a fiddle- faddle on the legal side that the assessor is officializing to put the whole house in order at last.’

‘That, my son, is a good thing to do,’ said the priest, full of glee. ‘Go with my blessing and come back soon. And if you should happen to see Lapuccio or Naldino, don’t let it slip your mind to tell them to bring me those straps for my threshing flails.’

Willy said he would do that and went off towards Florence, while the priest decided the time had come for him to go and try his luck with Rosie. He strode out vigorously and did not stop until he reached her house. He went in, calling out, ‘God be with us! Is anyone here?’

Rosie was up at the top of the house. Hearing him, she shouted, ‘Father, you’re very welcome. What are you doing all fancy free in this heat?’

‘God help me,’ said the priest, ‘ I’ve come to spend a little time with you, having just met your man on his way to town.’

Rosie was downstairs by now. She sat and began cleaning some cabbage seeds her husband had sifted out a short time before.

‘Well, Rosie,’ said the priest, ‘must you go on being the death of me like this?’

Rosie began to laugh.

‘Well, what am I doing to you?’ she said.

‘You’re not doing anything to me,’ said the priest, ‘but you don’t let me do what I’d like to do to you, which is love my neighbour as God commanded.’

‘Oh, get on with you,’ said Rosie. ‘Do priests do thing of that sort?’

‘Yes,’ said the priest, ‘and better than other men. And why shouldn’t we? I tell you, we do a much, much bette job. And do you know why? It’s because we let the pond fill up before the mill starts grinding. And truly I can give you just what you need, if you’ll only stay quiet and le me do the business.’

‘What do you mean, just what I need?’ said Rosie. ‘You priests are all tighter- fisted than the devil himself.’

‘I don’t know,’ said the priest. ‘Just ask me. Maybe you want a nice little pair of shoes, or a headscarf, or a pretty woollen waistband, or maybe something else.’

‘That’s all very well, Brother Priest,’ said Rosie. ‘I’ve enough of that stuff. But if you’re that keen on me, you can do me a particular favour, and then I’ll do what you want.’

‘Tell me what you’re after and I’ll be glad to do it,’ said the priest.

‘I have to go to Florence on Saturday,’ said Rosie, ‘to give in the wool I’ve been spinning and get my spinning wheel mended. If you let me have five pounds (which I know you’ve got), I’ll get the pawnbroker to give me back my purple skirt and the decorated Sunday belt I wore when I got married. You know not having it has meant I can’t go to church or anywhere respectable. And after that I’ll be up for what you want for evermore.’

‘God help me,’ said the priest, ‘I haven’t the money on me. But trust me, I’ll make sure you have it before Saturday.’

‘Oh yes,’ said Rosie, ‘you’re all great at making promises. And then you don’t keep any of them. Do you think you can treat me the way you treated Nell the Belle, who was left with just a big bass tum to play with? You’re not going to do the same to me, by God. She ended up on the game because of you. If you haven’t got it here, go and get it.’

‘Oh, please,’ said the priest, ‘don’t make me go all the way back to the house. You can tell my luck is up, and there’s no one about. It could be that when I came back someone would be here to get in our way. I don’t know when it might next stand up as well as it’s standing up now.’

‘That’s all very fine,’ she said, ‘but if you’re willing to go, go. If not, you’ll just have to manage.’

He saw that she was only going to agree to his wishes when a contract was signed and delivered, whereas he was hoping for a bit of free access.

‘Look,’ he said, ‘you don’t believe I’ll bring you the money. What about if I leave you this blue cape of mine as a guarantee? It’s a good one.’

Rosie gave him a haughty look.

‘This cape,’ she said, ‘how much is it worth?’

‘What do you mean, how much is it worth?’ said the priest. ‘Let me tell you it’s Douai cloth, double ply, maybe triple ply, and there are even people here who say it’s got some foreply in it. I paid seven pounds at Lotto’s second- hand clothes shop less than two weeks ago. It had five shillings knocked off, so it was a bargain, according to Bulietto d’Alberto, who you know is a bit of an exper in blue cloths.’

‘Oh yes?’ said Rosie. ‘God help me, I’d never have believed it. But give it to me first.’

The good priest, who was feeling hard- pressed by his loaded weapon, unfastened his cape and passed it over.

‘Well, Mr Priest,’ she said, when she’d put it away, ‘let’go down here to the shed. It doesn’t get visitors.’

So off they went. And there he covered her in the slop piest kisses in the world, introduced her to God’s holy bliss and enjoyed himself generally with her for a good while. He finally left in the uncaped state priests normally appear in only at weddings and went back to the church

There he reflected how all the candle- ends he picked up from his parishioners in the course of a year weren’worth half a fiver, and felt he had made a mistake. Now regretting leaving the cape behind, he started thinking about how to get it back at no cost to himself. Since he was quite crafty- minded, he figured out a good way o doing so. And it worked.

The next day being a feast- day, he sent the son of a neighbour of his to Rosie Hues’s house, with a reques for her to be so kind as to lend him her stone mortar since Binguccio del Poggio and Nuto Buglietti were din ing with him that morning and he wanted to make a sauce. Rosie sent it back with the boy. When it got to round lunchtime, the priest guessed Willy Welcome and Rosie Hues would be eating. He called his curate and said to him, ‘Pick up that mortar and take it back to Mrs Rosie. Tell her, “The Father is immensely grateful and would like to have back the cape the boy left with you as a guarantee.” ’

The curate went to Rosie’s house with the mortar and found her with Willy at the table eating their meal. He set down the mortar and gave them the priest’s message.

Rosie was all set to give her reply to this request for the cape. But Willy’s brow darkened.

‘So you need guarantees from our estimated father, do you?’ he said. ‘I swear to Christ, I could really give you a clout up the bracket. Go and fetch it right now, and get yourself cancered while you’re at it. And watch out for him wanting anything else of ours. He’d better not be told no, whatever it is. Even if it’s our donkey, our donkey he gets.’

Rosie got up grumbling to herself and went over to the linen- chest. She took out the cape and passed it to the curate.

‘You must give that priest a message from me,’ she said,‘Say, “Rosie Hues vows to God that you’ll never again be sauce- pounding in her mortar. That last time you didn’t do yourself any credit.” ’

The curate went off with the cape and relayed Rosie’s message to the priest, who burst out laughing.

‘You can tell her next time you see her,’ he told him‘that if she won’t lend out the mortar, I won’t lend he the pestle. The one goes with the other.’

Willy believed that his wife had spoken as she did because he had told her off and gave the matter no furthe thought. But coming off worst made Rosie fall out with the priest, and she refused to speak to him until the grape- harvest, when he terrified her by threatening to have her stuffed into the mouth of the biggest devil in hell. She made her peace with him over fermenting mus and roasting chestnuts, and after that the two of them had a good guzzle together on various occasions. To make up for the five pounds, the priest had her tambour ine re- covered and a dinky little bell attached, which made her very happy.

Patient Griselda

Years ago a young man called Gualtieri inherited the marquisate of Saluzzo as the eldest son of the family. Being unmarried and childless, he spent all his time hunting birds and beasts, without giving a thought to marriage or future offspring. He should have been considered a very wise man, but his subjects disapproved. They kept begging him to get himself a wife so that he should not die without an heir and they should not be left without a lord. They kept offering to find him one with a suitable father and mother, who would satisfy their hopes and who would make him very happy.

Gualtieri’s response was as follows: ‘My friends, you are forcing me into something I had been completely set on never ever doing, given how difficult it is to find someone with the right character and habits, how plentiful are the inappropriate candidates, and how hard life becomes for the man who ends up with someone he doesn’t get on with. You claim you can tell the daughters’ characters from how the fathers and mothers behave, and argue on that basis that you can provide me with a wife I’ll be pleased with. That is rubbish. I don’t see how you can know the fathers properly, or the mothers’ secrets for tha matter. Besides, even if you could, daughters are very often unlike their fathers and their mothers. But since you like the idea of tying me up in these chains, I’ll try to satisfy you, and, in order not to end up blaming anyone but myself if things should go wrong, I want to do the finding myself. But I tell you that if you don’t honou and respect whoever I choose, you’ll learn to your cos how hard it’s been for me to take a wife against my will just because you begged me to.’

His valiant subjects replied that they would be happy just so long as he could bring himself to get married.

Gualtieri had been impressed for a good while by the behaviour of a poverty- stricken young woman from a village near his family home. Since he also judged her to be beautiful, he calculated that life with her could be very pleasant. He looked no further and made up his mind to marry her. He had the father summoned and entered into an agreement with this complete pauper to take the gir as his wife.

That done, he called together all his friends in the area he ruled.

‘My friends,’ he said to them, ‘you have been eager fo me to make my mind up about a wife for some time. Well I have made a decision, more out of wanting to comply with your wishes than from any desire to be married on my part. You know what you promised me – that is, to be content with the woman I chose, whoever she was, and to honour her as your lady. The time has come when I am about to keep my promise to you, and when I expect you to keep yours to me. I have found very near here a young woman after my heart. I intend to make her my wife and to bring her into my house in a few days. So arrange for the marriage- feast to be a fine one and to give her an honourable welcome. In that way I shall be able to say I am happy with how you have fulfilled your promise, and you will be able to say the same about me.’

His trusty subjects all replied that they were happy with this and that, no matter who she was, they would treat her as their lady and would honour her as such in every way. Then they all set about organizing a suitably grand and joyous celebration. And Gualtieri did his part too, arranging for a sumptuous and splendid marriage- feast, to which he invited a multitude of friends, relations, great nobles and other people from the surrounding area. In addition he had beautiful, expensive dresses made to fit a young woman who, he judged, had the same measurements as the girl he had decided to marry. Not only that, but he ordered belts, rings and a lovely, costly tiara, plus everything else a new bride should have.

Soon after sunrise on the day appointed for the wedding, Gualtieri mounted his horse, and all those who had come to honour him did the same. Everything needed was now in order, and he called out, ‘Gentlemen, it is time to go for the new bride.’

After which he set off along the road to the village with the whole company. When they reached the girl’s father’s cottage, they found her hurrying back from the spring with some other women in the hope of catching sight o Gualtieri’s bride. When he saw her, he called out to he by her name – that is, Griselda – and asked her where her father was.

‘My lord,’ she replied bashfully, ‘he is in the house.’

Gualtieri dismounted and, telling everyone to wait entered the poor cottage. Inside he found the father, a man called Giannucolo, to whom he said, ‘I have come to make your Griselda my wife, but first I want to learn something from her own lips in your presence.’

What he asked her was whether, when he took her as his wife, she would do everything she could to please him would not be upset by anything he might say or do, and would be obedient, together with many other questions of this sort. She replied yes to everything. Then Gualtier took her by the hand and led her outside, where, in the presence of his whole company and everyone else, he had her stripped naked. He ordered the clothing he had had made to be brought and immediately had her dressed and shoes put on her, and a tiara placed on her hair unkempt though it was. Everyone was amazed.

‘Gentlemen,’ he said, ‘this is the person I intend should be my wife, if she wishes to have me for her husband.’

Then he turned to her, standing there bashful and awkward, and said, ‘Griselda, do you want me for your husband?’

‘Yes, my lord,’ she replied.

‘And I want you for my wife,’ he said.

With that, before everyone present, he formally married her. Then he had her set on a charger, with attendants to do her honour, and took her home. The marriage- feast was grand and fine, and the festivities no different from what they would have been if he had married the daughter of the king of France.

The young wife’s character and behaviour seemed to change with her change of clothing. As I said earlier, she had a lovely face and figure. And now to her natural good looks she added enough charm, attraction and refinement to make you think she could not possibly have been Giannucolo’s daughter and a shepherd- girl, but the daughter of some noble lord. Everyone who had known her before was astounded. What is more, she was so ready to obey and serve her husband that he considered himself the most contented and satisfied man in the world. She was similarly so gracious and kindly towards her husband’s subjects that every one of them loved her wholeheartedly and spontaneously honoured her in every way, asking God in their prayers to give her health, prosperity and greater glory still. If they used to say that Gualtieri had acted ill- advisedly in taking such a wife, now they said he was a paragon of wisdom and insight, arguing that no one else could have perceived the exceptional virtues concealed beneath the poverty of her peasant dress. Al in all, before much time had passed, she had people speaking of her good qualities and virtuous deeds throughout the marquisate and beyond, and completely turning round any negative comments about her husband that had been made when he married her.

She had not been with Gualtieri very long when she became pregnant, and in due course she gave birth to a little girl, much to Gualtieri’s delight. But a little later a strange idea came into his head. He felt a need to test her patience by inflicting unbearable torments on her over a prolonged period of time. First of all he made cutting remarks, and gave an impression of being angry with her He said that his men were badly put out by her low- class origins, all the more now that she was having children The girl- child was a particular source of resentment, and they wouldn’t stop muttering about her.

When his lady heard this, she kept her composure and gave no sign of being thrown off the virtuous course she had set herself.

‘My lord,’ she said, ‘treat me in the way that mos accords with your honour and your happiness. I shall be content with anything. I am aware I’m less than they are and that I didn’t deserve the honour you have had the generosity to bestow on me.’

Her response was warmly received by Gualtieri, who recognized that any honour that he or anyone else had paid her had not made her feel in the slightest bit superior.

A little while later, after giving his wife the general impression that his subjects couldn’t stand the little girl she had borne him, he had a word with one of the household staff and sent him to her. The man addressed her with a distressed air.

‘My lady,’ he said, ‘I am obliged to do something my lord commands me to do, if I do not wish to die. He has ordered me to take this daughter of yours and . . .’

He stopped there. Hearing his words and seeing his face, the lady recalled what her husband had been saying and deduced that he had orders to kill the child. She quickly took her from her cradle, kissed her and blessed her. For all the immense pain in her heart, she again kept her composure and put the child in the man’s arms.

‘Take her,’ she said, ‘and carry out to the letter what your lord and mine has ordered you to do. Only do not leave her for animals and birds to devour, unless he told you to.’

The servant took the child away and passed on what his wife had said to Gualtieri, who was astounded by her constancy. He then sent the servant off with the child to a female relative of his in Bologna, with a request to bring her up and educate her with the utmost care, but not to let anyone know whose daughter she was.

The next thing to happen was that the lady became pregnant again. In due course she gave birth to a male child, which pleased Gualtieri immensely. But what he had done already was not enough for him. His criticisms became sharper and sharper, and one day, his face con torted with rage, he said this to her:

‘My lady, ever since you had this boy child, I haven’been able to live with these men of mine. They are bitterly against some grandson of Giannucolo ending up thei lord after me. If I don’t want to be hounded out of here I’m afraid I’m going to have to do what I did the othe time, and then in the end I’m going to have to leave you and take another wife.’

The lady heard him out without flinching.

‘My lord,’ was all she replied, ‘think only of contenting yourself and following your own inclinations, and don’worry at all about me. Nothing matters to me excep whatever I see pleases you.’

A few days later Gualtieri sent someone for his son much as he had done as regards his daughter. After a similar show of having him murdered, he dispatched him to Bologna to be brought up there, like the little girl. Wha the lady said and showed in her face was no different from before, which stunned Gualtieri. He declared to himsel that there wasn’t a woman anywhere capable of behaving like that. If he hadn’t seen her visceral attachment to the children as long as she had his approval, he would have thought she was glad to see the back of them, but he knew that there was sense and wisdom in her.

His subjects, believing he had had his children killed strongly condemned him for his cruelty and felt nothing but compassion for the lady. When other ladies sympathized with her for having lost her children in this way, she said only that what pleased her was precisely what pleased the man who had fathered them.

Some years after the little girl’s birth, Gualtieri decided it was time to put her capacity for endurance to the ultimate test. He told many of his men that he just could not bear Griselda being his wife any more, and that it was clear to him that marrying her had been a bad juvenile error; he was now going to do all he could to obtain special dispensation from the Pope to take another wife and leave Griselda. Quite a few of his better men took him to task, but he only replied that that was how things had to be. When his lady heard the news, she found herself having to face the idea of going back to her father’s house, and perhaps tending the sheep as she had done in the past, with the added prospect of some other lady taking possession of the man to whom she had given all the love she had. She was devastated. But she had borne all the other wrongs that fortune had done her, and she set herself to bear this one with similar fortitude.

A little later Gualtieri arranged for some counterfeit letters to be sent from Rome and gave his subjects to believe that in these the Pope had given him dispensation to marry again and leave Griselda. He had her summoned and addressed her before a crowd of onlookers.

‘My lady,’ he said, ‘thanks to a special concession granted me by the Pope, I can take another wife and let you go. Since my ancestors were from the high nobility and the lords of these lands, whereas yours have always been labourers, I intend that you should no longer be my wife and should go back to Giannucolo’s house with the dowry you brought me. After that I shall marry someone I’ve found who will be appropriate for my station.’

Hearing this, the lady had to make an immense effort one beyond women’s natural capacities, in order to keep back her tears.

‘My lord,’ she replied, ‘I always knew my lowly origin in no way accorded with your own nobility. I was glad to attribute to God and to yourself the position I have enjoyed with you. I have never thought it something I had been given, or treated it as anything more than a loan. Your wish is to recover it. I must make it my wish to let you have it, and I am happy to do so. Here is the ring with which you married me. Take it. You order me to carry away with me the dowry I brought you. That’s not something for which you’ll need a banker, or fo which I’ll need a bag or a packhorse. It does not escape me that you took me in naked. If you consider it decen for that body in which I carried the children you fathered to be seen by all and sundry, I shall go away naked. Bu I beg you that you let me have some payment for the virginity that I brought here and do not take away again by allowing me, over and above my dowry, to have a sin gle shift to wear.’

Gualtieri wanted to weep more than anything else. But his face stayed as hard as ever.

‘So you go off with a shift then,’ he said.

Everyone round him begged him to make her the gift of a robe, and not let the woman who had been his wife for thirteen years or more be seen leaving his house penniless and utterly humiliated, which was what leaving in just a shift would mean. But their requests came to nothing. So it was in a shift, barefoot and bareheaded, that the lady commended them to God’s care, and walked out of her husband’s house and back to her father’s, amid the weeping and wailing of all who saw her.

Giannucolo had never been able to believe that Gualtieri really wanted his daughter as his wife, expecting every day something like this to happen, and had kept the clothes she was wearing on the morning Gualtieri married her. He brought them out and she put them on. Then she gave herself over to the menial tasks around her father’s house that she used to do in the past, valiantly bearing the savage assault that hostile fortune had inflicted on her.

Gualtieri’s next step was to pretend to his subjects that he had got himself a daughter of one of the Counts of Panago. In the course of the grandiose preparations for the marriage ceremony, he sent for Griselda to come and see him.

‘I’m bringing here as my bride,’ he said to her when she arrived, ‘this lady I’ve very recently promised to marry. My intention is to receive her with due honour when she comes here for the first time. You’re aware that I don’have ladies in the house who can spruce up the rooms and do all the things required for a festive occasion of this sort Since you know better than anyone else how this house works, sort out what needs to be done, and also invite a welcome party of ladies you think suitable, and receive them as if you were the lady in charge. Then once the marriage- feast is over, you can go back to your own house.

His words were so many knives in Griselda’s heart. She had never been able to abandon the love she felt for him in the way she had let go of her good fortune.

‘My lord, I am willing and ready,’ she said.

And so, in a makeshift dress of thick, rough cloth, she went back into the house she had left in just her shift no long before, and began sweeping the chambers and tidy ing them up, fixing hangings and drapes in the halls, and getting the kitchen ready, doing every single thing with her own hands as if she were nothing but a mere servant- girl. Nor did she stop till she had everything as neat and orderly as the occasion required.

Once she had had invitations sent out on Gualtieri’s behalf to all the ladies in the area, the only thing left fo her to do was to await the coming festivities. When the day of the wedding- feast arrived, in spite of the poor clothes she had on, she gave every one of the ladies who came a joyful and dignified welcome.

Gualtieri had taken care the children should be properly brought up in Bologna by his female relative, who had married into the house of the Counts of Panago. The girl was now twelve and the prettiest creature ever, and the boy was six. Gualtieri had written to the relative’s husband, asking him to be so good as to bring his daughter and son to Saluzzo, accompanied by an appropriate guard of honour, and to tell everyone that he was bringing the girl to be Gualtieri’s wife, with no hint to anyone of who she really was.

This gentleman did as the Marquis asked and set off with the girl, her brother and the guard of honour. After some days, around the time of the morning meal, they arrived in Saluzzo, where they found all the local people and many others from round about waiting for this new bride of Gualtieri. The girl was greeted by the ladies and entered the hall where the tables were laid out. Griselda, dressed just as she was, went towards her happily enough, saying, ‘My lady is welcome.’

The other ladies, who had repeatedly but fruitlessly begged Gualtieri either to let Griselda stay in one of the chambers or to lend her one of the robes that were once hers, so that she would not appear before the visitors looking as she did, were now assigned their places at the tables and began to be served. The girl was the object of everybody’s attention and the general view was that Gualtieri had made a good exchange. One of those who was most lavish with her praises, both of the girl and of her little brother, was Griselda.

Gualtieri thought he had now had all the proof he could want of the patience of his lady. He could tell tha it was not at all affected by events, no matter how bizarre they were, and, given the wisdom he knew was in her he was sure that dullness of mind was not a factor. He decided it was time to release her from the tortures he judged she must be suffering beneath her calm and steady exterior. He had her come forward and, before everyone who was there, gave her a smile and asked:

‘What do you think of our bride?’

‘My lord,’ replied Griselda, ‘I can only think very wel of her. If her good sense is equal to her beauty, as I believe it must be, I have no doubt that living with her will make you the most most contented lord in the world. But I beg you with all my heart not to inflict on her the sort o wounds you inflicted on the other one, the one who was your wife before. I can’t really believe that she could stand it. She’s younger, and what’s more she’s been brought up in luxury, whereas the other had spent her childhood doing hard physical work.’

Gualtieri could see that she firmly believed that the gir was going to be his wife and yet still said nothing he could disapprove of. He sat her down at his side and then spoke

‘Griselda,’ he said, ‘it is now time for you to taste the fruit of your steadfast patience and for those who judged me cruel, unjust and inhuman to acknowledge that wha I did had a deliberate purpose. I wanted to teach you to be a wife, to teach my critics how to take a wife and to keep one, and to bring about for myself unbroken peace and quiet for as long as my life with you might last. This was something I was very afraid wouldn’t happen when I first took a wife. It was to test if it were possible that I inflicted on you the wounds and torments you are all too aware of.

‘Since I have never perceived you going against my wishes in anything you have said or done, I judge that I do indeed have from you the contentment I desired. I therefore intend to restore to you in one single moment what I took from you over the years, and to apply the sweetest possible medicine to the wounds I inflicted. So now, with joy in your heart, receive this girl you think is my bride, and her brother too. These are our children that you and many others have long thought I had brutally murdered. And I myself am your husband, who loves you more than anything else. I think I can rightly and honestly boast that no other man alive can be as happy with his wife as I am.’

After this speech he put his arms round her and kissed her. He then raised her to her feet and led her, weeping for joy, over to where their daughter was sitting, astounded by what she was hearing. They tenderly embraced the two children, and then told the girl and many other people there the truth of the situation. The ladies were delighted to get up from the tables and go with Griselda into one of the chambers. Expressing hopes of a better outcome this time, they helped her out of her rough clothing and dressed her in one of her noble robes. Then they led he back into the hall a courtly lady, which even in her rags she had retained the air of being. There followed a moment of marvellous celebration with the children, and everyone showed their joy at the way things had turned out. Then they plunged into fun and merrymaking, which went on for days.

Everyone judged Gualtieri to have shown great wis dom, though they judged the tests inflicted on his lady to have been too severe, indeed intolerable. Griselda they held to have shown more wisdom than anyone.

After some days the Count of Panago returned to Bol ogna and Gualtieri took Giannucolo away from his work From then he was treated as a proper father- in- law, and lived very happily and much respected until a ripe old age. After finding a noble husband for his daughter, Gual tieri himself lived a long and happy life with Griselda and treated her with all possible honour.

What can be said here except that divine spirits descend from heaven even into poor houses and into royal houses come spirits which deserve more to look after pigs than be lords over men? Who else but Griselda could have borne the callous, unprecedented tests Gualtieri sub jected her to, not just without tears but with what looked like cheerfulness? Perhaps it would have served him righ if the woman he happened to pick had let another man shake her muff when she was driven from home in he shift, and that way got herself a decent dress.

泄密的心

对！神经质，我一直都患有严重的神经质；但是你们为什么要说我疯了呢？我的病并没有摧毁我的感觉力，没有使它变得迟钝，而是使它更加敏锐。尤其是听力异常地敏锐。我听得到天上和地下的所有声音。我听到地狱里的许多事情。试想，我怎么会是疯子呢？听吧！我来给你们把事情的来龙去脉讲一讲，看我讲得多么有条有理，心平气和。

不知道这个念头是什么时候钻进我的脑子里的；可是一旦形成，它就没日没夜地缠着我。说起来没有任何目的，也没有任何冲动的情感。我喜欢那个老头儿。他从来没有亏待过我，从来没有侮辱过我。我也不贪图他的财富。我想是他的眼睛！对，就是这个！他有一只眼睛很像兀鹰的眼——一只浅蓝色的，上面蒙着一层薄翳的眼睛。每当这目光一落到我身上，我浑身的血液就变得冰凉；因此我渐渐地很慢很慢地下定了决心，要干掉那个老头儿，从而永远摆脱那只眼睛。

要害就在这里。你们以为我疯了。疯子什么都不知道。可是你们没看到我是怎么做的。你们没看到我干得多么漂亮！那样地小心谨慎、深谋远虑，那样巧妙地掩饰！在下手的前一个星期中，我对老头儿比什么时候都好。每晚午夜时分，我悄悄拨动他的门闩，推开门——哦，动作轻极了！然后，当门缝打开到我的头可以伸进去的时候，我先把一只黑灯笼塞进去，灯笼上下封得严严实实，没有一丝光线漏出，然后我把脑袋伸了进去。哦，你要是看到我当时的那个机灵样，一定会哈哈大笑的！我的动作很慢，慢极了，生怕把老头儿从睡梦中惊醒。我用了一个钟头的时间才把整个脑袋伸进门缝，使我能看到他躺在床上。哈！——一个疯子会这样聪明吗？然后，当我的头完全伸进屋里之后，我小心地打开灯笼——哦，那么小心——小心（因为铰链会吱呀作响）。只打开那么一点，让一丝细细的光线落在那只兀鹰般的眼睛上。就这样我一连去了七个晚上，每次都在午夜时分，可是那只眼睛总是闭着的，这样我就无法干那桩事。因为惹恼我的并不是那个老头儿，而是他邪恶的眼睛。每天早晨天一亮，我就大胆地走进他的房间，勇敢地和他攀谈，亲热地唤着他的名字，问他晚上睡得可好。所以你瞧，老头儿要能想到我在每天午夜时分趁他睡着的时候窥视他的话，那他可真是老谋深算了。

第八个晚上我开门的时候特别地小心。手表的分针都比我的手动得快些。那晚我第一次感觉到了自己的力量有多大，感觉到自己是多么聪明。我几乎无法控制自己的得意。想想吧，我在那儿一点点地推门，而他做梦都想不到我秘密的行动和思想。想到这里我不禁窃笑了起来；可能听到了我的声音，床上的他突然动了一下，像是受了惊。你可能以为我会退缩——可我没有。他的房间漆黑一片，伸手不见五指（百叶窗紧紧地关着，因为怕有强盗），我知道他不会看见门开了，所以我继续稳稳地、稳稳地推动房门。

我把头伸进来了，正要打开灯笼时，我的手指不小心碰动了洋铁闩，老头儿从床上腾地坐了起来，叫道：“谁在那儿？”

我不吱声，一动不动地站着。整整一小时我一块肌肉都没动一下，同时也没有听到他躺下。他仍旧坐在床上听着；就像我自己这样，整夜整夜地，听着墙中死神守望者的声音。

不多久我听到了一声轻微的呻吟，我知道这是人在极度恐惧下发出的呻吟。它不是疼痛或悲哀的呻吟。哦，不是的！它是在不堪恐惧的重压时，从灵魂深处发出的低沉而压抑的声音。我很熟悉这种声音。许多夜晚，午夜时分，全世界都在熟睡的时候，它也会从我自己的胸中涌出，带着可怕的回音，加深了那令我不安的恐惧。我说我很了解。我了解老头儿的感受，并同情他，尽管我在心里偷偷暗笑。我知道自从听到第一声微响，他在床上翻了个身以后，他就一直没有再睡着。他的恐惧在不断地增强。他试图想象它们是毫无根据的，可是不能够。他对自己说“那只是烟囱里的风，那只是一只耗子跑过去了”或“只不过是一只蟋蟀叫了一声”。是的，他试图用这些假设来安慰自己，可是都没有用，都没用，因为死神在悄悄走近他时，已经把自己的影子投在了他的身上，把他整个笼罩了。正是这无形的影子的悲惨影响使他感到了——尽管他既没有看到也没有听到——房间中我的脑袋的存在。

我非常耐心地等了很长的时间，还没有听到他躺下，于是我决定把灯笼打开一条缝，一丝极小极小的缝。我便这么做了，你想象不出我是多么小心翼翼，小心翼翼，终于，缝隙中射出一线微光，细若蛛丝，正好落在那只兀鹰般的眼睛上。

那眼睛睁着，大大地睁着，我凝视着它，不禁火冒三丈。我对它看得一清二楚，灰暗的蓝眼珠，上面还蒙着一层可恶的薄翳，它使我骨髓发凉；可是我看不到老头儿脸上或身体的其他任何部分，我好像是本能地把光线对准了那个该死的部位。

我不是说过被你们当作疯子的人只是感觉过于敏锐吗？现在，啊，我听到了一种低低的、沉闷而急促的声音，像是一只裹在棉花里的表在响。我对这声音也很熟悉。这是那老头儿的心跳。它加剧着我的愤怒，就像战鼓激发士兵的勇气一样。即使是这样我仍然克制住了自己，静悄悄地站着，几乎连气都不出。我一动不动地举着灯笼，看自己能使光线在那只眼睛上保持得多稳。与此同时，那可怕的咚咚的心跳声在加剧，它每时每刻越来越快，越来越响。老头儿一定恐惧到了极点！它越来越响，随着时间的推移，一刻响过一刻！你听仔细了吗？我告诉过你我有些神经质，我确实是这样。半夜三更，在那座静得可怕的老房子里，这样一种奇怪的声音使我产生了无法控制的恐惧。然而，我克制着自己又待了几分钟没有动。可是那心跳越来越响，越来越响！我觉得那颗心要爆炸了。这时一种新的焦虑攫住了我，这声音会被邻居听到的！老头儿的死期到了！我一声大叫，扯开灯笼，跳进屋内。他尖叫一声，只一声。转眼我已把他拖到地上，拖过沉重的被褥压在他身上。然后我开心地微笑起来，这桩事情干完了。可是，那颗心继续沉闷地跳动了许多分钟。不过我并不为此而烦恼，隔着墙，人们是不会听到的。最后它终于停止了。老头儿死了。我搬开被子对尸体进行检查。没错，他已经死得跟石头一样了。我把手在他的心口上放了许久。没有搏动，他死得和石头一样了。他的眼睛再也不会使我心烦了。

如果你认为我疯了，那么等我讲述了我藏匿尸体时的谨慎周全之后，你就不会再这么想了。黑夜在渐渐过去，我急促却无声无息地干着活。首先我把尸体肢解了，把脑袋、胳膊和腿切了下来。

接着我抽出了三块地板，把尸体全部塞入地板中间，然后把地板重新铺好，铺得那样聪明，那样巧妙，任凭谁的眼睛——就连他的眼睛——也看不出任何破绽。没有什么需要冲洗，没有任何污迹，半点血迹也没有。我非常机警，全部都接在一只盆里了——哈！哈！

当我干完时，约莫是四点钟的光景，天仍然黑得像半夜一样。正在钟打四点的时候，大门上响起了敲门声。我怀着一颗轻松的心去开门，现在我有什么可怕的呢？进来了三个男人，十分和蔼地自我介绍说他们是警官。一个邻居在夜里听到了一声尖叫，因疑心有不轨行为，向警察局报了案，他们（这三个警官）奉命对屋子进行搜查。

我笑了，我有什么可怕的？我欢迎三位先生的来访。我说那声尖叫是我自己在睡梦中发出的。我提到那老头儿去乡下了。我领着客人视察了整幢房子。我请他们仔细地搜查。最后我把他们带到了他的房间。我让他们看他的财宝，样样安好，纹丝未动。我仗着自信头脑一热，干脆搬来了几把椅子，让他们就在这里歇一歇脚。我得意忘形，把自己的椅子正好搁在了安放死者尸体的那个地方。

警官很满意。我的态度打消了他们的疑心。我泰然自若。他们坐在那儿，我愉快地回答他们的问题，于是他们随便地闲聊起来。可是，没过多久，我感到自己脸色开始发白，希望他们快走。我的头疼了起来，耳朵里有个声音在响，可他们还坐在那里聊着。耳朵里的声音清晰起来了，它继续响着，越来越清晰。我更起劲地说话，试图摆脱这种感觉；可是它仍然在响，而且更清晰了，直到最后，我发现那声音不是在我的耳朵里。

我的脸色现在一定非常苍白，可是我更流利地说话，并且提高了嗓门儿。然而那声音更响了，我能怎么办呢？那是一种低低的、沉闷而急促的声音，很像一只裹在棉花里的表发出的声音。我喘息着，然而警官们没听到它。我更快地说话，我更激烈地说话；可那声音在不断地增强。我站起来，打着激烈的手势，提高了调门为一些小事而争论，可那声音在不断地增强。他们为什么还不走？我迈着沉重的步子在地板上走来走去，仿佛被他们的话所激怒，可那声音在不断地增强。哦，上帝啊！我能怎么办呢？我口吐白沫，我胡言乱语，我发誓赌咒！我挥舞着我坐的那把椅子，把它在地板上碾动，可是那声音高过了这一切，而且不断地增强着。它越来越响，越来越响，越来越响！那几个人仍然愉快地聊着，而且微笑着。他们会不会没有听见？万能的上帝！——不，不可能！他们听到了！——他们怀疑了！——他们知道了！——他们在讥笑着我的恐惧！——我这样想，现在也还这样想。可是什么都比这种痛苦要强！什么都比这种嘲笑要好受些！我再也受不了这种虚伪的微笑了！我感到必须要大声尖叫，或者死掉！——来来——又来了！——听啊！越来越响！越来越响！越来越响！越来越响！——

“坏家伙们！”我尖叫道，“别装了！我招认！——扯开地板！——这儿，就是这儿！——是他那颗该死的心在跳！”

厄歇尔府的倒塌

你的心是敏感的弦琴，轻轻一触便发出幽鸣。

——德·贝朗热

那年秋季的一天，整个白天愁云惨雾，死气沉沉，听不见一点声音，黑压压的乌云低悬在空中。我独自骑着马，穿过一片特别阴郁肃杀的乡村，最后当黄昏渐至，夜幕四合的时候，终于看见了那座忧郁的厄歇尔府邸。我不知道究竟是怎么回事，但当我第一眼看见那所房子，就有一种感伤之情在我心头弥漫，令我无法忍受。我说无法忍受，是因为当人们目睹自然界最荒凉萧条、最阴沉恐怖的景象时，通常会产生一种因富有诗意而令人欣慰的情愫，而此刻我的感伤却没有因这种情愫而得到丝毫解脱。我凝望眼前的这幅景象，凝望那座孤零零的房屋，以及周围纯朴的地貌风景，凝望那惨白凄凉的墙壁，凝望那像眼睛一样惆怅失神的窗户，凝望那几排熏衣草，凝望那几棵枯树的白色树干，内心感到万念俱灰，我只能把这种心境比作瘾君子服用鸦片后大梦初醒、陷入庸常生活后的痛苦以及脱去伪装面纱时的恐惧，除此之外没有任何尘世的情怀所能比拟。这是一种冷彻骨髓的感觉，是一种越陷越深的感觉，是一种心灵深处的厌憎，是一种从未体验过的恐怖意识，无论怎样百般地刺激想象力，都无法体会到任何崇高之感。是什么——我凝神静思——是什么使得我在凝视厄歇尔府邸时感到如此忧郁惆怅？这是一个无法破解的谜。而且我在沉思时无法抓住那些逼近我的阴暗朦胧的幻觉。我不得不勉强地聊以自慰地这么判定：肯定是一些十分简单的自然物体结合在一起，对我们构成了如此强烈的震撼力，而对这种力量的分析则超出了我们的理解深度。我思忖道，只要把这幅景象中的特殊物体稍做调整，把画面的细节略加修改，就足以改变甚至消灭它那令人无限忧伤的特性。为了把我的这一思想付诸实施，我勒住缰绳使马慢下步子，来到一个漆黑可怖的山中小湖的陡峭岸边。这个小湖坐落在寓所旁边，闪耀着宁静的光泽。我朝下面望去，却猛地打了一个寒噤，我看到灰色熏衣草、模样狰狞的树干和眼睛般空洞的窗户在水中扭曲的倒影，比刚才更感到毛骨悚然。

尽管如此，我还是建议自己在这座阴郁的房子里逗留几个星期。房子的主人罗德里克·厄歇尔曾经是我儿童时代的一个玩伴，但是我们已经有许多年没有见面了。不过，最近他有一封信寄给千里迢迢之外的我，其中以迫切的、不近情理的口吻，叫我务必亲自给他答复。信的手稿显示他的心情焦虑不安。写信人说到严重的身体疾病，说到一种令他忧虑的精神失常，还说到想见我一面的迫切愿望，因为我是他最亲，实际上也是唯一知心的朋友，他希望通过和我轻松愉快的交往，能够多少减轻他的疾病。他就是用这种口吻说到这些和其他许多事情的，他显然是以一片真心向我提出请求的，不允许我有半点迟疑。于是，我立刻服从了这一我仍然认为非常蹊跷的召唤。

尽管我们童年时代是十分亲密的玩伴，其实我对这位朋友了解甚少。他一向不爱说话，沉默寡言是他的习惯。不过，我知道他的渊源悠久的家族，多年以来一直因性情极为敏感而闻名。在久远的过去，这种敏感曾经通过许多杰出的艺术作品得到展现，而最近，这种敏感又通过不断慷慨而又谦逊的乐善好施得到体现，此外还有对复杂的音乐科学的全身心的热爱，这甚至超过对传统的、一目了然的美的恋慕。我还了解到这样一个惊人的事实，厄歇尔家族尽管多少年来深孚众望，但其根基上从未生长出常青不朽的枝蔓。也就是说，整个家庭代代一脉单传，除了十分个别、十分暂时的例外，总是人丁不旺。我一边思绪如潮地想着这座府邸的特色与厄歇尔的家族特征完全相符，想着在多少个漫长的世纪里，房屋可能对人产生的影响，同时想到，就是这种不足，这种也许属于次要问题的缺憾，以及由此产生的父亲将遗产和姓氏不偏不倚地传给儿子的做法，最终使得两者合而为一，把房屋原来的名字变成了“厄歇尔府”这个古怪而双关的称呼。这一称呼在使用它的庄户人看来，似乎既包含家族，又包含着家族宅屋的意思。

前面已经说过，我那多少有点孩子气的试验——在山中小湖边俯瞰——的唯一结果反倒是加深了最初的那种奇特印象。毫无疑问，我越是意识到迷信思想——为什么不能用这个词呢？——在我心中迅速泛滥，越是反而加速了它的泛滥。这就是基于恐怖的一切情感的荒谬法则，我很久以前就知道。也许正是仅仅由于这个原因，当我再次将目光从水中倒影中抬起，转而凝望宅屋本身时，心里便产生了一种奇特的幻想，这幻想是如此荒诞不经，我之所以提到它，只是为了说明当时困扰我的情感是多么鲜明强烈。我努力调动我的想象力，使自己真的相信，在这整个宅屋和领地上，笼罩着一种它们及毗邻地区所特有的气氛，这种气氛和空中的大气没有任何相似之处，它是从枯朽的古树、灰暗的墙壁和寂寞的小湖中散发出来的，是一种瘟疫般有害的、神秘诡谲的雾气，沉闷，迟滞，若隐若现，是一种沉甸甸的铅灰色。

我摆脱精神上那种如梦似幻的感觉，更加专注地审视那座宅屋的真实面貌。它最主要的特点似乎就在于极其古老。无数个岁月的风吹日晒使它剥蚀褪色。房子外部长满细小的菌类，像错综复杂的网一样，从屋檐上悬挂下来。然而，这一切绝不能算特别破败凋敝。砖石结构的每一部分都完好无损，它各个部分依然十分协调，但每块石头已渐渐碎裂，这之间似乎存在某种狂乱的、自相矛盾的东西。这不由得使我想起华而不实的老式木结构建筑：在漫长的岁月里，某个被人忽视的拱顶由于长年不通风，正在渐渐腐烂。不过，这座房屋除了外表有大面积的破败以外，整体结构丝毫没有动摇欲坠之感。也许，某个一丝不苟的观察者会发现一道几乎不易察觉的裂缝，从正面的屋顶延伸下来，蜿蜒曲折地贯穿整个墙壁，最后隐入小湖的死水中。

我注意到了这些，便骑马穿过一条短短的堤道，来到宅屋前。一位等在那里的仆人把马接了过去，我则跨入门厅哥特式的拱廊。一个男仆迈着鬼鬼祟祟的步子，一言不发地领我穿过许多黑暗而曲折的甬道，来到他主人的书房。不知怎的，一路上目之所及，竟使我刚才描述过的那种无法言说的感觉更加强烈了。尽管周围的一切——天花板上的雕画、墙壁上阴暗的挂毯、漆黑的乌木地板，以及随着我的脚步嗒嗒作响、显得鬼影幢幢的盔甲纪念品，都只是，或类似于我童年时代就已然看惯的事物——尽管迟疑着不愿意承认我对这一切是多么熟悉，我依然惊异地发现一些普通的形象竟能在人心里激起如此陌生的幻想。在一道楼梯上，我遇见了这里的家庭医生。在我看来，他的脸上是一种夹杂着卑劣狡诈和困惑茫然的混合表情。他惊惶失措地向我打个招呼，与我擦肩而过。这时男仆猛地推开一扇门，示意我进去见他的主人。

进到里面，我发现这是一个非常宽敞和高大的房间。窗户又长又窄，棱角分明，而且高高地远离乌黑的栎木地板，人在房间里根本接触不到它们。透过格子结构的窗玻璃，照射进几缕微弱的深红色的光线，使得周围几件比较突出的物体清晰可见；然而，若竭力想要看清房间里最深远的角落，或拱形的回纹饰天花板的幽秘之处，则是白费气力。墙壁上挂着黑暗的装饰布。整个房间布置铺张奢侈，古色古香，却毫无舒适之感，而且已是破旧不堪。到处散乱地放着许多书籍和乐器，却没有使整个房间增添丝毫活力。我感到自己呼吸到的是一种忧伤的气息。到处都笼罩着、弥漫着一种冷峻、幽深、无法改变的阴郁气氛。

看到我进来，厄歇尔从他平躺着的沙发上站起身来，以一种兴高采烈的热情招呼我。我起初认为，这种热情中包含着许多做过了头的亲热劲儿——是一个厌世者在强颜欢笑。但是，当我一眼瞥见他的面容时，才相信他的热情完全发自内心。我们坐了下来，他有片刻没有说话，我便带着一种半是怜悯半是惊惧的心情凝视着他。确实，从未见过有人像罗德里克·厄歇尔这样，在如此短的时间内，产生了如此触目惊心的变化！我好不容易才强迫自己承认，眼前的这个男人就是我孩提时代的玩伴。不过，他的面部特征倒一直都很鲜明独特。他脸如死灰，大大的眼睛泪汪汪的，放射出无与伦比的光芒；嘴唇略微薄了一点，没有一丝血色，但曲线轮廓却精美绝伦；鼻子是典雅的希伯来式，但鼻孔极为宽大，这在类似的鼻形中是十分少见的；下巴线条精致，轮廓并不突出，这说明了他在精神上缺少活力；头发柔软、纤细，酷似蛛网。这些面部特征，再加上天庭极为饱满宽阔，使他的模样令人难以忘怀。此刻，他的面部特征和一贯流露的神情，只比过去略微显著一些，却使他产生了如此惊人的变化，我简直怀疑是不是在跟他说话。最令我震惊甚至恐惧的，是他此刻死一般惨白的脸色，和他此刻眼睛里放射出的奇异的光芒。柔软如丝般的头发，主人无暇以顾，任其杂乱无章地生长着，丝丝缕缕的细发不是垂落下来，而是在面颊上随意流淌，我尽管拼命努力，也无法把这种奇异的面部表情与正常的人的概念联系起来。

我立刻就注意到我这位朋友的一举一动都颠三倒四，很不协调；很快，我发现这是由于他在吃力地克制一种惯性的痉挛——一种极度的神经焦虑，却又怎么也克制不住。对他的这副模样，我倒是有心理准备，一是因为读了他的来信，二是因为对他童年时的某些特征记忆犹新，三是因为从他与众不同的体质和脾性可以得出这样的结论。他的动作一会儿充满生机，一会儿垂头丧气。他的声音也瞬息多变，忽而吞吞吐吐、闪烁其辞（这时他身体里的元气似乎一时荡然无存），忽而又干脆有力、斩钉截铁——嗓音果断、沉着，掷地有声，听起来似乎不太真实，那种沉稳、镇定、被运用得游刃有余的喉音，只有神志恍惚的醉鬼，或是不可救药的烟鬼在极度兴奋、神魂颠倒时，才能发得出来。

他就是用这种口吻谈到他邀我前来的目的，说他诚心地盼着我，希望我给他提供安慰。他还颇为细致地谈到他自认为他的病情属于何种性质。他说，那是一种先天性的家族遗传病，他对药物治疗已经不抱任何希望。接着他又补充说道，这只是一种神经性疾病，不久自会痊愈。该病的症状是他经常出现大量离奇古怪的感觉。他详细叙述这些感觉，其中一些令我既感到有趣，又感到疑惑，尽管这也许是他说话时的措辞和口气在起作用。一种病态的神经过敏使他备受折磨；他只能吃最寡淡无味的饭菜；只能穿某一种面料的衣服；所有鲜花的芬芳都令他窒息；他的眼睛即使在微弱的光线下也刺痛难忍；而且，只有一些特殊的声音和弦乐器奏出的音响，他听了才不会感到心惊胆寒。

我看出来，他完全陷于变态的恐惧中不能自拔。“我要死了，”他说，“我一定会在这可悲的疯狂感觉中送命。就那样，就那样死去，不会有别的出路。我对将来要发生的事情感到害怕，倒不是害怕这些事情本身，而是害怕它们带来的后果。一想到任何意外，哪怕是最微不足道的小事，都会令我这敏感焦虑的心灵受到震撼，我就感到不寒而栗。说实在的，我倒不怕灾祸，怕就怕灾祸带来的绝对后果，它使我胆战心惊。在这种惶惶不可终日的状态下，在这种凄惨可悲的处境下，我感到那个时刻迟早都会到来，我定会在与恐惧这个狰狞幻影的一次抗争中，彻底放弃我的生命和理智。”

此外，我还不时从他那吞吞吐吐、含义模糊的暗示中，发现了他精神状态的另一个奇怪特征。他内心纠缠着许多迷信想法，都是关于他多年居住、从不敢擅自离开的那幢府邸——关于一种影响力，而他在谈到他所想象的这种影响力的能量时用词晦涩，使我在此无法复述——他说，由于常年忍受这幢府邸的形状实质上的某些特异之处，使他的精神受到了某种影响，那灰墙、塔楼，以及它们倒映其中的那一湖幽暗的死水，这所有的景象最终对他的生存状态产生了一种影响。

不过，他虽然犹疑再三，还是承认说，这种令他痛不欲生的异样的忧郁情绪，多半可以追溯到某个更合乎情理、更明白显见的根源。那是因为他心爱的妹妹，他多少年来唯一的伴侣，他在世上仅存的亲人，长时间来一直重病缠身，实际上已经眼看着奄奄一息了。“她一旦死去，”他说道，那口气里的酸楚令我难以忘怀，“这古老的厄歇尔家族就剩下我一个人（一个孤苦无望、精神脆弱的人）。”他正说着，玛德琳小姐（别人就是这样称呼她的）从房间的尽头慢慢走过，根本没有留意我的存在，就兀自隐去了。我凝视着她，突然产生一种极度的惊诧，甚至还夹杂着一些恐惧。但是要解释这种感觉所为何来，我却不能办到。我的目光追随着她离去的背影，心里感到一阵恍惚。最后，房门在她身后关上，我不由自主、迫不及待地转眼去看她哥哥的神情，然而他已用双手将脸紧紧捂住，我只能看见他那瘦骨嶙峋的手指显得比平时更加苍白，一行行冲动的泪水从指缝间滚落。

玛德琳小姐的病早就使那些医生束手无策。不可改变的冷漠倦怠，日渐消瘦的身体，再加上尽管转瞬即逝，却时常都要发作的强直性昏厥症，这些便是她的种种反常症候。她一直顽强地同病魔抗争，始终不甘心就此一病不起。但在我到达这里的当天晚上夜色渐浓时（她的哥哥在夜里失魂落魄地告诉我），她最终屈从于死神的淫威。我这才知道，我目送她背影的那匆匆一瞥，也许就是我见到她的最后一眼——那位小姐，至少在她弥留的时候，我是不会再见到她了。

在随后的几天里，厄歇尔和我都绝口不提她的名字。在此期间，我一直真心诚意地想法减轻我朋友的伤悲。我们一起绘画，一起读书，或者我就聆听他即兴弹奏他那把如泣如诉的吉他，宛若在梦境一般。这种朝夕相处，使我们越来越亲密，也使我越来越深入地了解他的内心世界，使我越来越痛苦地看出无论我怎样千方百计地鼓励他振作起来、摆脱忧郁，都是枉费心机，毫无结果。仿佛有一种与生俱来、根深蒂固的痛苦，像一道不死的幽光一样，把他精神世界和物质世界的一切笼罩得一片昏暗。

我就这样独自陪伴厄歇尔府的主人度过了许多忧郁凝重的时光，这是我永生难以忘怀的。但是，我却说不清楚他缠着我、领着我读的是些什么书，做的是些什么事。一种极度亢奋、完全失常的胡思乱想，使一切都蒙上了一层硫黄的微光，他即兴奏出的大段大段的挽歌，将永远在我耳畔回响。其中，我格外痛楚地记得，他对冯·韦伯的那首狂放的《最后的华尔兹》做了奇特的变异和夸张。他凭借他精巧的想象构思的一幅幅画面，在他的笔触下变得模糊不清，令我不寒而栗，而我因为不知道自己为何颤抖，就更感到格外恐怖。这些绘画（如今历历在目，依然鲜明），尽管我费尽心机，也只能表达出原本就属于书面语言范畴的那一小部分。他用极为简单的构图，用完全袒露的笔触，吸引和震慑着别人的注意力。如果世上曾经有人把思想绘诸笔端，那个人一定是罗德里克·厄歇尔。至少对于处在当时那种环境中的我来说，看到这位抑郁症患者企图在画布上表现的纯粹抽象的东西，我就感到一种难以忍受的强烈的恐惧，以前我在端详富塞利那些色彩十分艳丽但造型过于具体的幻想构图时，也未曾有过这种恐惧的感觉。

在我这位朋友的那些幻影幢幢的构图中，有一个倒是不那么绝对抽象，可以勉强用文字描述一个大概。这是一幅小画，描绘了一个其长无比的矩形地窖或隧道的内部，内壁低矮，光滑，呈白色，没有间断，也没有装饰。从画面上的某些陪衬物可以看出，这个洞穴处于地底深处。长长的地道无限延伸，四周不见一个出口，也没有火炬和其他人造光源；但是却有一道耀眼的强光滚过整个空间，使一切沐浴在诡谲可怖、突兀怪异的光辉之中。

我在上文已经提到他病态的听觉神经，一切音乐都令他无法忍受，只有用弦乐器奏出的某些曲调例外。也许，正是因为他只能局限于摆弄吉他，所以才弹得那么如梦似幻，空灵怪诞。但是他那些即兴曲的狂热流畅，却不能归结于这个原因。他的狂想曲的那些音符，那些歌词（他经常一边弹琴，一边即兴唱出押韵的歌词），都肯定是，也确实是他情绪镇静、精神集中时的产物，而我前面已经委婉地提到，这种现象只有在他拼命强颜欢笑时才会出现。我很容易就记住了其中一首狂想曲的歌词。也许，他当初弹唱这支曲子时给我的印象最为强烈，因为我幻想自己从那潜在、隐秘的含义中第一次觉察出，厄歇尔已经充分意识到他那高高在上的理智正摇摇欲坠。这首《闹鬼的宫殿》的歌词大致如下，也许记录得并非完全准确：

一

幽幽溪谷一片绿色葱茏，

曾有仁慈天使聚居其中，

还有一座宫殿气势恢宏——

金碧辉煌，傲然耸向苍穹。

在“思想”统治的国度里，

那座宫殿挺拔屹立！

就连展翅高飞的仙女，

也从未领略如此的美丽。

二

黄色的旗幡金光夺目，

在宫殿屋顶迎风飘舞，

（这一切的一切皆成虚无，

归于一去不返的远古）

在往昔甜蜜的岁月里，

阵阵微风在欢闹嬉戏，

沿着宫殿那粉白的墙壁，

有一缕幽香悠然飘去。

三

游子来到美丽的溪谷，

透过两扇明亮的窗户，

看见精灵们翩翩起舞，

和着琵琶柔美的旋律；

中间有个帝王气宇轩昂，

威严端坐在宝座之上！

他威风凛凛，通体辉煌，

俨然是一副国君之相。

四

珍珠美玉闪耀着光芒，

镶嵌在华丽的宫殿门上，

一群群回声你来我往，

在宫门间穿梭、飘荡，

回音女神的唯一职责，

就是唱出甜蜜的颂歌，

用曼妙绝伦的歌喉，

赞美帝王的足智多谋。

五

但是有恶魔身披黑衣，

闯入帝王高贵的领地；

（呜呼哀哉，帝王命毙！

让我们祝他永远安息）

昔日王宫的荣华富贵，

嫣红姹紫的夺目光辉，

如今随光阴一去无回，

宛若梦境萦绕在心扉。

六

如今游人来到这溪谷，

透过一扇扇猩红的窗户，

但见一些怪影狂野无主，

随着杂乱的旋律狂舞；

一群青面獠牙的鬼影，

像地狱之河湍急阴森，

穿过惨白无光的宫门，

不见笑容，只闻狂笑阵阵。

我清楚地记得，这首歌谣的意蕴曾引得我浮想联翩，厄歇尔的某个想法就在其中体现出来。我之所以提到这个想法，倒不是因为它新颖别致（其他人也有过类似的想法），而是因为厄歇尔始终对它执着不移。这种看法一般说来，就是认为花草树木皆有灵性。但是，在他狂乱的想象里，这种想法变得更加放纵，在某种特定的情况下竟拓展到了无机物的领域。我无法用语言来表达他对这一信条是何等执着，何等痴迷。但正如我前文所暗示的，他的信念与他祖先留下的这幢灰石房子有关。他想象着，那种灵性就具体表现在那些石头的排列顺序以及它们的安排规律上，在覆盖其上的大量苔藓上，在四周枯立的古树上，尤其表现在那种布局的永恒不变、始终如一之中，表现在那一湖死水的倒影之中。他说，在湖水和石墙周围逐渐凝聚着一团雾气，这便是证明——是那种灵性的证明，我听到这里，感到大为吃惊。他又补充说道，从那种寂然无声却又挥之不去的可怕的感染力上，可以见到那种灵性造成的后果，多少个世纪以来，这感染力主宰着他们家族的命运，并使他变成眼前这副模样——我所看到的这副模样。对这类看法无须评论，我也不想妄做评论。

正如人们所能猜到的，我们读的书与这种幻想十分吻合，许多年来，这些书对病人的精神状态起了不小的作用。我们一同聚精会神地研读格雷塞的《翠鸟》和《修道院》，马基雅弗利的《魔鬼》，斯韦登堡的《天堂和地狱》，霍尔堡的《尼古拉·克里姆地下旅行记》，罗伯特·弗拉德、让·汤达日涅和德·拉·尚布尔各自所著的《手相术》，蒂克的《蓝色的旅程》，康帕内拉的《太阳城》。我们最喜欢的一本书是多明我会[1]教士艾梅里克·德·吉罗尼所著的八开本《宗教法庭手册》；而读了庞波尼乌斯·梅拉的有关古代非洲森林神和牧羊神的一些章节，厄歇尔经常会如痴如梦地呆坐几小时。不过，他最感兴趣的是一本极其珍贵的四开本哥特体孤本奇书——一座被湮没教堂的祈祷手册——《在马因斯教会礼堂追思亡灵》。

那天晚上，当厄歇尔突然告诉我玛德琳小姐已然过世，并说他打算把尸体先在府邸的一个地窖中存放十四天之后再安葬时，我便不由自主地想起这本奇书中的荒唐仪式，以及它可能对这位忧郁症患者造成的影响。但是，他采取这一奇特做法也有其世俗的原因，我觉得不便贸然提出反对。他告诉我，他之所以这么决定，是考虑死者的病情不同一般，考虑到她那些医生会提出某些唐突的、刨根究底的疑问，还考虑到家族墓地偏僻荒凉，无人照看。当时我回想起我刚到厄歇尔府邸的那天，我在楼梯上遇见的那个人脸上的一副阴险表情，所以就无意反对他的做法，我认为这至少是一个没有害处、绝不算违背情理的防备措施。

应厄歇尔的请求，我亲自帮助他安排临时的入殓工作。尸体已经装入棺材，我们俩单独把它抬到停放处。停放尸体的那个地窖已经多年没有打开，我们的火把差点被令人窒息的空气熄灭，这使我们无法把里面查看清楚。只记得那个地窖窄小、潮湿，没有一点缝隙，透不进一丝光线，深深地埋在地下，上面正是我睡觉的那个房间。看来，在遥远的封建时代，那地窖曾被当作牢房，后来又作为贮存火药及其他易燃物品的地方，因为一部分地板和我们经过的整个长长的过道都仔细包裹着黄铜。那扇厚重的铁门也曾受到同样的保护。铁门因为沉重，在铰链上旋转时发出异常刺耳的吱嘎声。

在那可怕的地窖里，我们把令人悲伤的棺材放在架子上，稍稍掀开尚未钉上的棺盖，瞻仰死者的遗容。我第一次注意到他们兄妹二人长得极为相似。厄歇尔大概看出了我的心思，喃喃地解释了几句，我这才知道他和死者是孪生兄妹，彼此之间有着一种简直难以理解的心灵感应。然而，我们的目光却不敢在死者身上久留，因为看了不免心生恐惧。疾病就这样夺去了这位妙龄女子的生命，她像所有强直性晕厥症患者一样，胸口和脸上泛着一抹似真似假的红晕，一缕令人生疑的微笑在她唇角逗留不去，看上去十分可怕。我们把棺盖重新盖好，钉上钉子，然后关好铁门，迈着沉重的步伐，回到几乎和地窖同样阴暗凄凉的地面。

在度过几个悲痛欲绝的日子之后，我的朋友精神错乱的一些特征出现了显著的变化。平常的那副举止消失不见了。平常所做的事情也被他搁置一边或忘到脑后。他迈着慌慌张张、踉踉跄跄的步子，漫无目的地从一个房间徘徊到另一个房间。苍白的脸色变得更加惨白吓人，而眼里的光芒却熄灭无踪了。以往那种不时沙哑的嗓音不再听到；现在他的声音习惯性地颤抖不停，仿佛内心充满极度的恐惧。确实，有的时候，我认为他那终日惶恐不安的心里藏着某个令他窒息的秘密，他正在拼命积蓄足够的勇气，把它吐露出来。而有的时候，我又不得不把这一切当成莫名其妙的疯狂的胡思乱想，因为我看见他一连几小时两眼聚精会神地凝视空茫，仿佛在倾听冥冥之中的某个声音。也无怪他的这副状况令我害怕，令我也受到感染。我觉得他那种荒诞癫狂、动人心魄的迷信，正在缓慢而明确地潜入我的心头。

尤其是在我们把玛德琳小姐放置在地窖七八天后的一个深夜，我躺在床上更为真切地体会到这种情绪的影响。我辗转反侧不能入睡，而时间却在一小时一小时地流逝。我拼命排解，想驱散盘踞在我心头的紧张不安。我强迫自己相信，我的紧张多半（如果不是全部）是由于房间里沉闷的家具对我产生了令人惶惑的影响——由于那暗淡破旧的帷幔，随着即将来临的风暴的吹动，在墙上来回摆动，摩擦着床上的装饰布，发出骚乱不安的窸窸窣窣的声音。但是我的排解无济于事。一阵难以抑制的战栗渐渐传遍我的全身，最后，一种噩梦一般的无名的恐惧占据了我的心房。我喘着气，挣扎着摆脱出来，从枕头上抬起身子，仔细凝视漆黑一片的房间，屏息倾听——我不知道为何倾听，除非是受到本能驱使——倾听某种低微而模糊的声音，它在风暴暂停的间歇响起，却不知道从何处传来。我被一种不可名状、难以忍受的极度的恐惧所震慑，慌忙穿上衣服（我感到那天夜里我不能再睡了），开始在房间里匆匆地踱来踱去，努力想使自己摆脱那凄楚可怜的境地。

我就这样来回踱了几圈，突然附近楼梯上传来一阵轻微的脚步声，引起了我的注意。我很快听出这是厄歇尔的脚步声。紧接着，他轻轻敲了敲我的房门，端着一盏灯走了进来。他的脸色和平时一样惨白，但眼睛里却闪耀着一种疯狂的喜悦——一举一动都带着显然经过压抑的歇斯底里。他的这副神情令我毛骨悚然——但是，比起我独守长夜那份孤独来，什么都是好的，我甚至把他的光临看作缓解我孤独的救星。

“怎么，你还没有看见？”他一声不吭地四下盯视片刻，突然说道，“你还没有看见？——啊，等一等，你会看见的。”他一边说着，一边仔细把灯遮上，然后匆匆走到一扇窗户跟前，猛地将它推开，迎向外面的风暴。

一阵猛烈的强风刮进来，差点吹得我们站不稳脚跟。这一夜虽然狂风呼啸，却是异常美丽，是一个奇特的、交织着恐惧和美丽的夜晚。一股旋风显然已在附近聚集起力量，因为风向不时发生剧烈变化；沉重的乌云低低垂悬，仿佛压向府邸的塔楼；乌云尽管浓重，我们仍能看见云块从四面八方涌来，带着充沛的活力挤压碰撞，却并不飘向远方。我是说乌云尽管浓重，我们仍能看见这幅景象，但却不见月亮和星星，也不见闪电的影子。但是在大团大团翻滚涌动的云雾下面，在我们附近地面上的一切物体上面，闪耀着一种微弱而又清晰的雾气散发出的奇异的白光，这雾气笼罩着宅屋，像裹尸布一样把它覆盖。

“你不能看！你绝不能看！”我战战兢兢地对厄歇尔说，一边轻轻用力把他从窗口拖到一张椅子上。“这些使你迷惑的景象不过是普通的电光现象，也许是由于那小湖中瘴气弥漫所形成的。我们关上窗户吧。空气寒冷，对你的身体没有好处。这里有一本你最喜欢的传奇小说，我来念，你听着，我们就这样共同度过这个恐怖的夜晚吧。”

我随手拿起的那本旧书是劳斯洛特·坎宁先生所著的《疯狂的宴会》，我称它为厄歇尔最爱读的书，不过是无奈中的一句言不由衷的调侃。因为说实话，这本书语言粗俗，想象贫乏，故事拖沓，我这位品味高雅、精神世界丰富的朋友是不会对它感兴趣的。然而，当时手头只有这么一本书，我怀有一种侥幸心理，希望那些搅得这位忧郁症患者惶恐不安的激动情绪，能在我所读的荒唐透顶的故事中得到缓解（精神错乱的病史上有许多类似的奇特病例）。确实，如果我当时能从他听故事（或表面上在听）时那副紧张压抑的狂喜上做出判断，我就真可以庆幸自己妙计得逞了。

我已经读到人们所熟悉的那一段情节，宴会的主人埃瑟尔雷德千方百计想和平进入隐士的居所，却始终没有成功，便开始靠武力强行闯入。记得书里是这样叙述这段情节的：

埃瑟尔雷德性情本就刚烈勇猛。加之畅饮后酒性发作，就更加气势逼人，他不再同那顽固不化的歹毒隐士多费口舌。这时他感到雨点落在他的肩头，担心暴风雨就要来临，立时抡起钉头槌，狠狠砸了几下，转眼将门板凿了个窟窿，再把套着臂铠的胳膊伸进去，使劲一拉，那扇门顿时四分五裂，木板折断破裂时发出干

燥空洞令人心惊胆寒的声音，在森林里久久回荡。

念完这最后一句，我猛吃一惊，停住了。我仿佛听到（尽管立刻断定是我情绪激动产生的幻觉）——我仿佛隐隐约约地听到——从府邸中某个偏僻的角落传来一个声音，听上去和劳斯洛特先生格外详细描写的那破门的回声极为相似，只是更加沉闷、模糊。毫无疑问，正是这种巧合吸引了我的注意。在窗框啪嗒啪嗒的撞击声和外面一阵紧似一阵的狂风呼啸声中，这声音实在不算什么，不会使我感兴趣，也不会使我惶恐不安。我继续把故事念下去：

好汉埃瑟尔雷德破门而入后，却不见那个歹毒隐士的踪影，这使他既恼怒又惊讶。却只见一条满身鳞片、口吐火舌的巨龙，镇守着一座黄金建造、白银铺地的宫殿，墙上挂着一副闪闪发光的铜盾，上面镌刻着两行铭文：

进宝殿者成霸主；

屠巨龙者赢盾牌。

埃瑟尔雷德高高抡起钉头槌，一下击中龙头。龙头滚落在他脚下，喷出一口毒气，发出一声令人发指的尖厉刺耳的惨叫，埃瑟尔雷德只好用双手捂住耳朵，这声音实在是撕心裂肺，前所未闻。

念到这里，我又猝然停住，心中大为愕然——这次再也无法怀疑了。我确确实实听见（尽管我发现我很难说出这声音来自何方）一个微弱、遥远，但却尖厉刺耳的惨叫声或摩擦声，悠长不绝，诡谲离奇——我读着书中的描写，心里已然想象出巨龙的那声石破天惊的惨叫，而耳边听到的这个声音，正跟我的想象不差分毫。

这个无比怪异的声音，这种最最离奇的巧合，自然使我心头产生无数种互相矛盾的感觉，直压得我喘不过气来，其中最令我不堪忍受的是极度的惊愕和恐惧，但我仍然保持着足够的镇静，以免出言不慎，刺激了我这位朋友敏感的神经。我不敢肯定他是否听见这些声音，不过在刚刚几分钟内，他的举止确实发生了奇怪的变化。他原来坐在我对面，现在却已将椅子慢慢挪开，面对房门坐着。这样一来，我只能看到他脸的局部，只见他双唇颤抖不已，仿佛在无声地喃喃自语。他的脑袋耷拉在胸口，但我知道他并没有睡着，从侧面也能看到他两眼大睁，一眨不眨。他身体的动作也证明他没有睡着，他一直在不停地轻轻左右摇晃。我把这一切看在眼里，继续念劳斯洛特先生的故事，情节如下：

却说那好汉摆脱了巨龙的魔爪，猛然想到墙上的铜盾，想到要打破上面所附的魔咒，于是他搬开挡在前面的巨龙尸体，英勇无畏地踏过城堡的白银地面，走向挂着铜盾的那面墙壁。可实际上，没等他来到墙边，铜盾就掉落在他脚边的白银地面上，发出一声可怕的巨响，震耳欲聋。

我刚刚念出这几个字，仿佛在那一刹那，真的有一面铜盾重重摔落在白银地面上一样——我听到一阵金属撞击的声音，清晰，空洞，却又显得沉闷压抑。我大惊失色，一跃而起；厄歇尔却依旧坐在椅子里晃来晃去。我冲到他的椅子跟前，只见他双眼怔怔地凝视前方，整个表情像石头一般僵硬。但是，当我把手放在他的肩头时，他浑身一阵剧烈的震颤，嘴唇哆嗦着露出一个惨笑。我看见他颤抖着喃喃自语，声音又低又急，仿佛不知道我就在跟前。我弯腰向他靠近，终于听见了他话里的可怕含义。

“现在听见了吧？——是的，我听见了，我早就听见了。好久——好久——好久——好几分钟，好几小时，好几天以前，我就听见了——可是我不敢——哦，可怜可怜我吧，我是多么可怜啊！——我不敢——我不敢说啊！我们把她活埋啦！我不是说过我感觉敏锐吗？现在我告诉你，她在空洞洞的棺材里最初发出的微弱响动我都听见了。我听见了——好多好多天以前——可是我不敢——我不敢说啊！现在——今天夜里——埃瑟尔雷德——哈！哈哈！——撞破隐士的房门，巨龙临死的惨叫，盾牌落地的巨响——唉，那还不如说是她棺材的劈裂声，她牢房里铁铰链的摩擦声，和她在包着黄铜的地窖走廊里拼命挣扎的声音！啊！我逃到哪里去呢？她不是很快就会上这儿来吗？她不是正在匆匆赶来责备我行事仓促？我不是已经听见她的脚步踏上楼梯？我不是已经听出她的心脏在沉重而可怕地跳动？疯子！”说到这里，他疯狂地一跃而起，仿佛拼足了全身的气力，尖声怪叫着说：“疯子！我告诉你，她此刻就站在门外！”

似乎他那蕴含超凡力量的叫喊中真的有一股魔力，只见他用手指着那道宽大古老的房门，在刹那间，那两扇沉重的乌木门扉竟然徐徐打开了。这一定是狂风将它吹开的。但是，就在那两扇门外，果真站着厄歇尔家玛德琳小姐那体形高大、裹着尸衣的身影。她那白色的尸衣上血迹斑斑，瘦骨嶙峋的身体的每一部分都有苦苦挣扎过的痕迹。她浑身颤抖着，摇摇晃晃地站在门槛上，然后，随着一声低幽的呜咽，重重地跌进屋来，倒在她哥哥身上，一阵剧烈的、临终前的挣扎，把他也拖拽到地上，成为一具死尸，成为他曾经预料过的恐怖的牺牲品。

我吓得魂飞魄散，逃离了那个房间，逃离了那座宅屋。当我穿过那古老的堤道时，风暴仍然在疯狂肆虐。突然，沿着堤道射来一道耀眼的光芒，我转过身来，想看看这种不同寻常的光芒从何而来，因为我的身后只有那高大的府邸和它的影子。原来光芒来自那一轮正在西沉的血红色的满月，月光鲜明地照亮了我前文中提到的那道原来不易察觉的，从屋顶弯弯曲曲延伸至墙脚的裂缝。就在我凝视的时候，这道裂缝迅速变宽，随着一阵旋风呼啸着吹过，那轮圆满的红月亮赫然呈现在我眼前，我头晕目眩地看到宅屋那高大的墙壁纷纷坍塌，耳边传来一阵骚乱的喊叫。经久不息，仿佛十万个浪头在翻滚咆哮，而我脚下那黑暗幽深的小湖，沉闷地、寂无声息地淹没了已成碎石瓦砾的“厄歇尔府”。

[1] 多明我会，又名布道兄弟会，为天主教四大托钵修会之一，1215年由西班牙托钵修士圣多明我（约1170—1221）创立。——译者注

一桶白葡萄酒

福图纳托对我一而再再而三的伤害，我都能忍就忍了，可是他竟然敢侮辱我，我便发誓要报仇雪恨了。你这么了解我的脾气禀性，肯定知道我不会公开发出威胁。我最后必定要报仇雪恨，这是板上钉钉的事——但是报仇绝不能带来任何风险，这也是确凿无疑的。我不仅要惩罚对方，还要让自己不受惩罚。如果修正错误的人受到惩罚，那错误就得不到修正。如果复仇者没有让自己感觉到已经惩罚了做坏事的人，那错误也得不到修正。

你必须明白，我在语言和行为上，都没有给福图纳托任何理由来怀疑我的善良愿望。我继续按我的老习惯冲他微笑，他没有看出，我现在的笑容里藏着置他于死地的想法。

这位福图纳托老兄有一个弱点——在其他方面他倒是个令人尊敬甚至让人害怕的男人。他很为自己在葡萄酒方面的鉴赏力感到得意。意大利人很少具有真正的大师气质。在大多数情况下，他们的热情都只是逢场作戏，骗骗那些英国和美国的百万富翁。在绘画和宝石的领域，福图纳托跟他的同胞一样，是个江湖骗子，但是在陈年佳酿的问题上，他的态度十分认真。我在这方面跟他没有本质的区别——我本人对意大利葡萄酒也很精通，只要有可能就大量地购买。

话说，这是嘉年华到达癫狂顶峰的一个傍晚，我和我的朋友不期而遇。他过分热情地跟我搭话，因为他当时已经喝了不少。这家伙身上的衣服像个大杂烩。紧身的条纹衫，头上是一顶圆锥形的帽子，上面还挂着许多小铃铛。我见到他太高兴了，紧攥着他的手怎么也不肯松开。

我对他说：“亲爱的福图纳托，碰到你真是太巧了。你今天看上去气色很不错。我得到了一大桶好货，据说是阿蒙蒂亚多白葡萄酒，但我对此心存疑虑。”

“怎么会？”他说，“阿蒙蒂亚多？一大桶？不可能！而且是在嘉年华期间！”

“我心存疑虑，”我回答道，“当时我头脑发昏，没有征求一下你对此的看法，就按阿蒙蒂亚多的价钱付了全款。我那时候找不到你，又担心丢了一笔好买卖。”

“阿蒙蒂亚多！”

“我心存疑虑。”

“阿蒙蒂亚多！”

“我必须让他们满意。”

“阿蒙蒂亚多！”

“既然你有事在身，我这会儿正要去找卢切里西，有评论家天赋的人非他莫属。他会告诉我——”

“卢切里西根本分不清阿蒙蒂亚多酒和雪利酒。”

“可是有些傻瓜竟然说他的品位跟你不相上下。”

“快，我们走吧。”

“去哪儿？”

“去你的地下室。”

“不行，我的朋友。我不能因为你脾气好就强人所难。我看出你有应酬。卢切里西——”

“我没有应酬——快走吧。”

“我的朋友，不行啊。不是因为应酬，是我发现你正遭受重感冒的折磨。而地下室里潮湿得令人无法忍受。墙壁上都结了硝石。”

“我们还是走吧。感冒没什么大不了的。阿蒙蒂亚多！你准是受骗上当了。至于卢切里西，他根本就分不清雪利酒和阿蒙蒂亚多。”

这么说着话，福图纳托一把抓住了我的胳膊。我戴上一个黑色丝绸面罩，用一件短披风把身体紧紧裹住，他一个劲儿地催着我去我的豪华寝宫。

家里没有侍者，他们都逃出去过节，去寻欢作乐了。我跟他们说过我要次日早晨才回来，我还明确地命令他们不许离开家门。我心里很清楚，这些命令能有效地保证他们全都在我刚一转身就消失得无影无踪。

我从他们的烛台上拿了两根蜡烛，递了一根给福图纳托，前倨后恭地领他穿过几个套间，走向通往地下室的那道拱门。我走下一条长长的旋转楼梯，请求他跟上时多加小心。最后，我们来到了楼梯底部，一起站在蒙特雷索尔地下墓穴的潮湿的地面上。

我朋友的步子踉踉跄跄，帽子上的铃铛随着他的脚步叮叮作响。

“那桶酒。”他说。

“还得再往前走一点，”我说，“可是，你仔细看看这些洞穴墙壁上的亮晶晶的网状物。”

他转向我，盯着我的眼睛，他两个浑浊的眼球上渗出了迷醉的泪水。

“硝石？”他终于问道。

“硝石。”我回答道，“你那样咳嗽多久了？”

“喀！喀！喀！……喀！喀！喀！……喀！喀！喀！……喀！喀！喀！……喀！喀！喀！”

我可怜的朋友发现他好几分钟没法儿回答我的话。

“没关系。”他最后说道。

“走，”我果断地说，“我们回去吧，你的健康最宝贵。你富有，受人尊敬，受人景仰，受人爱戴。你是幸福的，就像我曾经一样。你是一个不可或缺的人。至于我嘛，根本不值一提。我们回去吧。你会生病的，这个责任我可负不起。而且，还有卢切里西——”

“够了，”他说，“咳嗽根本不算什么，要不了我的命。我不会因为咳嗽而丢了性命。”

“不错——不错，”我回答道，“其实，我也并没打算毫无必要地让你感到紧张——但是你应该保持适当的谨慎。喝一口这种梅多克红葡萄酒吧，它能帮助我们抵抗潮湿。”

说到这里，我从放在地面上的一长排酒瓶里抽出一瓶，敲掉了它的瓶颈。

“喝吧。”我说着，把葡萄酒递给他。

他乜斜着眼睛，把酒端到唇边。他顿了顿，冲我亲切地点了点头，那些铃铛发出叮叮的声音。

“我敬这些在我们周围安息的死者。”他说。

“我祝你长命百岁。”

他又一次抓住我的胳膊，我们继续往前走。

“这些地下室，”他说，“规模很大。”

“蒙特雷索尔，”我说，“是一个庞大的、人丁兴旺的家族。”

“我忘记你们的纹章是什么了。”

“一只巨大的金色人脚，底色是天蓝色。人脚踏碎了一条凶猛的蛇，蛇牙扎进了脚后跟。”

“铭词是什么？”

“凡伤我者必受惩罚。 ”[1]

“很好！”他说。

葡萄酒在他眼睛里闪烁，那些铃铛叮叮作响。我自己的想象也因梅多克红葡萄酒而有了温度。我们经过长长的墙壁，墙边堆着骷髅，大大小小的酒桶混杂其间，然后我们进入地下墓穴的最深的凹处。我又停了下来，这次冒昧地抓住了福图纳托一只胳膊的肘部上面。

“硝石！”我说，“看见了吗？越来越多了。像青苔一样挂在拱顶上。我们是在河床的下面了。湿气凝成的水珠在骨头间流淌。快，趁现在还来得及，我们回去吧。你的咳嗽——”

“那不算什么，”他说，“我们继续往前走吧。但是先给我再来一杯梅多克葡萄酒。”

我停住话头，给他拿了一瓶“坟墓诱惑”。他一饮而尽。他的眼睛里闪着灼热的光。他哈哈大笑，把酒瓶往上一扔，那姿势我看着有点奇怪。

我惊讶地看着他。他又做了一遍那个动作——十分怪异。

“你不懂吗？”他说。

“不懂。”我回答。

“看来你不是兄弟会的。”

“这怎么讲？”

“你不是瓦匠会的。”

“我是，我是，”我说，“我是瓦匠会的。”

“你？不可能！你是瓦匠？”

“我是瓦匠。”我回答。

“给个证明，”他说，“给个证明。”

“这就是。”我回答，从短风衣的褶皱中掏出一把泥刀。

“你开玩笑。”他惊叫道，向后退了几步，“不过，还是让我们继续去找阿蒙蒂亚多吧。”

“好的。”我说，把泥刀塞回短风衣下面，又让他挽住我的胳膊。他把沉重的身体靠在我胳膊上，我们继续前进，去寻找阿蒙蒂亚多。我们经过一连串低矮的拱门，往下，继续往前，再往下，来到一个很深的地下墓穴，里面浑浊的空气使我们的两根蜡烛不再燃烧，只发出一点微弱的亮光。

在地下墓穴的最远端，出现了另一个面积较小的墓穴。四壁堆着人类的遗骨，依照巴黎的地下墓穴的式样，一直堆到上面的拱顶。这个内部墓穴，三面墙都按这种风格装饰。第四面墙的遗骨坍塌了下来，乱七八糟地倒在地上，在某一处形成了相当大的一堆。因为遗骨的坍塌，我们看见墙里面是另一个内部墓穴或密室，深约四英尺，宽三英尺，高六七英尺。它似乎本身没有什么特殊的用途，只是在两根巨大的柱子之间形成了间隔，这两根柱子和其他柱子一起支撑起整个地下墓穴的顶部，密室的后部是坚实的花岗岩围墙。

福图纳托举起手里黯淡的蜡烛，努力想窥探这间密室的深处，可是没有成功。烛光太微弱了，我们无法看清密室的尽头。

“继续往前，”我说，“阿蒙蒂亚多就在这里面。那个卢切里西——”

“他是个无知的人。”我的朋友打断了我的话，继续踉踉跄跄地往前走，我立刻紧紧地跟上。一眨眼，他就来到了密室的尽头，发现被岩石挡住，没法儿再往前走了，他就一脸迷惑，呆呆地站在那儿。片刻之后，我就把他拴在了花岗岩上。花岗岩的表面有两个U形铁钉，在同一高度，相距大约两英尺。一个铁钉上挂着一根短短的链条，另一根铁钉上有个挂锁。我把链条从他的腰部甩过去，只用了几秒钟就把锁牢牢地锁住了。他完全被惊呆了，根本无力抵抗。我拔出钥匙，从密室里退了出来。

“把你的手，”我说，“放在墙上，你会忍不住摸那些硝石。这里确实非常潮湿。我再一次恳求你回去。不回？那么我必须果断地离开你了。但是我首先必须尽我所能对你表示一些关注。”

“阿蒙蒂亚多！”我的朋友突然喊道，还没有从他的惊愕中醒过神来。

“没错，”我回答道，“阿蒙蒂亚多。”

我一边说这句话，一边让我自己置身于前面说过的那堆尸骨中间。我把尸骨拨拉到旁边，很快就发现了大量的建筑石料和砂浆。我在那把泥刀的帮助下，开始充满干劲地用这些材料堵塞密室的入口。

我刚砌好第一层石料，就发现福图纳托的醉意大大地消退了。关于这点，我得到的最初迹象是密室深处传来一声低低的、呻吟般的喊叫。这不是一个醉汉的喊叫。在这之后是很长时间的顽强的沉默。我砌上第二层石料，然后是第三层、第四层，然后我听见链条在剧烈地摇晃。这声音持续了几分钟，在这期间，我停下手头的活儿，坐在那些尸骨上，让自己听得更加心满意足。最后，金属的碰撞声平静下来，我重新拿起泥刀，一口气砌完了第五层、第六层和第七层石料。现在石墙差不多到我胸口了。我又停下来，把蜡烛举到石墙上方，让几道微弱的亮光投向里面的那个身影。

一连串响亮而凄厉的尖叫，突然从那个被链条拴住的人影的嗓子里发出，像一记重拳把我打了回来。在那短短的一瞬间，我迟疑了，我颤抖了。我拔出我的长剑，开始用它在密室里探索，可是突然一个闪念，使我放下心来。我把手放在地下墓穴坚实的墙体上，心里感到很踏实。我再一次走近石墙，对那个拼命吵闹的人的叫嚷做出回答。我重复他的喊叫，给他推波助澜，在音量和力度上都超越他的喊声。我这么做了之后，里面的喊叫声就平静了下来。

时间已是午夜，我的任务快要完成了。我已经砌完了第八层、第九层和第十层石料。第十一层是最后一层，我也砌好了一部分，现在只要把最后一块石头填进去，再抹上砂浆，就大功告成了。我挣扎着搬起沉重的石料，把它的一部分塞进那个注定的位置。然而，此时从密室里传来一声低笑，吓得我头发都竖了起来。低笑之后，一个悲哀的声音说话了，我好不容易才辨认出那是高贵的福图纳托的声音。只听那声音说道：

“哈！哈！哈！嘿！嘿！嘿！真是一个很有意思的恶作剧——一个精彩的玩笑。我们可以在寝宫里喝着葡萄酒——嘿！嘿！嘿！——拿这件事情笑个够了——嘿！嘿！嘿！”

“阿蒙蒂亚多！”我说。

“嘿！嘿！嘿！……嘿！嘿！嘿！……没错，阿蒙蒂亚多。不过时间是不是很晚了？他们，福图纳托夫人和其他人，会不会在宫殿里等我们？我们离开吧。”

“好的，”我说，“我们离开吧。”

“为了上帝的爱，蒙特雷索尔！”

“是的，”我说，“为了上帝的爱！”

可是我没有听到对我这句话的回答。我失去了耐心，大声喊道：“福图纳托！”

没有回答。我再次喊道：“福图纳托！”

还是没有回答。我把一根蜡烛伸进最后那个缺口，让它落了下去。里面只传来一阵叮叮的铃铛声。我感到心里难受，这都是地下墓穴的潮湿造成的。我匆匆把手头的活儿干完。我把最后一块石料用力塞进去，用砂浆把它抹平。我把那些古老的尸骨重新垒在新砌的石墙边。半个世纪以来，没有一个活人过来打扰过它们。愿死者的灵魂安息！

[1] 原文为拉丁语。——译者注

吻

五月二十日傍晚八点钟，某炮兵后备旅的所有六个连，到露营地去的途中，在梅斯捷奇金村停下来过夜。他们那儿乱哄哄，有的军官在大炮四周忙碌，有的军官会合在教堂围墙附近的广场上听设营官讲话，这时候忽然从教堂后边闪出一个穿便服的男子，骑着一匹奇怪的马。那匹浅黄色的小马生着好看的脖子和短短的尾巴，一步步走过来，然而不是照直走，却像是斜着溜过来，踩着一种细碎的舞步，仿佛有人用鞭子抽它的腿似的。骑马的人走到军官们面前，抬了抬帽子说：

“本地的地主，陆军中将冯·拉别克大人请诸位军官先生马上赏光到家里去喝茶……”

马低下头，踩着舞步，斜着身子往后退去。骑马的人又抬了抬帽子，一刹那间，跟他那匹奇怪的马隐到教堂后面，不见了。

“鬼才知道这是怎么回事！”有几个军官嘟哝道，他们正在散开，要回到自己的住处去，“大家都想睡觉了这位冯·拉别克却要请人喝什么茶！什么叫作喝茶，我们心里可有数！”

所有六个连的军官们都清楚地记得去年的一件事在阅兵期间，他们跟一个哥萨克团的军官们，也像这样受到一位伯爵地主——一位退伍军人的邀请去喝茶。那位好客、殷勤的伯爵款待他们，请他们吃饱、喝足之后不肯放他们回到村里的住处去，却把他们留在自己家里过夜。所有这些当然都很好，简直没法儿希望更好的了然而糟糕的是那位退伍军人有这些年轻人做伴，高兴得过了头。他对军官们讲他过去的光辉事迹，领他们走遍各处房间，给他们看名贵的画片、古老的版画、珍奇的武器，给他们念大人物的亲笔信，一直忙到太阳东升那些疲乏厌倦的军官看着，听着，一心想睡觉，小心地对着袖口打呵欠。临了，主人总算放他们走了，可是要睡觉已经太迟了。

也许这个冯·拉别克就是这种人吧？是也好，不是也好，反正也没办法了。军官们换上整齐的军服，把周身收拾干净，成群结伙地去找那个地主的家。在教堂附近的广场上，他们打听出来要到那位先生的家可以沿着下面的路走——从教堂后面下坡到河边，沿着河岸走到一个花园，顺一条林荫路走到那所房子；或者走上面的路也成——从教堂照直顺着大路走，在离村子不到半俄里[1]的地方就到了地主的谷仓。军官们决定走上面的路。

“这个冯·拉别克是什么人？”他们一面走一面闲谈，“就是从前在普列夫纳统率H骑兵师的将领吧？”

“不，那人不叫冯·拉别克，单叫拉别克，没有冯。”

“多好的天气啊！”

大路在第一个谷仓那儿分成两股：一股照直往前去，消失在晦暗的暮色里；另一股往右去，通到主人的房子。军官们往右拐弯，讲话声音开始放低……路的两边排列着红房顶的石砌谷仓，笨重而森严，很像县城里的营房。前面，主人宅子的窗子里灯光明亮。

“好兆头，诸位先生！”有一个军官说，“我们的猎狗跑到大家前头去了。这是说，他闻出我们前头有猎物了！……”

中尉洛贝特科走在众人前面，他生得又高又结实可是没长唇髭（他已经过二十五岁了，可是不知什么缘故他那保养得很好的圆脸上却连一根胡子也没有），善于远远地辨出前面有女人，因此在这个旅里以这种嗅觉出名他扭转身来说：

“对了，这儿一定有女人。我凭本能就觉出来了。”

冯·拉别克本人在正屋门口迎接军官们，他是一位仪表优雅、年纪大约六十岁的老人，穿着便服。他跟客人们握手，说他见到他们很高兴，很幸福，可是诚恳地请求军官先生们看在上帝的分上原谅他不留他们过夜有两个带着孩子一起来的姐妹、几个弟兄、几个邻居来看望他，弄得他一个空房间也没有了。

将军跟每个人握手、道歉、微笑，可是凭他的脸色看得出他绝不像去年那位伯爵那么高兴接待这些客人他之所以邀请这些军官，只是因为他觉得这是一种必要的礼节罢了。军官们自己呢，走上铺着柔软的毡毯的楼梯一面听他讲话，一面觉得他们之所以受到邀请，也只是因为他不好意思不请他们罢了。他们看见听差们匆匆忙忙点亮楼下门道里和楼上前厅里的灯，觉得他们好像随身把不安和不便带进了这个宅子。既然已经有两个带着子女的姐妹、弟兄、邻人大概由于家庭的喜事或者变故而聚会在这所房子里，那么十九个素不相识的军官的光临会受到欢迎吗？

到了楼上，在大厅门口，军官们遇到一位身材高大、匀称的老太太，长脸上生着黑眉毛，很像厄热尼皇后[2]。她殷勤而庄严地微笑着，说她看到客人很高兴，很幸福，道歉说她丈夫和她这回不能够邀请军官先生们在这里过夜。每逢她从客人面前扭转身去办点什么事，她那美丽、庄严的笑容立刻就消失了。那么，事情很清楚：她这一辈子见过很多军官，现在她对他们不感兴趣，即使她邀他们到家里来，而且表示歉意，那也只是因为她的教养和社会地位要求她这样做罢了。

军官们走进一个大饭厅，那儿已经有十来个人，男男女女，老老少少，坐在长桌的一边喝茶。在他们的椅子背后可以隐约看见一群男人笼罩在雪茄烟的轻飘的云雾里，他们当中站着一个瘦长的青年，正在谈论什么，他留着红色的络腮胡子，讲英国话，声音响亮，可是咬字不清。这群人的背后有一扇门，从门口望出去可以看见一个明亮的房间，摆着淡蓝色的家具。

“诸位先生，你们人数这么多，简直没法儿跟你们介绍了！”将军大声说，极力说得很快活，“自己介绍吧诸位先生，不要客气！”

军官们有的带着很严肃的，甚至很严厉的脸相，有的现出勉强的笑容，大家都觉得很别扭，就好歹鞠一个躬坐下来喝茶。

其中觉得最别扭的是里亚博维奇上尉。他是一个戴眼镜的军官，身材矮小，背有点伛偻，生着山猫样的络腮胡子。他的同伴们有的做出严肃的神情，有的露出勉强的笑容，他那山猫样的络腮胡子和眼镜却好像在说“我是全旅当中顶腼腆、顶谦卑、顶没光彩的军官！”起初他刚走进饭厅以及后来坐下喝茶的时候，无论如何也不能够把注意力集中在一张脸或者一个东西上。那些脸衣服、盛着白兰地的玻璃长颈酒瓶、杯子里冒出来的热气、有着雕塑装饰的檐板，这一切合成一个总的强大印象在里亚博维奇心里引起不安，使他一心想把脑袋藏起来他像第一回当众表演的朗诵者一样，虽然瞧见他眼前的一切东西，可是对看到的东西却不十分理解，按照生理学家的说法，这种虽然看见然而不理解的情况叫作“意盲”。过了一会儿，里亚博维奇渐渐习惯新环境，眼睛亮了，就开始观察。他既是一个不善于交际的、腼腆的人，那么首先引起他注意的就是他自己最不行的，也就是他那些新相识的特别大胆的人。冯·拉别克，他的妻子，两位上了岁数的太太，一位穿淡紫色连衣裙的小姐，一个留着红色络腮胡子的青年（冯·拉别克的小儿子），仿佛事先排演过似的，很灵敏地夹在军官们当中坐好，立刻热烈地争论起来，弄得客人不得不插嘴。那位穿淡紫色衣服的小姐热烈地证明，做炮兵比做骑兵或者步兵轻松得多，冯·拉别克和上了岁数的太太们的看法则相反。紧跟着，大家七嘴八舌地谈起来。里亚博维奇瞧着淡紫色小姐十分激烈地争辩她所不熟悉的完全不感兴趣的事情，冷眼看出她脸上时而现出不诚恳的笑容，时而把笑容又收敛起来。

冯·拉别克和他的家人巧妙地把军官们引进争论中来，同时一刻也不放松地盯紧他们的杯子和嘴，注意他们是不是都在喝茶，是不是茶里都放了糖，为什么有人不吃饼干或者不喝白兰地。里亚博维奇看得越久，听得越久，他就越喜欢这个不诚恳的可是受过很好训练的家庭。

喝完茶以后，军官们走进客厅。洛贝特科中尉的本能没有欺骗他，客厅里果然有许多小姐和年轻女人。“猎狗”中尉不久就站在一个穿黑色连衣裙、年纪很轻的金发女郎身旁，神气十足地弯下腰来，仿佛倚着一把肉眼看不见的军刀似的，微微笑着，风流地耸动肩膀。他大概在讲些很有趣味的荒唐话，因为金发女郎带着鄙夷的神情瞧着他那保养得很好的脸，淡漠地问一句：“真的吗？”猎狗倘若乖巧一点，从这不关痛痒的“真的吗”应该可以推断出她未必喜欢这样的猎狗。

钢琴响了，忧郁的华尔兹舞曲从大厅里飘出敞开的窗口，不知什么缘故大家都想起来窗外现在是春天，五月的黄昏，人人都觉出空中有玫瑰、紫丁香、白杨的嫩叶的香气。在音乐的影响下，里亚博维奇喝下的那点白兰地正在起作用。他斜眼看着窗口，微微地笑，开始注意女人们的动作。他觉得玫瑰、白杨、紫丁香的气息好像不是从花园里飘来，而是从女人的脸上和衣服上冒出来的。

冯·拉别克的儿子请一位瘦弱的姑娘跳舞，跟她跳了两圈。洛贝特科在镶木地板上滑过去，飞到淡紫色小姐面前，带着她在大厅里翩翩起舞。跳舞开始了……里亚博维奇站在门旁，夹在不跳舞的人们当中，旁观着他这一辈子从没跳过一回舞，他的胳臂也从没搂过一回上流女人的腰。一个男人当着大家的面搂着一个不认得的姑娘的腰，让那姑娘把手放在自己的肩头，里亚博维奇看了总是很喜欢，可是他无论如何也不能想象自己会成为那样的男人。有些时候他嫉妒同伴们胆大、灵巧，心里很难过。他一想到自己胆小、背有点伛偻，没有光彩，腰细长，络腮胡子像山猫，就深深地痛心。可是年深日久，他也就习惯了，现在他瞧着同伴们跳舞，大声说话，不再嫉妒，光是觉得感伤罢了。

等到卡德里尔舞开始，小冯·拉别克就走到没跳舞的人们跟前，请两位军官去打台球。军官们答应了，跟他一块儿走出客厅。里亚博维奇没事可做，想参加大家的活动，就慢腾腾地跟着他们走去。他们从大厅里出来，走进客厅，然后走过一个有着玻璃顶棚的窄过道，走进一个房间。他们一进去，就有三个带着睡意的听差从沙发上很快地跳起来。小冯·拉别克和军官们穿过一长串房间，末后走进一个不大的房间，那里有一张台球桌子。他们就开始打台球。

里亚博维奇除了打纸牌以外从没玩过别的东西，他站在台球桌旁边，冷淡地瞧着打台球的人。他们呢，解开上衣扣子，手里拿着球杆走来走去，说俏皮话，不断地嚷出一些叫人听不懂的词。打台球的人没注意他，只是偶尔有谁的胳臂肘碰着他，或者一不小心，球杆的一头戳着他，才扭转身来说一声：“对不起！”第一局还没打完，他就厌倦了，开始觉得他待在这儿是多余的，而且碍人家的事了……他想回到大厅里，就走出去了。

在回去的路上，他遇到一桩小小的奇事。他走到半路上，发现自己走错了地方。他清楚地记得在路上应当遇见三个带睡意的听差，可是他穿过五六个房间，那几个带着睡意的人好像钻到地底下去了。他发觉自己走错了，就扭转身退回一小段路，往右转弯，走进了他到台球房间去的时候没见过的一个昏暗的房间。他在那儿站了一会儿，犹豫不决地打开一扇他的眼睛偶然看见的门走进一个漆黑的房间。他看见前面，正对面有一道门缝从那道缝里射进一束明亮的光。门外面传来隐隐约约的忧郁的玛祖卡舞曲的声音。这儿也跟大厅里一样，窗子敞开，有白杨、紫丁香和玫瑰的气味……

里亚博维奇迟疑地站住……这当儿，他出乎意料地听见匆匆的脚步声、连衣裙的沙沙声、喘吁吁的女人低语声：“到底来了！”有两条柔软的、香喷喷的、准定是女人的胳膊搂住他的脖子，温暖的脸颊贴到他的脸颊上来，同时发出了亲吻的声音。可是那个亲吻的人立刻轻轻地惊叫了一声，抽身躲开他，而且里亚博维奇觉得她是带着憎恶躲开的。他也差点儿叫起来，就向门边的亮光跑过去……

他回到大厅里，心怦怦地跳，手抖得厉害，他连忙把手藏到背后去。起初他羞得不得了，生怕满大厅的人知道他刚刚被一个女人搂抱过、吻过。他畏畏缩缩，不安地往四下里看，可是等到他相信大厅里的人们跟先前一样平静地跳舞、闲谈，他就完全让一种生平从没经历过的新感觉抓住了。他起了一种古怪的变化……他的脖子刚才给柔软芳香的胳膊搂过，觉得好像抹了一层油似的。他左脸上靠近唇髭、经那个素不相识的人吻过的地方，有一种舒服的、凉酥酥的感觉，仿佛擦了一点薄荷水似的。他越是擦那地方，凉酥酥的感觉就越是厉害。他周身上下，从头到脚充满一种古怪的新感觉，那感觉越来越强烈……他情不自禁地想跳舞、谈话、跑进花园、大声地笑……他完全忘了他的背有点伛偻，他没有光彩，他有山猫样的络腮胡子，而且“貌不惊人”（这是有一回他偶然听到几个女人在谈到他的相貌时所用的形容词）。正巧冯·拉别克的妻子走过他面前，他就对她亲切而欢畅地笑一笑笑得她站住了，探问地瞧着他。

“我非常喜欢您这所房子！……”他说，正了一下眼镜。

将军的妻子微笑着，说这房子原是她父亲的。后来她问起他的父母是否还在世，他在军队里待得是不是很久，为什么他这么瘦……她的问题得到答复后，她便往前走去。他跟她谈过话以后，他的笑容比先前越发亲切他觉得他的四周尽是些好人……

进晚餐的时候，里亚博维奇漫不经心地吃完给他端来的所有菜，自管喝酒，什么话也没听进去，极力要弄明白他方才遇到的究竟是怎么一回事。这件奇事具有神秘的、浪漫的性质，可是要解释却也不难。一定是有个姑娘或者太太跟别人约定在那个黑房间里相会。她等了很久，又烦躁又兴奋，竟把里亚博维奇当作她的情人了尤其因为里亚博维奇走过那个黑房间的时候迟迟疑疑地站住，仿佛也在等什么人似的，那么这就更近情理了……里亚博维奇就照这样解释他何以会受到那样的一吻。

“不过她是谁呢？”他瞧了瞧四周女人的脸想道，“她一定年轻，因为老太太是不会去幽会的。而且她是个受过教育的女人，这只要凭她衣服的沙沙声、她的香气、她的声调，就可以揣摩出来……”

他的目光停在淡紫色小姐的身上，他很喜欢她。她有美丽的肩膀和胳膊、聪明的脸、好听的声音。里亚博维奇瞧着她，希望那个不相识的女人就是她，而不是别人……可是她笑起来不怎么真诚，而且皱起她的长鼻子，这就使他觉得她显老了。然后他掉过眼睛去瞧那个穿黑色连衣裙的金发女郎。她年轻些，朴素些，真诚些，两鬓秀气，端起酒杯喝酒的样子很潇洒。现在里亚博维奇希望那个女人是她了。可是不久他又觉得她的脸平平常常，就掉过眼睛去瞧他身旁的那个女人……

“这是很难猜的，”他暗想，沉思着，“如若只要淡紫色小姐的肩膀和胳膊，再配上金发女郎的两鬓和洛贝特科左边坐着的那位姑娘的眼睛，那么……”

他暗自把这些东西搭配起来，就此凑成了吻过他的那个姑娘的模样。他希望她有那样的模样，可是在饭桌上又找不到。

晚餐以后，军官们酒足饭饱，精神抖擞，开始告辞和道谢。冯·拉别克和他的妻子又开始道歉，说是可惜不能留他们过夜。

“诸位先生，跟你们见面很高兴，很高兴！”将军说，这一回倒是诚恳的（大概因为人们在送走客人的时候总比在迎接客人的时候诚恳得多，也和蔼得多），“很高兴！希望你们回来路过的时候再光临！别客气！你们怎样走？你们要走上面的路吗？不，穿过花园走吧，下面那条路要近一点。”

军官们走出去，到了花园里。从充满亮光和喧闹声的地方走出来，花园里显得十分黑暗而宁静。他们沉默地一路走到花园门口。他们都有点醉意，兴致很好，心满意足，可是黑暗和静寂使他们沉思了一会儿。大概他们每个人都有着一种跟里亚博维奇相同的感触：将来是不是有一天他们也会像冯·拉别克一样有一所大房子一个家庭、一个花园，即使本心并不诚恳，也能欢迎人们来，请他们吃得酒醉饭饱，使他们心满意足呢？

他们一走出花园门外，就开始争着讲话，无缘无故地大笑。他们现在顺小路走着，那条小路通到下面河边然后沿着河岸向前伸展，绕过岸上的矮树丛、沟渠、枝条垂在水面上的柳树。河岸和小路都看不大清，对岸完全沉没在一片漆黑中。黑色的水面上这儿那儿映着星星它们颤抖着，破碎了，只凭这一点才能推断河水流得很急空中没有一丝风。河对岸有些带着睡意的麻鹬在悲凉地鸣叫，在这边岸上一个矮树丛里有一只夜莺一点也不理会这群军官，仍然在放声歌唱。军官们在矮树丛四周站了一会儿，拿手指头碰一碰它，可是夜莺仍旧唱下去。

“这家伙可真了不得！”他们赞许地叫道，“我们站在它旁边，它却一点也不在乎！好一个坏蛋！”

在道路的尽头，小路爬上坡去，在教堂的围墙附近跟大路会合了。军官们爬上坡，累了，就在这儿坐下，点上纸烟。河对面现出一块暗红色的光亮。他们反正没事可做，就花了不少工夫推断那是野火呢，还是窗子里的灯亮，还是别的什么东西……里亚博维奇也瞧那亮光，他觉得那一块光在向他微笑，䀹眼，仿佛它知道那一吻似的。

里亚博维奇回到驻营地，赶快脱掉衣服，上了床。洛贝特科和美尔兹里亚科夫中尉（一个和气而沉静的人，在他那伙人中被看作很有学问的军官，他一有空就老是看《欧洲通报》，这份杂志他随便到哪儿去都随身带着）跟里亚博维奇住在同一所农民的小木房里。洛贝特科脱了衣服，带着还没玩畅的神情在房间里走来走去，走了很久，随后打发勤务兵去买啤酒。美尔兹里亚科夫上了床，在枕头旁边放一支蜡烛，专心看那份《欧洲通报》。

“她是谁呢？”里亚博维奇瞧着被烟熏黑的天花板暗想。

他的脖子仍旧好像涂了油似的，嘴角旁边也仍旧带点凉意，仿佛擦了薄荷水一样。淡紫色小姐的肩膀和胳臂穿黑衣服的金发女郎的两鬓和诚恳的眼睛、柳腰、衣服胸针，在他的想象中闪动着。他极力注意这些形象，可是它们跳动着，逐渐变得模糊起来，摇曳不定。等到这些影子在每个人一闭上眼睛就会看见的宽阔的黑色背景上完全消失，他就开始听到匆忙的脚步声、衣裾的沙沙声亲吻的响声，一种没来由的、强烈的欢乐就涌上他的心头……他正在尽情享受这种欢乐，却听见勤务兵回来报告，说是没有啤酒。洛贝特科气得要命，又开始走来走去

“嘿，是不是蠢货？”他不断地说，先是在里亚博维奇面前站住，后来又在美尔兹里亚科夫面前站住，“连啤酒都买不着，真是个十足的蠢货，笨蛋！对不对？嘿恐怕是个坏蛋吧？”

“在这一带当然买不到啤酒。”美尔兹里亚科夫说眼睛却没离开《欧洲通报》。

“哦？您是这样看的吗？”洛贝特科坚持自己的意见“主啊，我的上帝，哪怕你把我送到月亮上去，我也会马上给您找着啤酒和女人！好，我马上就去找来……要是我找不着，您骂我是混蛋好了！”

他用很久的工夫穿上衣服，蹬上大皮靴，然后默默地抽完烟，走出去了。

“拉别克，格拉别克，拉别克，”他嘴里念着，却在前堂里站住了，“我一个人不高兴去，真该死！您肯出去溜达吗？啊？”

他没听见答话，就走回来，慢腾腾地脱掉衣服，上了床。美尔兹里亚科夫叹口气，收起《欧洲通报》，吹熄蜡烛。

“哼！……”洛贝特科嘟哝着，在黑暗里点上一支烟。

里亚博维奇拉起被子来蒙上头，蜷起身子，极力想把幻想中那些飘浮不定的影子拼凑起来，合成一个完整的人，可是任凭怎么样也拼凑不成。他不久就睡着了，他的最后一个思想是：不知一个什么人，对他温存了一下，使他喜悦，一件不平常的、荒唐的，可是非常美好快乐的事来到了他的生活里。哪怕在睡乡里，这个思想也没离开过他。

等到他醒来，他脖子上涂油的感觉和唇边薄荷的凉意都没有了，可是欢乐的波浪还是跟昨天一样在他的心中起伏。他痴迷地瞧着给初升的阳光镀上一层金的窗框听着街上行人走动的声音。贴近窗子，有人在大声讲话里亚博维奇的连长列别杰兹基刚刚赶到旅里来，由于不习惯低声讲话，正在大声地跟他的司务长讲话。

“还有什么事？”连长嚷道。

“昨天他们换马掌的时候，官长，他们钉伤了‘鸽子的蹄子。医士给涂上黏土和醋。现在他们用缰绳牵着它在边上走。还有，官长，昨天工匠阿尔捷米耶夫喝醉了中尉下命令把他拴在一个后备炮架的前车上。”

司务长还报告说，卡尔波夫忘了带来喇叭上用的新绳和支帐篷用的木桩，还提到各位军官昨天傍晚到冯·拉别克将军家里去做客。话正谈到半中腰，窗口出现了列别杰兹基的生着红头发的脑袋。他眯着近视的眼睛瞧着军官们带着睡意的脸，跟他们打招呼。

“没什么事吧？”他问。

“那匹备了鞍子的辕马戴上新套具，把脖子磨肿了。洛贝特科打着呵欠回答道。

连长叹口气，沉吟一下，大声说：

“我还要到阿列克山德拉·叶甫格拉佛芙娜那儿去一趟。我得去看看她。好，再见吧。到傍晚我会追上你们的。”

过了一刻钟，炮兵旅动身上路了。这个旅沿着大道走，经过地主粮仓的时候，里亚博维奇瞧了瞧右边的房子。所有的窗口都拉下着百叶窗。房子里的人分明都在睡觉。昨天吻过里亚博维奇的那个女人也在睡觉。他极力想象她睡熟的样子。卧室的敞开的窗子，伸进窗口的绿树枝，早晨的新鲜空气，白杨、紫丁香、玫瑰的幽香，一张床，一把椅子，昨天沙沙响、现在放在椅子上的连衣裙，小小的拖鞋，桌上的小表，所有这些，他暗自描摹着，清楚而逼真，可是偏偏那要紧的、关键的东西，她的脸庞和梦中甜蜜的微笑，却从他的幻想里滑出去，就跟水银从手指缝中间漏掉了一样。他骑着马走出半俄里远，回过头来看：黄色的教堂、房子、河、花园，都沉浸在阳光里；那条河很美，两岸绿油油的，水中映着蓝天，河面上这儿那儿闪着银色的阳光。里亚博维奇向梅斯捷奇金村最后看了一眼，心里觉得很难过，好像跟一个很接近、很亲密的东西拆开了似的。

他眼前的路上，只有那些早已熟悉的、没有趣味的画面……左右两旁是未成熟的黑麦和荞麦的田野，有些乌鸦在田野上蹦来蹦去。往前看，只瞧见灰尘和人的后脑勺儿。往后看，也只瞧见灰尘和人脸……打头的是四个举着佩刀步行前进的人，他们是前卫。后面，紧挨着的是一群歌手，歌手后面是骑马的司号员。前卫和歌咏队像送葬行列中擎火炬的人一样，常常忘记保持规定的距离，远远地赶到前头去了……里亚博维奇随着第五连的第一门炮走着。他可以看见在他前面走动的所有四个连在不是军人的人们看来，这个在行进的炮兵旅所形成的那条笨重的长行列好像是个复杂的、叫人不能理解的杂乱无章的东西，谁也不明白为什么有那么多人围着一尊大炮，为什么那尊炮由那么多套着古怪的挽具的马拉着，仿佛那尊炮真是很可怕、很沉重似的。在里亚博维奇看来，这一切却十分清楚，因此一点也引不起他的兴趣他老早就知道为什么每个连的前头除了军官以外还要有一个身材魁梧的士官骑在马上，为什么他叫作前导。紧跟在士官背后的是拉前套的马的骑手，随后是走在中间的马的骑手。里亚博维奇知道他们所骑的马，在左边的叫鞍马，在右边的叫副马，这些都很乏味。在那些骑手后面跟着两匹辕马。其中一匹马上坐着一个骑手，背上布满昨天的尘土，右腿上绑着一块粗笨的、样子可笑的小木头。里亚博维奇知道这块木头做什么用，并不觉得可笑。所有的骑手随便地摇动短皮鞭，不时嚷一声。炮本身也不好看。前车上面堆了一袋袋的燕麦，盖着帆布。炮身上挂着茶壶、兵士的行囊、口袋，看上去那尊炮像是一头小小的、不伤人的动物，不知什么缘故被人们和马匹包围着。炮的两旁，有六个兵，都是炮手，背着风走路，挥动着胳膊。在这尊炮后面又是另外的前导、骑手、辕马，这后面又来了一尊炮，跟前面那尊同样难看，不威严。这第二尊炮过去以后，随后来了第三尊、第四尊，靠近第四尊炮有一个军官，等等。这个旅一共有六个连，每个连有四尊炮。这行列有半俄里长，殿后的是一串货车，货车旁边有一头极可爱的牲口，驴子玛加尔，那是一个连长从土耳其带来的，它耷拉着耳朵挺长的脑袋，沉思着迈着步子。

里亚博维奇冷淡地瞧瞧前面和后面，瞧瞧人的后脑勺儿和脸。换了别的时候，他大概已经迷迷糊糊，要睡着了，可是现在他却完全沉浸在愉快的新体验到的思绪中了。起初在炮兵旅刚刚启程的时候，他想说服自己：那件亲吻的事，如果有趣味，也只因为那是一个小小的、神秘的奇遇罢了，其实那是没什么意思的，把这件事看得认真，至少也是愚蠢的。可是不久他就顾不得这些道理，想入非非了……他一会儿想着自己在冯·拉别克的客厅里，挨着一个姑娘，长得挺像淡紫色小姐和穿黑衣服的金发女郎；一会儿闭上眼睛，看见自己跟另一个完全不认得的姑娘待在一起，那人的脸相很模糊。他暗自跟她谈话，跟她温存，低下头去凑近她的肩头。他想象战争和离别，然后重逢，跟妻子儿女一块儿吃晚饭……

“煞住车！”每回他们下山，这个命令就响起来。

他也嚷着：“煞住车！”可是又生怕这一声喊搅乱他的幻梦，把他带回现实里来……

他们走过一个地主的庄园，里亚博维奇就隔着篱墙向花园里望。他的眼睛遇到一条很长的林荫路，像尺那么直，铺着黄沙土，夹道是新长出来的小桦树……他带着沉浸在幻想里的人的那份热情暗自想着女人的小小的脚在黄沙土上走着，于是突然间，在他的幻想中清清楚楚地出现了吻过他的那个姑娘的模样，正是昨天吃晚饭时候他描摹的那个样子。这个模样就此留在他的脑子里再也不离开他了。

中午，后面靠近那串货车的地方有人嚷道：

“立正！向左看！军官先生们！”

旅长是一位将军，坐着一辆由一对白马拉着的马车走过来了。他在第二连附近停住，嚷了一些谁也听不懂的话。好几个军官，里亚博维奇也在内，策动马，跑到他面前去。

“啊？怎么样？什么？”将军问，䀹着他的红眼睛，“有病号吗？”

将军是个瘦小的男子，听到回答，就动着嘴，好像在咀嚼什么。他沉吟一下，对一个军官说：

“你们第三尊炮的炮车辕马的骑手摘掉了护膝，把它挂在炮的前车上了，那混蛋。您得惩罚他。”

他抬起眼睛看看里亚博维奇，接着说：

“我觉得你们那根车带太长了……”

将军又说了几句别的乏味的话，瞧着洛贝特科，微微地笑了。

“今天您看起来很忧愁，洛贝特科中尉，”他说，“您在想念洛普霍娃吧？对不对？诸位先生，他在想念洛普霍娃！”

洛普霍娃是个很胖很高的女人，年纪早已过四十了。将军自己喜欢身材高大的女人，年纪大小倒不论，因此猜想他手下的军官们也有同样的爱好。军官们恭敬地赔着笑脸。将军觉得自己说了句很逗笑很尖刻的话，心里痛快，就扬声大笑，碰了碰他的车夫的后背，行了个军礼马车往前驶走了……

“我现在所梦想的一切，我现在觉得不能实现的、人们少有的一切，其实是很平常的，”里亚博维奇瞧着将军车子后面的滚滚尘土，暗自想着，“这种事平常得很，人人都经历过……比方说，那位将军当初就谈过恋爱，现在结了婚，有了子女。瓦赫捷尔大尉，虽然后脑勺儿很红很丑，没有腰身，可也结了婚，有人爱……萨尔玛诺夫呢，很粗野，简直跟鞑靼人一样，可是他也谈过恋爱最后结了婚……我跟大家一样，我早晚也会经历大家经历过的事……”

他想到自己是个平常的人，他的生活也平平常常，不由得很高兴，而且这给了他勇气。他由着性儿大胆描摹她和他自己的幸福，什么东西也不能束缚他的幻想了……

傍晚炮兵旅到达了驻扎地，军官们在帐篷里安歇里亚博维奇、美尔兹里亚科夫、洛贝特科围着一口箱子坐着吃晚饭。美尔兹里亚科夫不慌不忙地吃着，他一面从容地咀嚼，一面看一本摆在他膝头上的《欧洲通报》洛贝特科讲个没完，不断地往自己的杯子里斟啤酒。里亚博维奇做了一天的梦，脑筋都乱了，只顾喝酒，什么话也没说。喝过三杯酒，他有点醉了，浑身觉着软绵绵的，就起了一种熬不住的欲望，想把他的新感觉讲给他的同事们听。

“在冯·拉别克家里，我遇到一件怪事……”他开口说，极力在自己的声调里加进满不在乎的、讥诮的口吻，“你们知道，我走进了台球房……”

他开始详详细细地述说那件亲吻的事，过了一会儿就沉默了……一会儿的工夫他已经把前后情形都讲完了，这件事只要那么短短的工夫就讲完，他不由得大吃一惊。他本来以为会把这个亲吻的故事一直讲到第二天早晨呢。洛贝特科是个爱说谎的人，因此什么人的话也不相信。他听里亚博维奇讲完，怀疑地瞧着他，冷冷地一笑。美尔兹里亚科夫动了动眉毛，眼睛没离开《欧洲通报》，说：

“上帝才知道这是怎么回事！……这女人一下子就搂住一个男人的脖子，也没叫一声他的名字……她一定是个心理变态的女人。”

“对了，一定是个心理变态的女人……”里亚博维奇同意。

“有一次我也遇见过这一类的事……”洛贝特科说，装出惊骇的眼神，“去年我上科甫诺去……我买了一张二等客车的票……火车上挤得很，没法儿睡觉。我塞给乘务员半个卢布……他就拿着我的行李，领我到一个单人车室去……我躺下来，盖上毯子……你们知道，那儿挺黑。忽然我觉得有人碰了碰我的肩膀，朝我的脸上吹气我动一动手，却碰到了不知什么人的胳膊肘。我睁开眼你们猜怎么着，原来是一个女人！眼睛黑黑的，嘴唇红得好似一条新鲜的鲑鱼，鼻孔热情地呼气，胸脯活像一个软靠枕……”

“对不起，”美尔兹里亚科夫平静地插嘴，“关于胸脯的话，我倒能懂，可是既然那儿挺黑，你怎么看得清嘴唇呢？”

洛贝特科极力圆他的谎，嘲笑美尔兹里亚科夫缺乏想象力。这惹得里亚博维奇讨厌。他离开那口箱子，上了床，赌咒再也不向别人谈起这件事了。

露营生活开始了……日子一天天流过去，这一天跟那一天简直差不多。在那些日子，里亚博维奇的感情思想、举动都像是在谈恋爱。每天早晨他的勤务兵给他送水来洗脸，他用冷水冲头的时候，总想起他的生活里有了一件美好而温暖的事。

到傍晚，他的同事们一谈到爱情和女人，他就走近一点听着，脸上现出一种表情，仿佛兵士在听人述说他参加过的一个战役似的。有些天的傍晚，带着几分醉意的尉官们由“猎狗”洛贝特科领头到“城郊”去冶游，每逢里亚博维奇参加这类游乐的时候，他总是很难过，觉得深深的惭愧，暗自求“她”原谅……遇到空闲的当儿，或者失眠的夜晚，他回忆自己的童年、父亲、母亲，总之回想亲人的时候，他一定也会想起梅斯捷奇金村、那头怪马、冯·拉别克、他那长得像厄热尼皇后的妻子、那黑房间、门缝里漏进来的那一线亮光……

八月三十一日，他从露营地回去，然而不是跟整个炮兵旅，而是只跟其中的两个连一块儿走。他一路上梦想着，激动着，好像在回故乡似的。他热烈地盼望着再看见那匹怪马、那个教堂、冯·拉别克那个不诚恳的家庭、那黑房间。常常欺骗情人的那种“内心的声音”，不知什么缘故，向他悄悄说，他一定会看见她……他给种种疑问折磨着：他会怎样跟她见面？他跟她谈什么好呢？她忘了那回的亲吻没有？他想，就算事情真糟到这种地步，他竟不能再见到她，那么光是重走一遍那个黑房间，回想一下，在他也不失为一种乐趣……

将近傍晚，远远的地平线上出现了那熟悉的教堂和白色的谷仓。里亚博维奇的心怦怦地跳起来……他没听见跟他并排骑着马的军官对他说了些什么，他把一切都丢在脑后，眼巴巴地瞧着在远处发亮的那条河，瞧着那所房子的房顶，瞧着鸽子窝，在夕阳的余晖中鸽子正在那上面飞来飞去。

他们走到教堂那儿，听设营官指定宿营地的时候他时时刻刻巴望有一个骑马的人会从教堂的围墙后面走出来，请军官们去喝茶，可是……设营官讲完话，军官们下马，溜达到村里去了，那个骑马的人并没有来……

“冯·拉别克马上会从农民那儿听说我们来了，然后派人来请我们。”里亚博维奇想，这时候他走进农舍，不明白为什么一个同事点亮了一支蜡烛，为什么勤务兵忙着烧茶炊……

他心神不定。他躺下去，随后又起来，瞧着窗外看那骑马的人来了没有。可是骑马的人没来。他就又躺下去，可是过了半个钟头他又起来，压不住心里的不安就走到街上，向教堂走去。靠近教堂围墙的广场上又黑又荒凉……在下坡路那儿有三个兵士默默地排成一行站在那儿。他们一看见里亚博维奇，就挺起腰板，行军礼他回礼，开始顺着那条熟悉的小路走下去。

河对面，整个天空一片紫红色：月亮升上来了。有两个农妇大声说话，在菜园里摘白菜叶子。菜园后面有些小木房，颜色发黑……这边岸上的一切跟五月间一样：小路、矮树丛、挂在河面上的垂柳……不过那只勇敢的夜莺的声音却没有了，白杨和嫩草的香气也没有了。

里亚博维奇走到花园，往门里瞧，花园里黑暗而安静……他只看见近边桦树的白树干和一小段林荫路，别的东西全都化成漆黑的一团。里亚博维奇聚精会神地瞧着，听着，可是站了一刻钟工夫，既没听见一点声音，也没看见一点亮光，他就慢慢地往回走……

他走下坡，到了河边。将军的浴棚和挂在小桥栏杆上的浴巾，在他前面现出一片白色……他走到小桥上，站了一会儿，完全不必要地摸了摸浴巾，浴巾又粗又凉。他低下头看水……河水流得很快，在浴棚的木桩旁边发出勉强能听见的潺潺声。靠近左岸的河面上映着红月亮。小小的涟漪滚过月亮的倒影，把它拉长，扯碎，好像要把它带走似的……

“多么愚蠢，多么愚蠢啊！”里亚博维奇瞧着奔流的水，想着，“这是多么不近情理啊！”

现在他什么也不再盼望了，他这才清清楚楚地了解了那件亲吻的事、他的焦躁、他的模糊的希望和失望他想到他没有看见将军的使者，想到他永远也不会见到那个原该吻别人却错吻了他的姑娘，不再觉得奇怪了刚好相反，要是他见到了她，那倒奇怪了……

河水奔流着，谁也不知道它流到哪儿去，为什么流五月间它也像这样流，五月间它从小河流进大河，从大河流进海洋，然后化成蒸汽，变成雨水，也许如今在里亚博维奇面前流过去的仍旧是原先的那点水吧……这是为什么？为什么呢？

里亚博维奇觉得整个世界，整个生活，都好像是一个不能理解的、没有目的的玩笑……他从水面上移开眼睛，瞧着天空，又想起命运怎样化为一个不相识的女人对他偶然温存了一下，想起他的夏天的迷梦和幻象，他这才觉得他的生活异常空洞，贫乏，没有光彩……

他回到他住的农舍里，没有碰见一个同事。勤务兵报告说，他们都到“冯特利亚勃金将军”家里去了，因为将军派了一个骑马的使者来邀请他们……一刹那间里亚博维奇心里腾起一股欢乐，可是他立刻扑灭它，上了床他存心跟他的命运作对，仿佛要惹它气恼似的，偏不到将军家去。

[1] 一俄里等于1.06千米。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明的之外，均为编者注。）

[2] 厄热尼皇后（1826—1920），拿破仑三世的妻子。

大沃洛嘉和小沃洛嘉

“放开我，我要自己赶车！我要坐到车夫旁边去！”索菲雅·利沃芙娜大声说，“车夫，你等一等，我要跟你一块儿坐在赶车座位上。”

她在雪橇上站着，她的丈夫符拉季米尔·尼基狄奇和她小时候的朋友符拉季米尔·米海雷奇抓住她的胳膊，免得她跌倒。那辆三套马的雪橇跑得飞快。

“我早就说不该给她喝白兰地，”符拉季米尔·尼基狄奇烦恼地小声对他的旅伴说，“你这个人啊，真是的！”

上校凭经验知道，像他的妻子索菲雅·利沃芙娜这样的女人在这种带点醉意的、疯疯癫癫的快乐过去以后，紧跟着照例就是歇斯底里的大笑，接着是痛哭。他担心过一会儿他们回到家里以后，他没法儿睡觉，而不得不忙着张罗冷敷布和药水。

“嘘！”索菲雅·利沃芙娜叫道，“我要赶车。”

她心里真是快活和得意。自从举行婚礼那天起，最近两个月来，总有一个想法煎熬着她，她觉得她嫁给亚吉奇上校是因为贪图富贵，而且像人们常说的那样，因为赌气[1]；可是今天在城郊那家饭店里，她终于相信自己热烈地爱着他。尽管他已经五十四岁，却身材匀称，头脑机敏，动作灵活，擅长说俏皮话，给茨冈姑娘们伴唱真的，如今老头倒比青年可爱一千倍，仿佛老人和青年掉换了位置似的。尽管上校比她父亲还要大两岁，而她只有二十三岁，然而凭良心说，论精力和朝气，他却比她不知超出多少，那么，年纪大又有什么关系呢？

“啊，我亲爱的！”她暗想，“了不起的人！”

在那家饭店里，她还相信，她那旧日的感情已经连影子也没有了。对她小时候的朋友符拉季米尔·米海雷奇或者简称沃洛嘉，她昨天还爱得发疯，爱得要命，现在却完全淡漠了。今天整个傍晚，她觉得他无精打采，带着睡意，不招人喜欢，一无可取。他在饭店里照例厚着脸皮避免付账，这一回他的这种态度使她暗暗生气，好容易才忍住没对他说：“要是您没钱，就该坐在家里才对。”每次都是由上校一个人付钱。

也许由于她眼前不断地闪过树木、电线杆和雪堆吧，总之，各式各样的思想涌上了她的心头。她想起饭店的账单是一百二十卢布，另外还付给茨冈人一百卢布。明天，只要她乐意，她可以随便挥霍上千的卢布，可是两个月以前，在她结婚以前，她自己连三个卢布都没有，随便买一点小东西都得向她父亲要钱。生活的变化是多么大呀！

她的思路千头万绪，她想起当初她十岁的时候，她现在的丈夫亚吉奇上校追求过她的姑母，全家人都说他把她害苦了，事实上，她姑母走出房来吃饭的时候确实常常脸上带着泪痕，而且老是坐上马车不知到什么地方去。大家讲起她来总是说：这个可怜的人休想得到安宁了。那时候他很漂亮，大受女人们的垂青。因此全城的人都知道他，大家说他似乎每天都要分头到那些爱慕他的女人的家里去一趟，就跟医生去给病人看病一样。现在呢，尽管他头发白了，脸上起了皱纹，戴了眼镜，可是他那张瘦脸，特别是从侧面看过去，有时候还是显得挺漂亮的。

索菲雅·利沃芙娜的父亲是个军医官，从前跟亚吉奇在同一个部队里共过事。沃洛嘉的父亲也是军医官从前也跟亚吉奇上校和她父亲在同一个部队里共过事沃洛嘉虽然常常闹出很复杂、很烦心的恋爱纠纷，可是学业优良，他在大学毕业的时候，成绩极好，现在选定外国文学作为他的专业，据说正在写论文。他住在他那做军医的父亲的营房里，虽然三十岁了，自己却没有钱索菲雅·利沃芙娜小时候和他同住在一栋房子里，虽然两家各有自己的一套住宅。他常来找她一块儿游玩，一块儿学跳舞，一块儿学说法国话。可是等到他长大，变成一个身材匀称、十分漂亮的青年，她见着他就怕羞了后来暗自发疯似的爱上他，直到最近嫁给亚吉奇为止他也很受女人们的垂青，差不多从十四岁起，他就善于博得她们的欢心，那些为他而对丈夫不忠诚的太太，总是借口沃洛嘉年纪还小而为自己辩白。不久以前有人讲起他，说他做大学生的时候，住在大学附近的公寓房间里每次有人去找他，敲他的房门，就会听见门里面响起他的脚步声，然后是低声的道歉：“对不起，我不是一个人在屋里。”[2]亚吉奇很欣赏他，夸奖他前途无量，就像杰尔查文[3]对待普希金一样，显然，亚吉奇喜欢他。他们两人往往一连几个钟头沉默地打台球或者玩“辟开”[4]。亚吉奇如果坐上三套马的马车到什么地方去，总是把沃洛嘉带在身边，沃洛嘉也只把他论文的秘密讲给亚吉奇一个人听。当初上校比较年轻的时候，他们常常处于情敌的地位，可是彼此从来也不争风吃醋。在他们常常同去的社交场所，大家总是管亚吉奇叫作大沃洛嘉，管他的朋友叫作小沃洛嘉。

在雪橇上，除了大沃洛嘉、小沃洛嘉和索菲雅·利沃芙娜以外，还有一个女人，就是玛尔迦莉达·亚历山德罗芙娜，大家称呼她莉达。她是亚吉奇太太的表姐，一个三十岁开外的姑娘，脸色十分苍白，眉毛漆黑，戴着夹鼻眼镜，不停地吸纸烟，哪怕在天气严寒的时候也一样。她的胸前和膝盖上老是有烟灰。她说话带着鼻音，拖长每个字的字音，性情冷僻，随便喝多少蜜酒和白兰地总也不会醉，时常懒洋洋而又乏味地讲些含意暧昧的掌故。她在家里从早到晚翻看厚本的杂志，弄得杂志上撒满烟灰，或者吃冰冻的苹果。

“索尼雅[5]，别发疯了，”她用唱歌般的声调说，“真的这简直是愚蠢。”

在临近城门的地方，那三套马的雪橇跑得慢了点房屋和行人不断闪过去。索菲雅·利沃芙娜平静下来偎紧她的丈夫，专心想心事。小沃洛嘉坐在她对面。这时候，除了轻松快活的思想以外，又添上些阴郁的思想她暗想，坐在对面的这个人知道她爱他，他当然相信她是因为赌气嫁给上校的说法。她一次也没有向他表白过爱情，而且不希望他知道，总是隐瞒着她自己的感情可是从他的脸色看得出他十分了解她，这就伤了她的自尊心。不过在她的处境里最使她痛心的是，自从举行婚礼以后，这个小沃洛嘉倒忽然开始对她献起殷勤来，而这是以前从来也没有过的。他往往一连几个钟头默默地陪她坐着，或者谈些闲话，此刻在雪橇里他没有跟她谈话却微微地踩着她的脚，握握她的手。显然，他一心巴望她出嫁。他分明看不起她，她就像那种不规矩的坏女人那样在他心里只能引起某种性质的兴趣。当那种得意的感情和对丈夫的爱情跟屈辱的感情和受伤的自尊心在她心里混在一起的时候，她就不禁生出逞强的心，只想坐到赶车座位上去，嚷一阵，吹一阵口哨……

在他们的马车经过一个女修道院的当儿，院里那口一千普特[6]重的大钟敲响了。莉达在胸前画十字。

“我们的奥丽雅在这个修道院里。”索菲雅·利沃芙娜说，也在胸前画十字，身子哆嗦了一下。

“为什么她进了修道院？”上校问道。

“因为赌气，”莉达生气地回答说，显然暗指索菲雅·利沃芙娜和亚吉奇的婚姻，“现在这种因为赌气挺时行。它正向全世界挑战。她原是个爱说爱笑、极爱卖弄风情的女人，只喜欢舞会和舞伴，可是忽然间，她走了！弄得人人都吃了一惊！”

“这不是实情，”小沃洛嘉放下皮大衣的衣领，露出他那张漂亮的脸，说，“这跟赌气不相干，不瞒您说，这完全是由于遭了灾祸。她哥哥德米特利被流放去服苦役，如今下落不明。她母亲伤心而死。”

他又竖起他的衣领。

“奥丽雅做得好，”他声音低沉地接着说，“她处在养女的地位，况且又跟索菲雅·利沃芙娜那样的好人住在一起，这一点也得考虑到才是！”

索菲雅·利沃芙娜从他的声调里听出轻蔑的口气就想说几句话顶撞他，可是她没说出口。她又生出那种逞强的心情。她站起来，带着哭腔叫道：

“我要去做晨祷！车夫，往回走！我要去见见奥丽雅！”

雪橇往回驶去。修道院的钟声低沉，索菲雅·利沃芙娜感到这声音使人联想到奥丽雅和她的生活。别的教堂也在敲钟。等到车夫勒住那三匹马，索菲雅·利沃芙娜就跳下雪橇，独自一个人，也不要人陪伴，很快地往大门走去。

“劳驾，快一点！”她丈夫对她叫道，“时候已经不早了！”

她走进乌黑的大门口，然后顺着一条从大门通到大教堂的林荫路走去，积雪在她脚底下吱吱地响，钟声就在她的上空轰鸣，仿佛使她的全身震颤。她来到教堂门口走下三层台阶，然后穿过一道门廊，两旁都是圣徒的画像弥漫着刺柏和神香的气味。随后又是一道门，有一个穿黑衣服的人给她开门，对她深深地鞠躬……教堂里，晨祷还没开始。有一个修女在圣像壁旁边走动，点燃高烛台上的蜡烛，另一个修女点燃枝形烛台上的蜡烛。这儿那儿，圆柱附近和侧祭坛附近，有些黑色人影站着不动。“大概，他们现在这样站着，一直不离开，要到明天早晨才走吧。”索菲雅·利沃芙娜暗想。她觉得这儿又黑又冷，枯燥乏味，比墓园里还要乏味。她带着烦闷的感觉瞧着那些一动不动、呆若木鸡的人影，忽然她的心收紧了。不知怎的，她认出一个身量不高、肩膀窄小、头戴黑色三角头巾的修女就是奥丽雅，其实奥丽雅进修道院的时候长得挺胖，身量也似乎高一些。索菲雅·利沃芙娜不知什么缘故，心里十分激动，犹豫不决地走到那个见习修女跟前，从她肩膀上望过去，看清了她的脸，果然她就是奥丽雅。

“奥丽雅！”她说，举起两只手轻轻一拍，兴奋得说不出话来，“奥丽雅！”

那个修女立刻认出她来，惊讶地扬起眉毛。她那张刚洗过的、干净而苍白的脸高兴得放光，就连她那三角头巾下露出的白色包头布也似乎高兴得放光了。

“瞧，主赐的奇迹。”她说着，也举起她那两只干瘦的白手拍了一下。

索菲雅·利沃芙娜紧紧地抱住她，吻她，同时又担心别冒出酒气来。

“刚才我们路过这儿，想起了你。”她说，喘不过气来好像刚才很快地跑过一段路似的，“你的脸色多么苍白啊上帝！我……我见着你高兴极了。哦，怎么样？怎么样？你觉得寂寞吗？”

索菲雅·利沃芙娜往四下里看一眼别的修女们，接着低声说：

“我们那儿发生了好多变化。……你知道，我嫁给亚吉奇，符拉季米尔·尼基狄奇了。你一定记得他。……我跟他在一块儿，很幸福。”

“好，感谢上帝。你父亲身体好吗？”

“好。他常想起你。你，奥丽雅，到了假日务必来看我们。听见了吗？”

“我会去的，”奥丽雅说，微微一笑，“我明天就去。

索菲雅·利沃芙娜自己也不知道为什么，哭起来了她不出声地哭了一会儿，然后擦干眼泪说：

“莉达没有见到你，会觉得十分惋惜。她跟我们一块儿出来的。沃洛嘉也在。他们就在大门口。要是你能跟他们见面，他们会多么高兴啊！我们去找他们吧，反正祈祷还没开始。”

“那我们就去吧。”奥丽雅同意说。

她在胸前画了三次十字，然后跟索菲雅·利沃芙娜一块儿往门口走去。

“那么，索涅琪卡，你说你挺幸福？”她走出大门的时候问道。

“很幸福。”

“好，感谢上帝。”

大沃洛嘉和小沃洛嘉看见这个修女走出来，就跳下雪橇，恭恭敬敬向她问好。他们看见她那苍白的脸和黑色的修女服显然都感动了。而且，她还记得他们，出来向他们问候，两人心里暗暗高兴。索菲雅·利沃芙娜怕她冻着，就拿过一条车毯披在她身上，同时用她皮大衣的一块前襟把她裹住。方才的眼泪使她的心头轻松了一些，灵魂变得纯净了。她暗自欣喜，这个热闹的、不安宁的、实际上不纯洁的夜晚竟然出人意料，这样纯洁而温柔地结束了。为了要奥丽雅在她身边多留一会儿，她提议说：

“让她坐上雪橇兜一阵吧！奥丽雅，你坐上去，我们一会儿就回来。”

两个男人预料修女会拒绝，圣徒是不坐三套马的雪橇兜风的。可是使他们吃惊的是，她居然同意，还坐上了雪橇。这辆三套马的雪橇往城门那边跑去，大家都默不作声，只是极力让她坐得舒服点，暖和点，每个人都暗想她从前是什么样子，现在又是什么样子。现在她的脸缺乏热情，很少表情，冷淡而苍白，而且透明，好像她的血管里流着的是水而不是血。不过两三年前，她却长得丰满，脸颊绯红，常常谈论那些追求她的男人，为一丁点儿小事而扬声大笑。

在城门附近，雪橇掉转头往回跑，过了大约十分钟在修道院门前停住，奥丽雅走下雪橇。钟楼上，钟声响得更急了。

“求主保佑你们。”奥丽雅说，照修女那样深深一鞠躬

“那么你一定要来，奥丽雅。”

“我会去的，会去的。”

她很快地走了，不久就消失在乌黑的大门里。这以后雪橇往回跑，不知什么缘故，大家心里都感到十分愁闷人人都沉默不语。索菲雅·利沃芙娜觉得浑身发软，心情沮丧。她觉得刚才逼着修女坐上雪橇，夹在一伙喝过酒的人当中，乘着三套马的雪橇兜风，未免荒唐、鲁莽而且几乎可以说是不敬。她的酒意过去了，欺骗自己的愿望也就随之而消失，她已经清楚地感到她不爱她的丈夫，而且也不可能爱他，这件事简直是胡闹、愚蠢。她嫁给他是由于贪图富贵，因为他，按她中学里的女同学的说法，“阔绰得不得了”；又由于她生怕自己像莉达似的做老处女；还由于她厌烦她那做军医的父亲，而且想气气小沃洛嘉。要是她出嫁前能够预料到生活会这样沉重、可怕、讨厌，那么，就是拿全世界的财富都送给她，她也不会同意结婚。然而现在已经无法挽回。只好听天由命了。

他们回到家里。索菲雅·利沃芙娜在暖和而柔软的床上躺下，盖好被子，于是想起那道幽暗的门廊、那种神香的气味、那些圆柱旁边的人影。她想到在她睡着以后，那些人将会始终站着不动，就不由得害怕。晨祷的时间很长，然后是念经，然后是弥撒，祈祷……

“可是要知道，上帝是有的，一定是有的，而我总会死的，那就是说，我早晚得考虑灵魂，考虑永恒的生活，像奥丽雅一样。奥丽雅现在得救了，她给自己解决了所有的问题。……可是万一没有上帝呢？那她的一生就白白糟蹋了。可是怎么会是白白糟蹋呢？为什么就是白白糟蹋呢？”

过了一会儿又有些思想萦回在她的脑际：

“上帝是有的，死亡一定会来临，应当想到灵魂才对。如果奥丽雅此刻知道她马上会死掉，她也不会害怕她准备好了。主要的是她已经为自己解决了人生的问题上帝是有的……是啊……可是除了进修道院以外，难道就没有别的出路了？要知道，进修道院无非是放弃生活毁掉生活罢了……”

索菲雅·利沃芙娜有点害怕。她把脑袋埋在枕头底下。

“不应当想这些，”她小声说，“不应当。”

亚吉奇在隔壁房间里的地毯上走来走去，他的马刺轻轻地响着，他在想心事。索菲雅·利沃芙娜猛地想到这个人只在一点上使她感到亲切和可爱：他的名字也叫符拉季米尔。她从床上坐起来，柔声叫道：

“沃洛嘉！”

“什么事？”她丈夫应声说。

“没什么。”

她又躺下去。钟声响起来，也许就是修道院里的钟声吧。她又不由得想起那道门廊和那些乌黑的人影。那些关于上帝和不可避免的死亡的想法在她头脑里盘旋她就用被子蒙住头，免得听见钟声。她暗想，在衰老和不可避免的死亡来临以前，还有很长很长一段生活要过，她得每天忍受这个她所不爱的、此刻走进寝室里来睡觉的男子的亲近，她得扑灭她心里对另一个年轻迷人而且在她看来不平凡的男子的无望的爱情。她看一眼丈夫，想对他道一声晚安，可是没有说出口，却忽然哭起来。她恼恨自己。

“得，音乐开始了！”亚吉奇说，把“乐”字说得很重。

她哭了很久，一直到早晨九点多钟才平静下来。她停了哭，全身不再发抖，可是头痛欲裂。亚吉奇匆匆地赶着去做晚弥撒，在隔壁房间里抱怨帮他穿衣服的勤务兵。他到卧室里来取东西，马刺发出轻微的响声，后来又进来一趟，这一回已经戴上带穗的肩章和勋章了。他两条腿由于害风湿病而有点瘸。不知什么缘故，索菲雅·利沃芙娜觉得他的模样和步法像一头猛兽。

她听见亚吉奇在打电话。

“费心，请您接瓦西里耶夫营房！”他说。过了一会儿他又说：“瓦西里耶夫营房吗？劳驾，请萨里莫维奇医生接电话……”又过了一会儿：“是哪一位啊？是你吗，沃洛嘉？很高兴。亲爱的，请你父亲马上到我们家里来一趟，因为我的妻子昨天回来以后，觉得很不舒服。你是说他不在家？哦……谢谢。太好啦……非常感谢……谢谢[7]。”

亚吉奇第三次走进寝室来，弯下腰凑近他妻子，在她胸前画个十字，伸出手去让她吻（凡是爱他的女人都吻他的手，他已经养成习惯了），说他吃午饭的时候回来他说完就走了。

十一点多钟，使女通报说，符拉季米尔·米海雷奇来了。索菲雅·利沃芙娜又疲乏又头痛，身子摇摇晃晃很快地穿上她那件用毛皮镶边、又新又漂亮的淡紫色家常便服，赶紧把头发好歹梳理一下。她觉得她的灵魂里生出一种无法形容的温柔感情，高兴得周身发抖，生怕他会走掉。她只巴望看他一眼。

小沃洛嘉这次来访，装束整齐，穿着燕尾服，打着白领结。索菲雅·利沃芙娜走进客厅里，他吻她的手为她身体不爽而真诚地表示难过。后来他们坐下来，他就称赞她那件便服。

“昨天跟奥丽雅见过面以后，我心里很乱，”她说，“起初我感到害怕，而现在却羡慕她了。她好比牢不可破的山岩，谁都休想搬得动它。可是，沃洛嘉，难道她就没有别的出路了？难道活生生地埋葬自己才算是解决了人生问题？要知道，那是死而不是生啊。”

一提起奥丽雅，小沃洛嘉的脸上就现出感动的神情。

“您，沃洛嘉，是个聪明人，”索菲雅·利沃芙娜说，“请您指点我，好让我也能像她那样行事。当然，我不是个信徒，不会进修道院，不过我还是可以做些性质相似的事。我生活得不轻松啊。”她沉默一阵以后，接着说，“您指点我吧。……告诉我一种可以使我信服的办法。您哪怕只说一句话也好。”

“一句话？好吧：砰的一声响！”

“沃洛嘉，为什么您看不起我？”她痛心地问道，“您跟我讲起话来，原谅我这样说，总是用一种纨袴子弟的特别口气，不像是对朋友，对正派的女人讲话。您很有成就，您喜欢科学，可是为什么您从来也不对我谈科学呢？为什么？我不配吗？”

小沃洛嘉烦恼地皱起眉头，说：

“为什么您忽然需要起科学来了？也许您还需要宪法吧？或者需要鲟鱼肉烧辣根？”

“哦，好吧，我是个一无可取、渺小庸俗、品行不端、浅薄愚蠢的女人。……我干过许许多多错事，我心理变态，道德败坏，我活该受到轻视。可是话得说回来，您，沃洛嘉年纪比我大十岁，我的丈夫比我大三十岁。我是在你们眼前长大的，要是你们乐意，你们就可以随意把我培养成任什么样的人，哪怕培养成天使也未尝办不到。可是你们……”她的嗓音颤抖了，“这么可怕地对待我。亚吉奇年纪老了却跟我结婚，您呢……”

“哎，得了，得了，”沃洛嘉说，坐近一点，吻她的双手，“让叔本华去谈哲学，去证明他要证明的事吧，我们呢，还是来吻这两只小手的好。”

“您看不起我，但愿您能知道我为这种态度多么难过才好！”她迟疑地说，事先就知道他不会相信她的话。“但愿您知道我多么希望变个样子，开始过一种新的生活！我一想到这里就十分兴奋，”她说，果然兴奋得流下泪来“我想做一个诚实纯洁的好人，不作假，有生活目标。”

“行了，行了，行了，劳驾，别装腔作势了！我不喜欢这样！”沃洛嘉说，脸上现出不痛快的神情，“说真的这简直像是演戏了。我们还是做普通人的好。”

她怕他生气走掉，就赶紧辩白，而且做出勉强的笑容来向他讨好，又讲起奥丽雅，讲到她一心想解决她的人生问题，开始做一个堂堂正正的人。

“砰的……一声……响……”他低声唱起来，“砰的……一声……响……”

猛然间，他搂住她的腰。她自己也不知道自己在做什么，把两只手放在他的肩膀上，一时间痴迷地，仿佛在雾里似的，瞧着他那张聪明而讥诮的脸、额头、眼睛、漂亮的胡子……

“你自己早就知道我爱你，”她对他承认道，痛苦地红了脸，甚至感到她的嘴唇由于羞耻而抽搐起来，“我爱你。可是你为什么折磨我呢？”

她闭上眼睛，热烈地吻他的嘴唇，吻了大约有一分钟之久。虽然她知道这不正派，连他都会指责她，而且可能有使女走进来，不过她无论如何也没法儿结束这一吻。……

“啊，你在怎样折磨我呀！”她又说了一遍。

过了半个钟头，他得到他所需要的一切以后，在饭厅里坐下来吃东西。她跪在他面前，贪婪地瞧着他的脸。他就对她说，她活像一条小狗，等着人家丢给它一小块火腿吃。后来他叫她坐在他的膝头上，拿她当小娃娃似的摇来摇去，嘴里唱着：

“砰的……一声……响！”

临到他准备告辞，她就用热烈的口气问他：

“什么时候？今天吗？在什么地方？”

她伸出两只手凑到他的嘴边，好像要用手去抓住他的答话似的。

“今天恐怕不方便了，”他沉吟一下说，“明天也许行。

他们就分手了。午饭前，索菲雅·利沃芙娜坐上雪橇到修道院里去找奥丽雅，可是到了那边，人家告诉她说奥丽雅外出为死人念赞美诗去了。她从修道院里出来又坐上雪橇去找她父亲，也没在他家里碰到他，然后她就换一辆雪橇，毫无目的地串大街，走小巷，照这样坐车一直游逛到傍晚。不知什么缘故，她老是想起她那脸上带着泪痕、坐立不安的姑母。

到晚上，他们又坐上三套马的雪橇，到城郊饭店里去听茨冈人唱歌。当他们再次路过修道院的时候，索菲雅·利沃芙娜想起奥丽雅，不由得心惊肉跳，因为她思忖对她这个圈子里的姑娘和女人来说，除了坐着三套马的车子不停地逛荡，说谎，或者索性进修道院去扑灭生机以外，就没有别的出路了……

第二天索菲雅·利沃芙娜去赴幽会，然后又孤身一人坐在街头的雪橇上跑遍全城，心里想着她的姑母。

过了一个星期，小沃洛嘉把她丢开了。这以后生活又照原样进行，仍旧那么没趣味，无聊，有时候甚至痛苦。上校和小沃洛嘉打了很久的台球和玩“辟开”，莉达懒洋洋地、乏味地讲那些掌故，索菲雅·利沃芙娜老是坐着街头的雪橇游逛，或者要求她丈夫带她坐着三套马的雪橇去兜风。

她几乎每天都到修道院去，惹得奥丽雅厌烦了。她对奥丽雅诉说自己难以忍受的痛苦，哭哭啼啼，同时又感到她一走进修道院，就随身带进一种不洁、可怜、陈腐的东西。奥丽雅呢，老是用背书的腔调不动感情地对她说：这些都没关系，一切都会过去，上帝会宽恕她的。

[1] 原文为法语。

[2] 原文为法语。

[3] 杰尔查文（1743—1816），俄罗斯诗人。1815年1月8日，年轻的普希金在皇村学校参加考试时，当众朗诵他的诗篇，受到杰尔查文的赞赏。

[4] 一种纸牌游戏。

[5] 索尼雅和下文的索涅琪卡均为索菲雅的爱称。

[6] 俄国重量单位。一普特等于16.38千克。

[7] 原文为法语。

醋栗

从大清早起，整个天空就已经布满了雨云。那天没风不热，可是闷。每逢晦暗的阴天，乌云挂在田野的上空久久不散，看样子会下雨而又不下的时候，往往就会有这样的天气。兽医伊万·伊万内奇和中学教师布尔金已经走累了，依他们看来田野好像没有尽头似的。前面远处隐约可以看见米罗诺西茨戈耶村的风车，右边有一排高岗，伸展出去，越过村子，消失在远方。他们俩都知道那是河岸，那儿有草场、绿油油的柳树、庄园，要是站在一个高岗的顶上望出去，就可以看见同样辽阔的田野和电报线，远处的一列火车，像是一条毛毛虫在爬，遇上晴朗的天气，从那儿甚至可以看得见城市。如今，在没风的天气，整个大自然显得那么温和而沉静。伊万·伊万内奇和布尔金对这片田野生出满腔热爱，两人都心想：这个地方多么辽阔、多么美丽啊。

“上一次我们在村长普罗科菲的堆房里，”布尔金说，“您打算讲一个故事来着。”

“对了，当时我原想讲一讲我弟弟的事。”

伊万·伊万内奇深深地叹一口气，点上烟斗，预备开口讲故事，可是正巧这时候下雨了。过了大约五分钟，雨下大了，空中乌云密布，很难预测这场雨什么时候才会停。伊万·伊万内奇和布尔金站住，考虑起来。他们的狗已经淋湿，站在那儿，用后腿夹着尾巴，深情地瞧着他们。

“我们得找个地方避一避雨才好，”布尔金说，“那就到阿廖欣家去吧。离这儿挺近。”

“那我们就去吧。”

他们就往斜下里拐过去，穿过已经收割过的田地，时而照直走，时而往右拐，直到走上一条大道为止。不久就出现了杨树，园子，然后是谷仓的红房顶；有一条河，河水闪闪发光，顿时眼界豁然开朗，前面是一大片水，有一个磨坊和一个白色的浴棚。这就是阿廖欣所住的索菲诺村。

磨坊在工作，声音盖过了雨声，水坝在颤抖。有几匹淋湿的马垂着头，站在大车旁边。人们披着麻袋走来走去。这儿潮湿、泥泞、憋闷，看上去河水冰凉，凶险伊万·伊万内奇和布尔金已经觉得周身潮湿、不清爽不舒服，脚沾着烂泥而变得挺重。他们穿过水坝，爬上坡往地主的谷仓走去，一路上都没讲话，好像在互相生气似的。

有一个谷仓里筛谷机轰轰地响。仓门开着，滚滚的灰尘冒出来。阿廖欣本人就在门口站着，这是一个四十岁光景的男子，又高又胖，头发很长，与其说像地主不如说像教授或者画家。他穿一件很久没有洗过的白衬衫，拦腰系一根绳子，算是腰带，下身没穿外裤，只穿了一条长衬裤，靴子上也沾满了泥浆和麦秸。他的眼睛和鼻子扑满灰尘，变得乌黑。他认出了伊万·伊万内奇和布尔金，显然很高兴。

“请到屋里去吧，两位先生，”他含笑说道，“我马上就来，用不了一分钟。”

这是一所两层楼的大房子。阿廖欣住在楼下两个带拱顶的房间里，窗子很小，从前原是管家们居住的。屋里陈设简单，有黑面包、便宜的白酒和马具的气味。楼上的正房他难得去，只有客人来了他才去一趟。伊万·伊万内奇和布尔金在房子里遇到一个使女，是个年轻女人，长得那么美，他俩不由得同时站住，互相瞧了一眼。

“你们再也想不出我看见你们有多么高兴，两位先生，”阿廖欣说，跟着他们一块儿走进前厅，“这可是万万没想到！佩拉格娅，”他对那使女说，“给客人找几件衣服来换一换吧。顺便，我也要换一换。只是我先得去洗个澡，因为我大概打春天起就没洗过澡了。两位先生，你们愿意到浴棚里去吗？也好让他们趁这工夫把这儿收拾一下。”

美丽的佩拉格娅那么殷勤，看上去又那么温柔，她给他们送来了毛巾和肥皂，阿廖欣就陪着客人到浴棚里去了。

“是啊，我已经很久没有洗澡了，”他一面脱衣服一面说，“你们看，我的浴棚挺好，这还是我父亲盖起来的，可是不知怎的，我总是没工夫洗澡。”

他在台阶上坐下，给他的长头发和脖子擦满肥皂，他四周的水就变成棕色了。

“是啊，我看也是……”伊万·伊万内奇瞧着他的头，意味深长地说。

“我已经很久没洗过澡了……”阿廖欣难为情地重说一遍，又用肥皂洗起来，他四周的水就变成深蓝色，跟墨水一样了。

伊万·伊万内奇走到外面去，扑通一声跳进水里冒着雨抡开了胳膊游泳。他把身旁的水搅起波浪，睡莲就在水波上摇晃。他游到河中央水深处，扎一个猛子过一分钟又在另一个地方钻出来，再往远处游去，老是扎猛子，极力想够到河底。“哎呀，我的上帝啊！……他反复说着，游得痛快极了。“哎呀，我的上帝啊！……他游到磨坊那儿，跟几个农民谈了一阵，再游回来，到了河中央就平躺在水面上，让他的脸淋着雨。布尔金和阿廖欣已经穿好衣服，准备走了，可是他还在游泳，扎猛子。

“哎呀，我的上帝啊！……”他说，“哎呀，求主怜恤我！……”

“您也游得够了！”布尔金对他喊道。

他们回到房子里。等到楼上的大客厅里点上灯，布尔金和伊万·伊万内奇都穿上了丝绸长袍和暖和的便鞋在圈椅上坐下。阿廖欣本人也洗好脸，梳好头，穿好新上衣，在客厅里走来走去，显然因为换了干衣服、轻便的鞋子，身上温暖洁净而感到满足。一直等到俊俏的佩拉格娅不出声地在地毯上走着，温柔地微笑，用盘子端来加了果酱的茶，一直到了这时候，伊万·伊万内奇才开口讲他的故事，而且仿佛不光是布尔金和阿廖欣在听，就连藏在金边镜框里、严厉而沉静地瞧着他们的那些老老少少的太太以及军官也在听似的。

“我们一共弟兄两个，”他开口了，“我伊万·伊万内奇和弟弟尼古拉·伊万内奇，他比我小两岁。我学技术做了兽医。尼古拉从十九岁起就已经在税务局里工作了。家父奇姆沙－吉马莱斯基本来是个世袭兵[1]，不过后来当上了军官，给我们留下世袭的贵族身份和一份小小的田产。他死后，那份小田产抵了债，可是，不管怎样，我们的童年是在乡间自由自在地度过的。我们完全跟农民的孩子一样，一天到晚在田野上，在树林里度过，看守马匹，剥树皮，钓鱼，等等。……你们要知道，谁一生当中哪怕只钓到过一次鲈鱼，或者在秋天只见过一次鸫鸟南飞，看它们怎样在晴朗凉爽的日子里成群飞过村庄，那他就再也不想做城里人了，他一直到死都会向往那种自由的生活。我弟弟在税务局里老是惦记乡下。一年年过去了，他一直坐在他那老位子上，老是抄写那些文件老是想着一件事：怎样才能回到乡下去。他的这种苦恼渐渐成为明确的渴望，化成梦想，只求找个靠河或者近湖的地方给自己买下一个小小的庄园才好。”

“他是个温和善良的人，我喜欢他，可是这种把自己关在自家小庄园里过一辈子的愿望，我却素来不同情人们通常说：一个人只需要三俄尺的土地[2]。可是要知道需要三俄尺土地的是死尸，而不是活人。现在还有人说要是我们的知识分子向往土地，盼望有个庄园，那是好事。可是要知道，这些庄园跟三俄尺土地差不多。离开城市，离开斗争，离开生活的喧嚣，隐居起来，躲在自己的庄园里，这算不得生活，这是自私自利，偷懒，这也算是一种修道主义，可又是不见成绩的修道主义。人所需要的不是三俄尺土地，也不是一个庄园，而是整个地球，整个大自然，在那广阔的天地中人才能够尽情发挥他自由精神的所有品质和特点。

“我的弟弟尼古拉坐在他的办公室里，梦想将来怎样喝他自己家里的白菜汤，那种令人馋涎欲滴的香气弥漫在整个院子里。怎样在绿草地上吃饭，怎样在太阳底下睡觉，一连好几个钟头坐在大门外的凳子上眺望田野和树林。农艺书和日历上一切有关农艺方面的意见给了他乐趣，成了他心爱的精神食粮。他还喜欢看报，可是他光看报纸上的一种广告，说某地有若干俄亩[3]田地，连同草场、庄园、小溪、花园、磨坊和活水的池塘等一并出售。他脑子里就暗暗描出花园的幽径、花卉、水果、椋鸟巢、池塘里的鲫鱼，总之，你们知道，诸如此类的东西。这些想象的图画因他看到的广告不同而有所不同，可是不知什么缘故，其中每一个画面都一定有醋栗。他不能想象一个庄园，一个饶有诗意的安乐窝里会没有醋栗。

“‘乡村生活自有它舒服的地方，’他常说，‘人可以在露台上坐着，喝喝茶，自己养的小鸭子在池塘里泅水，空中弥漫着好闻的气味，而且……而且醋栗成熟了。’

“他常描画他田庄的草图，而每一回他的草图上都离不了这几样东西：（一）主人的正房，（二）仆人的下房，（三）菜园，（四）醋栗。他生活节俭，省吃省喝，上帝才知道他穿的是什么衣服，活像个叫花子；他不断地攒钱，存在银行里。他成了财迷。我一瞧见他就痛心，常给他点钱遇到过节也总要寄点钱给他，可是他连这点钱也收藏起来。一个人要是打定了主意，那你就拿他没办法了。

“若干年过去了，他调到另一个省里去了。他年纪已经过了四十岁，却仍旧看报上的广告，存钱。后来我听说他结婚了。他仍旧存心要买一个有醋栗的庄园，娶一个年老而难看的寡妇，对她一点感情也谈不上，只是因为她有几个钱罢了。跟她结婚以后，他生活仍旧吝啬老是弄得她吃不饱，同时，把她的钱存在银行里，却写上他自己的名字。早先她嫁给一个邮政局长，跟他一块儿过活的时候，吃惯馅饼，喝惯果子露酒，可是跟第二个丈夫一块儿过日子，却连黑面包也吃不饱。过着这样的生活，她开始憔悴，不出三年就把灵魂交给上帝了[4]当然，我的弟弟根本也没想过她的死要由他负责。金钱跟白酒一样，会把人变成怪物。从前我们城里有个垂危的商人。他临死叫人给他端来一碟蜂蜜，把他所有的钱钞和彩票就着蜜一股脑儿吃到肚子里，叫谁也得不着有一回我正在一个火车站检查畜群，正巧有个马贩子失足摔在火车头底下，压断了一条腿。我们把他抬到急诊室里，血哗哗地流，样子真是可怕，可是他老是求大家找回他的腿，老是放心不下：原来那条压断的腿所穿的靴子里有二十卢布，他生怕那点钱丢了。”

“您岔到别的事情上去了。”布尔金说。

“我的弟媳死后，”伊万·伊万内奇沉吟了半分钟，接着说，“我弟弟就开始给他自己物色一份田产。当然，尽管物色了五年，到头来仍旧会出错，买下来的东西跟所想望的迥然不同。我弟弟尼古拉托中人买了一个抵押过的庄园，有一百一十二俄亩，有主人的正房，有仆人的下房，有花园，可是单单没有果树园，没有醋栗，没有池塘和小鸭子。河倒是有，可是河水的颜色跟咖啡一样，因为庄园的一边是造砖厂，另一边是烧兽骨的工场[5]。”

“可是我的尼古拉·伊万内奇倒也并不十分难过，他订购二十株醋栗树，栽好，照地主的排场过起来了。

“去年我去探望他。我心想我要去看看那儿的情况怎么样。我弟弟在来信上称它为‘楚木巴罗克洛夫芜园，又称希马莱斯科耶’。我是在下午到达那个‘又称希马莱斯科耶’的。天很热。到处都是沟渠、围墙、篱笆、栽成一行行的杉树，弄得人不知道怎样才能走到院子里去，应该把马拴在哪儿。我往正房走去，迎面遇见一条红毛的肥狗，活像一头猪。它本想叫一声，可又懒得叫。厨娘从厨房里走出来，是一个光脚的胖女人，看样子也像一头猪。她说主人吃过饭后正在休息。我走进去看我弟弟他在床上坐着，膝上盖着一条被子。他老了，胖了，皮肉发松，他的脸颊、鼻子、嘴唇，全都往前拱出去，眼看就要跟猪那样呼噜呼噜叫着钻进被子里去了。

“我们互相拥抱，流下了眼泪，一半因为高兴，一半也因为忧郁地想到，从前我们都年轻，现在两人却白发苍苍，快要入土了。他穿好衣服，领我出去看他的田庄。

“‘哦，您在这儿过得怎么样？’我问。

“‘哦，还不坏，感谢上帝，我过得挺好。’

“他不再是往日那个畏畏缩缩的、可怜的小职员，而是真正的地主老爷了。他已经在这儿住熟，习惯，觉得很有味道了。他吃得很多，常到澡棚去洗澡，长得胖起来已经跟村社和两个工厂打过官司，遇上农民不称呼他‘老爷’，就老大地不高兴。他还带着老爷气派郑重其事地关心他的灵魂的得救，就做起好事来，然而并不是简简单单地做，却是摆足了架子做的。然而那是什么样的好事啊！他用苏打和蓖麻子油给农民治各种病，到了他的命名日就在村子中央做一回谢恩祈祷，然后摆出半桶白酒来请农民喝，自以为事情就该这么办。啊，那可怕的半桶白酒！今天，这位胖地主拉着农民们到地方行政长官那儿去控告他们放出牲畜来践踏他的庄稼，明天遇上隆重的节日，却请那些农民喝半桶白酒。他们喝酒，嚷着：‘乌拉！’喝醉了的人就给他叩头。生活只要变得好一点，吃得饱，喝得足，闲着不做事，就会在俄罗斯人身上培养出顶骄横的自大。尼古拉·伊万内奇当初在税务局里自己甚至不敢有自己的见解，现在说起话来却没有一句不是真理，而且总是用大臣的口气：‘教育是必不可少的，然而对老百姓来说，还未免言之过早。’‘总的来说体罚是有害的，可是遇到某些情形，这却是有益的，不可缺少的。’

“‘我了解老百姓，我会善于对付他们，’他说，‘老百姓都喜欢我。我只要动一动手指头，老百姓就会把我要办的事统统给我办好。’

“请注意，这些话都是带着聪明而善良的笑容说出来的。他把‘我们这些贵族’‘我以贵族的身份看来’反反复复说了二十遍。他分明已经不记得我们的祖父是个庄稼汉、父亲是个兵了。就连我们的姓，奇姆沙－希马莱斯基，实际上十分古怪，可他现在也觉着响亮、高贵十分中意了。

“可是问题不在他，而在我自己了。我要跟你们讲一讲我在他那庄园上盘桓了短短几个钟头，我自己起了什么变化。傍晚，我们正在喝茶，厨娘端来满满一盘醋栗放在桌子上。这不是买来的，而是他自己家里种的，自从那些灌木栽下以后，这还是头一回收果子。尼古拉·伊万内奇笑起来，对那些醋栗默默地瞧了一会儿，眼泪汪汪，激动得说不出话来。然后他拿起一颗果子送进嘴里瞧着我，现出小孩子终于得到心爱的玩具那种得意的神情，说：

“‘多么好吃啊！’

“他贪婪地吃着，不住地重复道：

“‘嘿，多么好吃啊！你尝一尝吧！’

“那些醋栗又硬又酸，可是正如普希金所说：‘我们喜爱使人高兴的谎话，胜过喜爱许许多多的真理。’[6]我看见了一个幸福的人，他心心念念的梦想显然已经实现他的生活目标已经达到，他所想望的东西已经到手，他对他的命运和他自己都满意了。不知什么缘故，往常我一想到人的幸福，就不免带一点哀伤的感觉，这一回亲眼看到幸福的人，我竟生出一种跟绝望相近的沉重感。夜里我心头特别沉重。他们在我弟弟卧室的隔壁房间里为我搭好一张床，我听见他没有睡着，老是爬下床来，走到那盘醋栗跟前，拿果子吃。我心想：实际上有多少满足而幸福的人啊！这是一种多么令人压抑的力量！你们来看一看这种生活吧：强者骄横而懒惰，弱者无知而且跟牲畜那样生活着，处处都是叫人难以忍受的贫穷、拥挤、退化、酗酒、伪善、撒谎……可是偏偏所有的屋子里也好，街上也好，却一味地心平气和，安安静静。一个城市的五万居民当中竟没有一个人叫喊一声，大声发泄一下他的愤慨。我们看见人们到市场上去买食物，白天吃饭，晚上睡觉，他们说废话，结婚，衰老，心平气和地送死人到墓园去。可是那些受苦受难的人，那些在幕后什么地方正在进行着的人生惨事，我们却没看见，也没听见。处处都安静而太平，提抗议的只有那些没声音的统计表：若干人发了疯，若干桶白酒喝光了，若干儿童死于营养不良……这样的世道显然是必要的，幸福的人之所以会感到逍遥自在，显然只是因为那些不幸的人沉默地背着他们的重担，而缺了这种沉默想要幸福就办不到。这是普遍的麻木不仁。每一个幸福而满足的人的房门边都应当站上一个人，拿一个小锤子经常敲着门提醒他：天下还有不幸的人，不管他自己怎样幸福，生活早晚会向他伸出魔爪，灾难会降临——疾病啦，贫穷啦，损失啦，到那时候谁也不会看见他，谁也不会听见他就跟现在他看不见别人，听不见别人一样。可是却没有拿小锤子的人，幸福的人无忧无虑地生活下去，日常的小烦恼微微地扰动他，就跟风吹动白杨一样，真是天下太平。”

“那天晚上我才明白：我也幸福而满足，”伊万·伊万内奇站起来接着说，“我在吃饭和打猎的时候也教导过别人，应该怎样生活，怎样信仰宗教，怎样驾驭老百姓我也常说学问是光明，教育是必不可少的，可是对普通人来说，目前只要认得字，能写字，也就够了。我常说自由是好东西，我们生活中不能没有它，就跟不能没有空气一样，不过我们得等待。对了，我常说那样的话现在我却要问：为什么要等？”伊万·伊万内奇生气地瞧着布尔金问道，“我问你们，为什么要等？根据什么理由？人家对我说，什么事都不是一下子就能办到的，各种思想都要渐渐地到一定的时期才能在生活里实现。可是这话是谁说的？有什么证据能够证明这话对？你们引证事物的自然规律，引证社会现象的合法性，可是我，一个有思想的活人，站在一道壕沟面前，本来也许可以从上面跳过去，或者在上面搭座桥走过去，却偏要等它自动封口，或者等它让淤泥填满，难道这样的事还说得上什么规律和合法性？再说一遍，为什么要等？等到没有了生活的力量才算吗？可是人又非生活不可，而且也渴望生活！”

“我一清早就离开了我弟弟的家，从此我在城里住着就感到不能忍受。城里的那种和平安静压得我不好受。我不敢看人家的窗子，因为这时候再也没有比幸福的一家人团团围住桌子喝茶的光景更使我难受的了。我已经老了，不适宜做斗争了，我甚至不会憎恨人了。我只能满心地悲伤，生气，烦恼，一到夜里，我的脑子里种种思想纷至沓来，弄得我十分激动，睡不着觉……唉，要是我年轻点就好了！”

伊万·伊万内奇激动得从这个墙角走到那个墙角，反复地说：

“要是我年轻就好了！”

他忽然走到阿廖欣面前，先是握住他的一只手，后来又握住他的另一只手。

“帕维尔·康斯坦丁内奇！”他用恳求的声调说，“不要心平气和，不要容您自己昏睡！趁您还年轻力壮，血气方刚，要永不疲倦地做好事情！幸福是没有的，也不应当有。如果生活有意义，有目标，那意义和目标就绝不是我们自己的幸福，而是比这更伟大更合理的东西做好事吧！”

所有这些话，伊万·伊万内奇都是带着可怜的、恳求的笑脸说出来的，仿佛他本人为自己请求一桩什么事似的。

然后这三个人在客厅里挑了三张圈椅各据一方坐下来，沉默了。伊万·伊万内奇的故事既没满足布尔金也没满足阿廖欣。金边镜框里的将军们和太太们在昏光中显得像是活人，低下眼睛来瞧他们，在这样的时候听那个可怜的、吃醋栗的文官的故事觉得乏味得很。不知什么缘故他们很想谈一谈或者听一听高雅的人和女人的事。他们所在的这个客厅里，样样东西，蒙着套子的枝形烛架啦，圈椅啦，脚底下的地毯啦，都在述说如今在镜框里低下眼睛瞧他们的那些人，从前就在这房间里走动过，坐过，喝过茶，现在俊俏的佩拉格娅正在这儿没一点声音地走来走去，这倒比一切故事都美妙得多呢。

阿廖欣困得要命，他一清早两点多钟就起床干农活儿，现在他的眼皮粘在一起了，可是他生怕客人等他走后也许会讲出什么有趣的故事，就流连着没走。他并没细想伊万·伊万内奇刚才所讲的是不是有道理、正确，反正他的客人没谈起麦粒，也没谈起干草，也没谈起煤焦油，所谈的都是跟他的生活没有什么直接关系的事，他不由得暗自高兴，盼望他们接着谈下去才好……

“不过，现在该睡了，”布尔金说，站起来，“请允许我跟你们道一声晚安吧。”

阿廖欣道了晚安，走下楼回到自己的住处去。客人们仍旧待在楼上。他俩被人领到一个大房间里过夜，房间里安着两张旧的雕花木床，墙角有一个象牙的耶稣受难像的十字架。那两张凉快的大床由美丽的佩拉格娅铺好了被褥，新洗过的床单冒出好闻的气味。

伊万·伊万内奇一声不响地脱掉衣服，躺下。

“主啊，饶恕我们这些罪人吧！”他说，拉过被子来蒙上头。

他的烟斗放在桌子上，冒出一股浓烈的烟草的焦气。布尔金很久睡不着觉，不住地纳闷儿，想不出这股难闻的气味是打哪儿来的。

雨点通宵抽打着窗子。

[1] 在19世纪中叶的俄国，兵士的儿子从出生的那天起就编入军籍，到相当年龄就入军事学校受训。

[2] 1俄尺等于0.711米，3俄尺的土地指墓穴的长度。

[3] 1俄亩等于1.09公顷。

[4] 意思是“死了”。

[5] 烧兽骨是为了制胶。

[6] 引自普希金的诗《英雄》，但引文不全，原文是：“我们喜爱使人高兴的谎话胜过喜爱许许多多卑微的真理。”——俄文本编者注

The Kiss

On 20 May, at eight o’clock in the evening, all six batteries of a reserve artillery brigade, on their way back to headquarters, stopped for the night at the village of Mestechki. At the height of all the confusion – some officers were busy with the guns, while others had assembled in the main square by the churchyard fence to receive their billetings – someone in civilian dress rode up from behind the church on a strange horse: it was small and dun- coloured with a fine neck and short tail, and seemed to move sideways instead of straight ahead, making small dancing movements with its legs as if they were being whipped. When the rider came up to the officers he doffed his hat and said, ‘Our squire, His Excellency, Lieutenant- General von Rabbeck, invites you for tea and would like you to come now . . .’

The horse performed a bow and a little dance, and retreated with the same sideways motion. The rider raised his hat again and quickly disappeared behind the church on his peculiar horse.

‘To hell with it!’ some of the officers grumbled as they rode off to their quarters. ‘We want to sleep and up pops this von Rabbeck with his tea! We know what that means all right!’

Every officer in the six batteries vividly remembered the previous year when they were on manoeuvres with officers from a Cossack regiment and had received a similar invitation from a landowning count, who was a retired officer. This hospitable and genial count had plied them with food and drink, would not hear of them returning to their billets and made them stay the night. That was all very well, of course, and they could not have hoped for better. But the trouble was that this retired officer was overjoyed beyond measure at having young men as his guests and he regaled them with stories from his glorious past until dawn, led them on a tour of the house, showed them his valuable paintings, old engravings and rare guns, and read out signed letters from eminent personages; and all this time the tired and weary officers listened, looked, pined for bed, and continuously yawned in their sleeves. When their host finally let them go, it was too late for bed.

Now, was this von Rabbeck one of the same breed? Whether he was or not, there was nothing they could do about it. The officers put clean uniforms on, smartened themselves up and went off en masse to look for the squire’s house. On the square by the church they were told that they could either take the lower path leading down to the river behind the church, and then go along the bank to the garden, or they could ride direct from the church along the higher road which would bring them to the count’s barns about a quarter of a mile from the village. The officers decided on the higher route.

‘Who is this von Rabbeck?’ they argued as they rode along. ‘Is he the one who commanded a cavalry division at Plevna?’

‘No, that wasn’t von Rabbeck, just Rabbe, and without the “von”.’

‘It’s marvellous weather, anyway!’

The road divided when they reached the first barn: one fork led straight on and disappeared in the darkness of the evening, while the other turned towards the squire’s house on the right. The officers took the right fork and began to lower their voices . . . Stone barns with red tiled roofs stood on both sides of the road and they had the heavy, forbidding look of some provincial barracks. Ahead of them were the lighted windows of the manor- house.

‘That’s a good sign, gentlemen!’ one of the officers said.‘Our setter’s going on in front. That means he scents game!’

Lieutenant Lobytko, a tall, strongly built officer, who was riding ahead of the others, who had no moustache (although he was over twenty- five there wasn’t a trace of hair on his face), and who was renowned in the brigade for his keen senses and ability to sniff a woman out from miles away, turned round and said, ‘Yes, there must be women here, my instinct tells me.’

The officers were met at the front door by von Rabbeck himself – a fine- looking man of about sixty, wearing civilian clothes. He said how very pleased and happy he was to see the officers as he shook hands, but begged them most sincerely, in the name of God, to excuse him for not inviting them to stay the night, as two sisters with their children, his brothers and some neighbours had turned up, and he didn’t have one spare room.

The general shook everyone’s hand, apologized and smiled, but they could tell from his face that he wasn’t nearly as pleased to have guests as last year’s count and he had only asked them as it was the done thing. And, as they climbed the softly carpeted stairs and listened, the officers sensed that they had been invited only because it would have caused embarrassment if they had not been invited. At the sight of footmen dashing around lighting the lamps in the hall and upstairs, they felt they had introduced a note of uneasiness and anxiety into the house. And how could any host be pleased at having nineteen strange officers descend on a house where two sisters, children, brothers and neighbours had already arrived, most probably to celebrate some family anniversary. They were met in the ballroom upstairs by a tall, stately old lady with black eyebrows and a long face – the living image of Empress Eugénie. She gave them a majestic, welcoming smile and said how glad and happy she was to have them as guests and apologized for the fact that she and her husband weren’t able to invite the officers to stay overnight on this occasion. Her beautiful, majestic smile, which momentarily disappeared every time she turned away from her guests, revealed that in her day she had seen many officers, that she had no time for them now, and that she had invited them and was apologizing only because her upbringing and social position demanded it.

The officers entered the large dining- room where about ten gentlemen and ladies, old and young, were sitting along one side of the table having tea. Behind their chairs, enveloped in a thin haze of cigar smoke, was a group of men with a rather lean, young, red- whiskered man in the middle, rolling his ‘r’s as he spoke out loud in English. Behind them, through a door, was a bright room with light blue furniture.

‘Gentlemen, there’s so many of you, it’s impossible to introduce everyone!’ the general was saying in a loud voice, trying to sound cheerful. ‘So don’t stand on ceremony, introduce yourselves!’

Some officers wore very serious, even solemn expressions; others forced a smile, and all of them felt awkward as they bowed rather indifferently and sat down to tea.

Staff- Captain Ryabovich, a short, stooping officer, with spectacles and lynx- like side whiskers, was more embarrassed than anyone else. While his fellow- officers were trying to look serious or force a smile, his face, lynx- like whiskers and spectacles seemed to be saying, ‘I’m the shyest, most modest and most insignificant officer in the whole brigade!’ When he first entered the dining- room and sat down to tea, he found it impossible to concentrate on any one face or object. All those faces, dresses, cut- glass decanters, steaming glasses, moulded cornices, merged into one composite sensation, making Ryabovich feel ill at ease, and he longed to bury his head somewhere. Like a lecturer at his first appearance in public, he could see everything in front of him well enough, but at the same time he could make little sense of it (physicians call this condition, when someone sees without understanding, ‘psychic blindness’). But after a little while Ryabovich began to feel more at home, recovered his normal vision and began to take stock of his surroundings. Since he was a timid and unsociable person, he was struck above all by what he himself had never possessed – the extraordinary boldness of these unfamiliar people. Von Rabbeck, two elderly ladies, a young girl in a lilac dress, and the young man with red whiskers – Rabbeck’s youngest son – had sat themselves very cunningly among the officers, as though it had all been rehearsed. Straight away they had launched into a heated argument, which the guests could not help joining. The girl in lilac very excitedly insisted that the artillery had a much easier time than either the cavalry or the infantry, while Rabbeck and the elderly ladies argued the contrary. A rapid conversational crossfire ensued. Ryabovich glanced at the lilac girl who was arguing so passionately about something that was so foreign to her, so utterly boring, and he could see artificial smiles flickering over her face.

Von Rabbeck and family skilfully drew the officers into the argument, at the same time watching their wine glasses with eagle eyes to check whether they were filled, that they had enough sugar, and one officer who wasn’t eating biscuits or drinking any brandy worried them. The more Ryabovich looked and listened, the more he began to like this insincere but wonderfully disciplined family.

After tea the officers went into the ballroom. Lieutenant Lobytko’s instinct had not failed him: the room was full of girls and young married women. Already this ‘setter’ lieutenant had positioned himself next to a young blonde in a black dress, bending over dashingly as though leaning on some invisible sabre, smiling and flirting with his shoulders. Most probably he was telling her some intriguing nonsense as the blonde glanced superciliously at his well- fed face and said, ‘Really?’

If that ‘setter’ had had any brains, that cool ‘Really?’should have told him that he would never be called ‘to heel’.

The grand piano suddenly thundered out. The sounds of a sad waltz drifted through the wide- open windows and everyone remembered that outside it was spring, an evening in May, and they smelt the fragrance of the young leaves of the poplars, of roses and lilac. Ryabovich, feeling the effects of the brandy and the music, squinted at a window, smiled and watched the movements of the women. Now it seemed that the fragrance of the roses, the poplars and lilac wasn’t coming from the garden but from the ladies’ faces and dresses.

Rabbeck’s son had invited a skinny girl to dance and waltzed twice round the room with her. Lobytko glided over the parquet floor as he flew up to the girl in lilac and whirled her round the room. They all began to dance . . . Ryabovich stood by the door with guests who were not dancing and watched. Not once in his life had he danced, not once had he put his arm round an attractive young woman’s waist. He would usually be absolutely delighted when, with everyone looking on, a man took a young girl he hadn’t met before by the waist and offered his shoulders for her to rest her hands on, but he could never imagine himself in that situation. There had been times when he envied his fellow- officers’daring and dashing ways and it made him very depressed. The realization that he was shy, round- shouldered, quite undistinguished, that he had a long waist, lynx- like side whiskers, hurt him deeply. But over the years this realization had become something of a habit and as he watched his friends dance or talk out loud he no longer envied them but was filled with sadness.

When the quadrille began, young von Rabbeck went over to the officers who were not dancing and invited two of them to a game of billiards. They accepted and left the great hall with him. As he had nothing else to do, and feeling he would like to take at least some part in what was going on, Ryabovich trudged off after them. First they went into the drawing- room, then down a narrow corridor with a glass ceiling, then into a room where three sleepy footmen leapt up from a sofa the moment they entered. Finally, after passing through a whole series of rooms, young Rabbeck and company reached a small billiard- room and the game began.

Ryabovich, who never played any games except cards, stood by the table and indifferently watched the players, cue in hand, walking up and down in their unbuttoned tunics, making puns and shouting things he could not understand. The players ignored him, only turning round to say, ‘I beg your pardon’, when one of them happened accidentally to nudge him with an elbow or prod him with a cue. Even before the first game was over, he was bored and began to feel he was not wanted, that he was in the way . . . He felt drawn back to the ballroom and walked away.

As he walked back he had a little adventure. Halfway, he realized he was lost – he knew very well he had to go by those three sleepy footmen, but already he had passed through five or six rooms and those footmen seemed to have vanished into thin air. He realized his mistake, retraced his steps a little and turned to the right, only to find himself in a small, dimly lit room he had not seen on the way to the billiard- room. He stood still for a minute or so, opened the first door he came to with determination and entered a completely dark room. Ahead of him he could see light coming through a crack in the door and beyond was the muffled sound of a sad mazurka. The windows here had been left open as they had in the ballroom and he could smell poplars, lilac and roses . . .

Ryabovich stopped, undecided what to do . . . Just then he was astonished to hear hurried footsteps, the rustle of a dress and a female voice whispering breathlessly, ‘At last!’Two soft, sweet- smelling arms (undoubtedly a woman’s) encircled his neck, a burning cheek pressed against his and at the same time there was the sound of a kiss. But immediately after the kiss the woman gave a faint cry and shrank backwards in disgust – that was how it seemed to Ryabovich.

He was on the point of crying out too and he rushed towards the bright chink in the door.

His heart pounded away when he was back in the hall and his hands trembled so obviously that he hastily hid them behind his back. At first he was tormented by shame and he feared everyone there knew he had just been embraced and kissed, and this made him hesitate and look around anxiously. But when he had convinced himself that everyone was dancing and gossiping just as peacefully as before, he gave himself up to a totally new kind of sensation, one he had never experienced before in all his life. Something strange was happening to him . . . his neck, which just a few moments ago had been embraced by sweet- smelling hands, seemed anointed with oil. And on his left cheek, just by his moustache, there was a faint, pleasant, cold, tingling sensation, the kind you get from peppermint drops and the more he rubbed the spot the stronger the tingling became. From head to heels he was overcome by a strange, new feeling which grew stronger every minute. He wanted to dance, speak to everyone, run out into the garden, laugh out loud. He completely forgot his stoop, his insignificant appearance, his lynx- like whiskers and ‘vague appearance’ (once he happened to hear some ladies saying this about him). When Rabbeck’s wife went by he gave her such a broad, warm smile that she stopped and gave him a very searching look.

‘I love this house so much!’ he said, adjusting his spectacles.

The general’s wife smiled and told him that the house still belonged to her father. Then she asked if his parents were still alive, how long he had been in the army, why he was so thin, and so on . . . When Ryabovich had replied, she moved on, leaving him smiling even more warmly and he began to think he was surrounded by the most wonderful people . . .

Mechanically, Ryabovich ate and drank everything he was offered at the dinner table, deaf to everything as he tried to find an explanation for what had just happened. It was a mysterious, romantic incident, but it wasn’t difficult to explain. No doubt some girl or young married woman had a rendezvous with someone in that dark room, had waited for a long time, and then mistook Ryabovich for her hero in her nervous excitement. This was the most likely explanation, all the more so as Ryabovich had hesitated in the middle of the room, which made it look as though he were expecting someone . . .

‘But who is she?’ he thought as he surveyed the ladies’faces. ‘She must be young, as old ladies don’t have rendezvous. And intelligent – I could tell from the rustle of her dress, her smell, her voice.’

He stared at the girl in lilac and found her very attractive. She had beautiful shoulders and arms, a clever face and a fine voice. As he gazed at her, Ryabovich wanted her, no one else, to be that mysterious stranger . . . But she gave a rather artificial laugh and wrinkled her long nose, which made her look old. Then he turned to the blonde in black. She was younger, simpler and less affected, with charming temples and she sipped daintily from her wine glass. Now Ryabovich wanted her to be the stranger. But he soon discovered that she had a featureless face and he turned to her neighbour . . . ‘It’s hard to say,’ he wondered dreamily. ‘If I could just take the lilac girl’s shoulders and arms away, add the blonde’s temples, then take those eyes away from the girl on Lobytko’s left, then.’ He merged them all into one, so that he had an image of the girl who had kissed him, the image he desired so much, but which he just could not find among the guests around the table.

After dinner the officers, well- fed and slightly tipsy by now, began to make their farewells and expressed their thanks. Once again the hosts apologized for not having them stay the night.

‘Delighted, gentlemen, absolutely delighted,’ the general was saying and this time he meant it – probably because people are usually more sincere and better- humoured saying goodbye to guests than welcoming them.

‘Delighted! Glad to see you back any time, so don’t stand on ceremony. Which way are you going? The higher road? No, go through the garden, it’s quicker.’

The officers went into the garden, where it seemed very dark and quiet after the bright lights and the noise. They did not say a word all the way to the gate. They were half- drunk, cheerful and contented, but the darkness and the silence made them pause for thought. Probably they were thinking the same as Ryabovich: would they ever see the day when they would own a large house, have a family, a garden, when they too would be able to entertain people (however much of a pretence this might be), feed them well, make them drunk and happy?

As they went through the garden gate they all started talking at once and, for no apparent reason, laughed out loud. Now they were descending the path that led down to the river and then ran along the water’s edge, weaving its way around the bushes, the little pools of water and the willows which overhung the river. The bank and the path were barely visible, and the far side was plunged in darkness. Here and there were reflections of the stars in the water, quivering and breaking up into little patches – the only sign that the river was flowing fast. All was quiet. Sleepy sandpipers called plaintively from the far bank and on the near side a nightingale in a bush poured out its song, ignoring the passing officers.

The men paused by the bush, touched it, but still the nightingale sang.

‘That’s a bird for you!’ approving voices murmured. ‘Here we are, right next to him and he doesn’t take a blind bit of notice! What a rascal!’

The path finally turned upwards and came out on to the high road by the church fence. The officers were exhausted from walking up the hill and sat down for a smoke. On the far bank they could make out a dim red light and they tried to pass the time by guessing whether it was a camp fire, a light in a window, or something else . . . Ryabovich looked at it and imagined that the light was winking at him and smiling, as though it knew all about that kiss.

When he reached his quarters Ryabovich quickly undressed and lay on his bed. In the same hut were Lobytko and Lieutenant Merzlyakov, a gentle, rather quiet young man, who was considered well- educated in his own little circle. He was always reading the European Herald when he had the chance and took it with him everywhere. Lobytko undressed, paced up and down for a long time, with the expression of a dissatisfied man, and sent the batman for some beer.

Merzlyakov lay down, placed a candle near his pillow and immersed himself in the European Herald.

‘Who is she?’ Ryabovich wondered as he glanced at the grimy ceiling. His neck still felt as if it had been anointed with oil and he had that tingling sensation around his mouth – just like peppermint drops. He had fleeting visions of the lilac girl’s shoulders and arms, the temples and truthful eyes of the blonde in black, waists, dresses, brooches. He tried to fix these visions firmly in his mind, but they kept dancing about, dissolving, flickering. When these visions vanished completely against that darkened background everyone has when he closes his eyes, he began to hear hurried steps, rustling dresses, the sound of a kiss and he was gripped by an inexplicable, overwhelming feeling of joy. Just as he was abandoning himself to it, he heard the batman come back and report that there wasn’t any beer. Lobytko became terribly agitated and started pacing up and down again.

‘Didn’t I tell you he’s an idiot?’ he said, stopping first in front of Ryabovich, then Merzlyakov. ‘A man must really be a blockhead and idiot to come back without any beer! The man’s a rogue, eh?’

‘Of course, you won’t find any beer in this place,’ Merzlyakov said without taking his eyes off the European Herald.

‘Oh, do you really think so?’ Lobytko persisted. ‘Good God, put me on the moon and I’ll find you beer and women right away! Yes, I’ll go now and find some . . . Call me a scoundrel if I don’t succeed!’

He slowly dressed and pulled on his high boots. Then he finished his cigarette in silence and left.

‘Rabbeck, Grabbeck, Labbeck,’ he muttered, pausing in the hall. ‘I don’t feel like going on my own, dammit! Fancy a little walk, Ryabovich?’

There was no reply, so he came back, slowly undressed and got into bed. Merzlyakov sighed, put the European Herald away and snuffed the candle.

‘Hm,’ Lobytko murmured as he puffed his cigarette in the dark.

Ryabovich pulled the blankets over his head, curled himself into a ball and tried to merge the visions fleeting through his mind into one fixed image. But he failed completely. Soon he fell asleep and his last waking thought was of someone caressing him and making him happy, of something absurd and unusual, but nonetheless exceptionally fine and joyful, that had entered his life. And his dreams centred around this one thought.

When he woke up, the sensation of oil on his cheek and the minty tingling near his lips had vanished, but the joy of yesterday still filled his heart. Delighted, he watched the window frames, gilded now by the rising sun, and listened intently to the street noises. Outside, just by the window, he could hear loud voices – Lebedetsky, Ryabovich’s battery commander, who had just caught up with the brigade, was shouting at his sergeant – simply because he had lost the habit of talking softly.

‘Is there anything else?’ he roared.

‘When they were shoeing yesterday, sir, someone drove a nail into Pigeon’s hoof. The medical orderly put clay and vinegar on it and they’re keeping the horse reined, away from the others. And artificer Artemyev got drunk yesterday and the lieutenant had him tied to the fore- carriage of an auxiliary field- gun.’

And the sergeant had more to report. Karpov had forgotten the new cords for the trumpets and the stakes for the tents, and the officers had spent the previous evening as guests of General von Rabbeck. During the conversation, Lebedetsky’s head and red beard appeared at the window. He blinked his short- sighted eyes at the sleepy officers and bade them good morning.

‘Everything all right?’ he asked.

‘One of the shaft- horses damaged its withers – it was the new collar,’ Lobytko answered, yawning.

The commander sighed, pondered for a moment and said in a loud voice, ‘I’m still wondering whether to pay Aleksandra a visit, I really ought to go and see how she is. Well, goodbye for now, I’ll catch you up by evening.’

A quarter of an hour later the brigade moved off. As it passed the general’s barns, Ryabovich looked to the right where the house was. The blinds were drawn in all the windows. Clearly, everyone was still asleep. And the girl who had kissed Ryabovich the day before was sleeping too. He tried to imagine her as she slept and he had a clear and distinct picture of the wide- open windows, the little green branches peeping into her bedroom, the morning freshness, the smell of poplars, lilac and roses, her bed and the chair with that dress which had rustled the day before lying over it, tiny slippers, a watch on the table. But the actual features of that face, that sweet, dreamy smile, exactly what was most characteristic of her, slipped through his imagination like mercury through the fingers. When he had ridden about a quarter of a mile, he looked back. The yellow church, the house, the river and garden were flooded in sunlight and the river, with its bright green banks and its waters reflecting the light blue sky and glinting silver here and there, looked very beautiful. Ryabovich took a last look at Mestechki and he felt so sad, as if he were saying farewell to what was very near and dear to him.

But there were only long- familiar, boring scenes ahead of him. On both sides of the road there were fields of young rye and buckwheat, where crows were hopping about. Ahead, all he could see was dust and the backs of soldiers’heads; and behind, the same dust, the same faces. The brigade was led by a vanguard of four soldiers bearing sabres and behind them rode the military choristers, followed by trumpeters. Every now and then, like torchbearers in a funeral cortège, the vanguard and singers ignored the regulation distance and pushed on far ahead. Ryabovich rode alongside the first field- gun of the fifth battery and he could see the other four in front. These long, ponderous processions formed by brigades on the move can strike civilians as very peculiar, an unintelligible muddle, and non- military people just cannot fathom why a single field- gun has to be escorted by so many soldiers, why it has to be drawn by so many horses all tangled up in such strange harness, as if it really was such a terrible, heavy object. But Ryabovich understood everything perfectly well and for that reason he found it all extremely boring. He had long known why a hefty bombardier always rides with the officer at the head of every battery and why he is called an outrider. Immediately behind this bombardier came the riders on the first, then the middle- section trace- horses. Ryabovich knew that the horses to the left were saddle- horses, while those on the right were auxiliary – all this was very boring. The horsemen were followed by two shaft- horses, one ridden by a horseman with yesterday’s dust still on his back and who had a clumsy- looking, very comical piece of wood fixed to his right leg. Ryabovich knew what it was for and did not find it funny. All the riders waved their whips mechanically and shouted now and again. As for the field- gun, it was an ugly thing. Sacks of oats covered with tarpaulin lay on the fore- carriage and the gun itself was hung with kettles, kitbags and little sacks: it resembled a small harmless animal which had been surrounded, for some reason, by men and horses. On the side sheltered from the wind a team of six strode along, swinging their arms. This gun was followed by more bombardiers, riders, shaft- horses and another field- gun – just as ugly and uninspiring as the first –lumbering along in the rear. After the second gun came a third, then a fourth with an officer riding alongside (there are six batteries to a brigade and four guns to a battery). The whole procession stretched about a quarter of a mile and ended with the baggage wagons, where a most likeable creature plodded thoughtfully along, his long- eared head drooping: this was Magar the donkey, brought from Turkey by a certain battery commander.

Ryabovich looked apathetically at all those necks and faces in front and behind. At any other time he would have dozed off, but now he was immersed in new, pleasant thoughts. When the brigade had first set off, he had tried to convince himself that the incident of the kiss was only some unimportant, mysterious adventure and that essentially it was trivial and too ridiculous for serious thought. But very quickly he waved logic aside and gave himself up to his dreams. First he pictured himself in von Rabbeck’s drawing- room, sitting next to a girl who resembled both the girl in lilac and the blonde in black. Then he closed his eyes and imagined himself with another, completely strange girl, with very indeterminate features: in his thoughts he spoke to her, caressed her and leaned his head on her shoulder. Then he thought of war and separation, reunion, dinner with his wife and children . . .

‘Brakes on!’ rang out the command every time they went downhill. He shouted the command too, and feared that his own shouts would shatter his daydreams and bring him back to reality.

As they passed some estate, Ryabovich peeped over the fence into the garden. There he saw a long avenue, straight as a ruler, strewn with yellow sand and lined with young birches. With the eagerness of a man who has surrendered himself to daydreaming, he imagined tiny female feet walking over the yellow sand. And, quite unexpectedly, he had a clear mental picture of the girl who had kissed him, the girl he had visualized the previous evening during dinner. This image had planted itself in his mind and would not leave him.

At midday someone shouted from a wagon in the rear,‘Attention, eyes left! Officers!’

The brigadier drove up in an open carriage drawn by two white horses. He ordered it to stop near the second battery and shouted something no one understood. Several officers galloped over to him, Ryabovich among them.

‘Well, what’s the news?’ asked the brigadier, blinking his red eyes. ‘Anyone ill?’

When they had replied, the brigadier, a small skinny man, chewed for a moment, pondered and then turned to one of the officers: ‘One of your drivers, on the third gun, has taken his knee- guard off and the devil’s hung it on the fore- carriage. Reprimand him!’

He looked up at Ryabovich and continued: ‘It strikes me your harness breeches are too long.’

After a few more tiresome comments, the brigadier glanced at Lobytko and grinned. ‘You look down in the dumps today, Lieutenant Lobytko. Pining for Madame Lopukhov, eh? Gentlemen, he’s pining for Madame Lopukhov!’

Madame Lopukhov was a very plump, tall lady, well past forty. The brigadier, who had a passion for large women, no matter what age, suspected his officers nurtured similar passions. They smiled politely. Then the brigadier, delighted with himself for having made a very amusing, cutting remark, roared with laughter, tapped his driver on the back and saluted. The carriage drove off.

‘All the things I’m dreaming about now and which seem impossible, out of this world, are in fact very ordinary,’ Ryabovich thought as he watched the clouds of dust rising in the wake of the brigadier’s carriage. ‘It’s all so very ordinary, everyone experiences it . . . The brigadier, for example. He was in love once, now he’s married, with children. Captain Vachter is married and loved, despite having an extremely ugly red neck and no waistline. Salmanov is coarse and too much of a Tartar, but he had an affair that finished in marriage. I’m the same as everyone else . . . sooner or later I’ll have to go through what they did . . .’

And he was delighted and encouraged by the thought that he was just an ordinary man, leading an ordinary life. Now he was bold enough to picture her and his happiness as much as he liked and he gave full rein to his imagination.

In the evening, when the brigade had reached its destination and the officers were resting in their tents, Ryabovich, Merzlyakov and Lobytko gathered round a trunk and had supper. Merzlyakov took his time, holding his European Herald on his knees and reading it as he slowly munched his food.

Lobytko could not stop talking and kept filling his glass with beer, while Ryabovich, whose head was rather hazy from dreaming all day long, said nothing as he drank. Three glasses made him tipsy and weak and he felt an irrepressible longing to share his new feelings with his friends.

‘A strange thing happened to me at the Rabbecks,’ he said, trying to sound cool and sarcastic. ‘I went to the billiard- room, you know . . .’

He began to tell them, in great detail, all about the kiss, but after a minute fell silent. In that one minute he had told them everything and he was astonished when he considered how little time was needed to tell his story: he had imagined it would take until morning. After he heard the story, Lobytko – who was a great liar and therefore a great sceptic – looked at him in disbelief and grinned. Merzlyakov twitched his eyebrows and kept his eyes glued to the European Herald as he calmly remarked, ‘Damned if I know what to make of it! Throwing herself round a stranger’s neck without saying a word first . . . She must have been a mental case . . .’

‘Yes, some kind of neurotic,’ Ryabovich agreed.

‘Something similar happened to me once,’ Lobytko said, assuming a frightened look. ‘Last year I was travelling to Kovno . . . second class. The compartment was chock- full and it was impossible to sleep. So I tipped the guard fifty copeks . . . he took my luggage and got me a berth in a sleeper. I lay down and covered myself with a blanket. It was dark, you understand. Suddenly someone was touching my shoulder and breathing into my face. So I moved my arm and felt an elbow. I opened my eyes and – can you imagine! –it was a woman. Black eyes, lips as red as the best salmon, nostrils breathing passion, breasts like buffers! . . .’

‘Just a minute,’ Merzlyakov calmly interrupted. ‘I don’t dispute what you said about her breasts, but how could you see her lips if it was dark?’

Lobytko tried to wriggle out by poking fun at Merzlyakov’s obtuseness and this jarred on Ryabovich. He went away from the trunk, lay down and vowed never again to tell his secrets.

Camp life fell back into its normal routine. The days flashed by, each exactly the same as the other. All this time Ryabovich felt, thought and behaved like someone in love. When his batman brought him cold water in the mornings, he poured it over his head and each time he remembered that there was something beautiful and loving in his life.

In the evenings, when his fellow- officers talked about love and women, he would listen very attentively, sitting very close to them and assuming the habitual expression of a soldier hearing stories about battles he himself fought in. On those evenings when senior officers, led by ‘setter’Lobytko, carried out ‘sorties’ on the local village, in true Don Juan style, Ryabovich went along with them and invariably returned feeling sad, deeply guilty and imploring her forgiveness. In his spare time, or on nights when he couldn’t sleep, when he wanted to recall his childhood days, his parents, everything that was near and dear to him, he would always find himself thinking of Mestechki instead, of that strange horse, of von Rabbeck and his wife, who looked like the Empress Eugénie, of that dark room with the bright chink in the door.

On 31 August he left camp – not with his own brigade, however, but with two batteries. All the way he daydreamed and became very excited, as though he were going home. He wanted passionately to see that strange horse again, the church, those artificial Rabbecks, the dark room. Some inner voice, which so often deceives those in love, whispered that he was bound to see her again. And he was tormented by such questions as: how could he arrange a meeting, what would she say, had she forgotten the kiss? If the worst came to the worst, he would at least have the pleasure of walking through that dark room and remembering . . .

Towards evening, that familiar church and the white barns appeared on the horizon. His heart began to pound. He did not listen to what the officer riding next to him was saying, he was oblivious of everything and looked eagerly at the river gleaming in the distance, at the loft above which pigeons were circling in the light of the setting sun.

As he rode up to the church and heard the quartermaster speaking, he expected a messenger on horseback to appear from behind the fence any minute and invite the officers to tea . . . but the quartermaster read the billeting list out, the officers dismounted and strolled off into the village – and no messenger came.

‘The people in the village will tell Rabbeck we’re here and he’ll send for us,’ Ryabovich thought as he went into his hut. He just could not understand why a fellow- officer was lighting a candle, why the batmen were hurriedly heating the samovars.

He was gripped by an acute feeling of anxiety. He lay down, then got up and looked out of the window to see if the messenger was coming. But there was no one. He lay down again but got up again after half an hour, unable to control his anxiety, went out into the street and strode off towards the church.

The square near the fence was dark and deserted. Some soldiers were standing in a row at the top of the slope, saying nothing. They jumped when they saw Ryabovich and saluted. He acknowledged the salute and went down the familiar path.

The entire sky over the far bank was flooded with crimson; the moon was rising. Two peasant women were talking loudly and picking cabbage leaves as they walked along the edge of a kitchen garden. Beyond the gardens were some dark huts. On the near bank everything was much the same as in May: the path, the bushes, the willows overhanging the river . . . only there was no bold nightingale singing, no fragrant poplars or young grass. Ryabovich reached the garden and peered over the gate. It was dark and quiet and all he could see were the white trunks of the nearest birches and here and there little patches of avenue – everything else had merged into one black mass. Ryabovich looked hard, listened eagerly, and after standing and waiting for about a quarter of an hour, without hearing a sound or seeing a single light, he trudged wearily away . . .

He went down to the river, where he could see the general’s bathing- hut and towels hanging over the rail on the little bridge. He went on to the bridge, stood for a moment and aimlessly fingered the towels. They felt cold and rough. He looked down at the water . . . the current was swift and purled, barely audibly, against the piles of the hut. The red moon was reflected in the water near the left bank; tiny waves rippled through the reflection, pulling it apart and breaking it up into little patches, as if trying to bear it away.

‘How stupid, how very stupid!’ Ryabovich thought as he looked at the fast- flowing water. Now, when he hoped for nothing, that adventure of the kiss, his impatience, his vague longings and disillusionment appeared in a new light. He didn’t think it at all strange that he hadn’t waited for the general’s messenger or that he would never see the girl who had kissed him by mistake. On the contrary, he would have thought it strange if he had seen her . . .

The water raced past and he did not know where or why; it had flowed just as swiftly in May, when it grew from a little stream into a large river, flowed into the sea, evaporated and turned into rain. Perhaps this was the same water flowing past. To what purpose?

And the whole world, the whole of life, struck Ryabovich as a meaningless, futile joke. As he turned his eyes from the water to the sky, he remembered how fate had accidentally caressed him – in the guise of an unknown woman. He recalled the dreams and visions of that summer and his life seemed terribly empty, miserable, colourless . . . When he returned to his hut, none of the officers was there.

The batman reported that they had all gone to ‘General Fontryabkin’s’ – he’d sent a messenger on horseback with the invitation. There was a brief flicker of joy in his heart, but he snuffed it out at once, lay on his bed and in defiance of fate – as though he wanted to bring its wrath down on his own head – he did not go to the general’s.

The Two Volodyas

‘Let me go, I want to drive. I’m going to sit next to the driver,’ Sophia Lvovna shouted. ‘Driver, wait. I’m coming up on to the box to sit next to you.’

She stood on the sledge while her husband Vladimir Nikitych and her childhood friend Vladimir Mikhaylych held her by the arm in case she fell. Away sped the troika.

‘I said you shouldn’t have given her brandy,’ Vladimir Nikitych whispered irritably to his companion. ‘You’re a fine one!’

From past experience the Colonel knew that when women like his wife Sophia Lvovna had been in riotous, rather inebriated high spirits he could normally expect fits of hysterical laughter and tears to follow. He was afraid that once they got home he would have to run around with the cold compresses and medicine instead of being able to go to bed.

‘Whoa!’ Sophia Lvovna shouted. ‘I want to drive.’

She was really very gay and in an exultant mood. For two months after her wedding she had been tormented by the thought that she had married Colonel Yagich for his money or, as they say, par dépit. That same evening, in the out- of- town restaurant, she finally became convinced that she loved him passionately. In spite of his fifty- four years, he was so trim, sprightly and athletic, and he told puns and joined in the gypsy girls’ songs with such charm. It is true that nowadays old men are a thousand times more interesting than young ones, as though age and youth had changed places. The Colonel was two years older than her father, but was that important if, to be quite honest, he was infinitely stronger, more energetic and livelier than she was, even though she was only twenty- three?

‘Oh, my darling!’ she thought. ‘My wonderful man!’

In the restaurant she had come to the conclusion too that not a spark remained of her old feelings. To her childhood friend Vladimir Mikhaylych, whom only yesterday she had loved to distraction, she now felt completely indifferent. The whole evening he had struck her as a lifeless, sleepy, boring nobody and the habitual coolness with which he avoided paying restaurant bills exasperated her so much this time that she very nearly told him, ‘You should have stayed at home if you’re so poor.’ The Colonel footed the bill.

Perhaps it was the trees, telegraph poles and snowdrifts all flashing past that aroused the most varied thoughts. She reflected that the meal had cost one hundred and twenty roubles – with a hundred for the gypsies – and that the next day, if she so wished, she could throw a thousand roubles away, whereas two months ago, before the wedding, she did not have three roubles to call her own and she had to turn to her father for every little thing. How her life had changed!

Her thoughts were in a muddle and she remembered how, when she was about ten, Colonel Yagich, her husband now, had made advances to her aunt and how everyone in the house had said that he had ruined her. In fact, her aunt often came down to dinner with tear- stained eyes and was always going away somewhere; people said the poor woman was suffering terribly. In those days he was very handsome and had extraordinary success with women; the whole town knew him and he was said to visit his admirers every day, like a doctor doing his rounds. Even now, despite his grey hair, wrinkles and spectacles, his thin face looked handsome, especially in profile.

Sophia Lvovna’s father was an army doctor and had once served in Yagich’s regiment. Volodya senior’s father had also been an army doctor and had once served in the same regiment as her own father and Yagich. Despite some highly involved and frantic amorous adventures Volodya junior had been an excellent student. He graduated with honours from university, had decided to specialize in foreign literature and was said to be writing his thesis. He lived in the barracks with his doctor father and he had no money of his own, although he was now thirty. When they were children, Sophia Lvovna and he had lived in different flats, but in the same building, and he often came to play with her; together they had dancing and French lessons. But when he grew up into a well- built, exceedingly good- looking young man, she began to be shy of him. Then she fell madly in love with him and was still in love until shortly before she married Yagich. He too had extraordinary success with women, from the age of fourteen almost, and the ladies who deceived their husbands with him exonerated themselves by saying Volodya was ‘so little’. Not long before, he was said to be living in digs close to the university and every time you knocked, his footsteps could be heard on the other side of the door and then the whispered apology: ‘Pardon, je ne suis pas seul.’ Yagich was delighted with him, gave him his blessing for the future as Derzhavin had blessed Pushkin, and was evidently very fond of him. For hours on end they would silently play billiards or piquet, and if Yagich went off somewhere in a troika, he would take Volodya with him; only Yagich shared the secret of his thesis. In earlier days, when the Colonel was younger, they were often rivals, but were never jealous of one another. When they were in company, which they frequented together, Yagich was called ‘Big Volodya’ and his friend ‘Little Volodya’.

Besides Big Volodya and Little Volodya, and Sophia Lvovna, there was someone else in the sledge, Margarita Aleksandrovna – or Rita as everyone called her – Mrs Yagich’s cousin. She was a spinster, in her thirties, very pale, with black eyebrows, pince- nez, who chain- smoked even when it was freezing; there was always ash on her lap and chest. She spoke through her nose and drawled; she was cold and unemotional, could drink any quantity of liqueur or brandy without getting drunk and told stories abounding in doubles entendres in a dull, tasteless way. At home she read the learned reviews all day long, scattering ash all over them; or she would eat crystallized apples.

‘Sophia, don’t play the fool,’ she drawled; ‘it’s really so stupid.’

When the town gates came into view the troika slowed down; they caught glimpses of people and houses, and Sophia quietened down, snuggled against her husband and gave herself up to her thoughts. And now gloomy thoughts began to mingle with her happy, carefree fantasies. The man opposite knew that she had loved him (so she thought), and of course he believed the reports that she had married the Colonel par dépit. Not once had she confessed her love and she did not want him to know. She had concealed her feelings, but his expression clearly showed that he understood her perfectly, and so her pride suffered. But most humiliating of all about her situation was the fact that Little Volodya had suddenly started paying attention to her after her marriage, which had never happened before. He would sit with her for hours on end, in silence, or telling her some nonsense; and now in the sledge he was gently touching her leg or squeezing her hand, without saying a word. Evidently, all he wanted was for her to get married. No less obviously, he did not think much of her and she interested him only in a certain way, as an immoral, disreputable woman. And this mingling of triumphant love for her husband and injured pride was the reason for her behaving so irresponsibly, prompting her to sit on the box and shout and whistle . . .

Just as they were passing the convent the great twenty- ton bell started clanging away. Rita crossed herself.

‘Our Olga is in that convent,’ Sophia Lvovna said, crossing herself and shuddering.

‘Why did she become a nun?’ the Colonel asked.

‘Par dépit,’ Rita answered angrily, obviously hinting at Sophia Lvovna’s marriage to Yagich. ‘This par dépit is all the rage now. It’s a challenge to the whole of society. She was a proper good- time girl, a terrible flirt, all she liked was dances and dancing partners. And then suddenly we have all this! She took us all by surprise!’

‘That’s not true,’ Little Volodya said, lowering the collar of his fur coat and revealing his handsome face. ‘This wasn’t a case of par dépit, but something really terrible. Her brother Dmitry was sentenced to hard labour in Siberia and no one knows where he is now. The mother died of grief.’ He raised his collar again. ‘And Olga did the right thing,’ he added dully. ‘Living as a ward, and with a treasure like our Sophia Lvovna, what’s more – that’s enough food for thought!’

Sophia Lvovna noted the contempt in his voice and wanted to say something very nasty in reply, but she said nothing. Once more euphoria gripped her. She stood up and shouted tearfully, ‘I want to go to morning service. Driver, turn back! I want to see Olga!’

They turned back. The convent bell had a dull peal and Sophia Lvovna felt there was something in it reminding her of Olga and her life. Bells rang out from other churches. When the driver had brought the troika to a halt, Sophia leapt from the sledge and rushed unescorted to the gates.

‘Please don’t be long!’ her husband shouted. ‘It’s late.’

She went through the dark gates, then along the path leading to the main church; the light snow crunched under her feet and the tolling of the bells sounded right over her head now and seemed to penetrate her whole being. First she came to the church door, the three steps down, then the porch, with paintings of the saints on both sides; there was a smell of juniper and incense. Then came another door, which a dark figure opened, bowing very low . . . In the church the service had not yet begun. One of the nuns was in front of the icon- screen lighting candles in their holders, another was lighting a chandelier. Here and there, close to the columns and side- chapels, were motionless, black figures.‘They’ll be standing in exactly the same places till morning,’Sophia Lvovna thought and the whole place struck her as dark, cold, depressing – more depressing than a graveyard. Feeling bored, she glanced at the motionless, frozen figures and suddenly her heart sank. Somehow she recognized one of the nuns – short, with thin shoulders and a black shawl on her head – as Olga, although when she had entered the convent she had been plump and taller, she thought. Deeply disturbed for some reason, Sophia Lvovna hesitantly walked over to the lay sister, looked over her shoulder into her face and saw it was Olga.

‘Olga!’ she said, clasping her hands and too excited to say anything else. ‘Olga!’

The nun recognized her immediately, raised her eyebrows in astonishment and her pale, freshly washed face (even, it seemed, her white kerchief visible under her shawl) glowed with joy.

‘God has performed a miracle,’ she said and also clasped her thin, pale little hands.

Sophia Lvovna firmly embraced her and kissed her, frightened as she did so that her breath might smell of drink.

‘We were just passing and we thought of you,’ she said breathlessly, as though she had just completed a fast walk.‘Heavens, how pale you are! I’m . . . I’m very pleased to see you. Well, how are you? Bored?’ Sophia Lvovna looked round at the other nuns and now she lowered her voice: ‘So much has happened . . . you know I married Volodya Yagich. You must remember him . . . I’m very happy.’

‘Well, thank the Lord for that! And is your father well?’

‘Yes, he often remembers you. But you must come and see us during the holidays, Olga. Will you do that?’

‘Yes, I’ll come,’ Olga said smiling. ‘I’ll come the day after tomorrow.’

Without even knowing why, Sophia burst into tears and cried in silence for a whole minute. Then she dried her eyes and said, ‘Rita will be very sorry she didn’t see you. She’s with us too. And Little Volodya. They’re at the gate. How pleased they would be to see you! Come out and see them, the service hasn’t started yet.’

‘All right,’ Olga agreed. She crossed herself three times and walked out with Sophia Lvovna.

‘So, you said you’re happy, Sophia,’ she said after they were past the gates.

‘Very.’

‘Well, thank God.’

When Big Volodya and Little Volodya saw the nun they got off the sledge and greeted her respectfully. They were visibly moved by her pale face and her nun’s black habit, and they were both pleased that she remembered them and had come to greet them. Sophia Lvovna wrapped her in a rug and covered her with one flap of her fur coat to protect her from the cold. Her recent tears had lightened and cleansed her soul and she was glad that the noisy, riotous and essentially immoral night had unexpectedly come to such a pure and quiet conclusion. Then to keep Olga by her side longer, she suggested, ‘Let’s take her for a ride! Olga, get in. Just a little one.’

The men expected the nun to refuse – religious people don’t go around in troikas – but to their amazement she agreed and got in. When the troika hurtled off towards the town gates, no one said a word; their only concern was to make her warm and comfortable. Each one of them thought about the difference in her from before. Her face was impassive, somewhat expressionless, cold, pale, transparent, as though water flowed in her veins instead of blood. Two or three years ago she had been buxom and rosy- cheeked, had talked about eligible bachelors and laughed loud at the least thing.

The troika turned round at the town gates. Ten minutes later they were back at the convent and Olga climbed out. The bells were ringing a series of chimes.

‘God be with you,’ Olga said, giving a low, nun- like bow.

‘So you will come then, Olga?’

‘Of course I will.’

She quickly left and soon disappeared through the dark gateway. After the troika had moved on everyone somehow felt very sad. No one said a word. Sophia Lvovna felt weak all over and her heart sank. Making a nun get into a sledge and go for a ride with that drunken crowd struck her now as stupid, tactless and almost sacrilegious. The desire for self- deception vanished with her tipsiness and now she clearly realized that she did not and could not love her husband, it was all nothing but silly nonsense. She had married for money because, as her ex- schoolgirl friends put it, he was‘madly rich’, because she was terrified of becoming an old maid, like Rita, because her doctor father got on her nerves and because she wanted to annoy Little Volodya. Had she guessed when she was contemplating marriage that it would turn out to be so nasty, painful and ugly, she would never have agreed to it, not for anything in the world. But the damage was done now, she had to accept things.

They arrived home. As she lay in her warm, soft bed and covered herself with a blanket, Sophia Lvovna recalled the dark porch, the smell of incense, the figures by the columns, and she was distressed at the thought that these figures would still be standing there, quite motionless, all the time she was sleeping. Early morning service would be interminably long, and after that there would be the hours, then Mass, then more prayers . . .

‘But surely God exists? He certainly exists and I must certainly die. Therefore, sooner or later, I must think of my soul, eternal life, like Olga does. Olga is saved now, she has solved all her problems for herself . . . But what if there is no God? Then her life has been wasted. But how has it been wasted? Why?’

A minute later another thought entered her head. ‘God exists, death will certainly come. I should be thinking of my soul. If Olga could see her death this very minute she would not be afraid. She’s ready. But the most important thing is, she’s solved the riddle of existence for herself. God exists . . . yes. But isn’t there another way out apart from becoming a nun? That means renouncing life, destroying it . . .’ Sophia Lvovna became rather scared and hid her head under the pillow. ‘I mustn’t think about it,’ she whispered, ‘I mustn’t.’

Yagich was walking up and down in the next room, his spurs softly jingling; he was deep in thought. Sophia Lvovna thought that this man was near and dear to her only in one thing – he was called Volodya too. She sat on her bed and tenderly called,‘Volodya!’

‘What do you want?’ her husband replied.

‘Nothing.’

She lay down again. There were bells tolling – from that same convent, perhaps – and once again she recalled the porch and the dark figures. Thoughts of God and inescapable death wandered through her mind; she pulled the blanket over her head to drown the sound of the bells. She expected, before old age and death came, that her life would drag on for such a terribly long time, and from one day to the next she would have to cope with the nearness of someone she did not love, and who had come into the room just at that moment and was getting into bed; and she would have to suppress that hopeless love for another – someone who was so young, so charming and apparently so unusual. She looked at her husband and wanted to say good night, but she suddenly burst into tears instead. She felt annoyed with herself.

‘Well, we’re off again,’ Yagich said.

She did calm down, but not until later, towards ten in the morning. She had stopped crying and shaking all over; she developed a severe headache, however. Yagich was hurrying, getting ready for late Mass and in the next room he was grumbling at the batman helping him dress. He came into the bedroom once, his spurs softly jingling, took something, and when he came in a second time he was wearing epaulettes and decorations; he limped slightly from rheumatism. He gave Sophia Lvovna the impression he was a beast of prey, prowling and looking round.

Then she heard him on the telephone. ‘Please put me through to the Vasilyevsky Barracks,’ he said. A minute later he went on, ‘Is that Vasilyevsky Barracks? Please ask Dr Salimovich to come to the phone.’ Then, a minute later, ‘Who am I speaking to? Volodya? Fine. My dear chap, please ask your father to come over right away, my wife is terribly off colour after what happened yesterday. What’s that? He’s out? Hm . . . thanks . . . Yes, I’d be much obliged. Merci.’

Yagich came into the bedroom for the third time, bent over his wife, made the sign of the cross over her, let her kiss his hand (women who loved him would kiss his hand, he was used to this), and said he would be back for dinner. And he left.

Towards noon the maid announced Little Volodya. Swaying from weariness and her headache, Sophia Lvovna quickly put on her stunning new lilac, fur- trimmed negligee and hurriedly tidied her hair. In her heart she felt inexpressibly tender and trembled for joy – and for fear he might leave. She wanted just one look at him.

Little Volodya was paying her a visit in formal dress –tailcoat and white tie. When Sophia Lvovna came into the drawing- room he kissed her hand, said how deeply sorry he was to see her so unwell. When they had sat down he praised her negligee.

‘Seeing Olga last night has upset me,’ she said. ‘At first it was painful for me, but now I envy her. She is like an immovable rock, it’s impossible to budge her. But was there really no other way out for her, Volodya? Can burying oneself alive really solve life’s problems? You’d call that death, not life, wouldn’t you?’ At the mention of Olga, Little Volodya’s face showed deep emotion. ‘Now look, Volodya, you’re a clever man,’ Sophia Lvovna said. ‘Teach me to be like her. Of course, I’m a non- believer and I couldn’t become a nun. But couldn’t I do something that would be just as good? I find life hard enough.’ After a brief silence she continued, ‘Teach me . . . tell me something that will convince me. Just one word.’

‘One word? Okay. Ta- ra- ra- boomdeay.’

‘Volodya, why do you despise me?’ she asked excitedly.‘You speak to me in some special – if you’ll forgive the expression – fancy language that one doesn’t use with friends and respectable women. You’re a successful scholar, you love your studies, but why do you never tell me about them? Why? Aren’t I good enough?’

Little Volodya frowned irritably and said, ‘Why this sudden passion for scholarship? Perhaps you want us to have a constitution? Or perhaps sturgeon with horseradish?’

‘Oh, have it your way then. I’m a mediocre, worthless, unprincipled, stupid woman . . . I’ve made thousands, thousands of mistakes. I’m not right in the head, a loose woman, and for that I deserve contempt. But you’re ten years older than me, Volodya, aren’t you? And my husband is thirty years older. You watched me grow up and if you’d wanted to, you could have made me anything you wanted, an angel even. But you . . .’ (here her voice shook) ‘treat me dreadfully. Yagich was an old man when he married me, and you . . .’

‘Well, enough of that. Enough,’ Volodya said, drawing closer to her and kissing both her hands. ‘We’ll leave the Schopenhauers to philosophize and argue about anything they like, but now we’re going to kiss these sweet little hands.’

‘You despise me and if only you knew the suffering it causes me,’ she said hesitantly, knowing beforehand that he would not believe her. ‘If you only knew how I want to improve myself, to start a new life! It fills me with joy just thinking about it,’ she murmured and actually shed a few joyous tears. ‘To be a good, honest, decent person, not to lie, to have a purpose in life.’

‘Stop it please! You don’t have to put on an act for me, I don’t like it,’ Volodya said, looking peevish. ‘Heavens, you’d think we were at the theatre! Let’s behave like normal human beings!’

To prevent him from leaving in a temper she began to make excuses, forced herself to smile – to please him –mentioned Olga again and that she wanted to solve the riddle of her existence, to become a real human being.

‘ Ta- ra- ra- boomdeay,’ he chanted softly. ‘ Ta- ra- ra- boomdeay!’

And then quite suddenly he clasped her waist. Barely conscious of what she was doing she put her hands on his shoulders and for a whole minute looked rapturously at his clever, sarcastic face, his forehead, eyes, handsome beard . . .

‘You’ve known for a long time that I love you,’ she confessed with an agonized blush and she felt that even her lips had twisted in a paroxysm of shame. ‘I love you. So why do you torment me?’

She closed her eyes and kissed him firmly on the lips. For a long time – a whole minute perhaps – she just could not bring herself to end this kiss, although she knew very well that she was behaving badly, that he might tell her off, or that a servant might come in . . .

Half an hour later, when he had got what he wanted, he sat in the dining- room eating a snack while she knelt before him, staring hungrily into his face. He told her she was like a small dog waiting for someone to toss it a piece of ham. Then he sat her on one knee, rocked her like a child and sang, ‘ Ta- ra- ra- boomdeay . . . Ta- ra- ra- boomdeay!’

When he was about to leave she asked him passionately,‘When? Later on? Where?’ And she held out both hands to his mouth, as if wanting to catch his reply in them.

‘It’s not really convenient today,’ he said after a moment’s thought. ‘Perhaps tomorrow, though.’

And they parted. Before lunch Sophia Lvovna went off to the convent to see Olga, but was told that she was reading the Psalter for someone who had died. From the convent she went to her father’s and drove aimlessly up and down the main streets and side- streets until evening. While she was riding, for some reason she kept remembering that aunt with the tear- stained eyes, who was fretting her life away.

That night they all went riding on troikas again and heard the gypsies in that out- of- town restaurant. And when they were once again passing the convent Sophia Lvovna thought of Olga and became terrified at the thought that there was no escape for girls and women in her circle, except perpetual troika- rides or entering a convent to mortify the flesh . . .

The following day she had a lovers’ rendezvous once again. She went for solitary cab- rides around town and thought of her aunt.

A week later Little Volodya dropped her. Then life reverted to normal and was just as boring, dreary – and sometimes just as excruciating as it had ever been. The Colonel and Little Volodya had long billiards and piquet sessions, Rita told her tasteless anecdotes in the same lifeless fashion, Sophia Lvovna kept driving in cabs and asking her husband to take her for troika- rides.

Almost every day she called at the convent, boring Olga with her complaints of intolerable suffering; she cried and felt that she had brought something impure, pathetic and shabby into the cell. Olga, however, as if repeating a well- learnt lesson parrot- fashion, told her that there was nothing to worry about, that it would all pass and that God would forgive her.

Gooseberries

The sky had been overcast with rain clouds since early morning. The weather was mild, and not hot and oppressive as it can be on dull grey days when storm clouds lie over the fields for ages and you wait for rain which never comes. Ivan Ivanych, the vet, and Burkin, a teacher at the high school, were tired of walking and thought they would never come to the end of the fields. They could just make out the windmills at the village of Mironositskoye in the far distance – a range of hills stretched away to the right and disappeared far beyond it. They both knew that the river was there, with meadows, green willows and farmsteads, and that if they climbed one of the hills they would see yet another vast expanse of fields, telegraph wires and a train resembling a caterpillar in the distance. In fine weather they could see even as far as the town. And now, in calm weather, when the whole of nature had become gentle and dreamy, Ivan Ivanych and Burkin were filled with love for those open spaces and they both thought what a vast and beautiful country it was.

‘Last time we were in Elder Prokofy’s barn, you were going to tell me a story,’ Burkin said.

‘Yes, I wanted to tell you about my brother.’

Ivan Ivanych heaved a long sigh and lit his pipe before beginning his narrative; but at that moment down came the rain. Five minutes later it was simply teeming. Ivan Ivanych and Burkin were in two minds as to what they should do. The dogs were already soaked through and stood with their tails drooping, looking at them affectionately.

‘We must take shelter,’ Burkin said. ‘Let’s go to Alyokhin’s, it’s not very far.’

‘All right, let’s go there.’

They changed direction and went across mown fields, walking straight on at first, and then bearing right until they came out on the high road. Before long, poplars, a garden, then the red roofs of barns came into view. The river glinted, and then they caught sight of a wide stretch of water and a white bathing- hut. This was Sofino, where Alyokhin lived.

The mill was turning and drowned the noise of the rain. The wall of the dam shook. Wet horses with downcast heads were standing by some carts and peasants went around with sacks on their heads. Everything was damp, muddy and bleak, and the water had a cold, malevolent look. Ivan Ivanych and Burkin felt wet, dirty and terribly uncomfortable. Their feet were weighed down by mud and when they crossed the dam and walked up to the barns near the manor house they did not say a word and seemed to be angry with each other.

A winnowing fan was droning away in one of the barns and dust poured out of the open door. On the threshold stood the master himself, Alyokhin, a man of about forty, tall, stout, with long hair, and he looked more like a professor or an artist than a landowner. He wore a white shirt that hadn’t been washed for a very long time, and it was tied round with a piece of rope as a belt. Instead of trousers he was wearing underpants; mud and straw clung to his boots. His nose and eyes were black with dust. He immediately recognized Ivan Ivanych and Burkin, and was clearly delighted to see them.

‘Please come into the house, gentlemen,’ he said, smiling,‘I’ll be with you in a jiffy.’

It was a large house, with two storeys. Alyokhin lived on the ground floor in the two rooms with vaulted ceilings and small windows where his estate managers used to live. They were simply furnished and smelled of rye bread, cheap vodka and harness. He seldom used the main rooms upstairs, reserving them for guests. Ivan Ivanych and Burkin were welcomed by the maid, who was such a beautiful young woman that they both stopped and stared at each other.

‘You can’t imagine how glad I am to see you, gentlemen,’Alyokhin said as he followed them into the hall. ‘A real surprise!’ Then he turned to the maid and said, ‘Pelageya, bring some dry clothes for the gentlemen. I suppose I’d better change too. But I must have a wash first, or you’ll think I haven’t had one since spring. Would you like to come to the bathing- hut while they get things ready in the house?’

The beautiful Pelageya, who had such a dainty look and gentle face, brought soap and towels, and Alyokhin went off with his guests to the bathing- hut.

‘Yes, it’s ages since I had a good wash,’ he said as he undressed. ‘As you can see, it’s a nice hut. My father built it, but I never find time these days for a swim.’

He sat on one of the steps and smothered his long hair and neck with soap; the water turned brown.

‘Yes, I must confess . . .’ Ivan Ivanych muttered, with a meaningful look at his head.

‘Haven’t had a wash for ages,’ Alyokhin repeated in his embarrassment and soaped himself again; the water turned a dark inky blue.

Ivan Ivanych came out of the cabin, dived in with a loud splash and swam in the rain, making broad sweeps with his arms and sending out waves with white lilies bobbing about on them. He swam right out to the middle of the reach and dived. A moment later he popped up somewhere else and swam on, continually trying to dive right to the bottom.

‘Oh, good God,’ he kept saying with great relish. ‘Good God . . .’

He reached the mill, said a few words to the peasants, then he turned and floated on his back in the middle with his face under the rain. Burkin and Alyokhin were already dressed and ready to leave, but he kept on swimming and diving.

‘Oh, dear God,’ he said. ‘Oh, God!’

‘Now that’s enough,’ Burkin shouted.

They went back to the house. Only when the lamp in the large upstairs drawing- room was alight and Burkin and Ivan Ivanych, wearing silk dressing- gowns and warm slippers, were sitting in armchairs and Alyokhin, washed and combed now and with a new frock- coat on, was walking up and down, obviously savouring the warmth, cleanliness, dry clothes and light shoes, while his beautiful Pelageya glided silently over the carpet and gently smiled as she served tea and jam on a tray – only then did Ivan Ivanych begin his story. It seemed that Burkin and Alyokhin were not the only ones who were listening, but also the ladies (young and old) and the officers, who were looking down calmly and solemnly from their gilt frames on the walls.

‘There are two of us brothers,’ he began, ‘myself – Ivan Ivanych – and Nikolay Ivanych, who’s two years younger. I studied to be a vet, while Nikolay worked in the district tax office from the time he was nineteen. Chimsha- Gimalaysky, our father, had served as a private, but when he was promoted to officer we became hereditary gentlemen and owners of a small estate. After he died, this estate was sequestrated to pay off his debts, but despite this we spent our boyhood in the country free to do what we wanted. Just like any other village children, we stayed out in the fields and woods for days and nights, minded horses, stripped bark, went fishing, and so on . . . As you know very well, anyone who has ever caught a ruff or watched migrating thrushes swarming over his native village on cool clear autumn days can never live in a town afterwards and he’ll always hanker after the free and open life until his dying day. My brother was miserable in the tax office. The years passed, but there he stayed, always at the same old desk, copying out the same old documents and obsessed with this longing for the country. And gradually this longing took the form of a definite wish, a dream of buying a nice little estate somewhere in the country, beside a river or a lake.

‘He was a kind, gentle man and I was very fond of him, but I could never feel any sympathy for him in this longing to lock himself away in a country house for the rest of his life. They say a man needs only six feet of earth, but surely they must mean a corpse – not a man! These days they seem to think that it’s very good if our educated classes want to go back to the land and set their hearts on a country estate. But in reality these estates are only that same six feet all over again. To leave the town and all its noise and hubbub, to go and shut yourself away on your little estate – that’s no life! It’s selfishness, laziness, a peculiar brand of monasticism that achieves nothing. A man needs more than six feet of earth and a little place in the country, he needs the whole wide world, the whole of nature, where there’s room for him to display his potential, all the manifold attributes of his free spirit.

‘As he sat there in his office, my brother Nikolay dreamt of soup made from his own home- grown cabbages, soup that would fill the whole house with a delicious smell; eating meals on the green grass; sleeping in the sun; sitting on a bench outside the main gates for hours on end and looking at the fields and woods. Booklets on agriculture and words of wisdom from calendars were his joy, his favourite spiritual nourishment. He liked newspapers as well, but he only read property adverts – for so many acres of arable land and meadows, with “house, river, garden, mill, and ponds fed by running springs”. And he had visions of garden paths, flowers, fruit, nesting- boxes for starlings, ponds teeming with carp – you know the kind of thing. These visions varied according to the adverts he happened to see, but for some reason, in every single one, there had to be gooseberry bushes. “Life in the country has its comforts,” he used to say.“You can sit drinking tea on your balcony, while your ducks are swimming in the pond . . . it all smells so good and um . . . there’s your gooseberries growing away!”

‘He drew up a plan for his estate and it turned out exactly the same every time: (a) manor house; (b) servants’ quarters;(c) kitchen garden; (d) gooseberry bushes. He lived a frugal life, economizing on food and drink, dressing any- old- how –just like a beggar – and putting every penny he saved straight into the bank. He was terribly mean. It was really painful to look at him, so I used to send him a little money on special occasions. But he would put that in the bank too. Once a man has his mind firmly made up there’s nothing you can do about it.

‘Years passed and he was transferred to another province. He was now in his forties, still reading newspaper adverts and still saving up. Then I heard that he’d got married. So that he could buy a country estate with gooseberry bushes, he married an ugly old widow, for whom he felt nothing and only because she had a little money tucked away. He made her life miserable too, half- starved her and banked her money into his own account. She’d been married to a postmaster and was used to pies and fruit liqueurs, but with her second husband she didn’t even have enough black bread. This kind of life made her wither away, and within three years she’d gone to join her maker. Of course, my brother didn’t think that he was to blame – not for one minute! Like vodka, money can make a man do the most peculiar things. There was once a merchant living in our town who was on his deathbed. Just before he died, he asked for some honey, stirred it up with all his money and winning lottery tickets, and swallowed the lot to stop anyone else from laying their hands on it. And another time, when I was inspecting cattle at some railway station, a dealer fell under a train and had his leg cut off. We took him to the local casualty department. The blood simply gushed out, a terrible sight, but all he did was ask for his leg back and was only bothered about the twenty roubles he had tucked away in the boot. Scared he might lose them, I dare say!’

‘But that’s neither here nor there,’ Burkin said.

‘When his wife died,’ Ivan continued, after a pause for thought, ‘my brother started looking for an estate. Of course, you can look around for five years and still make the wrong choice and you finish up with something you never even dreamt of. So brother Nikolay bought about three hundred acres, with manor house, servants’ quarters and a park, on a mortgage through an estate agent. But there wasn’t any orchard, gooseberries or duck pond. There was a river, but the water was always the colour of coffee because of the brickworks on one side of the estate and a bone- ash factory on the other. But my dear Nikolay didn’t seem to care. He ordered twenty gooseberry bushes, planted them out and settled down to a landowner’s life.

‘Last year I visited him, as I wanted to see what was going on. In his letter my brother had called his estate “Chumbaroklov Patch” or “Gimalaysky’s”. One afternoon I turned up at “Gimalaysky’s”. It was a hot day. Everywhere there were ditches, fences, hedges, rows of small fir trees and there seemed no way into the yard or anywhere to leave my horse. I went up to the house, only to be welcomed by a fat ginger dog that looked rather like a pig. It wanted to bark, but it was too lazy. Then a barefooted, plump cook – she resembled a pig as well – came out of the kitchen and told me the master was having his after- lunch nap. So I went to my brother’s room and there he was sitting up in bed with a blanket over his knees. He’d aged, put on weight and looked very flabby. His cheeks, nose and lips stuck out and I thought any moment he was going to grunt into his blanket, like a pig.

‘We embraced and wept for joy, and at the sad thought that once we were young and now both of us were grey, and that our lives were nearly over. He got dressed and led me on a tour of the estate.

‘ “Well, how’s it going?” I asked.

‘ “All right, thank God. It’s a good life.”

‘No longer was he the poor, timid little clerk of before, but a real squire, a gentleman. He felt quite at home, being used to country life by then and he was enjoying himself. He ate a great deal, took proper baths, and he was putting on weight. Already he was suing the district council and both factories, and he got very peeved when the villagers didn’t call him “sir”. He paid great attention to his spiritual wellbeing (as a gentleman should) and he couldn’t dispense charity nice and quietly, but had to make a great show of it. And what did it all add up to? He doled out bicarbonate of soda or castor oil to his villagers – regardless of what they were suffering from – and on his name- day held a thanksgiving service in the village, supplying vodka in plenty, as he thought this was the right thing to do. Oh, those horrid pints of vodka! Nowadays your fat squire drags his villagers off to court for letting their cattle stray on his land and the very next day (if it’s a high holiday) stands them all a few pints of vodka. They’ll drink it, shout hurray and fall at his feet in a drunken stupor. Better standards of living, plenty to eat, idleness – all this makes us Russians terribly smug. Back in his office, Nikolay had been too scared even to voice any opinions of his own, but now he was expounding the eternal verities in true ministerial style: “Education is essential, but premature as far as the common people are concerned” or“Corporal punishment, generally speaking, is harmful, but in certain cases it can be useful and irreplaceable”. And he’d say, “I know the working classes and how to handle them. They like me, I only have to lift my little finger and they’ll do anything for me.”

‘And he said all this, mark you, with a clever, good- natured smile. Time after time he’d say “we gentlemen” or “speaking as one of the gentry”. He’d evidently forgotten that our grandfather had been a peasant and our father a common soldier. Even our absolutely ridiculous surname, Chimsha- Gimalaysky, was melodious, distinguished and highly agreeable to his ears now.

‘But it’s myself I’m concerned with, not him. I’d like to tell you about the change that came over me during the few hours I spent on his estate. Later, when we were having tea, his cook brought us a plateful of gooseberries. They weren’t shop gooseberries, but home- grown, the first fruits of the bushes he’d planted. Nikolay laughed and stared at them for a whole minute, with tears in his eyes. He was too deeply moved for words. Then he popped one in his mouth, looked at me like an enraptured child that has finally been given a long- awaited toy and said, “Absolutely delicious!” He ate some greedily and kept repeating, “So tasty, you must try one!”

‘They were hard and sour, but as Pushkin says: “Uplifting illusion is dearer to us than a host of truths.” This was a happy man whose cherished dreams had clearly come true, who had achieved his life’s purpose, had got what he wanted and was happy with his lot – and himself. My thoughts about human happiness, for some peculiar reason, had always been tinged with a certain sadness. But now, seeing this happy man, I was overwhelmed by a feeling of despondency that was close to utter despair. I felt particularly low that night. They made up a bed for me in the room next to my brother’s. He was wide awake and I could hear him getting up, going over to the plate and helping himself to one gooseberry at a time. And I thought how many satisfied, happy people really do exist in this world! And what a powerful force they are! Just take a look at this life of ours and you will see the arrogance and idleness of the strong, the ignorance and bestiality of the weak. Everywhere there’s unspeakable poverty, overcrowding, degeneracy, drunkenness, hypocrisy and stupid lies . . . And yet peace and quiet reign in every house and street. Out of fifty thousand people you won’t find one who is prepared to shout out loud and make a strong protest. We see people buying food in the market, eating during the day, sleeping at night- time, talking nonsense, marrying, growing old and then contentedly carting their dead off to the cemetery. But we don’t hear or see those who suffer: the real tragedies of life are enacted somewhere behind the scenes. Everything is calm and peaceful and the only protest comes from statistics – and they can’t talk. Figures show that so many went mad, so many bottles of vodka were emptied, so many children died from malnutrition. And clearly this kind of system is what people need. It’s obvious that the happy man feels contented only because the unhappy ones bear their burden without saying a word: if it weren’t for their silence, happiness would be quite impossible. It’s a kind of mass hypnosis. Someone ought to stand with a hammer at the door of every happy contented man, continually banging on it to remind him that there are unhappy people around and that however happy he may be at the time, sooner or later life will show him its claws and disaster will overtake him in the form of illness, poverty, bereavement and there will be no one to hear or see him. But there isn’t anyone holding a hammer, so our happy man goes his own sweet way and is only gently ruffled by life’s trivial cares, as an aspen is ruffled by the breeze. All’s well as far as he’s concerned.

‘That night I realized that I too was happy and contented,’Ivan Ivanych went on, getting to his feet. ‘I too had lectured people over dinner – or out hunting – on how to live, on what to believe, on how to handle the common people. And I too had told them that knowledge is a shining lamp, that education is essential, and that plain reading and writing is good enough for the masses, for the moment. Freedom is a blessing, I told them, and we need it like the air we breathe, but we must wait for it patiently.’

Ivan Ivanych turned to Burkin and said angrily, ‘Yes, that’s what I used to say and now I’d like to know what is it we’re waiting for? I’m asking you, what? What is it we’re trying to prove? I’m told that nothing can be achieved in five minutes, that it takes time for any kind of idea to be realized; it’s a gradual process. But who says so? And what is there to prove he’s right? You refer to the natural order of things, to the law of cause and effect. But is there any law or order in a state of affairs where a lively, thinking person like myself should have to stand by a ditch and wait until it’s choked with weeds, or silted up, when I could quite easily, perhaps, leap across it or bridge it? I ask you again, what are we waiting for? Until we have no more strength to live, although we long to and need to go on living?

‘I left my brother early next morning and ever since then I’ve found town life unbearable. I’m depressed by peace and quiet, I’m scared of peering through windows, nothing makes me more dejected than the sight of a happy family sitting round the table drinking tea. But I’m old now, no longer fit for the fray, I’m even incapable of hating. I only feel sick at heart, irritable and exasperated. At night my head seems to be on fire with so many thoughts crowding in and I can’t get any sleep . . . Oh, if only I were young again!’

Ivan Ivanych paced the room excitedly, repeating, ‘If only I were young again!’

Suddenly he went up to Alyokhin and squeezed one hand, then the other.‘Pavel Konstantinych,’ he pleaded, ‘don’t go to sleep or be lulled into complacency! While you’re still young, strong and healthy, never stop doing good! Happiness doesn’t exist, we don’t need any such thing. If life has any meaning or purpose, you won’t find it in happiness, but in something more rational, in something greater. Doing good!’

Ivan Ivanych said all this with a pitiful, imploring smile, as though pleading for himself.

Afterwards all three of them sat in armchairs in different parts of the room and said nothing. Ivan Ivanych’s story satisfied neither Burkin nor Alyokhin. It was boring listening to that story about some poor devil of a clerk who ate gooseberries, while those generals and ladies, who seemed to have come to life in the gathering gloom, peered out of their gilt frames. For some reason they would have preferred discussing and hearing about refined people, about ladies. The fact that they were all sitting in a drawing- room where everything – the draped chandeliers, the armchairs, the carpets underfoot – indicated that those same people who were now looking out of their frames had once walked around, sat down and drunk their tea there . . . and with beautiful Pelageya moving about here without a sound – all this was better than any story.

Alyokhin was dying to get to bed. That morning he had been up and about very early (before three) working on the farm, and he could hardly keep his eyes open. However, he was frightened he might miss some interesting story if he left now, so he stayed. He didn’t even try to fathom if everything that Ivan Ivanych had just been saying was clever, or even true: he was only too glad that his guests did not discuss oats or hay or tar, but things that had nothing to do with his way of life, and he wanted them to continue . . .

‘But it’s time we got some sleep,’ Burkin said, standing up. ‘May I wish you all a very good night!’

Alyokhin bade them good night and went down to his room, while his guests stayed upstairs. They had been given the large room with two old, elaborately carved beds and an ivory crucifix in one corner. These wide, cool beds had been made by the beautiful Pelageya and the linen had a pleasant fresh smell.

Ivan Ivanych undressed without a word and got into bed. Then he muttered, ‘Lord have mercy on us sinners!’ and pulled the blankets over his head. His pipe, which was lying on a table, smelt strongly of stale tobacco and Burkin was so puzzled as to where the terrible smell was coming from that it was a long time before he fell asleep.

All night long the rain beat against the windows.

一个人需要许多土地吗？

一

姐姐从城里来乡下看望妹妹。姐姐嫁了个城里商人，妹妹嫁了个乡下农民。姐妹俩喝着茶，谈着天。姐姐得意扬扬地吹嘘她在城里的生活：她的房子多么宽敞，衣服多么时髦，她的孩子打扮得多么漂亮，她吃得多么香，喝得多么美，她怎么乘马车兜风，上剧场看戏。

妹妹听了很生气，就竭力贬低商人的生活，美化农民的生活。

她说：“我可不愿拿我的生活换你那种生活。尽管日子清苦，我们却无忧无虑。你们过得阔气，有时大发其财，但有时亏个精光。常言道：赚钱、亏本是双胞胎。今天百万富翁，明天上街要饭。我们庄稼人要稳当得多。我们肚子里油水少，但是寿命长，我们发不了财，也饿不了肚子。”

姐姐说：“成天同猪牛打交道，肚子能吃得多饱？你们不懂得文明，不知道礼貌！不论你们当家的怎样累死累活，一辈子泡在猪粪牛尿里，永远没有出头的日子，你们的孩子也一样。”

妹妹说：“是的，我们干的就是这样的活儿，但日子过得踏实，我们不求人，也不怕谁。你们在城里到处受诱惑：今天太太平平，明天就会碰上魔鬼，引诱你们当家的去赌钱喝酒，嫖妓宿娼，到头来一场空。难道没有这样的事吗？”

当家的巴霍姆这时躺在炕上，听着她们闲聊。

“说得对，”他说道，“我们庄稼人从小种地，脑子从来不胡思乱想。只对一件事烦恼——地太少！要是有足够的土地，别说人，就是魔鬼也吓不倒我！”

姐妹俩喝完茶，又谈了一通衣着打扮，收拾好杯盘，躺下睡觉。

不料魔鬼坐在炕后面，这番话他听得一清二楚。魔鬼感到高兴，因为农民老婆夸奖丈夫，说他要是有土地，就连魔鬼也不怕。

魔鬼想：“好吧，让我来跟你较量一下。我给你许多土地，就用土地来制服你。”

二

附近住着一个不大富裕的太太。她有一百二十俄亩[1]地。原来她跟农民相处得很好，她不欺负他们。后来她雇了一个退伍兵来当管家，他动不动就要罚农民款。尽管巴霍姆小心翼翼，还是常常出事，不是马冲进燕麦地，就是牛闯到花园里，再不就是牛犊践踏草地，他就只好被罚款。

巴霍姆付了罚款，就回家打骂老婆孩子。一个夏天，巴霍姆吃了这个管家许多苦。等到牲口圈起来过冬，他才放下心来，虽然得多费点儿饲料，但不用担惊受怕。

冬天，听说太太要出卖土地，大路上一家客店的老板想把它买下来。农民们听了都很恐慌。他们想：“要是客店老板买下这块地，他罚起款来一定比太太更厉害。我们不能没有这块地，我们都靠它过活。”农民们就一起来到太太那里，要求她别把地卖给客店老板而卖给他们，他们愿意多出点儿钱。太太答应了。农民们商量由村社买下整块土地。他们商量了一次又一次，但始终没有谈成。原来是魔鬼在其中作怪，使他们的意见不能统一。最后农民们决定各人根据自己的力量各买各的，太太也答应了。巴霍姆听说邻居向太太买了二十俄亩地，太太答应先收一半钱，其余一半一年后再付。巴霍姆很羡慕，想：“地都被买光了，弄得我一无所有。”他就同妻子商量。

他说：“大家都在买地，我们也得买十来俄亩。要不管家动不动就罚款，我们没法儿过日子。”

他们考虑怎样设法买地。他们有一百卢布存款，卖掉一匹马驹和一半蜜蜂，把儿子抵押出去当雇工，再向连襟借点儿钱，这样就能凑满一半地价。

巴霍姆凑齐钱，看中一块地，有十五俄亩，带一片小树林，就去同太太谈。他们谈成了这笔买卖，拍了板，付了定金。他们又进城，把地契过了户，付了一半款子，其余一半两年内付清。

这样，巴霍姆就有了自己的土地。他借了种子，播在他买来的土地上。庄稼长得很好。一年之内他就付清了太太的欠款，还了连襟的债。巴霍姆从此成了土地的主人：他耕种自己的地，在自己的地上割草，在自己的地上伐木，在自己的地上放牧牲口。不论翻耕自己的土地，还是观赏自己的作物或者草地，巴霍姆总是心花怒放。他总觉得他土地上的草长得特别茂盛，花开得格外美丽。以前他走过这片土地，觉得它同别的土地一样，但现在却觉得它完全与众不同。

三

巴霍姆这样过着日子，感到心满意足。只要邻居不来糟蹋他的庄稼和草地，就一切称心如意了。他恳求他们，但是没有用：一会儿牧人把牛放到他的草地上，一会儿夏天夜里放牧的马闯进他的庄稼地。巴霍姆总是把牲口赶走，原谅主人。他一直忍着不去告状，但后来实在受不了了，就告到乡里。他知道邻居这样做并不是有意的，而是因为土地太少，但又想：“也不能听任不管，这样下去他们会把地糟蹋光的。得教训教训他们。”

他一次一次上法院告状，法院罚一两个农民赔偿。邻居们对巴霍姆就怀恨在心，一再故意糟蹋他的地。有一天夜里他来到树林里，看见有十棵椴树被砍倒剥去树皮。巴霍姆来到树林里，看见有样东西白乎乎的。他骑马跑近一看，地上横着几棵椴树，旁边露出几个树桩。要是只砍去边上几棵倒也罢了，可是那坏蛋竟砍个精光。巴霍姆看了大为生气：“哼，我要知道是谁干的，我就找他算账。”他想来想去，断定：“不是别人，准是谢苗。”他走到谢苗家去找，什么也没有找到，两人只对骂了一通。他告到法院，谢苗被传去审问。法院一再审查，谢苗进行辩解，也没有找到罪证。巴霍姆越发生气，他跟乡长、法官都吵了嘴。

“你们包庇小偷。要是你们大公无私，就不会开脱小偷了。”

巴霍姆跟法官和左邻右舍都吵了嘴。有人威胁要烧他的房子。巴霍姆的地虽然多了，但他的日子却更加难过。

当时盛传有许多人迁移到新的地区去。巴霍姆想：“我可不用离开我的土地，要是有人离开这儿，我们的地盘可以宽广些。我会把他们的地弄到手，把我的农庄扩大，这样日子就会更舒坦。要不总觉得土地太少。”

一天，巴霍姆坐在家里，来了一个过路的农民。巴霍姆留他在家里过夜，给他饭吃，同他谈天，问他从什么地方来。农民说，他从伏尔加河下游来，他在那里当雇工。谈着谈着，农民说，有许多人迁移到那里，他们就在那里定居，加入村社，每人分到十俄亩地。

他说：“那边的地很肥，种下黑麦，麦秆长得比马背还高，可茂盛了，五把就可以扎一大捆。有个农民很穷，去的时候只有一双手，如今已有六匹马、两头牛了。”

巴霍姆心动了。他想：“既然有好日子可过，何必在这里受穷？我把这里的地和房子都卖掉，到那边另起炉灶，大干一番。挤在这小地方真是活受罪。不过我得亲自去了解了解。”

他在初夏动身，乘轮船沿伏尔加河到萨马拉，然后步行四百俄里[2]到达目的地。情况果然如此。农民的地很多，每人分到十俄亩，他们高高兴兴加入村社。谁要是有钱，除了份地外还可以买地，最好的地每俄亩只要三卢布，要多少可以买多少！

巴霍姆把情况了解清楚后，秋天回家把东西变卖一空。他带点儿赚头卖掉土地，又卖掉房子和牲口，退出村社。开春就全家搬到了新地方去。

四

巴霍姆带着一家人来到新地方，参加了一个大村的村社。他招待村社长辈喝酒，弄到了各种证件。村社接受巴霍姆入社，分给他五十俄亩份地，分在几个地方，牧场是公用的。巴霍姆盖了房子，养了牲口。单是从村社分到的地就比原来的多两倍，而且都是种庄稼的沃土。日子过得比原来好十倍。饲料也很充裕，牲口要养多少就可以养多少。

巴霍姆在这里安顿下来，感到称心如意，但定居后，又觉得土地不够。第一年，巴霍姆在份地上种小麦，收成很好。他种小麦来了劲，但觉得地不够。刚种过的地不宜立刻再种。当地人在熟荒地和休闲地上种小麦，种了一两年就让土地休闲，长野草。这种地要的人很多，不够分配，为此常常发生争吵。有钱的自己种，穷人则把地租给商人，租金用来缴税。巴霍姆想多种些，第二年就去向商人租来一块地，一年为期。他种得更多，收成更好，但那块地离家太远，赶车得走十五俄里。他看到有些农民兼做买卖，自己有农庄，日子过得很阔气。巴霍姆想：“我要是也买点儿私地，办个农庄，就更称心如意了。”巴霍姆开始考虑怎样买私地。

巴霍姆这样过了三年。他租地种小麦，年年风调雨顺，小麦喜获丰收，钱越存越多。这样的日子本可以一直过下去，但他感到麻烦，因为年年得为租地奔走忙碌，什么地方有好地，农民就涌到那里，把地一抢而光。你去晚了，就没有地种。第三年，他同一个商人向农民合买一片牧场，农民已耕了地，可是有纠纷，农民们告到官府，地也就白耕了。他想：“如果那地是自己的，就不用向人打躬作揖，也不会有麻烦了。”

巴霍姆到处打听哪里可以买到私地。他遇到一个农民，向他买了五百俄亩地，那人破产了，所以卖得很便宜。巴霍姆同他讨价还价，谈了半天，最后以一千五百卢布成交，一半付现金。这事差不多已办成，不想有个商人路过他那里喂马。巴霍姆同他一起喝茶，谈天。商人讲到他从遥远的巴什基尔来。他说，他向巴什基尔人买了五千俄亩地，总共才花了一千卢布。巴霍姆就向他详细打听这事。商人说：“不过先得去巴结老人。我花一百卢布买了绸袍、地毯送给他们，再加一箱茶叶，把能喝酒的都请来喝酒。结果我就以每俄亩二十戈比的价钱成交了。”他出示地契说，“地都在河边，上面长满茅草。”

巴霍姆又详细打听了一番。

商人说：“那边的土地一年也走不到头，全是巴什基尔人的。巴什基尔人像羊一样没有脑子，那里的地几乎可以白拿。”

巴霍姆想：“既然如此，我何必花一千五百卢布去买五百俄亩地，还要欠债！我拿一千卢布到那边可以买到多少地啊！”

五

巴霍姆问清了到那地方的路径。他送走商人就准备动身。他抛下家给妻子照管，自己带了一名雇工出发。他们来到城里，照商人的话买了一箱茶叶、礼品和酒。他们走啊走啊，一连走了大约五百俄里，第七天来到巴什基尔人的游牧地。一切就像商人所说的那样，巴什基尔人临河搭了毡帐篷，住在草原上。他们不种地，也不吃粮。草原上放着成群的牛马。马驹拴在帐篷后面，母马一天两次被牵来喂奶。他们挤马奶，做马奶酒。巴什基尔女人搅马奶酒，做干酪，男人只知道喝马奶酒，饮茶，吃羊肉，吹笛子。他们个个肥肥胖胖，快快活活，整个夏天就像过节一样不干活儿。他们愚昧无知，不懂俄语，但是和蔼可亲。

巴什基尔人一看见巴霍姆从帐篷里出来，就把他团团围住。他们找来一名翻译。巴霍姆对他们说，他是来看地的。巴什基尔人听了很高兴，把巴霍姆领到一个最好的帐篷里，让他坐在地毯上，又给了他羽绒靠枕。他们围坐在四周，请他饮茶，喝马奶酒。巴什基尔人还宰了一头羊，请他吃羊肉。巴霍姆从马车里取出礼品，分送给他们。巴霍姆送了巴什基尔人礼品，又把茶叶分给他们。巴什基尔人很高兴，彼此叽里咕噜地说了一通，然后叫翻译告诉巴霍姆。

翻译说：“他们说，他们喜欢你，我们这里的风俗是尽量让客人高兴，还要回赠礼品。你送了我们礼品，现在你说说，你喜欢我们这里什么东西，我们好给你还礼。”

“我最喜欢你们这里的土地，”巴霍姆说，“我们那里地少，而且种薄了，你们这里地多，而且很肥。这样好的地我还从没见过呢。”

翻译翻译了他的话。巴什基尔人又交谈了好一阵。巴霍姆不明白他们在说些什么，但看出他们很高兴，又是叫，又是笑。随后他们安静下来，望着巴霍姆，翻译就说：“他们要我对你说，他们愿意给你土地来回报你的好意，你要多少给你多少。你只要用手点一点，那地就是你的了。”

他们又谈了一会儿，像是在争论什么问题。巴霍姆问他们在争论什么，翻译说：“有人说，土地的事得问问头人，没得到他的许可不行。也有人说，没得到他的许可也可以。”

六

巴什基尔人争论着，突然来了个戴狐皮帽的人。大家都不说话，站起来。翻译说：“这位就是头人。”

巴霍姆立刻拿出一件最好的绸袍送给头人，还给了他五磅茶叶。头人接受了礼物，在首席坐下。巴什基尔人立刻对头人说着什么。头人听着听着，点了点头，告诉他们不用再说下去。然后他用俄语对巴霍姆说话。

“好吧，”他说，“你喜欢什么地方，就拿什么地方。地多的是。”

“我怎么才能把要的地都拿到手呢？”巴霍姆想，“总得有个保证啊。要不现在说是我的，以后又把地收回去。”

“谢谢你们的美意，”巴霍姆说，“你们的地很多，我要的不多。不过我要知道给我的地是哪一块。总得量一下，给我定下来。要不死生由命，现在你们这些好人给了我土地，但难保将来你们的子孙不收回去。”

“你说的有理，”头人说，“可以定下来。”

巴霍姆说：“我听说有个商人来过你们这儿，你们也给了他地，还写了契约，我也希望这样做。”

头人懂得他的意思。

“这都不成问题，”他说，“我们这儿有文书。我们到城里去一次，正式订个契约。”

“那么价钱怎么算？”巴霍姆问。

“我们这儿只有一个价：一千卢布一天。”

巴霍姆不懂他的意思。

“一天是多少啊？一天等于几俄亩？”

“我们不会算，”他说，“我们出卖土地用天计算；你一天能绕多少地，这些地就归你，价钱是一千卢布一天。”

巴霍姆感到惊讶，他说：“一天走下来，那地可多啦！”

头人笑起来。

“全部归你！”头人说，“但有一个条件：你要是当天不能回到出发的地方，你的钱就白花了。”

“那我怎么在走过的地方做记号？”巴霍姆问。

“我们将站在你看中的地方，你去绕一圈，随身带一把铲子，你要什么地方，就挖个坑盖上草做记号，我们再从一个坑到另一个坑犁出一条沟。你要绕多大的圈子，就绕多大的圈子，但日落之前一定要回到出发的地方。你一圈绕下来的地方都归你所有。”

巴霍姆高兴极了。他们决定第二天一早出发。接着大家又谈天，又喝马奶酒，又吃羊肉，又饮茶，直到天黑。他们安排巴霍姆睡羽绒褥子，讲定天一亮就集合，日出前出发，这才各自回家。

七

巴霍姆躺在羽绒褥子上睡不着，心里一直在想：“我要弄到一大块地。我一天可以走五十俄里路。现在日长，五十俄里绕一圈地可多啦。以后我把坏地卖掉，或者让给农民，挑最好的地自己种。我要买两头公牛，雇两名工人。我要种五十俄亩地，其余的养草放牲口。”

巴霍姆通宵没有合眼，直到天快亮才迷迷糊糊地睡着。他做了个梦，梦见他就躺在这个帐篷里，听见外面有人在哈哈大笑。他想看看谁在笑，就起身走出帐篷，看见巴什基尔头人坐在帐篷前捧腹大笑。他走过去问道：“你在笑什么呀？”他发现这人不是巴什基尔头人，而是几天前路过他家告诉他买地的商人。他刚问商人：“你来这儿好久了？”立刻又发现他不是商人，而是那个好久前从伏尔加河下游来的农民。接着巴霍姆又看见那不是农民，而是一个长着犄角和蹄子的魔鬼。魔鬼坐在那里哈哈大笑，前面躺着个只穿短衫裤的赤脚农民。巴霍姆仔细瞧瞧，才发现这是个死人，而且就是他自己。巴霍姆吓醒了，想：“真是什么梦都会做啊！”他回头一看，看见门外天色已经发白。他想：“得叫醒人，是时候了。”巴霍姆起身，叫醒车上的雇工，吩咐他套车，自己则去唤醒巴什基尔人。

“起来吧，到草原上去量地。”他说。

巴什基尔人纷纷起来，聚集在一起，头人也来了。巴什基尔人又喝马奶酒，还要请巴霍姆饮茶，但巴霍姆等不及了。

“要走就走吧，是时候了。”他说。

八

巴什基尔人集合起来，有的骑马，有的坐车，大家出发。巴霍姆跟他的雇工带了铲子，坐上自己的马车上路。他们来到草原上，朝霞刚刚出现。他们爬上一座小丘。大家下了车，下了马，聚在一起。头人走到巴霍姆跟前，用手指着说：“瞧，这片土地都是我们的，一眼望不到边。你随便挑吧。”

巴霍姆眼睛红了：这是一片熟荒地，平得像手掌，黑得像鸦片，洼地上野草丛生，长得齐胸高。

头人摘下狐皮帽放在地上，说：“瞧，这就是记号。你从这儿出发，再回到这儿。凡是你绕一圈走下来的地都归你。”

巴霍姆摸出钱放在帽子上，脱下长袍，只穿一件短袄，收紧宽腰带，把一袋面包揣在怀里，又把水壶挂在腰带上，拉拉靴筒，向雇工要了铲子，准备上路。他反复考虑走哪个方向，觉得到处都是好地。他想：“反正都一样，我朝太阳升起的地方走就是了。”他面对太阳站着，活动活动身子，等太阳从天边出来。他想：“不能浪费时间，要趁凉快赶路。”等太阳从地平线一出来，巴霍姆就背起铲子向草原走去。

巴霍姆走得不快不慢。他走了一俄里光景停下来站住，挖了一个坑，盖上草皮，这样醒目些。接着又向前走。他活动活动身子，加快脚步。他走了一段路，又挖了一个坑。

巴霍姆回头望了望。小丘在阳光下看得清清楚楚，人们站在那里，马车的轮子闪闪发亮。巴霍姆估计他已走了五俄里。他感到热，脱下短袄搭在肩上，继续往前走。又走了五俄里的样子。天气更热了。他望望太阳，已是吃早饭的时候。

“已经走了一程[3]，”巴霍姆想，“不过一天能走四程路，回去还早。让我把靴子脱掉。”他坐下来脱下靴子挂在腰带上，继续走路。现在比较轻松了。他想：“让我再走五俄里，然后往左拐。这地方太好了，放弃可惜。越往前，地越好。”他又一直走过去。他回头一看，小丘隐约可见，小丘上的人像黑蚂蚁，还有一样东西在发亮。

巴霍姆想：“是啊，这个方向已走了不少路，得拐弯了。可把我渴死了，真想喝点儿水。”他停下来，挖了个更大的坑，盖上草皮，解下水壶，喝了个够，就陡然向左拐弯。他走啊走，草长得更高，天更热了。

巴霍姆走累了。他望望太阳，已是吃午饭的时候。他想：“好吧，让我歇会儿。”巴霍姆收住脚步，蹲下来。他吃了点儿面包，又喝了点儿水，但没有躺下。他想：“我一躺下就会睡着的。”他坐了一会儿，继续往前走。起初走得还轻松，因为吃了点儿东西，添了力气。天气越来越热，他直想打瞌睡，但他没有停下来，心里想，忍耐一时，享福一世。

他朝这个方向又走了许多路，正想向左拐，忽然看见一片水洼地，觉得放弃可惜。他想：“这里种亚麻很好。”他又一直向前走去。他走过水洼地，在那边挖了一个坑，拐了弯。巴霍姆回头望望小丘，那边热得雾气弥漫，仿佛空气也在颤动，隐约看得见小丘上的人，离他大约有十五俄里。巴霍姆想：“哦，那两边走得够多了，这边得少走些。”他加快脚步朝第三个方向走去。他望望太阳，太阳已到中天，可第三个方向还只走了两俄里。距离出发的地方仍有十五俄里。他想：“不行，虽然这样我会弄到一块斜形地，但是必须笔直赶回去。我不要更多的地，现在已经很多了。”巴霍姆急忙挖了一个坑，拐弯笔直向小丘走去。

九

巴霍姆一直向小丘走去。他汗流浃背，两脚划破，浑身瘫软。他想歇一会儿，但是不能，日落之前要赶不回去的。太阳不等人，越来越往下沉，往下沉。他想：“哦，我是不是要的太多了？会不会来不及？”他往前望望小丘，望望太阳：离出发点很远，而太阳离地平线却不远了。

巴霍姆一直走着，越来越吃力，但仍不断加快脚步。他走啊走啊，离终点还是很远。他小跑起来。他抛下短袄、靴子、水壶和帽子，只拿着铲子当拐杖。他想：“唉，我太贪心，这下子全完了。日落以前我跑不到了。”他心里发慌，更加上气不接下气。巴霍姆跑得浑身大汗，衬衫衬裤都贴在身上，嘴巴发干。他的胸膛好像铁匠铺里的风箱一样拼命喘气，心上好像有一把铁锤在敲打，两腿失去知觉，好像散了架。巴霍姆感到害怕，心里想：“可别累死啊。”

他怕死，但又不愿停下来。他想：“已经跑了这么多，现在停下来，会被人家笑话的。”他跑啊跑啊，越来越接近终点，他听见巴什基尔人在向他大声叫喊，心里更加发慌。他拼出最后的力气向前跑去，太阳已接近地平线，落到迷雾中，它又大又红，像血染了一样，眼看就要落下去了。太阳离地平线很近，他到达出发点也不远了。巴霍姆已看见小丘上人们在向他招手，要他加油。他看见地上的狐皮帽，看见帽子上的钱；他看见头人坐在地上，双手按住肚子。巴霍姆想起了他的梦，同时想：“土地很多，但上帝是不是让我在上面过？唉，我把自己给毁了，我跑不到了。”

巴霍姆望望太阳，太阳已触到地平线，一半已隐没不见，只剩下一半。巴霍姆竭尽全力冲去，两只脚勉强跟上，使自己不致倒下。巴霍姆跑近小丘，天色突然黑下来。他回头一看，太阳已经落山了。巴霍姆大叫一声，想：“我白费力气了。”他想停下来，但听见巴什基尔人还在叫喊。他突然想到，他从低处看太阳已经落下，但从小丘上看太阳一定还没有落下。他拼着最后一口气跑上小丘。小丘上还很亮。巴霍姆跑上去，看见了帽子。帽子前面坐着头人，双手捧腹哈哈笑着。巴霍姆想起了那个梦，他惊叫一声，两腿一软扑倒在地，他的手伸出去够着了帽子。

“啊，真是条好汉！”头人叫道，“你得到了许多土地！”

巴霍姆的雇工跑过来，想把他扶起，但他口吐鲜血，躺在地上死了。

巴什基尔人叹息不已。

雇工拿起铲子给巴霍姆挖了一个坑，从头到脚有三俄尺[4]长，就把他埋了。

[1] 一俄亩约合1.09公顷。（说明：书中脚注均为译者注。）

[2] 一俄里约合1.0668公里。

[3] 一程指马一口气能走的路。

[4] 一俄尺合0.71米。

人靠什么生活

我们因为爱弟兄，就晓得是已经出生入死了。没有爱心的，仍住在死中。（《新约·约翰一书》，第三章，第十四节）

凡有世上财物的，看见弟兄穷乏，却塞住怜恤的心，爱上帝的心怎能存在他里面呢？（同上，第三章，第十七节）

小子们哪，我们相爱，不要只在言语和舌头上，总要在行为和诚实上。（同上，第三章，第十八节）

爱是从上帝来的，凡有爱心的，都是由上帝而生，并且认识上帝。（同上，第四章，第七节）

没有爱心的，就不认识上帝，因为上帝就是爱。（同上，第四章，第八节）

从来没有人见过上帝。我们若彼此相爱，上帝就住在我们里面。（同上，第四章，第十二节）

上帝就是爱。住在爱里面的，就是住在上帝里面，上帝也住在他里面。（同上，第四章，第十六节）

人若说，我爱上帝却恨他的弟兄，就是说谎话的。不爱他所看见的弟兄，就不能爱没有看见的上帝。（同上，第四章，第二十节）

一

从前有个鞋匠，他带着老婆、孩子租了农民的一所小房子，住在那里。他没有自己的房子，没有土地，靠做鞋养家糊口。粮食贵，工钱贱，挣得的钱全部吃光。夫妻俩只有一件皮袄，而且这件皮袄也已穿得破破烂烂。鞋匠想买一块羊皮做件新皮袄，为此他已攒了一年多的钱。

到今年秋天，鞋匠已攒了一些钱；老婆箱子里藏着一张三卢布钞票，还有五卢布二十戈比是村里农民欠他的债。

一天早晨，鞋匠打算去村里买羊皮。他在衬衫外面穿上老婆的布棉袄，外面再套一件布长袍，口袋里放着那张三卢布钞票。他折了一根棍子，吃过早饭就动身。他想：“我从农民那里收来五卢布，再加上自己的三卢布，就可以买一块羊皮做新皮袄了。”

鞋匠来到村里，走进一个农民家，农民出去了，他老婆没钱，但答应一星期内叫丈夫送去。他去找另一个农民，那农民指天发誓说他没有钱，只付了二十戈比修鞋费。鞋匠想赊一块羊皮，可是卖皮货的信不过他。

“拿钱来，”他说，“皮子随你挑，我可尝过讨债的滋味。”

结果鞋匠一事无成，只收到二十戈比修鞋钱，还有一双旧毡靴，那是一个农民要他拿回去用皮子码边的。

鞋匠垂头丧气，拿二十戈比全喝了伏特加，空着一双手回家。早晨，鞋匠感到寒冷彻骨，但喝了点儿酒，不穿皮袄也还暖和。鞋匠走大路回家，一手拿棍子敲着冰冻的地面，一手摇摇晃晃提着毡靴，嘴里自言自语：“我不穿皮袄也挺暖和。一杯酒下肚，浑身发热，皮袄都用不着了。我现在高高兴兴回家去。嗨，我就是这样一个人！有什么可烦恼的？没有皮袄照样活下去。我一辈子也用不着皮袄，可是老太婆会不高兴的。再说，你整天给人干活儿，却一个钱也拿不到，总叫人生气。哼，你要是不拿钱来，我就摘你帽子，真的，摘你帽子。要不这像什么话？一次只给你二十戈比！哼，二十戈比能干什么？只能喝一盅。他说他手头紧。你手头紧，我就不紧？你有房子，有牲口，什么都有。你有自己种的粮，可我得花钱买粮吃。不论怎么说，我光买面包每星期就得三卢布。我回去，家里没有面包，又得掏出一个半卢布去买。所以你得把欠的钱还我。”

这时鞋匠来到大路转角处的一座小教堂旁。他看见教堂那边有个白乎乎的东西。天已黑下来，鞋匠仔细看了半天，也看不清究竟是什么。他想：“石头吗？这里没有这样的石头。牲口吗？又不像牲口。脑袋有点儿像人，但怎么会是白乎乎的？再说，人怎么会待在那里？”

他走近些，看清楚了。真稀奇，的确是一个人，但不知是死是活，光着身子坐在那里，身子靠在教堂墙上，一动不动。鞋匠很害怕，心里想：“准是谁杀了他，剥去衣服，把他扔在这里。我要是再走近点儿，就脱不了干系啦。”

鞋匠从旁边绕过去，走到教堂后面就看不见那个人了。他走过教堂，回头一看，那人已不再靠着墙壁，身子在动，仿佛也瞧着他。鞋匠越发害怕，心里想：“走过去，还是绕开？走过去，难保不出事，谁知道他是什么人？他落到这里准不是什么好事。要是走过去，他跳起来掐我的脖子，我就别想脱身了。即使他不掐脖子，你能拿一个光身子的人怎么办？总不能把自己身上最后一件衣服脱给他吧。上帝保佑！”

鞋匠加快脚步，眼看就要绕过教堂，但他的良心不答应。

鞋匠在路上站住。

“谢苗，你这算什么呀？”他自己对自己说，“人家遭难都快死了，你却害怕，想绕过去。难道你发了大财，怕人家抢你的钱吗？唉，谢苗，这样可不好！”

谢苗转身向那人走去。

二

谢苗走到那人身边，仔细一看，发现他年轻力壮，身上没有伤痕，但是几乎冻僵了。这可把他吓坏了。那人斜靠在墙上，眼睛不看谢苗，样子非常虚弱，连眼皮也抬不起来。谢苗走到他跟前，那人仿佛突然清醒过来，转过头，睁开眼睛，瞧了瞧谢苗。他的目光引起谢苗的爱怜。谢苗把毡靴往地上一扔，解下腰带放在毡靴上，然后脱下长袍。

“你不用说什么！”谢苗说，“快穿上！来！”

谢苗抓住那人的手肘，扶他站起来。那人站了起来。谢苗看到他身体细长、干净，手脚完整，相貌和蔼可亲。谢苗把长袍披在他肩上，可是他的手臂伸不进衣袖。谢苗把他的手塞进衣袖里，给他掩上前襟，束好腰带。

谢苗摘下破便帽，想给那人戴上，但自己头上感到冷。他想：“我的头全秃了，他却有一头长长的鬈发。”于是他又戴上帽子，“还是给他穿上靴子吧。”

谢苗让他坐下，给他穿上毡靴。

谢苗给他穿好衣服说：“好了，兄弟。你活动活动身子，暖和暖和。别的我就不管了。你能走吗？”

那人站在那里，温柔地瞧着谢苗，但说不出话来。

“你怎么不说话？总不能在这里过冬啊。得到有人家的地方去。喏，把我的棍子拿去，你身子虚，就拄着棍子走。打起精神来！”

那人就迈开步子。他走得挺轻松，没有落后。

他们在大路上走着，谢苗问：“你是哪里人？”

“我不是本地人。”

“本地人我都认识。你怎么会到教堂这儿来的？”

“我不能告诉你。”

“是不是有人欺负你了？”

“谁也没有欺负我。是上帝惩罚我。”

“当然，一切都是上帝的旨意，但你总得找个地方安顿啊。你要上哪儿去？”

“我都无所谓。”

谢苗听了觉得奇怪。那人不像个泼皮，说话也挺温和，可自己的事却绝口不谈。谢苗想：“天下什么怪事没有啊。”接着就对他说：“好吧，你就到我家去吧，哪怕去暖和暖和身子也好。”

谢苗向家里走去，陌生人跟在他旁边。起风了，谢苗穿着衬衫感到冷，他已酒意全消，身体都快冻僵了。他走着，吸着鼻子，掩紧身上的女短袄，想：“哼，买皮袄，买皮袄，回来连长袍都没有了，还带回一个光身男子。玛特廖娜准会不高兴的！”一想到玛特廖娜，谢苗就很担忧。他望望陌生人，记起那人在教堂旁的目光，心里感到一阵温暖。

三

谢苗的妻子一早就料理好家务。她劈了柴，打了水，让孩子们吃饱，自己也吃了点儿东西，坐着想心事。她在考虑，面包今天做还是明天做？家里还剩有一大块面包。

她想：“谢苗要是在那里吃了中饭，晚饭就吃不了多少，面包就够明天吃了。”

玛特廖娜反复掂着那块面包的重量，想：“今天不做面包吧。面粉只够烤一炉面包了，我们得熬到星期五。”

玛特廖娜收拾好面包，坐到桌子旁给丈夫补衬衫。她一面补，一边想着丈夫，不知他会买一块怎样的羊皮回来。

“他可别被卖皮的骗了。我男人实在是个老实人。他从来不骗人，可是连小孩子都会让他上当。八卢布不是个小数目，可以做一件好皮袄。就算不是熟皮，也总是一件皮袄。去年冬天没有皮袄可难过啦！去河边不行，去哪儿都不行。他出门把衣服都穿走，我就没有衣服穿了。他今天出门不算早，但也该回来了。我这个老头子总不会去喝酒吧？”

玛特廖娜刚想到这里，台阶上就响起吱吱嘎嘎的声音，有人走进来。她把针插好，看见进来的有两个人：谢苗和一个汉子，那汉子光着头，脚上却穿着毡靴。

玛特廖娜立刻闻到丈夫身上酒气熏天。她想：“哼，真的喝过酒了。”她看见他身上没有穿长袍，只有—件女短袄，空着一双手，一声不吭，显出一副畏畏缩缩的样子，她的心都凉了。她想：“他准是把钱都喝光了，同这种浪荡汉鬼混，还把他带回家来。”

玛特廖娜让他们走进屋，自己也跟着进去。她发现这个陌生人年纪很轻，瘦瘦的，身上穿着他们家的长袍。长袍里没有衬衫，头上没戴帽子。他一进来，就垂下眼睛，一动不动地站着。玛特廖娜想，看来不是个正经人，这么鬼鬼祟祟的。

玛特廖娜皱起眉头，走到灶边，冷眼看他们怎么样。

谢苗摘下帽子，规规矩矩地坐到长凳上。

“哎，玛特廖娜，”谢苗说，“给我们吃晚饭吧！”

玛特廖娜低声嘀咕着。她一动不动地站在灶旁，一会儿看看这个，一会儿望望那个，不住地摇头。谢苗看到老婆不高兴，但他无可奈何。他装作没注意，拉起陌生人的手说：“坐吧，兄弟，我们吃饭吧。”

陌生人在长凳上坐下。

“怎么，饭还没做吗？”

玛特廖娜火冒三丈。

“做了，可不是为你做的。我看你是喝糊涂了。你出去买皮袄，可回来连长袍也没有了，还带来一个光身子的无赖。我这儿没有你们酒鬼吃的饭！”

“够了，玛特廖娜，别胡说八道！你得先问问他是个什么人……”

“你说说，钱到哪儿去了？”

谢苗伸手到长袍口袋里，掏出钞票，把它们摊开来。

“钱在这里，特里丰诺夫没给钱，他答应明天给。”

玛特廖娜特别生气的是，他没有买皮袄，把最后一件长袍给了一个光身子的人，还把他领回家来。

她一把抓住桌上的钞票，把它们藏好，说：“我没有晚饭。光身子的酒鬼太多了，喂不过来。”

“喂，玛特廖娜，别乱说。先听听人家……”

“酒鬼的傻话我可听够了。是的，我当初就不肯嫁给你这个酒鬼。妈妈给我的麻布被你喝掉了，这回买皮袄的钱又被你喝掉了。”

谢苗要向妻子解释他只喝掉二十戈比，他要说明他在哪儿找到这个人，但玛特廖娜不让他插嘴。她喋喋不休地说个没完，连十年前的旧账都翻了出来。

玛特廖娜说着说着，突然冲到谢苗跟前，抓住他的衣袖。

“还我的短袄。我只剩下这么一件衣服，你还要从我身上剥去，穿到自己身上。拿来，癞皮狗，叫你不得好死！”

谢苗从身上脱下短袄，把一个衣袖翻了过来，玛特廖娜一扯，把线脚都扯开了。玛特廖娜抓住短袄套到头上，走到门口。她想出去，但又站住。她怒气冲天，很想发作，但又想知道来的是个什么人。

四

玛特廖娜在门口站住说：“他要是个好人，也不会光着身子，可他连衬衫都不穿一件。他要是干的正经事，你也得说说从哪儿弄来这样一个花花公子。”

“对，我正要告诉你。我在路上看见这个人光着身子坐在教堂旁，完全冻僵了。又不是夏天，怎么能光着身子？上帝让我碰上他，要不他会冻死的。咳，叫我怎么办？天知道他会怎么样！我就把他拉起来，给他穿上衣服，带回家来。你别这样发火，玛特廖娜，罪过啊！我们都是凡人，有一天都要死的。”

玛特廖娜正要破口大骂，但看了陌生人一眼，就不作声了。陌生人坐在凳子边上，一动不动。他的双手放在膝盖上，头垂在胸前，眼睛闭着，眉头皱紧，仿佛喘不过气来。玛特廖娜没作声。谢苗说：“玛特廖娜，难道你心里没有上帝吗？！”

玛特廖娜听见这话，又瞧了陌生人一眼，她的心肠顿时软了下来。她从门边走到灶旁，端出晚饭。她把碗放在桌上，倒了一碗格瓦斯，拿出最后一块面包，又给了陌生人刀和匙子。

“您吃吧！”她说。

谢苗推了推陌生人说：“坐吧，年轻人！”

谢苗切了面包，把它撕碎，吃起来。玛特廖娜坐在桌子角上，一只手托着脑袋，望着陌生人。

玛特廖娜可怜陌生人，对他产生了好感。陌生人也突然高兴起来，不再皱眉头，抬眼望望玛特廖娜，微微一笑。

他们吃完晚饭，女主人收拾好餐桌，问陌生人：“你是哪里人？”

“我不是本地人。”

“你是怎么流落街头的？”

“我不能说。”

“是不是有谁抢劫了你？”

“是上帝惩罚我。”

“你就这样光着身子躺在那儿吗？”

“就这样光着身子躺在那儿，我冻坏了。谢苗看见我，可怜我，把身上的长袍脱下来给我穿上，叫我到这儿来。到了这儿，你也可怜我，给我吃，给我喝。上帝保佑你们！”

玛特廖娜站起来，从窗上取下她刚补好的谢苗的旧衬衫递给陌生人，还找出一条裤子给他穿。

“拿去吧，我看你身上没有衬衣。你穿上，爱睡哪儿就睡哪儿，睡阁楼也行，睡炕也行。”

陌生人脱下长袍，穿上衬衫和裤子，躺到阁楼上。玛特廖娜熄了灯，拿起长袍，爬到丈夫身边。

玛特廖娜拿长袍一角盖在身上躺下来，但是睡不着，脑子里一直想着陌生人。

她想到，最后一块面包让他吃掉，他们明天就没有面包了。她想到，她给了他衬衫和裤子，心里闷闷不乐。可她想到他的微笑，心里便高兴了。

玛特廖娜好久都没有睡着，她听见谢苗也没有睡着，把长袍往他那边拉。

“谢苗！”

“嗯！”

“面包都吃光了，可我没发面。我不知道明天怎么过。是不是去向邻居玛拉尼雅借一点儿？”

“活一天是一天，不会挨饿的。”

老婆又躺了一会儿，不再作声。

“看样子他是个好人，只是干吗不肯讲他的来历？”

“大概不便说吧。”

“谢苗！”

“嗯！”

“我们给人家东西，可是怎么没有人给我们东西啊？”

谢苗不知道怎么回答，他只说：“别啰唆了！”他转了个身，睡着了。

五

第二天早晨谢苗醒来，孩子们还睡着，妻子向邻居借面包去了。那个陌生人穿着旧裤旧衬衫独自坐在长凳上，眼睛向上望。他的气色比昨天好。

谢苗说：“朋友，肚子饿了要吃面包，身子光着要穿衣服。人得养活自己。你会干什么活儿？”

“我什么也不会。”

谢苗感到奇怪，就说：“只要肯学，什么都学得会的。”

“人家都在干活儿，我也要干。”

“你叫什么名字？”

“米哈伊尔。”

“那么，米哈伊尔，你不愿谈自己，这随你的便，但你得养活自己。你要是能照我的话做，我就养你。”

“上帝保佑你，我愿意学。你教我怎么干就行。”

谢苗拿起纱，把它绕在手指上捻。

“你瞧，这事并不难……”

米哈伊尔瞧了一会儿，也把纱绕在手指上捻了起来。

谢苗教他给纱线上蜡。米哈伊尔立刻懂了。谢苗又教他把鬃毛捻到纱线上，怎样上靴子。米哈伊尔也立刻学会了。

不论谢苗教他做什么，他都一学就会。第三天他开始独自干活儿，仿佛做了一辈子的鞋。他干活儿不休息，吃得又少。工作间歇，他不说话，眼睛望着天空。他不上街，不闲聊，也不开玩笑。

只有第一天晚上，玛特廖娜给他吃晚饭，他才微微笑了笑。

六

日子过了一天又一天，过了一周又一周，不觉已过了一年。米哈伊尔仍在谢苗家干活儿。他的名声传开了：他做的靴子又挺括又结实，谁也比不上。附近一带的人都来找谢苗定做靴子，他的日子越过越富裕。

冬季的一天，谢苗和米哈伊尔正在干活儿，有一辆带铃铛的三驾雪橇向他家驶来。他们向窗外一望，看见雪橇在门口停下，一个汉子从驭座上下来，打开雪橇门。一位老爷身穿皮大衣，走下雪橇。他下了雪橇，走到谢苗家门口。玛特廖娜连忙起来打开门。老爷低下头走进小屋，又挺直身子，脑袋差点儿碰到天花板。他高大的身子把屋角都塞满了。

谢苗站起来鞠了一躬，看到老爷觉得很奇怪。他从没见过这样的人。谢苗自己筋脉毕露，米哈伊尔皮包骨头，玛特廖娜像一片木板，而这位老爷却像来自另一个世界：面色红润，体格魁梧，脖子粗得像公牛。他的整个身体就像用生铁铸成的。

老爷气喘吁吁，脱下皮大衣，坐在凳子上说：“谁是鞋匠老板？”

谢苗走过去说：“是我，老爷。”

老爷对他的跟班吆喝道：“喂，费杰卡，拿皮子来。”

跟班跑进来，拿来一个包裹。老爷接过包裹，把它放在桌上。“解开来。”他说。跟班解开包裹。

老爷用一根手指戳戳皮子，对谢苗说：“喂，听我说，鞋匠，你看见皮子了吗？”

“看见了，”谢苗说，“老爷。”

“那你知道这是什么皮子吗？”

谢苗摸摸皮子，说：“皮子挺好。”

“对，挺好！你这傻瓜还没见过这样的皮子吧。这是德国货，我花二十卢布买来的。”

谢苗吓了一跳，说：“我们哪里见过。”

“对了，一点儿不错。你能用这块皮子给我做一双靴子吗？”

“能，老爷。”

“这就对了。你要明白，你这是给谁做靴子，用的是什么皮子。我要你替我做一双靴子，穿上一年不走样、不开线。你能，就拿去裁；你不能，就别动。我把丑话说在前头：要是不到一年靴子开线、走样，我叫你坐班房；要是穿上一年不走样、不开线，我给你十卢布工钱。”

谢苗害怕了，不知道怎样回答。他回头瞧瞧米哈伊尔，用手肘推推他，低声问：“接不接？”

米哈伊尔点点头，说：“接。”

谢苗听了米哈伊尔的话，同意做一双一年不走样、不开线的靴子。

老爷唤来跟班，脱下左脚的靴子，伸直腿。

“给我量尺寸！”

谢苗缝了一个十俄寸[1]长的纸样，把它抚平，又跪下来，在围裙上仔细擦了擦手，以免弄脏老爷的袜子，这才动手量尺寸。谢苗量了鞋底，量了脚背，再量小腿肚，可是纸不够大。他的小腿肚粗得像圆木。

“注意，靴筒不要做得太紧。”

谢苗又缝了一个纸样。老爷坐着，动动穿着袜子的脚趾，环顾屋里的人。他看见米哈伊尔。

“这人是谁啊？”他问。

“他是我这里的师傅，靴子由他给您做。”

“留神啊，”老爷对米哈伊尔说，“记住，要一年穿不坏。”

谢苗回头看了看米哈伊尔，看见米哈伊尔根本不瞧老爷，却盯着老爷后面的角落，仿佛盯着什么人。米哈伊尔望着，望着，突然微微一笑，容光焕发。

“傻瓜，你龇牙咧嘴干什么？你还是留点儿神，到时候把靴子做好。”

米哈伊尔说：“到时候一定做好。”

“那就对了。”

老爷穿上靴子，掩上皮袄，向门口走去。他忘了弯弯腰，头在门楣上撞了一下。

老爷破口大骂，摸摸脑袋，坐上雪橇走了。

老爷走后，谢苗说：“哼，这可是个人物。这样的汉子棍子也打不倒。门楣都快被他撞倒了，可他却没有事。”

玛特廖娜说：“过这样的日子怎么会不胖！这样的树墩连死神也搬不动。”

七

谢苗对米哈伊尔说：“活儿是接下来了，我们可别给自己惹麻烦。皮子很贵，老爷脾气又大，可不能出岔子。你来吧，你眼睛尖，手艺比我强。这是尺寸，你来裁，我来上靴头。”

米哈伊尔听从他的话，拿起老爷的皮子摊在桌上，折成两半，拿起剪刀动手裁剪。

玛特廖娜走过来，看米哈伊尔裁皮子，对他的裁法感到惊讶。玛特廖娜看惯鞋匠活儿，现在看见米哈伊尔不按鞋匠的规矩裁，而是剪成圆形。

玛特廖娜想说但没有说出来：“看来是我不懂怎样给老爷做靴子。米哈伊尔一定更懂行，我还是不要去干涉他。”

米哈伊尔裁好一双，拿起麻线缝，但不像一般做靴子那样用两根线，而是像做便鞋那样只用一根线。

玛特廖娜看见这情景感到奇怪，但还是没说什么。米哈伊尔则一直缝下去。到吃午饭的时候，谢苗站起来，看见米哈伊尔已用老爷的皮子做了一双便鞋。

谢苗大吃一惊。他想：“这是怎么搞的，米哈伊尔来了整整一年，还从未出过岔子，这回竟会闯下这样大的祸？老爷要做一双有延条的皮靴，他却做了一双不打底的便鞋，把皮子都糟蹋了。如今叫我怎样向老爷交代？这样的皮子上哪儿去找啊？”

他对米哈伊尔说：“朋友，你这是怎么啦？你这是要我的命！老爷定的是一双靴子，可你做了什么？”

他刚在责备米哈伊尔，门环响了起来，有人敲门。他们往窗外一看，看见一个人骑马跑来，正在系马。他们开了门，进来的是老爷的跟班。

“你们好！”

“你好！你有什么事？”

“太太派我来取靴子。”

“什么靴子？”

“靴子嘛！我家老爷已用不着靴子了。他归天了。”

“你说什么？”

“他离开你们，还没到家就死在雪橇上。雪橇一到家，我们要扶他下雪橇，可他已像口袋那样倒在雪橇里。他已经死了，身子都硬了。我们好不容易才把他抬下雪橇。太太就派我到这儿来。她说：‘你对鞋匠说，老爷向你们定了一双靴子，还留下皮子，现在他不要靴子了，你赶快拿皮子给他做一双死人穿的便鞋。’她还叫我等着，等你们一做好就把鞋带回家。所以我来了。”

米哈伊尔捡起桌上裁剩的皮料卷起来，拿起两只做好的便鞋拍了一下，又用围裙擦了擦，交给跟班。

跟班接过便鞋说：“再见，老板！祝你好运！”

八

又过了一年，两年……米哈伊尔住在谢苗家不觉已是第六个年头了。他还是那样过日子，哪儿也不去，多余的话一句也不说，脸上只出现过两次笑容：一次是女主人第一回请他吃晚饭，另一次是那个老爷来定靴子。谢苗对他这个工人真是再满意不过了。他不再问他从哪儿来，只担心他离开他们。

有一天，他们都在家。女主人正把锅子放在灶上，孩子们在长凳上嬉戏，眼睛望着窗外。谢苗在一个窗口里钉靴子，米哈伊尔在另一个窗口里钉鞋跟。

一个男孩儿从长凳上跑到米哈伊尔旁边，靠在他肩上，眼睛望着窗外。

“米哈伊尔叔叔，你瞧，老板娘带着几个姑娘到我们家来了。有一个姑娘是瘸子。”

男孩儿一说完这话，米哈伊尔就扔下活儿，转身往街上望。

谢苗感到奇怪。米哈伊尔一向不往街上望，现在却伏在窗口望着什么。谢苗也往窗外望了望，果然有一个女人向他家走来，衣服干干净净，手里拉着两个身穿皮袄、头包羊毛围巾的女孩儿。两个女孩儿长得一模一样，叫你没法儿分辨，只是一个女孩儿左腿有毛病，走路一瘸一拐的。

那女人上了台阶，走进门廊，摸到门，抓住把手，打开门。她让两个女孩儿走在前头，自己跟着走进屋里。

“你好，老板！”

“请进。有什么事啊？”

那女人在桌旁坐下。两个女孩儿伏在她的膝上，她们看到陌生人有点儿害怕。

“想给这两个姑娘做两双春天穿的皮鞋。”

“行，没问题。我们没有做过这样小的鞋，但我们能做。有延条的，没延条的，都行。我们这位米哈伊尔师傅手艺可好啦。”

谢苗回头望了望米哈伊尔，看见他放下活计坐在那里，眼睛盯住两个小姑娘。

谢苗觉得米哈伊尔很怪。他想，这两个姑娘确实长得不错：黑眼睛，红脸颊，胖鼓鼓的，她们身上的皮大衣也挺漂亮。但谢苗不明白，米哈伊尔为什么这样盯着她们，仿佛认识她们似的。

谢苗感到困惑不解。他同那女人讲价钱，讲好价钱，动手量尺寸。女人把瘸腿的女孩儿抱到膝上，说：“你替这姑娘量两个尺寸；给这只跛脚做一只鞋，给这只好脚做三只鞋。她们俩的脚一样大。她们是双胞胎。”

谢苗量了尺寸，指着瘸腿的姑娘说：“她怎么会弄成这样？这么好看的姑娘。生下来就是这样的吗？”

“不，是她母亲把她压坏的。”

玛特廖娜想知道那女人是谁，姑娘们又是谁的孩子，就问：“那你不是她们的母亲吗？”

“老板娘，我不是她们的母亲，也不是亲戚，我完全是外人，只是领养了她们。”

“她们不是你自己的孩子，你却这样疼她们。”

“我怎能不疼她们呢？是我用自己的奶把她们喂大的。我自己有过一个孩子，可是上帝把他召去了，我疼他还不如疼她们呢。”

“那她们到底是谁的孩子啊？”

九

那女人就把事情从头到尾讲了一遍：

“大概六七年前吧，她们的父母在一个星期里相继去世。星期二刚葬了父亲，星期五母亲也死了。父亲在这两个孤儿出世前三天就死了，母亲生下她们连一天也没有活满。当时我跟丈夫住在乡下种庄稼，跟他们是邻居，两家门挨着门。她们的父亲一个人在树林里干活儿。那一天一棵树倒下来，把他拦腰压住，内脏都压了出来。他被抬到家里，就把灵魂交给了上帝。他老婆就在那个星期生下双胞胎，就是这两个姑娘。贫穷，孤独，上无老，下无小。她孤独地生下孩子，孤独地死去。

“第二天早晨我去看望邻居，走进小屋，她这个可怜人已经僵了。她死的时候身子把这个姑娘压住。她就这样把她的一条腿压坏了。乡亲们走来，把她洗干净，换上衣服，装进棺材，把她埋了。都是好人帮的忙。只留下两个没爹没娘的娃娃。怎么办？当时村里只有我一人奶娃娃，我正在喂养我那才八个星期的头生儿。我就把她们暂时带回家。庄稼人聚在一起，反复商量拿她们怎么办。他们对我说：‘玛丽亚，你先把这两个娃娃带回家去，我们再想想办法。’我用奶先喂没病的那个娃娃，却不喂腿被压坏的娃娃，我想她恐怕活不成了。但后来又想，怎么能亏待那个小东西呢？我也可怜她，我就一人喂三个——自己的一个再加上这两个！我当时年轻力壮，吃得又好。上帝开恩，奶汁多得直往外流。我常常同时喂两个，让第三个等着。等两个喂饱了，再喂第三个。上帝保佑，我把这两个喂大了，可自己那一个不满两岁就死了。上帝从此没再给我孩子，不过我们的日子越过越宽裕。现在，我丈夫在磨坊干活儿，工钱多，日子过得挺好，可我们没有自己的孩子。要是没有这两个姑娘，我真不知道日子怎么过！叫我怎能不疼她们呢？她们是我的心头肉！”

女人一手搂住瘸腿的姑娘，一手擦着脸上的眼泪。

玛特廖娜叹了口气，说：“常言说得好，没有爹娘还能过，没有上帝无法活。”

她们这样谈了一会儿，那女人站起来走了。主人两口子送她走，又回头望望米哈伊尔，只见米哈伊尔双手放在膝盖上，仰天微笑着。

十

谢苗走到他跟前说：“米哈伊尔，你怎么啦？”

米哈伊尔从长凳上站起来，放下活计，解下围裙，向主人两口子鞠躬说：“当家的，请你们饶恕我。上帝已经饶恕了我，你们也饶恕我吧。”

主人两口子看见米哈伊尔身上发出一道光。谢苗站起来，向米哈伊尔鞠了一躬说：“米哈伊尔，我知道你不是一个凡人，我不能留你，我也不能盘问你。只是请你告诉我：为什么当我发现你，把你领回家时，你神情忧郁，等我老婆给你端来了晚饭，你对她一笑，从此你就变得高兴了？为什么后来老爷来定做靴子，你又笑了一次，而且从此变得更开心？现在，那女人带了两个姑娘来，你第三次笑了，而且容光焕发，精神振奋。告诉我，米哈伊尔，为什么你身上会发光，而且笑了三次？”

米哈伊尔回答说：“我身上发光，那是因为上帝惩罚我，如今上帝饶恕我了。我笑了三次，因为我必须懂得上帝的三个道理，现在都懂了。那天你妻子可怜我，我懂得了第一个道理，因此第一次笑了。后来富人来定做靴子，我懂得了第二个道理，因此第二次笑了。现在我看见两个姑娘，我懂得了第三个道理，也就是最后一个道理，因此第三次笑了。”

谢苗又问：“告诉我，米哈伊尔，上帝为什么要惩罚你，上帝的那三个道理是什么。”

米哈伊尔说：“上帝惩罚我，因为我不听他的话。我原是天上的天使，但我不听上帝的旨意。

“我本是天上的天使，上帝派我去勾一个女人的魂。我降到地上，看见一个女人生病躺在床上，她一胎生了两个女孩儿。两个娃娃在母亲身旁蠕动，但她没有力气把她们抱过来喂奶。那女人看见我，知道是上帝派来取她的魂的，就哭诉道：‘天使啊！我的丈夫刚刚落葬，是被一棵树压死的。我没有姐妹，没有姨妈，没有婆婆，没人帮我养孩子。你先别取我的魂，让我先把两个孩子喂养长大！孩子没爹没娘活不成！’我听了她的话，把一个娃娃放在她怀里吃奶，另一个让她搂着，自己回到天上。我飞到上帝面前说：‘我不能取走产妇的灵魂。她男人被树压死了，她自己生了双胞胎，恳求我不要取走她的灵魂，说让她把孩子喂养长大，孩子没爹没娘活不成。我就没有取走产妇的灵魂。’上帝就说：‘你再去取那产妇的灵魂，并且弄懂三个道理：第一，人心里存在着什么；第二，人天生缺少什么；第三，人靠什么生活。等你弄懂了这三个道理，你就回天上来。’我又降到地上，取走了产妇的灵魂。

“两个娃娃就离开奶头。死人横在床上，压住了一个娃娃，把她的一条腿压坏了。我升到村庄上空，想把产妇的灵魂带给上帝，可是一阵风吹来把我的翅膀吹落，她的灵魂就单独去见上帝，而我就落到大路旁的地上。”

十一

谢苗和玛特廖娜这时才明白他们收留的人是谁，跟他们住在一起的人是谁，他们又惊又喜，不禁哭了起来。

天使说：“我就独自光着身子落在田野里。以前我不知道人们的贫困，不知道饥寒，这下我可成为人了。我肚子饿，身上冷，但不知道怎么办。我看见田野里有一座为上帝盖的教堂，就走到那儿，想在那里安身。教堂锁着，进不去。我坐在教堂后面避风。到了晚上，我又饿又冷，全身疼痛。忽然听见有人沿大路走来，手里拿着靴子，自言自语。我这是变人以后第一次看见一张凡人的脸，这脸使我害怕，我就转过身去。我听见这人在自言自语，盘算冬天用什么御寒，怎样养活老婆孩子。我想：‘我又饿又冷，现在来了一个人，可他只考虑怎样搞到皮袄给自己和妻子御寒，怎样弄到粮食充饥，他是不会帮助我的。’这人看见我皱起眉头，样子更加害怕，他从我身旁走过去。我绝望了。忽然我听见这人走回来。我朝他一看，简直认不出了：他的脸原来死气沉沉，如今变得生气勃勃，我从他脸上认识了上帝。他走到我跟前，给我衣服穿，把我领回家。我走进他家，一个女人朝我们走过来，嘴里说着什么。这女人比男人更可怕，嘴里吐出一股死气，憋得我喘不过气来。她想把我赶到冰天雪地里，我知道，她要是把我赶出去，她准会死掉。她丈夫突然向她提到上帝，她的态度顿时变了。她给我们端来晚饭，眼睛瞧着我，我也看了她一眼，她身上的死气已没有了，变得生气勃勃，我又从她身上认识了上帝。

“我记起上帝的第一句话：‘人心里存在着什么。’我知道人心里存在着爱。上帝向我启示他交代的事，我感到高兴，第一次笑了。但我还没懂得另外两个道理。我不懂得人天生缺少什么，以及人靠什么生活。

“我在你们家里住了一年。有人来定做靴子，要能穿上一年不走样、不开线。我瞧了他一眼，忽然看见他背后有我的同伴死亡天使的影子。这个天使，除了我，谁也看不见，可我认识他，并且知道不等太阳落山这个富人的灵魂就会被取走。我想：‘这人要做一双可以穿上一年的靴子，却不知道自己已活不到晚上。’于是我想起了上帝说的另一句话：‘人天生缺少什么。’

“人心里存在着什么，我已知道了。现在我又知道了人缺少什么。人们不知道他们为了自己的肉体需要什么。我又一次笑了。我高兴的是因为看见了我的同伴死亡天使，上帝又向我启示了第二个道理。

“但我还不懂得第三个道理。我还不懂得人靠什么生活。于是我继续等待上帝向我启示最后一个道理。第六年出现了双胞胎姑娘和那个女人。我认出这两个姑娘，知道她们是怎样活下来的。我当时想：‘母亲为了孩子求我不要取走她的灵魂，她说没有爹妈孩子们活不成，我相信了她的话，可是另一个女人把她们喂养长大了。’当这个女人爱惜别人的孩子并且痛哭流涕时，我从她身上看到了活生生的上帝，我懂得了人靠什么生活。我懂得上帝向我启示了最后一个道理并且饶恕了我，我就第三次笑了。”

十二

天使光着身子，全身发光，肉眼无法逼视。他说话的声音越来越响，仿佛这声音不是出自他的嘴，而是自天而降。天使说：“我知道，一切人活着不是靠自私，而是依靠爱。

“做母亲的不知道她的孩子要活下去需要的是什么。那富人不知道他究竟需要什么。谁也不知道，到傍晚他需要活人穿的靴子，还是死人穿的便鞋。

“我变成了人，我活着不是依靠自己的打算，而是依靠一个过路人和他妻子的爱心，他们怜悯我，爱我。两个孤女能活下来，不是依靠母亲的照顾，而是依靠一个陌生女人心中的爱，她怜悯她们，爱她们。一切人活着不是依靠自己的打算，而是依靠人们心中的爱。

“以前我知道上帝赐给人们生命，要他们活在世上。现在我知道的事更多了。

“我懂得了，上帝不愿人们分开来生活，因此不向他们启示每个人单独需要什么；他要人们一起生活，因此向他们启示为了自己和为了大伙儿需要什么。

“现在我懂得了，人们以为他们活着靠自己的盘算，其实他们活着全靠爱。谁生活在爱之中，谁就生活在上帝之中，上帝就在他心里，因为上帝就是爱。”

天使对上帝唱起了赞美诗，他的歌声震动了小屋。这时房顶开了，一根火柱从地面直冲天上。谢苗夫妻和孩子们拜倒在地。天使张开背上的一对翅膀，升上天去。

等谢苗清醒过来，他的小屋又恢复了原状，屋里只有他们一家，没有一个外人。

[1] 一俄寸合4.44厘米。

How Much Land Does A Man Need?

1

An elder sister came from the town to visit her younger sister in the country. This elder sister was married to a merchant and the younger to a peasant in the village. The two sisters sat down for a talk over a cup of tea and the elder started boasting about the superiority of town life, with all its comforts, the fine clothes her children wore, the exquisite food and drink, the skating, parties and visits to the theatre.

The younger sister resented this and in turn scoffed at the life of a merchant’s wife and sang the praises of her own life as a peasant.

‘I wouldn’t care to change my life for yours,’ she said. ‘I admit mine is dull, but at least we have no worries. You live in grander style, but you must do a great deal of business or you’ll be ruined. You know the proverb, “Loss is Gain’s elder brother.” One day you are rich and the next you might find yourself out in the street. Here in the country we don’t have those ups and downs. A peasant’s life may be poor, but it’s long. Although we may never be rich, we’ll always have enough to eat.’

Then the elder sister said her piece.

‘Enough to eat indeed with nothing but those filthy pig and calves! What do you know about nice clothes and goo manners! However hard your good husband slaves awa you’ll spend your lives in the muck and that’s where you’l die. And the same goes for your children.’

‘Well, what of it?’ the younger sister retorted. ‘That’s how it is here. But at least we know where we are. We don’t hav to crawl to anyone and we’re afraid of no one. But you i the town are surrounded by temptations. All may be wel one day, the next the Devil comes along and tempts you husband with cards, women and drink. And then you’r ruined. It does happen, doesn’t it?’

Pakhom, the younger sister’s husband, was lying over th stove listening to the women’s chatter.

‘It’s true what you say,’ he said. ‘Take me. Ever since I wa a youngster I’ve been too busy tilling the soil to let that kin of nonsense enter my head. My only grievance is that I don’have enough land. Give me enough of that and I’d fear n one – not even the Devil himself!’

The sisters finished their tea, talked a little longer abou dresses, cleared away the tea things and went to bed.

But the Devil had been sitting behind the stove and ha heard everything. He was delighted that a peasant’s wif had led her husband to boast that if he had enough lan he would fear no one, not even the Devil. ‘Good!’ h thought. ‘I’ll have a little game with you. I shall see tha you have plenty of land and that way I’ll get you in m clutches!’

2

Not far from the village lived a lady with a small estate of about three hundred acres. She had always been on good terms with the peasants and had never ill- treated them. But then she had taken on an old soldier to manage her estate and he proceeded to harass the peasants by constantly imposing fines. No matter how careful Pakhom was, one of his horses might stray into the lady’s oats, or a cow might sometimes wander into her garden, or some calves might venture out on to her meadows. Every time this happened he would have to pay a fine.

Pakhom would pay up and then he would go and swear at his family and beat them. All that summer Pakhom had to put up with a great deal from that manager, so he welcomed winter when it came and his cattle had to be kept in the shed: although he begrudged the fodder, at least he wouldn’t have to worry about them straying.

That winter word got round that the lady wanted to sell some of her land and that the innkeeper on the highway was trying to agree on a price with her. The peasants took this news very badly. ‘If that innkeeper gets his hands on that land he’ll start slapping even more fines on us than that manager. But we can’t survive without it, we all depend on it for our living.’

So a few peasants, in the name of the village commune, begged the lady not to sell any of her land to the innkeeper and to let them buy it, offering her a better price. The lady agreed. Then the members of the commune thought of buying the whole estate. They met once, they met twice, but no progress was made: the Devil had set them at loggerheads and there was nothing they could agree upon. In the end they decided to buy the land in separate lots, each according to what he could afford. The lady agreed to this as well.

One day Pakhom learned that one of his neighbours was buying about fifty acres and that the lady had taken half payment in cash, allowing the man one year to pay the balance. This made Pakhom very envious. ‘They’ll buy up all the land,’ he thought, ‘and I’ll be left with nothing.’ So he conferred with his wife.

‘Everyone’s buying land,’ he said. ‘We must get hold of twenty acres, or thereabouts. If we don’t we won’t be able to live, what with that manager bleeding us white with fines.’

So they racked their brains as to how they could buy some of the land. They had a hundred roubles saved up, so that by selling a foal and half their bees, by sending one of their sons out to work for someone who paid wages in advance and borrowing from a brother- in- law, they managed to scrape together half the money.

Then Pakhom took the money, chose about thirty acres of partly wooded land and went off to the lady to see if he could strike a deal. He managed to get the thirty acres, they shook hands on it and Pakhom paid a deposit. Then they went into town and signed the deeds, Pakhom paying half cash down and pledging to settle the balance within two years.

And so Pakhom now had land. He borrowed money for seeds and sowed the newly bought land; the harvest was excellent. Within a year he had repaid both the lady and his brother- in- law. Now he was a landowner, in the full sense of the word: he ploughed and sowed his own fields, reaped his own hay, cut his own timber and could pasture his cattle on his own land. Whenever he rode out to plough the land which was now his for ever, or to inspect his young corn and meadows, he was filled with joy. He felt that the grass that grew and the flowers that bloomed were different from any other grass and flowers. Before, when he had ridden over that land, it had seemed the same as any other. But now it was something quite special.

3

So Pakhom lived a landowner’s life and he was happy. And in fact all would have been well had other peasants not trespassed on his cornfields and meadows. He spoke to them very politely, but they took no notice. Herdsmen let their cows stray on to his meadows, then horses wandered into his corn on their way home from night pasture. Again and again Pakhom drove them out without taking further action, but in the end he lost patience and complained to the District Court. He knew very well that the peasants weren’t doing it deliberately but because they were short of land. But still he thought, ‘I can’t let this go on. Before long they’ll have destroyed all I have. I must teach them a lesson.’

So he taught them a lesson in court, then another, making several of them pay fines. Pakhom’s neighbours resented this and once again began to let their cattle stray on his land, this time on purpose. One night someone managed to get into Pakhom’s wood and felled about ten young lime- trees for their bark. Next day, when Pakhom was riding through his wood, he suddenly noticed something white on the ground. He went nearer and saw tree- trunks lying all around, stripped of their bark, with the stumps lying nearby. ‘If he’d only just cut one or two down, but that devil’s left me with one tree standing and cleared the rest.’ Pakhom seethed with anger. ‘Oh, if I knew who did it I’d show him a thing or two!’For a long time he racked his brains and finally concluded,‘It must be Semyon, it can’t be anyone else.’ So off he went to search Semyon’s place, but he found nothing and all the two men did was swear at each other. Pakhom was more convinced than ever that it was Semyon’s work and he lodged a complaint. The magistrates sat for ages debating the case and finally acquitted Semyon for lack of evidence. This incensed Pakhom even more and he had a stormy session with the village elder and the magistrates.

‘You are hand in glove with thieves,’ he protested. ‘If you were honest men you wouldn’t let a thief like him off the hook.’

As a result Pakhom fell out with the magistrates as well as his neighbours, who threatened to burn his cottage down.

And so, although Pakhom had plenty of leg- room now, he felt that the commune was hemming him in.

Around that time rumours were in the air that many peasants were leaving to settle in new parts of the country. Pakhom thought, ‘I don’t really need to go away, what with all that land of mine. But if some of the villagers were to go there’d be more room for others. I could buy their land and make my estate bigger. Life would be easier then, but as things are, it’s still too cramped here for my liking.’

One day a peasant who was passing through stopped at Pakhom’s cottage. They let him stay the night and gave him food. Pakhom asked where he was from and the man replied that he had come from the south, from the other side of the Volga, where he had been working. Then he told how people from his own village had settled there, joined the commune and had been allotted twenty- five acres each. ‘The land is so fertile,’ he said, ‘that rye grows as high as a horse and it’s so thick you can make a whole sheaf from only five handfuls! One peasant arrived with a copeck and only his bare hands to work with and now he has six horses and two cows.’

Pakhom was terribly excited by this news. ‘Why should I have to scrape a living cooped up here,’ he thought, ‘when I could be leading a good life somewhere else? I could sell the land and cottage and with the money I’d be able to build myself a house there and start a whole new farm. But here there’s no room to breathe and I get nothing but aggravation. I must go and find out what it’s like for myself.’

When summer came he was ready and he set off. He went down the Volga to Samara by steamboat, then walked the remaining three hundred miles to the new settlement, which was just as the visitor had described. All the men had plenty of space, each having been allotted twenty- five acres without charge and welcomed into the commune. Anyone who had the money could also buy as much of the finest freehold land as he wanted, at three roubles an acre – there was no limit!

Towards autumn, after finding out all he needed to know, Pakhom went home and started selling up. He sold the land at a profit, his home and all his cattle, resigned from the commune and waited until the spring, when he left with his family for the new settlement.

4

When he arrived with his family Pakhom managed to get himself on the register of a large village commune, having duly moistened the elders’ throats. All was signed and sealed and Pakhom was granted a hundred acres (twenty for each member of his family, in different fields), besides the use of the communal pasture. Then he put up some buildings and stocked his farm with cattle. The allotted land alone was three times as much as at home and it was perfect for growing corn. He was ten times better off here, for he had plenty of arable land and pasturage, and he was able to keep as many cattle as he wanted.

At first, while he was busy building and stocking up, everything seemed wonderful. But no sooner had he settled down to his new life than he began to feel cramped even here. During the first year he had sowed wheat on the allotted land and the crop had been excellent. But when he wanted to sow more wheat he found he needed more land: the other land he had been allotted was not suitable for wheat. In the south wheat is sown only on grass or on fallow land. They sow it for one or two years and then leave it fallow until the land is overgrown with feather- grass again. This type of land was in great demand and there wasn’t enough to go round, so that people quarrelled over it. The richer ones sowed their own, whilst the poorer ones had to mortgage theirs to merchants to pay their taxes. Pakhom wanted to sow more wheat, so the following year he rented some fields from a dealer for one year. He sowed a great deal of wheat and had a good crop. But the fields were a long way from the village and the wheat had to be carted more than ten miles. Then Pakhom noticed that some peasant farmers with large homesteads in the neighbourhood were becoming very wealthy. ‘What if I bought some freehold land and built myself a homestead like theirs?’ he wondered. ‘Then everything would be within easy reach.’ And he tried to think how he could buy some.

Pakhom farmed the same way for three years, renting land and sowing wheat. They were good years, the crops were good and he was able to save some money. But Pakhom grew tired of having to rent land, year after year, of having to waste his time scrambling after it. Whenever good land came up for sale the peasants would immediately fall over themselves to buy it and it would all be gone before he could do anything: he was never quick enough and so he had no land for sowing his wheat. So in the third year he went halves with a merchant in buying a plot of pasture land outright from some peasants. They had already ploughed it when someone sued the peasants over it and as a result all their work was wasted. ‘If it had been my land,’ Pakhom thought,‘I wouldn’t have been under an obligation to anyone and I wouldn’t have got into that mess.’

So Pakhom tried to discover where to buy some freehold land. He came across a peasant who, having purchased some thirteen hundred acres, had then gone bankrupt and was selling the land off very cheaply. Pakhom bargained with him. After much haggling they finally agreed upon fifteen hundred roubles, half cash down, half to be paid at a later date. The deal was all but signed and sealed when a passing merchant called at Pakhom’s to have his horses fed. They drank tea together and got into conversation. The merchant said that he was on his way back from the far- off land of the Bashkirs, where he had bought some thirteen thousand acres for a mere thousand roubles. When Pakhom questioned him further the merchant told him, ‘All I had to do was give the old men there a few presents – a hundred roubles’ worth of silk robes and carpets, a chest of tea, and vodka for anyone who wanted it. I managed to get the land for twenty copecks an acre.’ He showed Pakhom the title deeds. ‘The land is near a river and it’s all beautiful grassy steppe.’

Pakhom continued to ply him with questions.

‘There’s so much land that you couldn’t walk round it all in a year. It all belongs to the Bashkirs. Yes, the people there are as stupid as sheep and you can get land off them for practically nothing.’

‘Well,’ Pakhom thought, ‘why should I pay a thousand roubles for thirteen hundred acres and saddle myself with debt? To think what I could buy with the same money down there!’

5

Pakhom asked him how to get there and as soon as he had said goodbye to the merchant he prepared to leave. He left his wife behind and set off, taking a workman with him. First they stopped off in town and bought a chest of tea, vodka and other presents, just as the old merchant had advised. Then they travelled for miles and miles until, on the seventh day, they reached the Bashkir settlement. Everything was as the merchant had described: the people lived on the steppe, near a river, in tents of thick felt. They neither ploughed the soil nor ate bread, and their cattle and horses wandered in herds over the steppe. The foals were tethered behind the tents and the mares brought over to them twice a day. These mares were milked and from the milk kumiss was made. The women also made cheese from the kumiss and all the men seemed concerned with was drinking kumiss and tea, eating mutton and playing their pipes. All of them were cheerful and well- fed, and they spent the whole summer idling about. The Bashkirs were very ignorant, knew no Russian, but were kindly people.

The moment they spotted Pakhom, the Bashkirs streamed out of their tents and surrounded their visitor. An interpreter was found and Pakhom told him that he had come about some land. The Bashkirs were delighted and took Pakhom off to one of the finest tents, where they made him sit on some rugs piled with cushions, while they formed a circle and offered him tea and kumiss. Then they slaughtered a sheep and fed him with mutton. Pakhom fetched the presents from his cart, handed them round and shared the tea out. The Bashkirs were delighted. For a while they talked away amongst themselves and then told the interpreter to translate.

‘They want me to tell you,’ the interpreter said, ‘that they’ve taken a great liking to you and that it’s our custom to do all we can to please a guest and repay him for his gifts. You have given us presents, so please tell us if there is anything of ours that you would like so we can show our gratitude.’

‘What I like most of all here,’ Pakhom replied, ‘is your land. Back home there isn’t enough to go round and, what’s more, the soil is exhausted. But here you have plenty and it looks very good. I’ve never seen soil like it.’

The interpreter translated and then the Bashkirs went into a lengthy conference. Although Pakhom did not understand, he could see how cheerful they were, laughing and shouting. Then they all became quiet, glanced at Pakhom and the interpreter continued, ‘I’m to tell you that they would be only too pleased to let you have as much land as you like in return for your kindness. All you have to do is point it out and it will be yours.’

Then they conferred again and started arguing about something. Pakhom asked what it was and the interpreter told him, ‘Some of them are saying they should first consult the elder about the land. They can’t do anything without his permission, but some of the others say it’s not necessary.’

6

While the Bashkirs were arguing, a man in a fox- fur cap suddenly came into the tent, whereupon they all became quiet and stood up.

‘It’s the elder,’ the interpreter explained.

Pakhom immediately fetched his best robe and presented it with five pounds of tea to the elder, who accepted the gifts and then sat in the place of honour. The Bashkirs immediately started telling him something. After listening for a while the elder motioned with his head for them to be quiet and then spoke to Pakhom in Russian.

‘Well now,’ he said. ‘It’s all right. Choose whatever land you like, there’s plenty of it.’

‘How can I just go and take whatever I like?’ Pakhom wondered. ‘I must have it all signed and sealed somehow. Now they tell me it’s mine, but who knows, they might change their minds?’ So he told them, ‘Thank you for your kind words. Yes, you do have a great deal of land, but I need only a little. However, I would like to be sure which will be mine, so couldn’t it be measured and made over to me by some sort of contract? Our lives are in God’s hands and although you good people are willing to give me the land now, it’s possible your children might want it back again.’

‘What you say is true,’ said the elder. ‘We can have a contract drawn up.’

Pakhom said, ‘I’ve heard that you made some land over to a merchant not long ago, together with the title deeds. I would like you to do the same with me.’

The elder understood. ‘That’s no problem,’ he said. ‘We have a clerk here and we can ride into town and have the documents properly witnessed and signed.’

‘But what about the price?’ Pakhom asked.

‘We have a set price – a thousand roubles a day.’

Pakhom did not understand.

‘What kind of rate is that – a day? How many acres would that be?’

‘We don’t reckon your way. We sell by the day. However much you can walk round in one day will be yours. And the price is a thousand roubles a day.’

Pakhom was amazed. ‘Well, a man can walk round a lot of land in one day,’ he said.

The elder burst out laughing. ‘Well, all of it will be yours,’he replied. ‘But there’s one condition: if you don’t return to your starting- point the same day, your money will be forfeited.’

‘But how can I mark where I’ve been?’

‘We’ll all go to whatever place you select and wait until you’ve completed your circuit. You must take a spade, dig a hole at every turning and leave the turf piled up. Afterwards, we will go from hole to hole with a plough. You may make as large a circuit as you like, only you must be back at your starting- point by sunset. All the land you can walk round will be yours.’

Pakhom was absolutely delighted. An early start was decided on and after talking for a while they drank kumiss, ate some mutton and then had tea. This went on until nightfall. Then the Bashkirs made up a feather- bed for Pakhom and left. They promised to be ready to ride out to the chosen spot before sunrise.

7

Pakhom lay down on the feather- bed, but the thought of all that land kept him awake. ‘Tomorrow,’ he thought, ‘I shall mark out a really large stretch. In one day I can easily walk thirty- five miles. The days are long now – just think how much land I’ll have from walking that distance! I’ll sell the poorer bits, or let it to the peasants. I’ll take the best for myself and farm it. I’ll have two ox- ploughs and hire a couple of labourers to work them. Yes, I’ll cultivate about a hundred and fifty acres and let the cattle graze the rest.’

Pakhom did not sleep a wink that night and dozed off only just before dawn. The moment he fell asleep he had a dream: he seemed to be lying in the same tent and could hear someone roaring with laughter outside. Wondering who was laughing like that he got up, went out and saw that same Bashkir elder sitting there, holding his sides and rolling about in fits of laughter. He went closer and asked, ‘What are you laughing at?’ And then he saw that it wasn’t the elder at all, but the merchant who had called on him a few days before and told him about the land. And just as Pakhom asked him, ‘Have you been here long?’ the merchant turned into the peasant who had come up from the Volga and visited him at home. And then Pakhom saw that it wasn’t the peasant, but the Devil himself, with horns and hoofs, sitting there laughing his head off, while before him lay a barefoot man wearing only shirt and trousers. When Pakhom took a closer look he saw that the man was dead and that it was himself. Pakhom woke up in a cold sweat. ‘The things one dreams about!’ he thought. Then he looked round and saw that it was getting light at the open door – dawn was breaking. ‘I must go and wake them,’ he thought, ‘it’s time to start.’ So Pakhom got up, roused the workman, who was sleeping in the cart, ordered him to harness the horse and went off to wake the Bashkirs. ‘It’s time to go out on the steppe and measure the land,’ he said. The Bashkirs got up, assembled, and then the elder came and joined them. They drank some more kumiss and offered Pakhom tea, but he was impatient to be off. ‘If we’re going,’ he said, ‘let’s go. It’s time.’

8

So the Bashkirs got ready and left, some on horses, others in carts. Pakhom went to his little cart with him. They came out on to the open steppe just as the sun was rising. They climbed a small hill (called a ‘shikhan’ in Bashkir). Then the Bashkirs got out of their carts, dismounted from their horses and gathered in one place. The elder went over to Pakhom and pointed.

‘Look,’ he said, ‘that’s all ours, as far as the eye can see. Choose any part you like.’

Pakhom’s eyes lit up, for the land was all virgin soil, flat as the palm of one’s hand, black as poppy- seed, with different kinds of grass growing breast- high in the hollows.

The elder took off his fox- fur cap and put it on the ground.

‘Let this be the marker: this is the starting point to which you must return. All the land you can walk round will be yours.’

Pakhom took out his money, placed it on the cap, took off his outer coat, so that he was wearing only a sleeveless undercoat, tightened his belt below the waist and stuffed a small bag of bread inside his shirt. Then he tied a flask of water to the belt, pulled up his boots, took the spade from his workman and was ready to leave. He could not decide which direction to take at first as the land was so good everywhere. Then he decided, ‘It’s all good land, so I’ll walk towards the sunrise.’ He turned to the east, stretching himself as he waited for the sun to appear above the horizon. ‘There’s no point in wasting time,’ he thought. ‘And it’s easier walking while it’s still cool.’ The moment the sun’s rays came flooding over the horizon Pakhom put the spade on one shoulder and walked out on to the steppe.

Pakhom walked neither quickly nor slowly. When he had gone about three quarters of a mile he stopped, dug a hole and piled the pieces of turf high on top of each other so that they were easily visible. The stiffness had now gone from his legs and he lengthened his stride. A little further on he stopped again and dug another hole.

When Pakhom looked back he could see quite clearly the small hill tyres of the cart- wheels. Pakhom guessed that he had covered about three miles. He was beginning to feel warmer, so he tool off his undercoat, flung it over his shoulder and walked another three miles. It was hot, and a look at the sun reminded him it was time for breakfast.

‘Well, that’s the first stretch completed!’ he thought. ‘But there are four to a day and it’s too early to start turning. I must take these boots off, though.’

So he sat down, took off his boots, stuck them behind his belt and moved on. The going was easy now and he thought.‘I’ll do another three miles and then turn left. The land’s so beautiful here, it would be a pity to miss out on any of it. The further I go, the better the land gets.’ So for a while he carried straight on and when he looked back the hill was barely visible and the people on it looked like black ants; he could just glimpse something that glinted in the sun.

‘Well,’ thought Pakhom, ‘I’ve walked enough in this direction, I should be turning now. Besides, I’m stewing in this heat and terribly thirsty.’ So he stopped, dug a large hole, piled up the turf, untied his flask, drank and then turned sharp left. On and on he walked – the grass was higher here and it was very hot.

Pakhom began to feel tired. He glanced at the sun and saw that it was noon. ‘Well,’ he thought, ‘I must have a little rest.’ So he stopped, sat down and had some bread and water. He did not stretch out, though, thinking, ‘Once I lie down I’ll fall asleep.’ After a few minutes he carried on. At first it was easy – the food had given him strength. But by now it was extremely hot and he began to feel sleepy. Still, he kept going and thought of the proverb, ‘A moment’s pain can be a lifetime’s gain.’

He had walked a long way in the same direction and was just about to turn left when he spotted a lush hollow and decided it would be a pity to lose it. ‘What a good place for growing flax!’ he thought. So he carried straight on until he had walked right round the low- lying meadows, dug a hole the other side, and then he turned the second corner. Pakhom looked back at the hill: it was shimmering in the heat and through the haze it was difficult to see all the people there – they were at least ten miles away. ‘Well,’thought Pakhom, ‘I’ve made those sides too long, this one has to be shorter.’ So he started the third side, quickening his step. He looked at the sun and saw that it was already half way to the horizon, but he had completed only about one mile of the third side. The starting- point was still ten miles away. ‘No,’ he thought, ‘although it will make the land a bit lopsided I must take the shortest way back. It’s no good trying to grab too much, I’ve quite enough already!’

Pakhom hastily dug another hole and headed straight for the hill.

9

On the way back Pakhom found the going tough. The heat had exhausted him, his bare feet were cut and bruised and his legs were giving way. He wanted to rest, but this was out of the question – he would never get back by sunset. The sun waits for no man and was sinking lower and lower. ‘Oh,’ he wondered, ‘have I blundered, trying to take too much? What if I’m not back in time?’ He looked towards the hill, then at the sun. The hill was far off, the sun was close to the horizon.

But Pakhom struggled on. Although it was very hard, he walked faster and faster. On and on he went – but there was still a long way to go. He started running and threw away his coat, boots, flask, cap, keeping only the spade which he used for leaning on. ‘Oh dear,’ he thought, ‘I’ve been too greedy. Now I’ve ruined it. I’ll never get back by sunset.’ His fear made him only more breathless. On he ran, his shirt soaking and his trousers clinging to him: his throat was parched. His lungs were working like a blacksmith’s bellows, his heart beat like a hammer and his legs did not seem to be his – he felt that they were breaking . . . Pakhom was terrified and thought, ‘All this strain will be the death of me.’

Although he feared death, he could not stop. ‘If I stopped now, after coming all this way – well, they’d call me an idiot!’So on he ran until he was close enough to hear the Bashkirs yelling and cheering him on. Their shouts spurred him on all the more, so he summoned his last ounce of strength and kept running. But by now the sun was almost touching the horizon: veiled in mist, it was large and blood- red. It was about to set, but although it did not have very far to sink it was no distance to the starting- point either. Pakhom could see the people on the hill now, waving their arms and urging him on. He could see the fox- fur cap on the ground with the money on it; he could see the elder sitting there with his arms pressed to his sides. And Pakhom remembered his dream.‘I’ve plenty of land now, but will God let me live to enjoy it? No, I’m finished . . . I’ll never make it.’

Pakhom looked at the sun – it had reached the earth now: half of its great disc had dipped below the horizon. With all the strength he had left Pakhom lurched forwards with his full weight, hardly able to move his legs quickly enough to stop himself falling. He reached the hill – and everything suddenly became dark. He looked round and saw that the sun had set. Pakhom groaned. ‘All that effort has been in vain,’ he thought. He wanted to stop, when he heard the Bashkirs still cheering him on and he realized that from where he was at the bottom of the hill the sun had apparently set, but not for those on top. Pakhom took a deep breath and rushed up the hill which was still bathed in sunlight. When he reached the top he saw his cap with the elder sitting by it, holding his sides and laughing his head off. Then he remembered the dream and he groaned. His legs gave way, he fell forward and managed to reach the cap with his hands.

‘Oh, well done!’ exclaimed the elder. ‘That’s a lot of land you’ve earned yourself!’

Pakhom’s workman ran up and tried to lift his master, but the blood flowed from his mouth. Pakhom was dead.

The Bashkirs clicked their tongues sympathetically.

Pakhom’s workman picked up the spade, dug a grave for his master – six feet from head to heel, which was exactly the right length – and buried him.

What Men Live By

We know that we have passed from death unto life, because we love the brethren. He that loveth not his brother abideth in death. (I John iii, 14)

But whoso hath this world’s good, and seeth his brother have need, and shutteth up his bowels of compassion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him? (I John iii, 17)

My little children, let us not love in word, neither in tongue: but in deed and in truth. (I John iii, 18)

. . . for love is of God; and every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God. (I John iv, 7)

He that loveth not knoweth not God; for God is love.(I John iv, 8)

No man hath seen God at any time. If we love one another, God dwelleth in us . . . (I John iv, 12)

God is love; and he that dwelleth in love dwelleth in God, and God in him. (I John iv, 16)

If a man say, I love God, and hateth his brother, he is a liar: for he that loveth not his brother whom he hath seen, how can he love God whom he hath not seen? (I John iv, 20)

1

Once there was a shoemaker who had neither house nor land of his own and who lived in a peasant’s cottage with his wife and children, supporting them by what work he could get. Bread was expensive but his work was cheap and the little he earned was spent on food for his family. He and his wife had only one winter coat between them and even that was in a sorry state. For the past two years he had been saving to buy sheepskins for a new one.

By autumn he had scraped together a small sum: there was the three- rouble note that his wife kept in a little wooden box, as well as the five roubles and twenty copecks that some of the villagers owed him.

One morning he decided to go to the village to buy the skins. He put his wife’s wadded twill jacket over his shirt and over that his own cloth coat. After breakfast he put the three- rouble note in his pocket, cut himself a walking- stick and set off.

‘With the five roubles that one of them owes me,’ he thought, ‘plus the three I already have, I should have enough to buy the sheep skins.’

When he reached the village he stopped at a cottage, but the owner was out. His wife did not have the money, but she promised to send her husband over with it by the end of the week. So he called on another peasant who swore he was short of cash and that all he could manage was twenty copecks that were owing for some boot repairs. And then, when the shoemaker tried to buy the skins on credit, the dealer would not trust him.

‘Bring me the money first,’ he said. ‘Then you can pick whatever skins you like. We all know how hard it is to collect what’s owing to us!’

And so the shoemaker did no business that day, apart from twenty copecks for the repairs and a pair of felt boots that needed soling.

All this depressed the shoemaker and after spending the twenty copecks on vodka he set off for home without any skins. Earlier that morning he had felt a sharp nip in the air, but after a few vodkas he warmed up – even though he had no proper winter coat. As he walked down the road, striking frozen clods of earth with his stick in one hand and swinging the felt boots in the other, he started talking to himself.

‘I feel quite warm without a coat,’ he said. ‘I’ve only had a drop, yet I can feel it rushing through every vein in my body. I don’t need any sheepskins! I’m going home, with all my troubles behind me. That’s the sort of man I am! Why should I worry? I can survive without a new coat – I won’t need one for ages. Only, the wife won’t be too happy. But it’s really rotten when you do a job and the customer tries to string you along and doesn’t pay up. You just wait – if you don’t bring me the money I’ll have the shirt off your back, I swear it! It’s a bit much, what with a measly twenty copecks at a time. What can I do with twenty copecks? Spend it on drink, that’s all. You say you’re hard up. Well, what about me? You’ve a house, cattle, everything, but all I have is on my back. You grow your own corn, while I have to go out and buy mine. Whatever happens I must spend three roubles a week on bread alone. By the time I get home there won’t be any left and I’ll have to fork out another rouble and a half. So, you’d better pay up!’

The shoemaker kept rambling on like this until he drew near the wayside chapel at the bend in the road where something whitish just behind it caught his eye. But by now it was growing dark and although he strained his eyes he could not make out what it was. ‘There wasn’t any stone there before,’ he thought. ‘Perhaps it’s a cow? No, it doesn’t look like one at all. From the head it looks like a man and it’s all white. But what would a man be doing there?’

He went a few steps closer and could now make it out quite clearly. How amazing! It was a man sitting there, but he could not see if he were dead or alive, and he was naked and quite motionless, his back propped against the chapel wall. The shoemaker was terrified and thought, ‘A man’s been murdered, stripped naked and dumped. If I go any nearer I might get mixed up in all sorts of troubles.’

And so the shoemaker went on his way. He walked behind the chapel to avoid having to look at him again. After a short distance he turned round and saw that the man was no longer leaning against the wall, but was moving, as if trying to see who he was. The shoemaker felt even more frightened and thought, ‘Shall I go back or simply carry on? If I go back something terrible might happen. Who knows what kind of man he might be? I bet he’s up to no good. Besides, he might suddenly jump to his feet and start choking the life out of me – and there’d be nothing I could do about it. And if he doesn’t throttle me I might get lumbered with looking after him. But how can I help a naked man? I couldn’t let him have the last shirt off my back. Please God, help me!’

And the shoemaker quickened his stride. He had almost left the chapel behind when his conscience began to prick him. He stopped in the middle of the road.

‘How could you do such a thing, Semyon?’ he reproached himself. ‘That man might be dying miserably and you’re such a coward you’d leave him there to die. Or have you become so rich all of a sudden that you’re scared stiff he might steal all your money? You should be ashamed, Semyon!’

And he turned round again and went right up to the man.

2

After a close look Semyon could see that he was young and healthy. There were no bruises on his body: he was just chilled to the bone and terrified. There he sat, leaning forward without looking at Semyon and apparently too weak to raise his eyes. When Semyon was right next to him he suddenly seemed to wake as if from a trance. He turned his head, opened his eyes and looked straight at Semyon. That one look was enough to allay all Semyon’s fears. He threw down the felt boots, undid his belt, laid it over the boots and took off his cloth coat.

‘There’s no time for talking,’ he said. ‘Put that on – and be quick about it!’

Then Semyon took the man under the arms and tried to lift him, but he got to his feet without any help. And then Semyon saw that his body was slender and clean, that his legs and arms bore no trace of any wounds; his face was mild and gentle. Semyon threw his coat over his shoulders, but the man could not find the sleeves, so Semyon guided his arms into them, pulled on the coat, wrapped it around him and fastened it with his belt.

Then Semyon took off his tattered cap, intending to put it on the naked man’s head, but he felt the cold on his own head and thought, ‘I’m completely bald, while he’s got long, curly hair.’ And he put it back on again. ‘It would be better to give him the boots,’ he thought.

So he made the man sit down again and put the felt boots on his feet, after which he said, ‘There you are, my friend. Stretch your legs a bit and warm yourself. Don’t worry, it will all be sorted out later. Now, can you walk?’

The man stood up, looked tenderly at Semyon, but was unable to say one word.

‘Why don’t you say something? Come on, we can’t spend all winter here, we must be on our way. Here, you can lean on my stick if you feel weak. Right, come on!’

And the man started walking – and he walked effortlessly, without lagging behind.

As they went down the road Semyon asked, ‘Where are you from?’

‘Not from these parts.’

‘I thought so – I know everyone round here. But how did you come to be there, by the chapel?’

‘I cannot tell you that.’

‘Did some men attack you?’

‘No, no one harmed me. It was God who punished me.’

‘Well, we are all in His hands. All the same, you must have somewhere to go. Where are you heading?’

‘Nowhere in particular.’

Semyon was amazed. The man did not strike him as a ruffian, he was so softly spoken, yet he revealed nothing about himself. ‘Anything can happen in this world,’ Semyon reflected and he told the man, ‘All right, come home with me, even if it is a bit out of your way.’

As Semyon walked down the road the stranger did not lag behind for one moment, but kept abreast. The wind got up and the cold air crept under Semyon’s shirt. The drink was beginning to wear off and he felt chilled to the marrow.

Sniffling as he went, he wrapped his wife’s jacket tighter around himself and thought, ‘So much for sheepskins! I go off to buy some and all I do is come home without even the old coat on my back, and with a naked stranger into the bargain! Matryona won’t be too pleased about that!’ And the thought of his wife depressed him. But the moment he looked at the stranger he remembered the look he had given him at the chapel and his heart filled with joy.

3

Semyon’s wife had finished her chores early that day. She had chopped the wood, fetched water, fed the children, had a bite to eat herself and had then sat for a long time wondering when she should bake the bread – that same day or the next. There was still one thick slice left.

‘If Semyon has his dinner in the village,’ she thought,‘then he won’t want much for supper and there’ll be enough bread for tomorrow.’

She turned the slice over, ‘I shan’t do any baking today,’she decided, ‘there’s only enough flour for one loaf. But we can make this last till Friday.’

So Matryona put the bread away and sat down at the table to patch her husband’s shirt. As she worked she thought of him buying the sheepskins for the new winter coat.

‘I hope the dealer won’t swindle him. He’s so simple, that husband of mine. He’d never cheat a soul himself and even a little child could trick him. Eight roubles is a lot of money, enough to buy very good sheepskins. Not the best quality tanned ones perhaps, but still good enough for a nice coat. Last winter was so hard without a proper one! I couldn’t even go down to the river, couldn’t go anywhere. And when he left this morning he took all the warm clothes we have, leaving me with nothing to wear. Now, he didn’t leave all that early. All the same, it’s time he was back. I hope my old man hasn’t gone drinking!’

These thoughts had just crossed Matryona’s mind when the front steps creaked and someone came in. Matryona stuck her needle into the shirt and went out into the hall. There she saw two men – Semyon and someone in felt boots and without a cap.

Matryona immediately smelt the vodka on her husband’s breath. ‘So, I was right, he’s been on the drink,’ she thought. And when she saw him standing there, empty- handed and with a guilty grin on his face, wearing nothing but the jacket she had lent him, her heart sank. ‘He’s gone and spent all that money drinking with some good- for- nothing. What’s more, he’s got the nerve to bring him home.’

Matryona ushered them in and followed them into the living- room. Now she could see that the stranger was a thin young man and that he was wearing her husband’s coat. She could see no shirt under it and he had no cap. Once inside he stood quite still and kept looking down. Matryona concluded that he was a bad lot, as he seemed so nervous.

Frowning, she went over to the stove and waited to see what they would do next.

Semyon took off his cap and sat down on the bench as if he had done no wrong.

‘Come on, Matryona, let’s have some supper!’ he said.

Matryona muttered something to herself and stayed quite still by the stove. She kept looking first at one, then the other, shaking her head. Semyon realized that his wife was annoyed, but there was nothing he could do about it. Pretending not to notice, he took the stranger by the arm.

‘Sit down,’ he said. ‘Let’s have something to eat.’

The stranger sat on the bench.

‘Well, don’t you have anything?’

Matryona lost her temper. ‘Yes, I do, but not for you. It seems you’ve drunk your brains away. You went out to buy some sheepskins and back you come without even the coat you left in. What’s more, you bring some half- naked tramp back with you. I don’t have any supper for a pair of drunkards like you!’

‘Now that’s enough of your stupid tongue- wagging, Matryona! You might at least ask who he is.’

‘And you can tell me what you did with the money.’

Semyon felt in his pocket, took out the three- rouble note and unfolded it.

‘Here it is. Trifonov wouldn’t give me any money, but he promised to pay up in a day or so.’

Matryona grew even more furious: in addition to not buying the sheepskins, her husband had lent their only coat to some naked stranger. What’s more, he’d brought him back home.

She snatched the note from the table and went off to hide it somewhere.

‘I’ve no supper for you,’ she told them. ‘You can’t expect me to feed every naked drunkard.’

‘And you mind your tongue, Matryona. First hear what he has to say . . .’

‘What sense will I get from a drunken fool like him? I was right in not wanting to marry an old soak like you! You sold all Mother’s linen for drink. And then, instead of buying sheepskins you spend the money on drink.’

Semyon tried hard to make his wife understand that all he had spent on drink was a mere twenty copecks and to explain where he had found the stranger. But she would not let him get a word in edgeways, rattling away nineteen to the dozen and even reminding him of things that had happened ten years ago. On and on she went, until finally she dashed over to Semyon and grabbed his sleeve.

‘Give me my jacket back, it’s the only one I have and you took it to wear yourself. Give it back, you flea- bitten dog. May you die of a fit!’

Semyon began taking the jacket off and turned a sleeve inside- out, but his wife tugged so hard that it came apart at the seams. Then she seized it, threw it over her head and made for the door. But then she stopped. Her heart seemed to melt and she felt that she wanted to banish all those spiteful feelings and to find out who that man really was.

4

As she stood there, quite still, Matryona said, ‘If he were an honest man he wouldn’t be going around without a shirt to his back. And if you’d been doing what you were supposed to you’d have told me where you picked up this fine young fellow!’

‘All right, I’ll tell you. I was on my way home when I saw this man sitting by the chapel, naked and frozen. Now, it’s not the kind of weather to go about naked! God must have led me to him, or he’d have perished. What could I do? Who knows what may have happened to him? So, I made him stand up, clothed him and brought him back here. Please don’t be angry, Matryona, it’s sinful. Don’t forget that we must all die one day.’

Matryona was about to give him a piece of her mind again, but then she looked at the stranger and became silent. There he sat, motionless, on the edge of the bench, his hands folded on his knees, his head drooping on his breast. His eyes were closed and he wrinkled his face as if something were choking him. Matryona still said nothing, but Semyon asked, ‘Matryona, is there no love of God within you?’

At these words Matryona glanced at the stranger and her heart suddenly filled with pity. She came back from the door, went over to the stove, took out the supper, placed a cup on the table, poured out some kvass, brought out the last slice of bread and set out a knife and some spoons. Please eat,’she said.

Semyon nudged the stranger and told him, ‘Come and sit at the table.’

Semyon divided the bread into small pieces and they started eating. Matryona sat at one corner of the table, her head on her hand, gazing at the stranger. And she was filled with pity and her heart went out to him. Suddenly, his face brightened, the wrinkles disappeared and he looked up at Matryona and smiled.

After supper Matryona cleared the table and began questioning him.

‘Where are you from?’

‘Not from these parts.’

‘How did you come to be by the wayside?’

‘I cannot tell you.’

‘Who stole your clothes?’

‘God punished me.’

‘And you were lying there, all naked?’

‘Yes, naked and freezing. And then Semyon saw me and took pity on me. He took off his coat, put it over me and insisted I came home with him. You have given me food and drink and shown compassion. God will reward you!’

Matryona got up, took from the window- sill the old shirt of Semyon’s she had been patching and handed it to the stranger. Then she found him some trousers.

‘Here, I see you’ve no shirt, so put this on and lie down where you like – up on the sleeping- bench or over the stove.’

The stranger took off the coat, put on the shirt and trousers and lay on the sleeping- bench. Matryona blew out the candle, took the coat and joined her husband over the stove.

Matryona drew the skirts of the coat over herself and lay down. But she did not fall asleep, for she could not get that stranger out of her mind.

When she remembered that he had eaten their last slice of bread and that they would have none for tomorrow, and that she had given him the shirt and trousers, she became terribly dejected. But then, when she recalled his smile her heart leapt up. For a long time she lay awake and she noticed that Semyon was awake too, as he kept pulling the coat up.

‘Semyon!’

‘What is it?’

‘You two have eaten the last slice of bread and I haven’t prepared any more. I don’t know what we’re going to do tomorrow. Perhaps I can borrow some from our neighbour Malanya.’

‘Yes, we’ll get by, we won’t starve.’

Matryona lay silently for a while and then she said, ‘He seems to be a good man, only he doesn’t tell us anything about himself.’

‘I suppose he can’t.’

‘Semyon!’

‘What?’

‘We’re always giving, but why does nobody ever give us anything?’

Semyon didn’t know what to reply. All he said was, ‘Let’s talk about that another time,’ after which he turned over and went to sleep.

5

Next morning, when Semyon woke up, the children were still asleep and his wife had gone over to the neighbour’s to borrow some bread. Only the stranger was sitting on the bench, wearing the old trousers and shirt and looking up. His face was brighter than the evening before. Semyon said, ‘Well, my friend. The belly needs food and the body clothes. We all have to earn a living, so what sort of work can you do?’

‘I can’t do anything.’

Semyon was amazed and replied, ‘If a man has the will he can learn anything.’

‘Yes, men work for their living, so I’ll work too.’

‘What’s your name?’

‘Mikhail.’

‘Well, Mikhail, if you don’t want to tell us about yourself that’s your affair. But we have to earn our living. If you do as I tell you I’ll see you have enough to eat.’

‘God bless you! I’ll learn how to work, just tell me what to do.’

Semyon took a piece of yarn, wound it round his fingers and twisted it.

‘It’s not hard, just watch . . .’

Mikhail watched and right away he caught the knack, winding the yarn and twisting it just like Semyon.

Then Semyon showed him how to wax it and Mikhail understood at once. Then he showed him how to draw it through and how to stitch. Again Mikhail immediately understood.

Whatever Semyon showed him he mastered right away and within three days was working as if he had been making shoes all his life. He would work without any let- up and ate very little. Only when one job was finished would he stop for a moment and silently look up. He never went out, only spoke when he really had to, and he never joked or laughed.

And in fact the only time they had seen him smile was on that very first evening, when Matryona had given him supper.

6

The days passed, weeks passed, and a year ran its course. Mikhail was still living with Semyon and working for him. The word got round that Semyon’s new workman could make boots better and stronger than anyone else. People from all over the district came to Semyon for new boots and he prospered.

One winter’s day Semyon and Mikhail were sitting at their work when a three- horse carriage on sleigh runners drove up to the cottage, its bells gaily ringing. When they looked out of the window they saw it had stopped right outside. A boy jumped down from the box and opened the carriage door. A gentleman in a fur coat stepped out, walked up to the front door and climbed the steps. Matryona rushed to fling open the door.

As he came in, the gentleman had to lower his head and then straighten up. But still his head almost touched the ceiling and he filled a whole corner of the room.

Semyon stood up and marvelled at the gentleman: he had never seen anyone like him. Semyon himself was lean, Mikhail was skinny, while Matryona was as thin as a rake. But this visitor seemed like someone from another world: with his full red face and his bull’s neck he seemed to be made of cast iron.

He puffed, took off his fur coat, sat on the bench and asked, ‘Who is the master bootmaker here?’

Semyon stepped forward and said, ‘I am, Your Honour.’

Then the gentleman shouted to his boy, ‘Hey, Fedka, bring the leather!’

The boy ran in with a parcel, which the gentleman took and placed on the table.

‘Untie it,’ he said. The boy untied it.

Then the gentleman pointed at the leather and told Semyon, ‘Now, listen to me, bootmaker. Do you see that leather?’

‘Yes, I do, Your Honour.’

‘Do you know what kind it is?’

Semyon felt it and said, ‘It’s very good quality.’

‘I should say it’s good quality! You fool, I bet you’ve never set eyes on leather like that. It’s German and I paid twenty roubles for it.’

Semyon quailed and said, ‘Now where would I see leather like that?’

‘Yes, where indeed! Could you make me a pair of boots out of it?’

‘It’s possible, Your Honour.’

‘I’ll give you possible!’ the gentleman shouted. ‘Now, see you don’t forget for whom you’re making them and the quality of the leather you’ll be using. I want a pair of boots that will last me a year without losing their shape or coming apart at the stitches. If you can do the job, take the leather and cut it up. But if you can’t, you’d better tell me here and now. I’m warning you: if the boots split or lose their shape before the year’s out I’ll have you clapped in prison. But if they keep their shape and don’t split for a year I’ll pay you ten roubles.’

Semyon was quite afraid and did not know what to reply. He glanced at Mikhail, nudged him with his elbow and whispered, ‘Well, shall I take it on?’

Mikhail nodded as if to say, ‘Yes, take it on.’

So Semyon followed Mikhail’s advice and undertook to make a pair of boots that would not lose their shape or split for a whole year.

Then the gentleman called the boy over to take off his left boot for him and stretched out his leg.

‘Take my measurements!’

Semyon sewed together a strip of paper about seventeen inches long, smoothed it out, knelt down, wiped his hands thoroughly on his apron so as not to dirty the gentleman’s sock and started measuring. He took the sole and instep measurements. But when he tried to measure the calf he found that the strip of paper was not long enough – the gentleman’s calf was as thick as a log.

‘Mind you don’t make them too tight in the leg,’ he said.

Semyon sewed another piece to the strip of paper, while the gentleman sat wriggling his toes in his sock and surveying the people in the room. And then he noticed Mikhail.

‘Who’s that over there?’ he asked.

‘He’s my master craftsman, he’ll be making the boots.’

‘Now you watch out,’ the gentleman said, ‘remember they have to last a whole year.’

When Semyon turned towards Mikhail he saw that he was not even looking at the gentleman, but staring into the corner, as if someone was standing behind him. Mikhail kept staring until suddenly he smiled and his whole face lit up.

‘What are you grinning at, idiot?’ the gentleman asked.‘You’d better see to it that the boots are ready on time!’

‘They’ll be ready whenever you want them,’ Mikhail replied.

‘Good.’

The gentleman put on his boots again, then his fur coat, which he wrapped tightly around him, and went to the door. But he forgot to lower his head and banged it against the lintel. He cursed and rubbed it. Then he climbed into the carriage and drove off.

As soon as he had gone Semyon remarked, ‘He’s as tough as nails! You couldn’t kill him with a mallet. Why, he nearly knocked the lintel out and still he hardly felt a thing!’

‘You’d expect him to be strong with the kind of life he leads,’ Matryona said. ‘Death itself couldn’t touch that iron girder!’

7

‘Well, we’ve taken on the work now,’ Semyon told Mikhail,‘and I only hope it doesn’t land us in trouble. The leather’s very expensive and the gentleman’s short- tempered, so we’d better not slip up. Your eyes are sharper than mine and your hands are more skilled, so take the measure and start cutting the leather. I’ll sew the vamps later.’

Mikhail obediently took the leather, spread it on the table, folded it in two, took a knife and started cutting.

Matryona went over to watch Mikhail working and was amazed to see what he was doing. Naturally she knew all about boot- making and could see that instead of cutting the leather into the normal shape for boots Mikhail was cutting it into round pieces.

Matryona felt she should point it out, but then she thought, ‘Maybe I don’t understand how a gentleman’s boots should be made. Maybe Mikhail knows best, so I won’t interfere.’

When he had finished cutting Mikhail took some thread and started sewing the pieces together – not with two ends, as he should have done for boots, but with one end, as if for slippers.

Although Matryona was astonished by this as well, she did not interfere and Mikhail carried on sewing until midday.

When Semyon got up and saw that Mikhail had made a pair of slippers from the gentleman’s leather he groaned.

‘I don’t understand,’ he thought, ‘how Mikhail, who’s been with me for a whole year without making one mistake, should now go and make such a dreadful mess of things. The gentleman ordered welted high boots and he’s made slippers without soles and ruined the leather. How can I face the gentleman now? I can’t replace leather of that quality.’

And he told Mikhail, ‘What on earth have you done, my friend? You’ve ruined me! The gentleman ordered high boots and just look what you’ve made!’

And he was just about to give Mikhail a stern lecture when someone knocked hard on the front door with the iron ring. They looked out of the window and saw that someone had ridden up and was tethering his horse. When the door was opened in came the same young boy who had accompanied the gentleman.

‘Good afternoon to you!’

‘Good afternoon. What can we do for you?’

‘The mistress sent me about those boots.’

‘What about them?’

‘Just this: the master won’t be needing them. He’s dead.’

‘What did you say?’

‘He died in the carriage even before we got home. When we reached the house the others came to help him out, but there he lay, slumped like a sack of potatoes. He was already stiff, stone- dead, and we had a real struggle getting him out. So the mistress told me to come back here. “Tell that shoemaker,” she said, “that the gentleman who called and ordered some boots and left the leather won’t be needing them and that instead he must make a pair of soft corpse- slippers as soon as he can.” She told me to wait until they’re ready. So here I am.’

Mikhail collected the offcuts from the table and rolled them up. Then he took the soft slippers he had already made, slapped them together, wiped them with his apron and handed them to the boy, who took them.

‘Goodbye, masters! Good luck to you!’ he said as he left.

8

Another year passed, then another, until Mikhail was in his sixth year with Semyon. He lived just as before, never going out, speaking only when he had to. And all that time he smiled only twice – when the old woman had first given him supper and then when the rich gentleman called. Semyon thought the world of his workman and no longer inquired where he was from. His only fear was that Mikhail might leave him.

One day they were all at home and Matryona was putting iron pots into the oven, while the children were scampering along the benches and looking out of the windows. Semyon was stitching at one window, while Mikhail was heeling a boot at the other.

One of the little boys ran along the bench to Mikhail, leant on his shoulder and looked through the window.

‘Look, Uncle Mikhail! There’s a lady with two little girls. I think she’s coming here. One of the girls is limping.’

When the boy said this, Mikhail put down his work, turned to the window and looked out into the street.

Semyon was amazed: Mikhail had never looked out into the street before, but now he was glued to the window and staring at something. Semyon, too, looked out and saw that a well- dressed woman with two little girls in fur coats and thick woollen shawls were in fact coming towards the cottage. The girls were so alike it would have been impossible to tell them apart were it not that one had a crippled left leg and walked with a limp.

The woman climbed the steps, fumbled for the latch and opened the door. She let the little girls in first and then followed them.

‘Good day, everyone!’ she said.

‘Welcome! What can we do for you?’

The woman sat at the table while the girls, feeling shy with all those people in the room, snuggled against her knees.

‘I’d like some leather shoes for the girls, for the spring,’she said.

‘That’s no problem. Although we’ve never made such small ones before we can do them – either welted or lined with linen. This is Mikhail, my master shoemaker.’

Semyon turned to Mikhail and saw that he had stopped working and was sitting there with his eyes fixed on the little girls.

Semyon was quite surprised. True, the girls were very pretty – plump, with black eyes and rosy little cheeks – and wore fine fur coats and shawls. Still, he could not understand why Mikhail should be staring like that, as if he knew them.

Semyon kept wondering and then started discussing the price with the woman. This was finally agreed and Semyon took his measure. The woman lifted the lame girl on to one knee and said, ‘Measure her twice and make one shoe for her lame foot and three for the sound one: they take exactly the same size, because they’re twins.’

Semyon took the measurements and inquired about the little lame girl.

‘What happened? Such a pretty little girl. Was she born like that?’

‘No, she was crushed by her mother.’

Just then Matryona joined in. She was wondering who the woman was and whose children they were.

‘You’re their mother, aren’t you?’

‘No, dear woman, I’m not their mother, nor am I a relative. They were complete strangers and I adopted them.’

‘They’re not your own and yet you seem so fond of them!’

‘How can I help being fond of them? I breast- fed them both. I did have a child of my own once, but it pleased God to take him. I didn’t love him as much as these little girls, though.’

‘So whose are they?’

9

And the woman proceeded to tell them the whole story.

‘It all started about six years ago, when these little girls lost their father and mother the same week – the father was buried on the Tuesday and the mother died on the Friday. So, for three days they had no father and on the fourth they lost their mother. At that time my husband and I were farm- workers and our yard was right next door. The father was a lone wolf and worked as a woodcutter. One day when they were cutting down some trees they let one fall right on him and it crushed his insides. They had hardly got him back to the village when his soul went up to heaven and the same week his widow gave birth to twins – these little girls. She was a poor woman, all on her own, with no other women, young or old, to help her. Alone she gave birth and alone she died.

‘The next morning I went to see how she was, but the poor thing was already stiff and cold. When she died she’d rolled over on to this little girl and twisted her leg out of shape. Then the villagers came, washed the body and laid it out. Then they made a coffin and buried her. Good folk they were. So the two little girls were left alone in the world, and who was going to look after them? I happened to be the only woman in that village who’d had a baby at the time and I’d been breast- feeding my first- born for about eight weeks. So I took care of the girls for the time being. The men thought hard about what to do with the orphans and in the end they told me, “You’d better look after them for now, Marya, until we manage to sort something out.” So I breast- fed the girl who hadn’t been harmed, but not the one who’d been crippled, as I didn’t expect her to live. And then I thought to myself, “Why should that little angel be left to fade away?”I took pity on her too and started feeding her, so that in the end I was feeding all three of them – my own first- born and these two, at my own breasts! I was young, strong and well- nourished and God gave me so much milk that it filled my breasts to overflowing. Sometimes I’d feed two at a time, with the third waiting, and when one had had its fill, I’d put the third to my breast. But it was God’s will that I should nurse these little girls and bury my own child before he was two years old. And God never gave me another one. But after that I became quite well off. My second husband’s working for a corn merchant and we live at the mill. He earns good money and we live well. But as we’ve no children of our own I’d be terribly lonely without these two little girls. How can I help loving them? They are the apple of my eye!’

The woman pressed the lame girl to her with one hand and wiped the tears from her cheeks with the other.

Matryona sighed. ‘There’s a lot of truth in the saying “You can live without mother or father, but you can’t live without God.” ’

They chatted together for a while and then the woman got up to leave. Semyon and his wife saw them out and then they looked at Mikhail: he was sitting there, his arms folded on his knees, and he was looking up and smiling.

10

Semyon went over to Mikhail and asked, ‘What is it?’

Mikhail rose from the bench, put down his work, took off his apron, bowed to Semyon and Matryona and said, ‘Please forgive me, you good people. God has forgiven me, so please forgive me too.’

And the shoemaker and his wife saw a light shining from Mikhail. And Semyon stood up, bowed in turn and said, ‘I can see you are no ordinary mortal and I cannot detain you any longer or question you. But please tell me one thing: why were you so miserable when I first found you and brought you home? And why, when my wife gave you supper, did you smile and from that time onwards brighten up? And why, when that rich gentleman ordered those boots, did you smile again and become even more cheerful? And why, when that woman brought those little girls here just now, did you smile a third time and become the very picture of joy? Please tell me, Mikhail. What is that light coming from you and why did you smile three times?’

‘The light is radiating from me,’ Mikhail replied, ‘because I had been punished, but now God has forgiven me. And I smiled three times because I was commanded to discover three truths and I have discovered them. I discovered the first truth when your wife took pity on me – that is why I smiled for the first time. The second truth I discovered when that rich gentleman ordered the boots – and then I smiled again. And just now, when I saw those two little girls, I discovered the last of the three truths – and I smiled for the third time.’

‘Tell me, Mikhail,’ Semyon asked, ‘why did God punish you and what are those three truths, so that I too may know them?’

Mikhail replied, ‘God punished me because I disobeyed Him. I was an angel of the Lord and I disobeyed Him. Yes, I was an angel in heaven and the Lord sent me down to earth to take a woman’s soul. I flew down and saw the woman lying there. She was sick, all alone and had just given birth to twins, two little girls. There they were, crawling around their mother, but she was unable to put them to her breasts. When she saw me she understood that God had sent me to take her soul. She burst into tears and said, “Angel of the Lord! My husband has just been buried, killed by a falling tree. I have no sister, no aunt, no grandmother – no one to bring up my little orphans. So please don’t take my soul, let me suckle my babies, bring them up and set them on their feet. Children cannot live without father or mother!” And I did what she asked, pressed one little girl to her breast, put the other in her arms and ascended to heaven. I flew to God and told Him, “I could not bring myself to take the soul of a woman who had just borne twins. The father was killed by a falling tree and the mother had just given birth and begged me not to take her soul. ‘Let me suckle my children, bring them up and set them on their feet. Children cannot live without a father or mother,’ she pleaded. So I did not take that woman’s soul.” And then God said, “If you go down to earth and take that woman’s soul you will discover three truths: you will learn what dwells in man, what is not given to man and what men live by. When you have learnt these truths you shall return to heaven.” So I flew down to earth again and took the mother’s soul. The babies dropped from her breasts and her body rolled over on to one of them, crushing its leg. Then I rose above the village, wishing to return her soul to God, but I was seized by a strong wind and my wings drooped and fell off. And so the soul alone returned to God and I fell to earth, by the roadside.’

11

And now Semyon and Matryona realized whom they had been clothing and feeding and had taken in to live with them. And they both wept for joy and fear. And the angel said, ‘I was alone and naked in that field. Never before had I known the needs of man, never had I known cold or hunger. But now I was an ordinary mortal, cold and hungry and not knowing what to do. And then I saw a chapel in the field, built for the glory of God. So I went to it to seek shelter. But it was locked and I could not enter. So I sat down behind it to shelter from the wind. Evening came and I was famished, freezing and in pain. Suddenly I heard a man coming down the road. He was carrying a pair of boots and talking to himself. For the first time since I became a man I saw the mortal face of man. It terrified me and I turned away. And I could hear this man wondering how to protect his body from the winter cold and feed his wife and children. And I thought, “I am perishing with cold and hunger, but here is someone whose only thought is how to find a warm coat for himself and his wife, and food for his family. I cannot expect any help from him.” When the man saw me he frowned, looking even more terrifying, and he passed me by. I was desperate. But suddenly I heard him coming back. As I looked he no longer seemed the same man. Before, his face had borne the stamp of death, but now he had suddenly become alive again and in that face I could see God. He came up to me, clothed me and took me to his home. When we arrived a woman came out to meet us and she spoke. This woman was even more terrifying than the man. Her breath seemed to come from the grave and I was almost choked by that deathly stench. She wished to cast me out into the cold and I knew that if she did that she would die. Then suddenly her husband told her to think of God and at once she was transformed. When she had given us supper I returned the look she gave me and saw that death no longer dwelt in her, but life. And in her too I could see God.

‘And I recalled God’s first lesson: thou shalt learn what dwelleth in man. And now I knew that it is Love that dwells in man. I was overjoyed that God had begun to reveal what He had promised to reveal, and I smiled for the first time. But I did not know the whole truth yet. I did not yet know what is not given to man and what men live by.

‘And so I came to live with you and one year passed. One day a rich gentleman came to order a pair of boots that would last a year without splitting or losing their shape. When I looked at him I suddenly saw my comrade, the Angel of Death, standing behind him. No one but I could see that angel. And I knew that he would take the gentleman’s soul before sunset. And I thought, “Here is a man who wants to provide for himself for a year from now but does not know that by evening he will be dead.’ And so I remembered God’s second lesson: thou shalt learn what is not given to man.

‘What dwells in man I already knew. Now I knew that which is not given to man: it is not given to him to know his bodily needs. And I smiled for the second time. I rejoiced that I had seen my fellow angel and that God had revealed His second truth.

‘But still I did not know everything. I did not understand what it is that men live by. And so I lived on, waiting for God to reveal this last truth to me. In my sixth year that woman came here with the two little girls. I recognized the girls and learnt how they had stayed alive. After this discovery I thought, “The mother pleaded with me for her children’s sake and I believed what she said, thinking that children cannot live without father or mother. But the other woman had nursed them and brought them up.” And when I saw how much love this woman had for the children and how she wept over them I saw the living God in her and understood what men live by. And I realized that God had revealed His last lesson and had forgiven me. So I smiled for the third time.’

12

And the angel’s body was bared and it was robed in light, so that the eye could not look upon it. And the angel’s voice grew louder, as though it came not from him, but from heaven itself. And the angel said, ‘I have learned that men live not by selfishness, but by love.

‘It was not given to the mother to know what her children needed for their lives. Nor was it given to the rich man to know what his true needs were. Nor is it given to any man to know, before the sun has set, whether he will need boots for his living body or slippers for his corpse. When I became a mortal I survived not by thinking of myself, but through the love that dwelt in a passer- by and his wife, and the compassion and love they showed me. The two orphans’ lives were preserved, not by what others may have intended for them, but by the love that dwelt in the heart of a woman, a complete stranger, and by the love and compassion she showed them. Indeed, all men live not by what they may intend for their own well- being, but by the love that dwells in others.

‘Previously I had known that God gave life to men and desired that they should live. But then I came to know something else.

‘I came to understand that God does not wish men to live apart and that is why He does not reveal to each man what he needs for himself alone. On the contrary, He wishes men to live in peace and harmony with each other and for this reason He has revealed to each and every one of them what all men need, as well as themselves.

‘And I understood that men only think that they live by caring only about themselves: in reality they live by love alone. He who dwells in love dwells in God, and God in him, for God is love.’

And the angel sang the Lord’s praises and the hut shook with the sound of his voice. And the roof parted and a pillar of fire rose from earth to heaven. Semyon and his wife and children prostrated themselves; the angel’s wings unfurled and he soared into the sky.

When Semyon came to his senses the hut was just as it had always been and there was no one there but him and his family.

一

欧班夫人的女仆费莉西泰，让蓬莱韦克那些好太太羡慕了整整半个世纪。

她一年的工钱也就一百法郎，却包揽了所有下厨房的事和家务活。她缝补，清洗，熨烫衣裳；套马，喂养家禽，炼制奶油。不仅如此，她对女主人也一直忠心耿耿，而我们得说，那女主人可不好相处。

欧班夫人嫁给了一位英俊而贫穷的年轻人。一八〇九年初，他过世了，留下她和两个年幼的孩子，以及一笔数额可观的债务。她只好变卖家产，仅留下图克和热福塞两处的农庄。这两处农庄一年能提供给她的租金收入，最多不过五千法郎。为了维持生计，她只好搬出圣梅兰的住宅，住进一栋相对便宜的房子。那房子本是她家族的，坐落在集市后面。

这栋房子有着石板瓦屋顶，在一条小巷和一条通往河边的窄街之间。房子里，地面高低不平，走在上面很容易被绊倒。一条狭窄的过道隔开了厨房与起居室。欧班夫人整日待在起居室，坐在平开窗前一张柳条编的扶手椅上。一排八张红木椅靠着白漆护壁板。晴雨表挂在墙上，下方是架古旧的钢琴。各种小包裹、纸板箱在钢琴上堆得高高的，像一座金字塔。两张铺着挂毯的简易椅，分别放置在路易十五风格的黄色大理石壁炉旁。一只钟，挂在壁炉上方的中央，设计得像座维斯塔神庙。整个房间散发着霉味，那是因为地面比花园低的缘故。

二楼，有一间“夫人”的卧室。那是一个很大的房间，装饰着暗淡的、带有花纹的墙纸。墙上挂着幅“老爷”的画像，他穿着在那时很时髦的奇特服装。卧室径直通往一个更小的房间，里面放着两张孩子的床，每张床的垫子都被移走了。再过去便是客厅，常年关闭，堆满了蒙着布罩的家具。最后，有一个过道通向书房。堆着书和纸的书橱，占据了三面墙，将一个很大的乌木书桌包围其中。书橱的侧板上贴满了素描画、水粉风景画，以及奥德朗的版画，让人想起已然逝去的美好时日，以及更奢华的品位。三楼是费莉西泰的卧室，被天窗所照亮。窗外，可以见到牧场。

费莉西泰总在天蒙蒙亮时起床，以确保能赶上弥撒。之后，她便一口气也不歇地劳作到晚上。晚餐结束后，她收拾好陶盘，紧实地闩上门，用灰烬埋了柴火，便手拿念珠，在壁炉前睡去了。在讨价还价时，没人能比她更固执。而论干净，她洗刷的平底小圆锅，足以让蓬莱韦克别家的女仆绝望。她从不浪费，吃得很慢，还会用手指把掉在桌上的面包屑沾干净。那面包是专为她烤的，足有十二磅，能让她吃上二十天。

无论遇上什么天气，她都披一条印花方头巾，用别针扣在后面，戴一顶完全盖住头发的女帽，穿一双灰色长筒袜、一条红色裙子，再在上衣外面罩着背带围裙，像医院护士穿的那样。

她的脸是瘦削的，声音是尖锐的。二十五岁时，人们以为她有四十岁。而在她五十岁生日过后，倒让人越发难以看出她的年纪了。她不怎么说话，身板挺直，步调僵硬，就像一位被发条驱使的、木头做的女人。

二

和别的女孩一样，她也曾恋爱过。

她的父亲是个石匠，从脚手架上跌下来摔死了。随后，母亲过世，姐姐们也各自谋生去了。一个农民收留了她。尽管她还很小，仍被派去牧场看顾牛群。她总是衣不遮体，冷得直哆嗦；趴在地上喝池塘里的水。她经常毫无缘由地挨打，最后被赶出了房子，说是她偷了三十苏[1]，但她其实是无辜的。后来，她在别的农场找了份工作，饲养家禽。雇主喜爱她，却招来了朋友们的妒忌。

八月的一个晚上（那时她十八岁），她被拉去参加科勒维尔的乡村游园会。喧闹的提琴声、树上的彩灯、一件件绚丽多彩的衣裳、金色的十字架和丝带，以及那些随音乐跳动的人，一时间让她茫然不知所措。她独自站在一旁，怯生生的。一个看起来很有钱的年轻人，靠在农场马车的车轴上抽着烟斗。他走来，邀请她跳舞。他为她买了一杯苹果汁、一杯咖啡、一个蛋糕和一条丝绸围巾。他想着她已领会了他的意思，便提议送她回家。走到燕麦田边时，他将她推倒在地。她害怕地尖叫起来。他跑了。

不久后的一个晚上，她在前往博蒙特的路上遇到一辆大车。车子载着干草，缓慢笨拙地前行着。她想超过它。在挨着车轮走过去的时候，她认出车上的人是泰奥多尔。

他面无愧色地看着她，说她理应原谅他那晚的行为，毕竟他“那晚只是喝多了”。

她不知该如何作答，只想逃走。

于是，他转换话题，谈起了当年的收成，以及这个地区的各大人物。他说，他父亲已离开科勒维尔，在艾科特买了处农庄，也就是说，他们现在是邻居了。她回应说：“哦，这样啊！”他说，他父母希望他安定下来，但他不着急，更愿意在结婚前遇见那个对的女人。她听了，垂下双眼。他问，她是否正考虑结婚的事情。她笑了，说他那样取笑她可不好。“但我发誓，我不是在取笑你。”他说着，伸出左手，搂住了她的腰。她就这样让他搂着，继续往前走。现在，他们走得更慢了。微风徐徐，星辰闪耀。在他们面前，大马车上的干草来回晃动。四匹马艰难地踱步向前，起了片片尘土。未经任何指令，马儿向右转了。这时，他吻了吻她，而她在夜色里逃开了。

接下来的那周，泰奥多尔约她出来了几次。

他们在农家院子的角落里碰面，躲在墙后或一棵树下。费莉西泰并不像同龄的年轻姑娘那般懵懂无知。和农场牲口打交道，让她学会了很多。然而，她与生俱来的慎重，以及保持贞洁的本能，使她避免了屈从泰奥多尔的欲求。她这般推阻，让泰奥多尔很是泄气。为了满足欲望（或者，也可能是出于单纯的想法），他开始向她求婚。她不知道是否该相信他，而他则坚持说自己是认真的。

不久，他说起一件烦心的事：一年前，他父母花钱让人代他服兵役，但他仍有可能随时被征召。一想起有这种可能，他就害怕。费莉西泰将这种怯懦看成是爱的讯息，这让她更爱他了。夜里，她从房子里溜出来去见泰奥多尔，而他则用忧惧和哀求，向她发起进攻。

最终，他说他要亲自去市政府查探情况。他会在下个星期天的十一点至午夜间回来，告诉费莉西泰结果。

到了约定的时间，费莉西泰去见她的情人。

但她见到的并不是泰奥多尔，而是他的一个朋友。

他告诉她，她再也不会见到泰奥多尔了。为了确保不被征召入伍，他娶了图克一个有钱的老女人，勒胡塞太太。

费莉西泰很悲伤。她扑倒在地，号啕痛哭；她祈求上天的帮助，独自一人躺在田野里，哭到天亮。然后，她回到农场，说她决定要离开了。到了月底，她领了工钱，将几样东西用披巾包好，便前往蓬莱韦克了。

她来到一家客栈前，向一个戴寡妇帽的女人打听。正好她也在找一个厨子。这位年轻的姑娘对烹饪所知不多，但似乎很乐意学习，而且随时准备帮忙，于是欧班夫人最后说：“那好吧，就你了。”

一刻钟后，费莉西泰就在她家安置下来。

起初，她时常感到不安，因为这家人规矩很多，而对“老爷”的怀念似乎徘徊在所有事物之上。维尔吉妮和保罗，一个七岁，一个只有四岁，都像是某种珍贵的材料做的。她喜欢像马似的驮着他们，只在欧班夫人不许她老是亲吻他们时，才会让她觉得受了委屈。即使如此，她仍很快乐。新的环境很舒适，她早先的不愉快很快就消散了。

每逢周四，欧班夫人的朋友会来玩波士顿牌。费莉西泰事先备好了纸牌和暖脚炉。客人们总是八点准时到，十一点钟声响起时离开。

每周一早上，在小巷尽头有家店面的旧货商，会在人行道上摆出各种零碎的五金器件。整个城镇充满了嘈杂的声响，有马嘶、羊叫、猪哼，以及马车驶过街面的咔嗒声。正午左右，也就是集市最繁忙的时候，一个老农会跨上台阶，前来拜访欧班夫人。他身材高大，鹰钩鼻，脑后面歪戴着顶帽子。他叫罗伯兰，来自热福塞农场。随之而来的，是图克农场的里埃巴。他又矮又胖，脸色红润，穿着一件灰夹克，长筒皮靴上绑着马刺。

他们俩都带着鸡或奶酪，想着办法让女地主能买下来。但无论耍什么把戏，费莉西泰总能赢过他们，他们也因此总是很尊敬她。

有时，欧班夫人也会接待她的叔叔，德·格莱芒维特侯爵。他因生活放纵，败光了所有的钱财。现在，住在法莱斯仅剩的一小块领地上。他总是在午餐时间来，带着一条惹人厌的小贵宾犬，它会在家具上涂满泥爪印。他表现得像一位绅士，每次提及“先父”，总会抬一下帽子。但终究恶习难改，很快他就会给自己倒上一杯又一杯酒，尽说一些下流的玩笑话。费莉西泰会礼貌地将他带到门边，说：“我想，今天差不多了，德·格莱芒维特侯爵！下回再来看我们吧！”说完，便把他关在了门外。

不过，她倒是很乐意迎接退休的律师布雷先生。他的白领带、秃脑门、衬衫前襟上的荷叶花边、宽大的棕色大衣、捏鼻烟时弯起胳膊的独特姿态——事实上，有关这个人的一切，都让费莉西泰心慌意乱，就像我们见到大人物时那样。

他替“夫人”照管产业，会连着好几小时和夫人关在“老爷”的书房里。他总担心名誉受损，对法院尊敬万分，并声称自己懂一些拉丁文。

他给孩子们买了一本带插图的地理书，因为他认为这将有利于他们从学习中得到乐趣。这本书描述了世界各地的场景：戴着羽毛头饰的食人族，一只诱拐年轻女孩的猴子，一群沙漠中的贝都因人，一条中了鱼叉的鲸鱼，等等。

保罗将所有这些插图仔细地讲解给费莉西泰听。实际上，这是唯一一次有人教她如何阅读一本书。

给孩子们上课的是居尤，那是一个着实可怜的家伙。他在镇公所工作，因写一手好字而出名，喜欢在靴底磨砺他的笔刀。

一旦天气晴好，全家都会起得早早的，前往热福塞农庄消磨一整天。

院子坐落在斜坡上，农舍则在院子中央。从那里可以望见远处的海，像一条小小的灰色带子。

费莉西泰从篮子里拿出片片冷肉。他们在挨着牛奶房的房间里吃饭。那个房间是已然塌毁的乡村别墅中唯一残存的部分。墙纸剥落，垂了下来，随穿堂风摆动着。欧班夫人低着头，沉浸在往事里。这让孩子们几乎不敢说话。她说：“你们去玩吧。”于是，他们就走开了。

保罗会爬上谷仓，捉小鸟，在池塘里打水漂，或用木杖敲打大木桶，发出轰隆轰隆的响声，像在敲鼓。

维尔吉妮会去喂兔子，或跑过牧场去采矢车菊。她跑的时候，会露出靓丽的绣花短裤。

秋天的一个晚上，他们穿过草地回家。

上弦月照亮了天空。薄雾飘移着，像纱一样蒙在图克河蜿蜒的水面上。有一群牛躺在草地中央，慵懒地看着他们路过。到了第三块草地，一些牛站起来，在他们面前围成一个圈。费莉西泰说：“不用怕!”她边往前走，边哼着引人沉思的小调。来到最近的动物旁，她轻轻拍着它的背脊。它走开了，其他的牛也一样。然而，刚穿过下块草地，他们就听到一声可怕的牛哞。那是一头隐藏在雾中的公牛。它开始朝那两位女士走来。欧班夫人想逃走。费莉西泰说：“不不，不能走得太快！”但她们却走得更快了。即使如此，她们仍能听到身后越来越近的公牛鼻息，以及牛蹄捶打青草的声响。她们知道它正飞奔而来。费莉西泰转身，面对公牛，从地上捡起土块，扔向它的脸。公牛低下头，晃着双角，颤抖着发出怒吼。现在，欧班夫人带着两个孩子，已到了草地边，急着想穿过树篱。费莉西泰则面对公牛，仍有条不紊地撤退，将一块草根土扔进它的眼睛里，一边还喊着：“快，快！”

欧班夫人下了沟底，相继推着维尔吉妮和保罗上去了。她爬堤岸时，跌落了几次。不过最终还是凭着股子意志力，成功地爬了上去。

公牛已将费莉西泰逼到一扇栅栏门前，喷吐的口水溅到了她脸上。下一秒，牛角就要顶到她了。在这危急时刻，她竟从两根木桩之间硬挤了过去。这庞大的家伙吓了一跳，愣在了原地。

多年以后，蓬莱韦克的人仍会谈起这桩历险。但费莉西泰并不引以为傲，也丝毫不觉得她的作为有什么英勇可言。

维尔吉妮占据了她全部的心神。那场公牛带来的可怕经历，已影响了维尔吉妮的神经。普帕特医生建议她到特鲁维尔洗海水浴。

那时候，还鲜有人来这处风景胜地。欧班夫人四处打听，还请教了布雷先生，做了充分准备，仿佛是一场很漫长的旅程。

临行前一天，行李由里埃巴的农场马车送走了。第二天，他牵着两匹马回来。一匹有女士马鞍，带着天鹅绒靠背。另一匹马的背上放着一个斗篷卷成的坐垫。欧班夫人骑上马，跟在里埃巴后头。费莉西泰在另一匹马上照顾维尔吉妮。保罗骑的则是夏勒杜瓦先生的驴。借这头驴，有一个明确的条件，他们得精心照顾它。

路况很糟。五英里的路，他们走了两小时。马匹踩在泥地里，陷到踝骨。它们得猛然向前，才能自如地拔出脚来。它们的脚绊在车辙里，有时不得不跳一下。在路上的某些地方，里埃巴的母马突然不走了。里埃巴耐心等着，直到它再次走动。骑行时，他会说起住在路旁那些人的故事，并总是额外添加些许个人的评判。比如，到了图克镇中心，他们行经一栋房子，窗外围着簇旱金莲。他耸耸肩，说：“这里住着一位勒胡塞太太，她倒不挑年轻人，反而……”费莉西泰没有听到下文，因为这时马儿开始慢跑起来，驴也在前头跑了。他们下了条小道，一扇门开了，出来两位年轻的农场工人。他们就在农舍门外的肥料堆旁下了马。

里埃巴老夫人迎接女东家，一脸的欢喜溢于言表。午饭时，她摆出牛里脊、大肠、灌肠、奶油炖鸡块、泛着泡沫的果汁、水果馅饼、酒浸李子。全程都在说着恭维的话，说夫人看起来“气色更好了”，说小姐已长成一位“美丽的少女”，说少爷保罗是个多“壮实”的年轻人，还不忘提及他们过世的祖父母。里埃巴一家数代为他们服务，因此老一辈的人也都认识。这农场和里埃巴一家一样，透着股陈旧年代的味道。虫子蛀蚀了房顶的横梁，烟熏黑了墙面，尘土蒙上了窗玻璃。一个橡木架上堆着各种工具：水壶、碟子、锡盘、捕狼器、剪羊毛的大剪刀，以及一个让孩子们觉得格外逗乐的巨大的灌肠器。外面有三所院子，那里的每棵树都长着蘑菇，许多树枝中间生着槲寄生。有些树被风吹倒了，但在树干绽裂的地方又重新长出来。在果实的重压下，所有的树都弯了。茅草屋顶像是厚薄不一的棕色天鹅绒，倒是经受住了最猛烈的风，但马车房坍塌了。欧班夫人说，她会安排人去修的，接着就让人备马去了。

他们花了半小时，来到特鲁维尔。这支小小的旅行队伍，在来到文考尔——一座从船上方延展的悬崖时，不得不下了马。三分钟后，他们来到码头的一端，进了大卫老夫人的客栈“金色羊羔”的院子。

由于空气变换，以及海水浴的关系，维尔吉妮很快就康复了。她没有泳衣，是穿着衬衫下水的。她的女仆会在一间海关人员的简陋小屋帮她穿衣服，这间小屋也供淋浴的人使用。

下午，他们骑驴走过罗切斯-诺雷斯，去往恩克维尔。起初，小道在像公园草地般轻柔起伏的牧场间蜿蜒攀升。接着，便来到一片高原，那里是牧场和耕地。小道旁种植着冬青，与杂乱的树莓丛长在一起。一棵枯死的大树，其枝丫呈之字形，横亘在蓝天下。

他们总是在一块特定的草地停下休息。往下看，左边是多维尔，右边是勒阿弗尔。前方则是开阔的海。在阳光下，大海散发着微光，像镜面一样光滑。四周围很安静，几乎能听到海浪持续而低沉的声音。麻雀在附近吱吱叫着。巨大的天穹铺展在上方。欧班夫人坐在那里，做着针线活儿。维尔吉妮坐在她身旁，编织着灯芯草。费莉西泰采摘一束束野生薰衣草。而保罗则很无聊，总想着早点上路。

别的时候，他们坐船渡过图克河，去找贝壳。退潮时，海胆、鲍鱼、水母被留在沙滩上。孩子们追逐风吹来的星星点点的泡沫。波浪从海滩一边到另一边，慵懒地破碎在沙子里。海滩延展着，没有边际，但在陆地那一侧，以沙丘为界，将它和跑马场似的玛黑大牧场分隔开来。他们穿过牧场，往回走向特鲁维尔——它就躺在山脚下，每走一步，这座小镇就大一些。各式房子错落开来，像花园里缤纷的花朵。

天气热的时候，他们便待在房间里。外面炫目的光透过百叶窗的缝隙，投进一道道光束。乡村里听不到一丝声响。没有一个人敢冒险来到大街上。占据一切的寂静，让万物显得更为平静。远处，传来船工的锤子在敲打船体的声音，而柏油的气息也随着倦怠的微风飘荡而来。

一天中最激动人心的事，发生在渔船归来的时候。一旦过了入口浮标，他们便开始迂回前进。他们的主帆降到桅杆的一半高，前帆膨胀，像巨大的气球。他们滑过飞溅的海浪，直达海港的中央，随后便突然抛锚。渔船被带到码头后，水手吊起他们的鱼，扔到岸上。鱼还是活的，轻微颤动着。一排马车早就等在那里了。戴着棉布帽的女人们冲向前，去拿篮子，亲吻她们的男人。

有一天，有个女人向费莉西泰走来。不久，费莉西泰便兴冲冲地回到客栈的房间。她找到了失散姐妹中的一个，这位纳斯塔西·巴奈特，也就是勒鲁夫人，紧随其后进了房间，怀里抱着一个宝宝。一个小孩握着她的右手，而她的左手边是一个小水手。他的手放在臀部上，贝雷帽扣到了耳朵上。

一刻钟后，欧班太太就让她走了。

但之后并没有摆脱他们。他们会刚好等在厨房外面，或者在她们外出散步时，尾随而来。至于那个丈夫，则一直没有现身。

费莉西泰倒是很依恋他们。她给他们买了一条毯子、几件衬衫，和一只炉子。他们很明显在利用她。欧班夫人对费莉西泰这种软心肠很是懊恼。她也反对那个外甥对保罗所表现出的亲密举止。再加上，维尔吉妮犯了咳嗽，天气也更恶劣了，她便返回了蓬莱韦克。

在为保罗选择一所好学校时，布雷先生提了建议。在康城有所公认是最好的学校。因此保罗就被送到了康城。他告别时很勇敢，为即将住在一个会有自己朋友的地方而心满意足。

欧班夫人只好任由她儿子离去，因为她知道他必将获得良好的教育。维尔吉妮很快就适应了，倒是费莉西泰发现，没有他，房子变得太安静了。不过，很快地就有别的事吸引了她的注意力。圣诞节后，她每天得带着维尔吉妮去学习教理问答。

[1] 苏（sou），法国曾发行的一种铜币。——译者注

三

费莉西泰进门时，屈膝行了个礼，沿着教堂中堂高耸的天花板下方的过道一路走来，打开欧班夫人坐的教堂长椅的挡门后，自行坐下，环顾了一下四周。

孩子们已在唱诗班的席位入座，男孩在右，女孩居左。神父站在他们前面，靠近读经台。在后殿，一扇彩色玻璃上显示着圣灵在俯视圣母玛利亚。另一扇窗上，则是圣母跪在圣婴耶稣前面。神龛的背后是圣米迦勒屠龙的木雕。

神父开始讲起圣典的梗概。于是，费莉西泰的脑子里便满是伊甸园、大洪水、巴别塔、大火焚毁的城市、灭亡的种族，以及被推倒的偶像。这绚烂的叙事慢慢灌输给她，让她充满了对天父的尊崇，以及对天谴的极度恐惧。听到耶稣受难的故事，她哭了。他们为什么要将他钉在十字架上？既然他对孩子那么善良，他给饥饿的人以粮食，让盲人重见光明；既然他已被选中，出于温和的天性，选择降生于穷人家一座马厩的麦秆堆上。播种与收获，葡萄树上的果实，所有这些在福音书里提及的常见事物，也在她的生活里头出现。现在，有了与上帝的联系，这些事物更显神圣了。费莉西泰比以往更爱羊羔，因为她爱上帝的羔羊。而鸽子则会让她想起圣灵。

她发现很难想象圣灵到底是什么模样，因为他不仅是一只鸟，有时还是火，有时则是气息。入夜时，她看到在沼泽闪耀的，可能就是圣灵的光；或者是他的气息促使云朵飘过天空；或者是他的声音让教堂的钟声如此悦耳动听。她坐在那里，沉浸于对这些奇迹的敬仰之中，在石头墙的冰凉和教堂的平和里感到身心愉悦。

她丝毫也不理解教义，也没有想过去理解。当神父站着给孩子们讲解，而孩子们重复着所学的时候，费莉西泰睡着了，直到孩子们离开教堂，木屐拍打着石头地面所发出的声响才将她惊醒。就这样，费莉西泰靠着听孩子们背诵，学到了她的教理问答，而这种宗教教育在她年轻时却被忽略了。此后，她便模仿起维尔吉妮的宗教戒律。她斋戒，她也斋戒。无论她何时去忏悔，她便跟着去。为了圣体瞻礼节，费莉西泰和维尔吉妮还一起做了个圣坛。

维尔吉妮初次领圣餐的前几天，费莉西泰为要准备什么而着急。她担忧她的鞋子，她的念珠，她的弥撒用书，她的手套。她帮着欧班夫人给维尔吉妮穿衣服的时候，手一直在抖。

整个弥撒期间，她都焦虑不安。唱诗班的一侧被布雷先生挡住了，她看不见。但在正对面，她能看见一群女孩，低垂着面纱，戴着白色花冠，看上去像是一片雪地。即使隔着一段距离，她仍能从那线条优美的脖颈、虔诚沉思的情态，认出她深爱的小维尔吉妮。钟声响了。他们全都在静默中低下头，跪了下来。接着，伴随着管风琴强而有力的演奏，唱诗班和教众唱起了《上帝的羔羊》。男孩们列队向前，女孩们随之站起身来。她们双手合十，祈祷着，缓慢地走向点着蜡烛的圣坛。她们一个接一个地跪在圣坛台阶上，领受圣餐，又以相同的顺序，返回到唱诗班的位置。轮到维尔吉妮时，费莉西泰倾身向前，以便能看到她。带着那种出于真爱的非凡想象，她觉得自己就是维尔吉妮本人，借用了她的表情，穿着她的衣服，用她的心在她的胸口跳动。维尔吉妮张开嘴时，费莉西泰闭上眼睛，几乎要晕厥过去。

第二天一早，费莉西泰前往圣器室，请求给予她圣餐。她带着应有的钦敬领受圣餐，但并没有体验到那相同的狂喜。

欧班夫人想要给女儿最好的教育。既然居尤不能教她英语或音乐，她决定将女儿送往翁弗勒的乌尔苏拉修女学校。

维尔吉妮对此没有意见，但费莉西泰却很不开心，觉得夫人过于严厉了。然而，她还是接受了，毕竟这件事并不是她所能决定的，而她的女主人可能最了解情况。

有一天，一俩老旧的马车来到门外。车上下来一位修女，她是来接小姐的。费莉西泰将行李放在行李架上，向车夫叮嘱了几句，便将六罐果酱、一打梨子和一束紫罗兰放在车座上。

就在要离去时，维尔吉妮哭了。她紧紧抱着母亲，而母亲则亲吻她的额头，不断地对她说：“好了，好了，我们得勇敢些！”步梯拉上来了，马车出发了。

马车走后，欧班夫人的情绪失控了。那天晚上，她所有的朋友，劳尔曼夫妇、勒沙普图瓦夫人、洛赫弗耶姐妹、胡波维尔先生、布雷先生都来安慰她。

起初，女儿不在让她很伤心。但每周有三天，她都能收到女儿的信。其他几天，她则给女儿回信，在花园里散步、读书，以此打发时间。

每天早上，费莉西泰会习惯性地走进维尔吉妮的卧室，凝视着墙壁。她多想还能给她梳头，给她系鞋带，把她塞进被窝啊；多想能成天见到她那甜蜜的小脸蛋，握着她的手一起外出啊。为了找点事做，她试着做一些针线活儿。但她的手指太笨了，老是把线弄断。她没心思做任何事情，晚上也睡不着。她现在，用自己的话说，就是“体内空空的”。

为了能“有个伴儿”，她问欧班夫人能否允许她的外甥维克多过来看望。

维克多总在星期天弥撒过后那会儿来。他脸色红润，敞着胸，带着一股他刚刚走过的乡野的气息。她会立即为他摆好桌子。他们坐在桌子两头，面对面地吃午饭。为了节省开支，费莉西泰尽可能吃得少些，而维克多则吃很多，甚至吃到最后都睡着了。晚祷的钟声响了，她叫醒他，给他刷干净裤子，系好领带，然后靠在他的肩膀上，像一位自豪的母亲，向教堂走去。

他父母总是让他带点东西回去，一包糖、一块肥皂、一小瓶白兰地，有时甚至是钱。任何一件需要缝补的衣服，他都会带过来，而费莉西泰总是很乐意做这样的事情。一有机会，她就高兴地鼓励他再次过来。

八月里，维克多和他父亲一起到沿海一带捕鱼去了。

这时，暑假刚刚开始，孩子们回家了，这让费莉西泰有了些许的安慰。只是保罗变任性了，维尔吉妮也已大了，没法儿像对孩子那样待她了。这让他们之间的氛围变得尴尬，疏远。

维克多先后去了默尔克、敦刻尔克和布莱顿。每次航行回来，他都会带一份礼物给费莉西泰。第一次是贝壳做的盒子。第二次是一个咖啡杯。第三次是一个大大的姜饼人。他正长成一个英俊的年轻人。优美的身形，刚长出的一点胡髭，一副直爽开朗的表情，一顶总是戴在后脑勺上的小皮帽，让他看起来像是个领航员。为了逗费莉西泰高兴，他夹杂着水手的各种行话，给她讲故事。

一八一九年七月十四日，星期一（这是费莉西泰永远也不会忘记的日子），维克多说，他已签约受雇于一艘远洋轮船。两天后，他将从翁弗勒坐晚上的渡轮前往他的纵帆船，这艘船很快就会从勒阿弗尔启航。他这一去，也许要两年。

想到要分别这么久，费莉西泰极为伤心。为了能与他最后告别，星期三晚上，在欧班夫人吃完饭后，她便从蓬莱韦克到翁弗勒，穿着木屐跑了十英里。

到各各他时，她没有朝左，而是向右走，结果在造船厂里迷了路，不得不原路返回。她向路人打听方向，那人告诉她得快点了。一路上，她绕着满是船只的海港走着，碰到了各种缆索。突然，她脚下的地面似乎倾斜了，光束呈十字形交织在眼前。她看到空中有几匹马，心想自己一定是疯了。

码头边，马群因害怕大海嘶鸣着。它们被起重架吊起，放到船里。船上人满为患，在苹果酒桶、奶酪筐和谷袋间拥挤着，走动着。母鸡在咯咯叫，船长在咒骂。甲板上，有个水手似乎对周遭的一切丝毫都不在意，靠着船头站着。费莉西泰没认出他，正一遍遍地叫着“维克多”。他抬起头，她向前冲来，但就在这时，舷梯突然从岸上被抽走了。

船只离了海港，被一群女人拖拽向前。她们在做事的时候，会齐声唱着歌。船体咯吱作响，沉重的波浪拍打着船头。然后船帆掉转，将所有人都遮挡在视线之外。月光下，海面闪着银色的光泽，而航行其上的船看起来像是个黑点，越来越暗淡。最终，在远处被吞没，消失不见了。

回家的路上，途经各各他，费莉西泰突然想请求上帝怜悯所有她珍爱的人。她站在那里，祈祷了很长时间。她的双眼凝视着上方的云朵，眼泪滑落她的脸颊。整座城镇都睡了，除了那些海关的人。可以听见水从闸门的孔中流过，像是激流。钟声敲响了两点。

天亮前，女修道院是不会接待访客的。而费莉西泰也知道，如果她回来晚了，夫人肯定会很生气。因此，尽管她很想从维尔吉妮那儿得到一个小小的吻，但还是启程回家了。她踏进蓬莱韦克时，客栈的女仆才刚刚起床。

维克多太可怜了，他得在海浪上持续颠簸数月！她并不担忧他之前的航行，毕竟英格兰也好，布列塔尼也罢，都是可以回来的地方。但美洲，殖民地和安的列斯群岛，则迷失在世界另一边的未知领域里。

自他走后，费莉西泰无时不在想着她的外甥。天气炎热、阳光充足时，她担心他可能会渴了。暴风雨来临时，她害怕他可能会被雷电击中。听到风在烟囱里呼啸，将屋顶上的瓦片吹落，她则想象他正经受着同样的风暴，正紧紧抓住折断的桅杆顶端，身子向后，被抛掷在大海的白沫之中。别的时候，受她所记得的地理书上那些插图的刺激，她想象他正在被野人吃掉，在树林里被猿猴捕获，或者正死在一片荒凉的海滩上。但她从未将这些焦虑告诉任何人。

欧班夫人则在担忧她的女儿。

修道院的修女说，她是个情感丰富的孩子，只是太过敏感。哪怕一点点的情感波动都会影响到她。这让她不得不放弃弹钢琴。

她母亲坚持要她定期写信。有一天早晨，邮差没有出现，她几乎不能自制，在房间里的扶手椅和窗户之间，来回走个不停。实在太过分了！都四天没消息了！

费莉西泰想到自己的境况可能对女主人有所安抚，便说：

“但是夫人，我已经六个月没有收到消息了。”

“谁的消息？”

“哎呀，我外甥的消息呀。”费莉西泰温柔地回答。

“哦，你的外甥！”欧班夫人耸耸肩，又在房间里踱起步来，那似乎在说：“我想都没想过他！他关我什么事呢！只不过是个小船员，一个乞丐。他不值得我焦虑。但像我的女儿那样的……想想看！”

尽管自小就受尽虐待，但费莉西泰还是被欧班夫人深深伤害了。不过很快，她就平复了。

毕竟夫人为她的女儿心烦意乱，是可以理解的。

对费莉西泰来说，两个孩子是同等重要的。他们因她的爱而连接在一起。而让他们享有相同的命运，看起来也是恰当的。

费莉西泰听药剂师说，维克多的船已到了哈瓦那。他是在报纸上读到这则消息的。

由于与雪茄有关，费莉西泰幻想着哈瓦那是这样的一个地方：人们除了抽烟，什么都不干。她想象着维克多正走在一群黑鬼之间，被烟雾笼罩着。“如果需要的话”，从哈瓦那可以走回来吗？那里离蓬莱韦克有多远？为此，她去请教了布雷先生。

他找来地图册，开始解说经纬线。费莉西泰听蒙了。布雷先生坐在她前面，沾沾自喜，好像他无所不知似的。最后，他拿出铅笔，在地图上一个椭圆形斑点的缺口处，指了指一个几乎看不见的黑点说：“就是这里了。”费莉西泰凑近看着地图。这些彩色的线条组成的网络压迫着她的双眼，但并没有告诉她任何事情。布雷先生问，她在迷惑什么。她说，他是否可以指出维克多现在住的房子。布雷先生举起手臂，打了个喷嚏，哈哈大笑，被自己遇到头脑如此简单的人逗乐了。费莉西泰没能理解他的笑点。毕竟，她理解力有限，她甚至期望能在那里看到一张她外甥的照片呢。

两周后，是里埃巴照常去集市的日子。他走进厨房，递给费莉西泰一封她姐夫的信。两人都不识字，费莉西泰只好拿给女主人看。

欧班夫人正在数一件织物的针脚。她将活儿放在一边，打开信，停顿了片刻，然后低沉着声音，严肃地说：“他们给你带来了……坏消息。你外甥……”

维克多死了。这就是那封信所说的。

费莉西泰倒在了椅子上，头抵着墙，眼皮紧闭，眼眶泛红。她僵在那儿，低垂着头，双手无力地垂在身旁，凝视前方，一遍遍地重复说：“可怜的孩子！可怜的孩子！”

里埃巴站在那里，看着她，叹了口气。欧班夫人轻轻颤抖。

她建议费莉西泰到特鲁维尔去看看她姐姐。

费莉西泰做了个手势，意思是那没有必要。

一片沉默。里埃巴老头觉得他最好离开。

他走后，费莉西泰说：“他们是不会在意的，一点都不会。”

她再次低头，坐在那儿，不时心烦意乱地玩弄着摆在桌上的编织针。

院子里走过一群女人，正推着一车湿漉漉的亚麻衣服。

透过窗户，费莉西泰看见了她们，突然想起要洗的衣服。昨天她用碱液泡过，今天该洗出来了。于是，她起身出了房间。

她的洗衣板和木盆都在图克河边。她将一堆内衣扔到岸边，卷起袖子，抓住棒槌。这捶打的声响，在邻居的花园里都能听到。牧场空落无人，风吹皱了河面。河床上长长的水草，随波漂流着，像死人的头发在水里向下漂移。费莉西泰很勇敢，克制着她的悲痛，一直到天黑。但当她独自一人在房间里时，还是没能忍住。她平躺在床垫上，将脸埋在枕头里，用拳头挤压着太阳穴。

很久以后，她从那艘船的船长那里得知维克多死时的情况。他得了黄热病，在医院里放了很多血。四个医生同时在给他治疗，而他立即死了。主治医生说：“上帝啊，又死了一个。”

维克多一直受父母苛待。费莉西泰不再乐意见到他们。他们也没有去联系费莉西泰。可能他们只是把她忘了，也可能是因为贫穷让他们生就了一副硬心肠。

维尔吉妮越来越虚弱了。

呼吸困难，咳嗽持续，高烧不断，脸上布满暗淡的红疹，所有这些都在显示某种隐晦的身心失调。普帕特医生建议她去普罗旺斯度假。欧班夫人听从了他的意见。如果不是蓬莱韦克的天气不好，她会立即将维尔吉妮接回家的。

她和一个出租马车的人达成协议，让他每周二带她去往修道院。修道院的花园里有一座露台，可以俯瞰塞纳河。维尔吉妮靠着母亲的手臂，踩着掉落的葡萄叶，上下来回地散步。她会望着远处的帆船，以及从唐卡维尔的别墅到勒阿弗尔的灯塔这一带的海岸。有时，太阳突然穿破云层，照得她直眨眼睛。之后，她们会坐在棚架下休息。她母亲弄来一小杯上等的马拉加葡萄酒。维尔吉妮会喝那么两口，一想到自己会喝醉就发笑。

她开始恢复元气。秋天缓慢地滑过。费莉西泰竭尽所能安慰欧班夫人。但有一天傍晚，她在镇里办完差事回来，发现普帕特医生的马车停在门前。普帕特医生在大厅出口处，欧班夫人在系她的帽子。

“把我的脚炉、钱包和手套拿来，快！”

维尔吉妮患了肺炎，夫人怕她好不了。

“我确信没那么糟糕。”医生说。于是，两人一起爬上了他的马车。四周落着慌乱的雪。夜晚正在来临，天气异常寒冷。

费莉西泰猛冲进教堂，点了一支蜡烛后，就去追赶普帕特医生的马车了。过了整整一小时，她从后头跳上来，紧紧抓住马车的边。突然，她想起来：“院门没有关！万一小偷进来怎么办？”于是，她又从车里跳回了路上。

第二天，在最初的日光中，她来到医生家。医生回来过，但又去乡下探望病人了。她在客栈里等着，想着有人可能会捎信过来。最终，在早晨的朦胧光线里，她坐上了利雪来的公共马车。

修道院坐落在一条陡窄的街道底部。她从半途往下走时，听到修道院里传来的奇怪声响。那是丧钟的鸣响。“那一定是为别人敲的。”她想着，大声地叩着门环。

不久，她听到有脚步声拖拽而来，门开了些许，一个修女出现了。

这位善良的修女庄重地宣称“她刚过世”。就在这时，圣里奥纳多教堂的钟声响起，越发显得响亮。

费莉西泰来到三楼。

在门口，她看到维尔吉妮仰卧着，双手紧握，嘴巴张着，头向后仰。头上方，一尊黑色的受难像向她倾斜而来。她的脸，比她周边僵直地垂挂下来的帘子还要惨白。欧班夫人躺在那里，抱着床脚，疯狂地啜泣。院长站在她右边。三支蜡烛在五斗柜上闪着小小的红色光圈。外面，雾气蒙上了窗玻璃。几位修女来了，带走了欧班夫人。

整整两个晚上，费莉西泰都没有离开维尔吉妮的床边。她坐在那儿，不断重复着相同的祷词。她起身，将圣水洒在被单上，又回到椅子里，继续凝视这位死去的姑娘。第一天守夜结束时，她注意到她的脸变黄了，嘴唇变蓝了，鼻子变瘦了，而她的眼睛也凹陷了下来。不止一次，她亲吻她的眼睛。此时，如果维尔吉妮再次睁开眼，她也不会有丝毫的惊讶。对她这样的人来说，超自然的事情是很平常的。她将她放好，给她穿上寿衣，放入棺材，给她戴上花环，将她的头发铺展开来。她的头发很美，对她这个年龄的女孩来说，算是长的了。费莉西泰剪下一大卷头发，将其中一半放进怀中，打定主意，永不分离。

按欧班夫人的意思，人们将尸体运回了蓬莱韦克。欧班夫人坐在关得严实的马车里，尾随着灵车。

葬礼弥撒过后，要过三刻钟才能到达公墓。保罗领着队伍，哭泣着。布雷先生在他后面，随后是蓬莱韦克的各个名流，以及戴着黑面纱哭泣的女人，最后是费莉西泰。费莉西泰不禁想起她的外甥。想到不能给他这最后的荣耀，她感到了双重的悲伤，就好像他正随着维尔吉妮一同被埋葬了。

欧班夫人绝望了。

起初，她反抗上帝，认为他将维尔吉妮从她身边带走是不公正的，因为她从未做过错事，也没有什么事能让她内疚。然而，也许是有的。她应该带她去南方。别的医生会治好她。她自我谴责，希望能随女儿而去，并在睡梦中痛苦地呼叫。有一个梦特别折磨她。她的丈夫，打扮得像一个水手，从漫长的旅途归来，流着泪，哽咽着说，他收到指示，要带维尔吉妮走。接着，他们绞尽脑汁，想给她找一个躲藏的地方。

有一次，她失魂落魄地从花园回来。就在这之前（她指着一个地方），父亲和女儿依次出现在她面前。他们什么也没做，只是望着她。

有好几个月，她都待在房间里，无精打采的。费莉西泰温柔地劝说她，要她好好照顾自己，为了她的儿子，她过世的丈夫，以及出于对“她”的怀念。

“她？”欧班夫人说着，仿佛从睡梦中醒来。“哦，是的，你当然没有忘记她，你有吗？”她说的是公墓，那是欧班夫人绝不会去的地方。

费莉西泰每天都去那儿。

四点的钟声一响，她便走过一排房子，爬上山，打开门，来到维尔吉妮的墓前。墓上立着一根粉色的大理石柱，底下是块石板，一条链子将四周围成一个小花园。繁花几乎要淹没那张独立的花床了。费莉西泰给叶子浇水，换上新的沙子，然后趴在地上，除尽地面的杂草。如果欧班夫人最终能来，她会从中找到安慰，一种对痛失所爱的慰藉。

多年过去了，年岁间极为相似，无非是来来去去的年度教堂节日：复活节、圣母升天节、万圣节。反倒是日常中那些微小的事件，在数年后，会让她们想起某些特殊的日子。例如，一八二五年，两个装玻璃的工人粉刷过堂；一八二七年，屋顶的一部分掉落在院子里，差点砸死了路人；一八二八年夏天，轮到夫人给教区居民发放祝圣面包，差不多就在这时，布雷先生神秘地离开了镇子。然后，一个接一个地，相识的熟人都离开了：居尤、里埃巴、勒沙普图瓦夫人、罗贝林，以及她那已瘫痪多年的老叔叔格莱芒维特。

有一晚，邮车的车夫来到蓬莱韦克，带来“七月革命”的消息。几天后，新的县长上任了：勒森尼耶男爵，曾经的美洲领事。他来到蓬莱韦克，带着他的妻子，以及他的小姨和三位年纪很大的小姐。人们经常看见她们，穿着飘逸的长罩衣，出现在她们家的草坪上。她们还有一个黑人仆从和一只鹦鹉。她们拜访欧班夫人，以表达敬意。她也回访。只要远远看见，费莉西泰就会跑来告诉欧班夫人，说她们已在路上了。但能唤起欧班夫人兴趣的只有一件事，那就是她儿子的来信。

他看似无法专注于任何事情，整日沉湎于酒馆。欧班夫人会支付他的账单，但新的账单很快就来了。她在窗旁织着毛衣，发出沉重的叹息。即使身在厨房摇着手纺车的费莉西泰也能听到。

两个女人经常一起沿着花园的格子墙漫步。她们仍会频繁地谈起维尔吉妮，想着她是否会喜欢某某事，或她对某某场合会说些什么。

她所有的东西仍保存在儿童房卧室的橱柜里。欧班夫人尽量避免往里查看。但在夏日的一天，她终究没能忍住，打开了。橱柜里飞出了好多蛾子。

维尔吉妮的连衣裙成排地挂在架子下，上面摆着三个玩偶、一些发箍、一副玩偶的家具和她的洗手盆。两个女人拿出所有的裙子、袜子和手帕，平铺在两张床上，再叠起来。这些可怜的东西躺在那儿，在一束阳光的照耀下，显出了所有的污渍，以及因维尔吉妮的身体运动弄出来的折痕。空气温暖，天空湛蓝，一只黑鸟在外面鸣唱，整个世界显得格外平和。她们找到一顶栗色的长毛绒帽，但已被飞蛾蛀蚀了。费莉西泰问是否可以将它作为纪念品留下来。两个女人看着彼此，双眼满是泪水。欧班夫人张开双臂，费莉西泰扑了过去。女主人和仆人相互拥抱着，在一个不分贵贱的吻里，联结起她们的悲伤。

她们是第一次这样做，之前从未发生过。因为就其天性而言，欧班夫人是非常矜持的。费莉西泰从未如此感激她，仿佛得了一份无价的礼物。自此之后，她更为溺爱女主人，像狗一般忠贞，像对待圣人一般虔诚。

随着时间的流逝，她本性中的善意越发凸显了。

有一天，她听到街上行军的鼓声，便站在门前，捧着一壶苹果酒，递给士兵喝。她帮着看护霍乱病人，照顾波兰的难民。有一个波兰人甚至说，想要娶她，但他们发生了很严重的争执。那是在一天早晨，她做完礼拜回来，发现他坐在她的厨房里，镇定自若地吃着一盘色拉，而那是她为午饭准备的。

波兰人走后，她注意到了一个叫考尔米克的老人。传言他在一七九三年做过很残暴的事情。现在他住在河边一间破败的猪圈里。镇里的小孩经常从墙缝里窥看他，朝他扔石子。他躺在草垫上，咳得快呛住了。他有一头披散的长发，眼皮发炎了，手臂上长着一个比他的头还大的瘤子。费莉西泰给了他一些布，竭力打扫干净他简陋的住所。她甚至想，也许可以将他安置在外屋，一处不会打扰到夫人的地方。瘤子破了，她就每天都给他换衣服。有时，她会给他带来一小片蛋糕，或扶他出去，将他放在一捆麦秆上，晒晒太阳。这个贫穷可怜的人语无伦次，颤动着，以一种几乎听不见的低语感谢她，说害怕她走掉。见她要走，就会伸出双手。他死了，费莉西泰做了一场弥撒，让他的灵魂安息。

同一天，她收到一份极为美妙的惊喜。在她吃饭时，勒森尼耶夫人的黑人仆从来了，带着一只关在笼子里的鹦鹉，还有栖木、链子和挂锁。男爵夫人给欧班夫人带来一张字条，说她丈夫荣升省长了，晚上他们就要离开蓬莱韦克。她问欧班夫人，能否发善心收下这只鹦鹉，作为她们友谊的纪念，以及她表达敬意的象征。

很长一段时间，费莉西泰对这只鹦鹉心存好奇。因为它来自美洲，一个总能让她想起她的维克多的地方。她曾就这只鸟问过仆从。有一次，她甚至说“夫人若能照料它，会很开心的”。

黑人仆从就把这事说给他的女主人，而她反正也不能带走，于是很乐意抓住这次机会，将它脱手了。

四

这只鹦鹉叫露露。他的身子是绿色的，翼尖是粉色的，额头是蓝色的，而胸脯是金色的。

不幸的是，他有着很惹人厌的习惯：咬栖木，拔羽毛，到处抛洒粪便，还将杯里的水飞溅得满笼子都是。欧班夫人被惹怒了，就把他送给费莉西泰来照料。

她决心教他说话，而且没过多久，他便会说：‘好孩子！’‘您的仆人，先生！’‘万福玛利亚！’她把他放在正门附近，路过的人都很惊奇，因为他竟对“波利”没有反应，而所有的鹦鹉都叫这个名字。有人说他更像火鸡，有人则叫他傻瓜。费莉西泰觉得这些嘲弄太伤人了。令人惊奇的是，露露有种奇怪的执拗：有人看他就拒绝说话。

但他无疑还是喜欢有人陪伴的。星期天，当洛赫弗耶姐妹、胡波维尔先生，欧班夫人的新朋友药剂师翁弗洛瓦、瓦林先生和马修船长来玩纸牌的时候，露露就会用翅膀拍打窗玻璃,发出剧烈的骚乱声，闹得人都无法听清在说什么。

显然，他觉得布雷先生的脸很可笑。一见到他，就会忍不住爆发出一阵笑声。他粗砺的声音回荡在院子四周。邻居们听到后，就会来到窗前，也随之大笑。为了不让他看见，布雷先生会将脸藏在帽子后面，沿着墙偷偷地走过房前。他走过河边，从后花园绕进屋里。他投向这只鸟的眼神，可不是很温柔的。

肉铺的伙计在露露想偷吃他篮子里的东西时，弹了弹他的脑门儿。自那以后，露露总想隔着衬衫啄他。于是，法布威胁说要扭断他的脖子。他倒不是天性残忍，只是手臂上的文身和那长长的络腮胡，可能会给人留下这样的印象。事实上，他很喜欢这只鹦鹉。为了逗乐，甚至想教他脏话。费莉西泰怕他沾上这些坏毛病，就把他移到了厨房里。链子也被拿掉了，他可以在房子里四处逗留。

下楼的时候，他会用嘴钩子顶在前面的台阶上，抬起右脚，接着是左脚。费莉西泰总担心这些奇怪的动作，会将鹦鹉弄晕。果然，他生病了，不能说话，不能吃东西。他的舌尖下生了溃疡，有时候母鸡也会得这种病。费莉西泰用指甲戳破他嘴里的肿块，治好了他。有一天，保罗少爷愚蠢地将雪茄烟喷到他的鼻子里。还有一次，劳尔曼夫人用伞尖逗弄他，他咬掉了金属箍。后来，他就不见了。

费莉西泰将他放在草地上，让他呼吸新鲜空气，然后便回了室内一会儿。回来时，鹦鹉就不见了。她在灌木丛、河边，甚至在屋顶上找着，也不顾女主人喊着说：“小心，你一定是疯啦！”随后，她找遍了蓬莱韦克的每一座花园，遇到路人就问：“你凑巧见过我的鹦鹉吗？”对不熟悉鹦鹉的人，她还会做一番详细的描述。突然，她似乎看到一个绿色的东西在山脚下的磨坊后面飞着。可到了山顶，却什么也没有。一个小贩说，不久前，他在圣梅兰区西蒙老夫人的店里见过它。费莉西泰就一路跑去，但没人知道她在说什么。最后，她回来了，精疲力竭，鞋子磨破了，意志消沉。她坐在花园的椅子中央，挨着夫人，说着她所做的事情。这时，有什么轻柔地落在肩上。是露露！他究竟去干吗了？也许只是绕着镇子走了走。

费莉西泰没能立即从惊吓中复原。如果知道真相，也可以说，她再也不能恢复了。

因为着凉，她患上了扁桃体炎。不久，耳朵也疼了。三年后，她全聋了，说话特别大声，即使在教堂里也是。她的罪过散播在教区的各个角落，即使这并非有损她的名声，也不冒犯他人，但神父仍然觉得，听她忏悔最好在圣器室内。

头脑中想象的嗡嗡声令她备受折磨。她的女主人经常说：“天啊，你多蠢啊！”费莉西泰会回答说：“是的，夫人。”然后，她四处打量，仍想要找寻这嘈杂声是哪里发出的。

她陷入越来越小的自我世界里。教堂的钟声、牧场上的牛哞，永远地离她而去了。所有的活物都如鬼魂，从旁静默地经过。现在唯一能抵达她耳朵的声音，便是鹦鹉的叫声。

像是有意给她解闷似的，他模仿起烤肉叉转动的咔嗒响、鱼贩子尖锐的叫声，或者街对面工匠的锯齿声。无论何时，门铃一响起来，他就会模仿欧班夫人说：“费莉西泰，门，门！”

他们彼此交谈。鹦鹉不断地重复着三个烂熟的短句。而费莉西泰呢，则用没什么意义但发自肺腑的话来回答。在她孤绝的世界里，露露几乎成了她的儿子，她溺爱他。而他则爬上她的手指，咬咬她的唇，挂在她的披肩上。有时，她的脸会挨着他的，摇晃着，就像护士对婴儿做的那样。帽子的两翼和鸟的翅膀一起颤动着。

乌云聚集，雷电轰隆作响的时候，鹦鹉就大声地叫着，显然是忆起了野生森林里的暴雨。下雨的声音，让他很不安。他满屋子疯狂地飞着，撞上天花板，撞倒了所有的东西，最后穿过窗户逃到花园里，泼溅着泥水。但他很快就会回来，高高地栖息在壁炉架上，跳上跳下的，晾干了羽毛，自豪地展示着他的尾巴或者嘴。

一八三七年那个可怕的冬日，有一天早晨，她见天冷，就把他放在壁炉旁。这时，她发现他死在了笼子里。头下垂着，爪子抓着金属门闩。想必是死于中风吧，但费莉西泰却想，他可能吃了欧芹，毒发而死。尽管没有确切的证据，但她怀疑是法布干的。

她哭得很伤心，最终女主人说：“为什么不把他做成标本呢？”

费莉西泰咨询了药剂师，他对鹦鹉一向很好。

他写信到勒阿弗尔，一个叫弗拉切的接了这份活儿。考虑到公共马车有时会丢失包裹，费莉西泰决定亲自带着鹦鹉，前往翁弗勒。

道路向前延伸，两旁是无尽的苹果树，光秃秃的，没什么叶子。水沟里结着冰。她走过农场时，狗吠叫着。她的手缩在斗篷下方，篮子挂在手臂上。费莉西泰穿着黑色小木屐，在路中央快步走着。

她穿过树林，走过上歇纳，最终来到了圣加蒂安。

这时，在她身后起了一团尘土，只见一辆邮车飓风似的，从山上疾驰而来。车夫看女人没有躲开的意思，便站起身，目光越过马车顶，朝外望去。他和车童都竭力叫喊着。他想让四匹马停下，但没有用。它们反而越来越快，朝着她奔来。他们经过时，前头的两匹马蹭过了费莉西泰。车夫猛地一拉缰绳，迫使马匹转向了路旁。盛怒之下，他举起手臂，挥鞭打去，从她的脸一直打到了上半身。她仰面倒在了地上。

醒来时，她所做的第一件事，就是看看篮子。还好，露露毫发无损。她觉得右脸一阵阵地灼痛，便用手摸了摸，看见手是血红色的。她正在流血。

她坐在石堆上，用手帕轻抚着脸，然后吃了点预先备好的面包。她看着鹦鹉，试图借此忘记伤口。

到了埃屈埃莫维尔的山顶，她便看见翁弗勒像是群星般闪烁的夜间灯火。再过去便是大海，朦胧地延展向远方。突然，她感到一阵晕眩。悲惨的童年，初恋带来的失望之情，外甥的离世，维尔吉妮的亡故，所有这些都潮水似的，汹涌袭来，涌进她的体内，让她窒息。

她坚持要和船长当面说话，要他好好照顾这个包裹，尽管她没说这里面有什么。

弗拉切拖了很长时间，尽管他总说下周就会寄出来。六个月后，他才说将箱子寄出来了，但之后就再没有下文了。费莉西泰怕露露再也不会回来。她想：“他被偷了，我知道的。”

最终，他还是来了。他看起来也很棒，栖息在一根树枝上，用螺丝钉固定在桃木底座上。他抬着一只爪，头侧向一边，嘴里叼着一颗坚果。标本师为了添加一点华丽的质感，还给坚果镀了金。

费莉西泰将他安置在房间里。

她很少让人进入这个房间，里面放着各种宗教小摆件和杂七杂八的东西，像是小教堂，又像是集市。

门旁有个大衣橱，妨碍人开门。面向花园的窗户对面，有一扇能望见院子的圆形小窗。有一张没有弹簧的、朴素的床。床旁边是一张桌子，桌上放着一个水壶、两把梳子、一个带缺口的碟子——上面放着一小块蓝色的肥皂。墙上挂着念珠、纪念章、几幅圣母像、一个椰子壳做的圣水杯。五斗橱蒙着布，像是圣坛，上面放着维克多给她的贝壳盒子，还有一把喷壶、一个球、一些练习册、一本带插图的地理书和一双小小的短筒靴。镜子的挂钉上，挂着那顶小小的长绒帽！这些纪念品，对费莉西泰来说，都有着很深的意义。她甚至连老爷的一件礼服都留着。欧班夫人不要的东西，她都在房间里找地方放着，像五斗橱旁放着人造花，天窗里挂着阿图瓦伯爵的画像。

至于露露，则放在专为他准备的小木架上。那木架被固定在面向房间凸起的壁炉侧墙上。每天早上醒来时，她都会在晨光中看见他。她会想起那些过去的日子，那些微小的事件，直至想到各种细枝末节。想起这些，并不让她感到悲伤，反而充满了平静。

由于不能和人交流，她的生活像是在梦游。唯有圣体瞻礼节的游行，似乎还能将她带回到生活里来。她拜访邻居，收集烛台和垫子，用来装饰那些一般会放在街上的圣坛。

她来到教堂，坐下来，凝视着圣灵的画像。她发现圣灵和她的鹦鹉很像。这种相像在一幅埃皮纳勒版画上表现得尤为明显，上面画着我主受洗的情景。那鸽子有着深红的翅膀、祖母绿的身体，跟露露一模一样。费莉西泰将这幅画买回来，挂在阿图瓦伯爵画像挂的地方，这样她就能同时看到它们。在她的心中，两者联结在了一起。因着与圣灵的联结，鹦鹉更神圣了；而圣灵也因此更显生动，更有意义。上帝当然不会选中一只鸽子去言说，因为鸽子不能说话。那么，一定会选露露的先祖吧。费莉西泰望着圣灵那幅画祈祷时，不时会微微转头，看着鹦鹉。

她想过加入圣女姐妹团，但被欧班夫人劝阻了。

现在，发生了一件大事——保罗结婚了。

起先，他是法庭书记员，随后他去经商，在海关工作，在税务局做事，甚至还考虑过加入森林和水利部门。到了三十六岁时，仿佛受了神启似的，他突然发现了自己的天职——登记处办公室！事实上，他已展现出了这方面的天赋。一位检查官已将女儿许配给他，并答应动用他的影响力，助他晋升。

他正严肃地履行自己的职责，带她来见母亲。

她指摘蓬莱韦克的所有事情，期望自己能像皇族一样被人对待。她伤害费莉西泰甚深。见她走了，欧班夫人顿觉松了口气。

接下来的那周，她们听闻布雷先生死在了下布列塔尼的一家客栈里。谣传说，他是自杀的。很快，这就被证实了。人们开始质疑他的正直。欧班夫人检查她的账本，发现了一系列他的不法行为：盗用应收租金、没有申报树木所得、伪造收据，等等。他还有一个私生子，与“多聚莱的某人有着不正当的关系”。

欧班夫人很难过。一八五三年三月，她觉得胸口疼痛。舌头上覆着层灰色的苔衣。几次放血治疗都没能减轻她的呼吸困难。到了第九晚，她就死了，刚好七十二岁。

人们觉得她看起来要年轻些，因为她的头发是黑色的，还一束束地垂在两旁，裹着她苍白的麻脸。没什么朋友来哀悼她。她平素傲慢，让人对她保持了距离。

费莉西泰哭了，很少有仆人像她那样为主人哭。夫人先于她去世，让她怎么也想不通，觉得这违背了事物的自然秩序。无法接受，也不真实。

十天后，也就是从贝桑松赶来所费的时间，继承人来到了现场。欧班夫人的媳妇翻开了所有的抽屉，留了一些家具，剩下的全卖掉了。随后，他们便返回了登记处办公室。

欧班夫人的扶手椅、小桌子、暖脚炉和八张椅子都被运走了！墙上的画像也被拿掉了，只留下一块黄色的空当。他们还带走了两张小孩的床和床垫，以及橱柜里维尔吉妮的东西。费莉西泰在房间之间来回走着，心都碎了。

第二天，门上贴着一张告示。药剂师对着她的耳朵大声说，房子要卖掉了。

费莉西泰一阵晕眩，坐了下来。

一想到要搬出自己的房间，她就极为不安。对可怜的露露来说，那也是再合适不过的地方了。她满怀痛苦，凝视着他，祈求圣灵帮助。她跪在鹦鹉面前祈祷，养成了崇拜偶像的习惯。有时候，阳光透过小窗，落在鹦鹉的玻璃眼珠上，散发着明亮的光，将她带入了狂喜之中。

女主人给费莉西泰留了一笔三百八十法郎的退休金。花园可以供给她蔬菜。至于衣服，足够她穿到生命中的最后一刻。为了节省灯火，天一黑，她就上床睡觉。

她不怎么出门，免得走过二手商店时看见正摆着的那些旧家具。自被摔晕后，她就拖着一条腿走路。现在，她更虚弱了。最近，西蒙老夫人的杂货店破产了，她每天早晨都来为她劈柴打水。

她的视力越来越差。百叶窗也不再打开了。一晃多年，没人来租房子，也没人来买。

费莉西泰怕被人赶走，从未让人来修房子。屋顶的木板条烂了，整个冬天，雨水打湿了她的长枕头。复活节过去不久，她咯血了。

西蒙老夫人叫来一位医生。费莉西泰想知道她怎么了，但她的耳朵全聋了，很难听到他们说什么，只捕捉到一个词：“肺炎”。她是知道这个词的。她平静地回答说：“哈！跟夫人一样。”跟随夫人的脚步，她觉得这很自然。

准备圣坛的日子临近了。

第一座圣坛照例放在山脚下，第二座在邮局外面，第三座在街道的半途。最后一座该放在哪儿，起了些争执，但教区的女人们最终同意放在欧班夫人的院子里。

费莉西泰呼吸更艰难了，发烧也更严重。不能为圣坛做点什么，让她很难过。至少她得在上面放点什么吧。于是，她想到了鹦鹉。邻居们反对说，这样并不合适，但神父却允许了。这让费莉西泰很快乐，要神父收下她唯一的财产露露，作为死前送出的礼物。

从星期二到星期六，圣体瞻礼节前夕，她的咳嗽加剧。到了晚上，脸绷得紧紧的，嘴唇粘着牙床。她开始呕吐。第二天一早，天蒙蒙亮，她感觉很不好，便请求见神父。临终涂油礼时，四周站着三位善良的女人。然后，她说要和法布谈谈。

法布穿着他星期天最好的衣服来了。如此忧伤的氛围，令他很不舒服。

“请你原谅我。”她说着，用力朝他伸出手臂，“我还以为是你杀了他。”

她在说什么废话？她怎能怀疑像他这样的人是一个凶手！法布很生气，忍不住要发脾气。

“她头脑迷糊了，”她们说，“你肯定能看得出来。”

费莉西泰似乎不时地在同幽灵谈话。女人们走了，只有西蒙老夫人留了下来，在吃午饭。

不久，她拿来露露，靠近费莉西泰。“来吧，”她说，“和他道别。”

露露不是尸体，但也被蛆蛀食了。一只翅膀断了，填充物从肚子里露了出来。但费莉西泰眼睛已瞎，没能看到。她亲吻他的额头，让他贴着自己的脸颊。西蒙老夫人将他从她那里拿开，重新放在了圣坛上。

五

从牧场那里飘来夏日的气息。苍蝇在空中嗡嗡作响。阳光在河面闪耀，照暖了屋顶上的石板瓦。西蒙老夫人回了房间，正轻柔地打着盹睡去。

突然，她被钟声惊醒了。人们正做完晚祷出来。费莉西泰镇静了许多。她想到了游行，清晰地看到了所有的一切，仿佛就置身于其中。

所有的小学生、唱诗班和消防员，都走在了人行道上。街道中央，走在队伍前头的，是执戟的教堂守卫、捧着大十字架的教区执事、管理男孩的学校校长，以及母亲般盯着女孩的修女。三个最可爱的女孩，像头发卷曲的天使，正将玫瑰花瓣撒向空中。在她们身后，助祭张开双臂，正指挥着乐队；两个捧香炉的，每走一步，都会转过头看着圣体。圣体由穿着华丽长袍的神父捧着，由四个教区委员在其上举着顶红色的天鹅绒华盖护佑。在路上，在挂着白布的房墙之间，一大群人尾随而来，最终来到山脚下。

费莉西泰额前直冒冷汗。西蒙老夫人用布给她擦拭，对自己说，终有一天她也会这样走的。

人群的嘈杂声越来越响，有一瞬间特别响亮，然后又消退了。

一阵枪声震得窗户嗡嗡作响。那是骑马的人正在向圣体匣致敬。费莉西泰转动眼珠，费力地问：“他还好吗？”她还在担心鹦鹉。

费莉西泰正进入她的弥留时刻。她喘着气，短促而嘶哑，两肋艰难地起伏，嘴角聚集着泡沫，全身开始颤抖。

外面，街上传来乐器的嘟嘟声、孩子响亮的声音，以及男人低沉的声响。有那么一些时刻，一切都沉寂了，能听到脚步因散落的花瓣变得轻柔，像是羊群穿过牧场。

神职人员走进院子。西蒙老夫人爬上椅子，朝小窗外张望，正好能看到窗下的圣坛。

圣坛挂着绿色花环，镶着英式针织的花边。正中间有一个小小的方盒子，放着圣人的遗物。两边各有一棵橘子树。沿着圣坛摆放的是一排银烛台、瓷花瓶。花瓶里插着向日葵、百合、牡丹、毛地黄和绣球花。这串绚烂的色彩，从圣坛高处一路向下，延展至铺在鹅卵石上方的毯子。花丛里，可以见到其他一些珍贵的装饰品：一个装饰着紫罗兰花环的镀银糖罐，在小片青苔上闪烁的阿朗松宝石耳坠，两扇描画着风景的中国屏风。露露掩藏在玫瑰花底下，只见到他额头上的那点蓝，像块青金石。

教区委员、唱诗班、小孩在院子的三面站好。神父缓缓走来，将那大大的闪光的球体放在圣坛的花边上。所有人都跪了下来，一片沉静。香炉随链子晃动来回摇摆着。

一道蓝色的烟升起，进入费莉西泰的房间。她张大鼻孔，以一种神秘的狂热品味着。随后，她闭上眼睛，唇间现出一抹微笑。她的心跳放慢了，越来越微弱、模糊，像泉水干涸，回音消逝。就在呼出最后一口气时，她仿佛看到，天国开启的地方，一只巨大的鹦鹉在头上徘徊，来接纳她。

1

For half a century, Madame Aubain’s housemaid Félicitéwas the envy of all the good ladies of Pont‑ l’Evêque.

For just one hundred francs a year, she did all the cook‑ing and the housework, she saw to the darning, the washing and the ironing, she could bridle a horse, keep the chickens well fed and churn the butter. What is more she remained faithful to her mistress, who, it must be said, was not the easiest of people to get on with.

Madame Aubain had married a handsome but impe‑cunious young man, who had died at the beginning of 1809, leaving her with two very young children and sub‑stantial debts. Upon his death, she sold her properties, with the exception of the two farms at Toucques and Geffosses, which between them provided her with an income of no more than five thousand francs in rent, and she moved out of her house in Saint‑ Melaine to live in another which was less costly to maintain, which had belonged to her family and which was situated behind the market.

This house had a slate roof and stood between an alley and a narrow street leading down to the river. Inside, the floors were at different levels, making it very easy to trip up. A narrow hallway separated the kitchen from the liv ing room in which Madame Aubain remained all day long, sitting in a wicker armchair close to the casement window. Against the wainscoting, which was painted white, there stood a row of eight mahogany chairs. A barometer hung on the wall above an old piano, piled high with a pyramid‑ shaped assortment of packets and cardboard boxes. Two easy chairs upholstered in tapestry stood on either side of a Louis‑ Quinze‑ style mantelpiece in yellow marble. The clock, in the middle, was designed to look like a Temple of Vesta, and the whole room smelt musty, due to the fact that the floor level was lower than the garden.

On the first floor, there was ‘Madame’s’ bedroom, a very large room, decorated with pale, flowery wallpaper and containing a picture of ‘Monsieur’ dressed up in the fanciful attire that was fashionable at the time. This room led directly to a smaller bedroom which housed two chil dren’s beds, each with the mattress removed. Next came the parlour, which was always kept locked and was full of furniture draped in dust‑ sheets. Finally, there was a corridor leading to a study; books and papers lay stacked on the shelves of a bookcase which ran around three walls of the room and surrounded a large writing‑ desk in dark wood. The two end panels of this bookcase were covered in line drawings, landscapes in gouache and etchings by Audran, a reminder of better days and of more expensive tastes that were now a thing of the past. On the second floor was Félicité’s bedroom, lit by a dormer window which looked out over the fields.

Félicité always rose at first light to make sure she was in time for mass, and then worked without a break until the evening. As soon as dinner was finished, the crockery cleared away and the door firmly bolted, she would cover the log fire with ashes and go to sleep in front of the fire‑place, holding her rosary in her hand. No one could have been more persistent when it came to haggling over prices and, as for cleanliness, the spotless state of her saucepans was the despair of all the other serving maids in Pont‑ l’Evêque. She wasted nothing and ate slowly, gath‑ering every crumb of her loaf from the table with her fingers, a twelve‑ pound loaf baked especially for her and which lasted her twenty days.

In all weathers she wore a printed kerchief fastened behind with a pin, a bonnet which completely covered her hair, grey stockings, a red skirt and over her jacket a bibbed apron like those worn by hospital nurses.

Her face was thin and her voice was shrill. At twenty‑ five, people took her to be as old as forty. After her fiftieth birthday, it became impossible to say what age she was at all. She hardly ever spoke, and her upright stance and deliberate movements gave her the appearance of a woman made out of wood, driven as if by clockwork.

2

Like other girls, she had once fallen in love.

Her father, a stonemason by trade, had been killed fall ing from some scaffolding. Following this, her mother died and her sisters went their separate ways. A farmer took her in and, even though she was still a very young girl, he would send her out into the fields to look after the cows. She was dressed in mere rags, she shivered with cold and would lie flat on her stomach to drink water from ponds. She was regularly beaten for no reason at al and was eventually turned out of the house for having stolen thirty sous, a theft of which she was quite innocent. She was taken on at another farm, where she looked after the poultry and, because she was well liked by her employ ers, her friends were jealous of her.

One evening in August (she was eighteen at the time) she was taken to the village fête at Colleville. She was instantly overcome, bewildered by the boisterous sounds of the fiddle music, the lamps in the trees, the array of brightly coloured clothes, the gold crosses and the lace all those people moving as one in time to the tune. She was standing on her own, shyly, when a young man, fairly well off to judge by his appearance and who had been leaning against the shaft of a farm wagon smoking his pipe, approached her and asked her to dance. He bought her a glass of cider, a cup of coffee, a cake and a silk scarf and, imagining that she understood his motive, offered to accompany her back home. As they were walking along the edge of a field of oats, he thrust her to the ground. She was terrified and began to scream. He ran off.

One evening a little later, she was walking along the road leading to Beaumont and was trying to get past a large hay wagon as it lumbered slowly along. As she was edging her way round the wheels, she recognized Théodore.

He looked at her quite unabashed and said she should forgive his behaviour of the other night; he ‘had just had too much to drink’.

She did not know how to answer him and wanted to run away.

He immediately began to talk about the harvest and various important people in the district and told her that his father had left Colleville and bought a farm at Les Ecots, which meant that they were now neighbours. ‘Oh, are we!’ she said. He said that his parents wanted him to settle down but that he was in no rush and preferred to wait until the right woman came along before he married. She lowered her eyes. He then asked her if she was think‑ing of marrying. She smiled and said that he was wrong to tease her. ‘But I am not teasing you, I swear,’ he said, and slipped his left arm around her waist. She walked on with his arm still around her. They were now walking more slowly. There was a gentle breeze, the stars were shining, the huge wagon‑ load of hay swayed from side to side in front of them and dust rose from the feet of the four horses as they plodded along. Then, without any word of command, the horses turned off to the right. He kissed her once more and she vanished into the darkness.

The following week, Théodore persuaded her to go out with him on several other occasions.

They would meet in a corner of some farmyard, behind a wall or beneath a solitary tree. Félicité was not naive like other young girls of her age; working with the farm animals had taught her a great deal. However, her natural discretion and an intuitive sense of honour prevented her from giving in to Théodore’s demands. Théodore found this resistance so frustrating that, in order to satisfy his passion (or maybe out of sheer simple‑ mindedness), he proposed to her. She was not sure whether to believe him or not, but he insisted that he was serious.

He then announced something rather disturbing: a year ago his parents had paid for someone else to do his mili tary service but he might still be called up at any time The prospect of serving in the army terrified him. Félicitétook this cowardice as a sign of his affection for her and it made her love him all the more. She would slip out of the house at night to meet Théodore, who assailed her with his fears and entreaties.

Eventually, he declared that he would go to the Préfec ture himself and find out what the situation was. He would come back and tell Félicité the following Sunday between eleven o’clock and midnight.

At the appointed time, Félicité ran to meet her lover.

But instead of Théodore, it was one of his friends who stood waiting to meet her.

He informed her that she would never see Théodore again. In order to make sure he could not be called up, he had married a wealthy old lady from Toucques, by the name of Madame Lehoussais.

Félicité’s distress was unbounded. She threw herself to the ground, weeping and wailing; she implored God to come to her aid and lay moaning, all alone in the fields, until daylight. Then she made her way back to the farm and announced that she had decided to leave. At the end of the month, having received her wages, she wrapped her few belongings in a shawl and left for Pont‑ l’Evêque.

Outside the inn she spoke to a woman wearing a widow’s hood who, as it happened, was looking for a cook. The young girl knew precious little about cooking but she seemed so willing and so ready to oblige that Madame Aubain eventually said: ‘Very well, you may work for me.’

A quarter of an hour later, Félicité was installed in her house.

At first she lived in a constant state of trepidation as a result of ‘the sort of house it was’ and the memory of‘Monsieur’ which seemed to hover over everything! Paul and Virginie, one aged seven and the other barely four, seemed made of some precious material; she liked to give them piggyback rides and was mortified when Madame Aubain instructed her not to keep kissing them. Even so, she was happy. Her new surroundings were very pleasant and her earlier unhappiness quickly faded.

Every Thursday, a group of Madame Aubain’s friends came to play Boston. Félicité would set out the cards and the foot‑ warmers in readiness. The guests always arrived punctually at eight and left as the clock struck eleven.

On Monday mornings, the secondhand dealer who had a shop at the end of the lane would spread his various bits and pieces of ironmongery out on the pavement. The town would be filled with the buzz of voices, with the sounds of horses neighing, lambs bleating, pigs grunting and carts rattling through the streets. At about midday, just when the market was at its busiest, an old peasant would present himself on Madame Aubain’s front doorstep – a tall man with a hooked nose and with his hat perched on the back of his head. This was Robelin, the farmer from Geffosses He would be followed shortly afterwards by Liébard, the farmer from Toucques, short, fat and red in the face, wear ing a grey jacket and leather gaiters complete with spurs.

They would both come bearing chickens or cheeses which they hoped they might persuade their landlady to buy. But Félicité was more than a match for their banter and they always respected her for this.

Madame Aubain also received sporadic visits from the Marquis de Grémanville, an uncle of hers who had squan dered his money in loose living and who now lived at Falaise on the last bit of property he could still call his own. He would always turn up at lunch time with a loathsome little poodle which left its muddy paw marks all over the furniture. Despite his efforts to behave like a gentleman, raising his hat every time he mentioned his‘late father’, habit would soon get the better of him and he would pour himself glass after glass and start telling bawdy jokes. Félicité would politely show him to the door. ‘I think you have had enough for today, Monsieur de Grémanville! Do come and see us again soon!’ And she would close the door behind him.

But she was always delighted to welcome Monsieur Bourais, a retired solicitor. His white cravat and bald head, the flounces on his shirt‑ front and the generous cut of his brown frock‑ coat, the special way he had of bending his arm when taking snuff, indeed everything about his person prompted in Félicité the sort of agitation we always feel when in the presence of some great man.

He looked after the management of ‘Madame’s’ proper‑ties and would shut himself away with her for hours on end in ‘Monsieur’s’ study. He lived in constant fear for his own reputation, had an inordinate respect for the judiciary and claimed to know some Latin.

Thinking that it would help the children to derive some enjoyment from their studies, he bought them an illustrated geography book. It depicted scenes from different parts of the world, cannibals wearing feathered head‑ dresses, a mon‑key abducting a young girl, a group of Bedouins in the desert, a whale being harpooned, and so on.

Paul carefully explained all these pictures to Félicité. In fact, this was the only time anyone ever taught her how to read a book.

The children received their lessons from Guyot, a rather pitiful character who worked at the Town Hall, who was noted for his fine handwriting and who used to sharpen his penknife on the sole of his shoe.

Whenever the weather was fine, the whole family would get up early and spend the day at the farm at Geffosses.

The farmyard there was on a slope, with the farmhouse in the middle. One could just see the sea, a little streak of grey in the distance.

Félicité would take a few slices of cold meat from her basket and they would eat in a room adjoining the dairy This room was all that now remained of a country house which had fallen into ruin. The paper hung in strips from the wall and fluttered in the draught. Madame Aubain sat with her head bowed, absorbed in her memories, the children hardly daring to speak. ‘Off you go and play, she would say. And off they went.

Paul would climb up into the barn, catch birds, play ducks and drakes on the pond or bang the great farm barrels with a stick to make them boom like drums.

Virginie would go and feed the rabbits or run off across the fields gathering cornflowers, showing her dainty embroidered knickers as she ran.

One evening in autumn, they were coming back through the fields.

The moon, which was in its first quarter, lit up part of the sky, and a mist drifted like a scarf over the windings of the river Toucques. A group of cattle, lying in the mid‑dle of a field, lazily watched them go by. When they came to the third field, a few of them got to their feet and stood in a circle in front of them. ‘There’s nothing to be fright‑ened of!’ said Félicité and, humming a wistful little tune as she approached, she went up to the nearest of the ani‑mals and patted it on the back. It turned away and the others did the same. But no sooner had they got through the next field when they heard a terrifying bellowing. It was a bull that had been hidden by the mist. It began to come towards the two women. Madame Aubain wanted to run. ‘No, no, we must not move too quickly!’ said Félicité. They walked more quickly, even so, and could hear the bull’s loud breathing getting nearer behind them and the pounding of its hoofs on the grass. They knew it was now galloping towards them! Félicité turned round to face it, grabbed clods of earth from the ground and flung them into the bull’s face. It lowered its muzzle, shook its horns and began to shudder and bellow with rage. Madame Aubain had now reached the edge of the field with the two children and was frantically trying to find a way of getting over the hedge. Félicité was still steadily retreating before the bull, throwing lumps of turf into its eyes and calling out, ‘Hurry up! Hurry up!’

Madame Aubain got down into the ditch, pushing first Virginie and then Paul in front of her. She fell several times as she tried to climb the bank and at last, by dint of sheer determination, she succeeded.

The bull had driven Félicité up against a gate and was blowing slaver into her face. A second later and it would have gored her. In the nick of time she managed to squeeze herself between two bars in the gate. The huge animal was taken completely by surprise and stopped in its tracks.

People in Pont‑ l’Evêque talked about this adventure for years afterwards. But Félicité never boasted about it and hardly seemed to realize that she had done anything heroic.

Virginie commanded all her attention. The frightening experience with the bull had affected her nerves and Mon sieur Poupart, the doctor, recommended sea bathing at Trouville.

In those days, very few people visited the resort. Mad ame Aubain made enquiries, sought the advice of Bourais and made preparations as if for a long journey.

The day before they left, the luggage was sent off in Liébard’s farm wagon. The next day he returned with two horses. One of them had a woman’s saddle with a velvet backrest and the other had a cloak rolled up across its back as a makeshift seat. Madame Aubain sat on this behind Liébard. Félicité looked after Virginie on the other horse and Paul rode separately on Monsieur Lechaptois’s donkey, which had been lent on the clear understanding that they took great care of it.

The road was so bad that the five‑ mile journey took them two hours. The horses sank up to their pasterns in the mud and lurched forward in order to pull themselves free. They lost their footing in the ruts and sometimes had to jump. At certain points on the road, Liébard’s mare would suddenly stop dead. Liébard would wait patiently for her to move forward again. As they rode on, he would tell them stories about the people who lived along the way, always adding a few personal comments of his own for good measure. In the town centre of Toucques, for instance, as they were passing alongside a house with nasturtiums growing around the windows, he said, with a shrug of his shoulders, ‘There’s a Madame Lehoussais lives there and, rather than take a young man . . .’ Félicitédid not hear the rest, for the horses had broken into a trot and the donkey had run on ahead. They turned down a track, a gate swung open, two young farmhands appeared and they all dismounted beside the manure‑ heap right outside the front door of the farmhouse.

Old Madame Liébard greeted her mistress with effusive expressions of delight. For lunch she served a sirloin of beef, along with tripe, black pudding, a fricassee of chicken, sparkling cider, a fruit tart and plums in brandy, all accom‑panied by a stream of compliments to Madame who seemed‘in much better health’, to Mademoiselle who had grown up into such ‘a fine looking young woman’, to Monsieur Paul who was such a ‘strapping’ young man, not forgetting their dear departed grandparents whom the Liébards had known personally, having been in service to the family for several generations. The farm, like the Liébards themselves, had an old‑ world feel to it. The beams in the ceiling were pitted with woodworm, the walls blackened with smoke the window panes grey with dust. There was an oak dresser, cluttered with all manner of implements – jugs, plates, pew ter bowls, wolf‑ traps, shears for the sheep and a huge syringe which particularly amused the children. In the three yards outside, there was not a single tree which did not have mushrooms growing at its foot or clumps of mistletoe in its branches. Several had been blown down by the wind but had begun to grow again where the trunk had been split and all of them were bent beneath the weight of apples. The thatched roofs looked like brown velvet of unequal thickness and weathered the fiercest winds. But the shed for the carts was falling down. Madame Aubain said that she would arrange to have it repaired and asked for the horses to be reharnessed.

It took them another half‑ hour to reach Trouville. The little caravan had to dismount when they came to the Ecores, a cliff which jutted out over the boats below Three minutes later they had arrived at the end of the quay and turned into the courtyard of the Golden Lamb an inn run by old Madame David.

Virginie very quickly began to recover her strength as a result of the change of air and of bathing in the sea. She did not have a bathing costume and so she went into the water wearing a chemise. Afterwards, her maid would help her to get dressed in a customs officer’s hut that was also used by the bathers.

In the afternoon, they would take the donkey and walk out beyond the Roches‑ Noires, towards Hennequeville. At first the path wound up between gently rolling mea‑dows like the lawn in a park and then came to a plateau where there were grazing pastures and ploughed fields. The path was lined by holly bushes which grew amongst the tangles of brambles, and here and there the branches of a large dead tree traced their zigzag patterns against the blue of the sky.

There was one particular field in which they usually stopped to rest themselves, looking down towards Deau‑ville to their left, Le Havre to their right and, in front of them, the open sea. It lay shimmering in the sunshine, as smooth as the surface of a mirror and so calm that they could barely hear the murmur of the waves. Sparrows twit‑tered from somewhere nearby and the great dome of the sky lay spread out above them. Madame Aubain would sit with her needlework, Virginie would sit beside her, plaiting rushes, Félicité gathered bunches of wild lavender and Paul, utterly bored, would always be itching to move on.

At other times they would take the ferry across the Toucques and go looking for shells. At low tide, sea urchins, ormers and jellyfish were left behind on the sand. The chil‑dren would chase after flecks of foam blown about by the breeze. The waves broke lazily on the sand from one end of the beach to the other. The beach stretched as far as the eye could see but was bounded on the landward side by sand dunes which separated it from the Marais, a broad meadow in the shape of a racecourse. As they walked back through it towards Trouville, which lay at the foot of the hill, the town appeared to grow bigger at every step they took and, with its motley assortment of houses, it seemed to blossom like a flower garden in colourful disarray.

When it was too hot, they kept to their room. The daz zling brightness outside cast bars of light through the slats in the window blinds. There was not a sound to be heard in the village. Not a soul ventured out into the streets. The prevailing quiet made everything seem all the more peace ful. From far away came the sound of the caulkers’hammers beating against the hull of a boat and the smell of tar was wafted to them on the listless breeze.

The most exciting event of the day was when the fishing boats came in. Once past the entrance buoys, they would begin to tack from side to side. Their main sails would be lowered to half‑ mast and, with their foresail swollen like a great balloon, they would come gliding through the splashing waves right into the middle of the harbour and suddenly drop anchor. The boat would then be brought alongside the quay. The sailors would hoist their fish ashore, still live and quivering. A line of carts was ready waiting and women in cotton bonnets rushed for ward to take the baskets and to kiss their menfolk.

One day one of these women came up to Félicité. A moment or two later, Félicité was back in the room at the inn, beside herself with excitement. She had found one of her lost sisters, and into the room walked Nastasie Barette, now Leroux, with a baby at her breast, another child holding her right hand and, on her left, a little ship’s boy with his hands on his hips and his beret over one ear.

After a quarter of an hour, Madame Aubain asked her to leave.

But after that there was no getting away from them. They would wait just outside the kitchen or follow them when they went for walks. The husband always kept well out of sight.

Félicité became very attached to them. She bought them a blanket, some shirts and a cooking stove. They were obviously out to take advantage of her. Madame Aubain was annoyed that Félicité was not more firm with them. She also took objection to the familiar way in which the nephew spoke to Paul. So, because Virginie had developed a cough and the weather had taken a turn for the worse, she returned to Pont‑ l’Evêque.

Monsieur Bourais offered his advice on choosing a good school for Paul. The one at Caen was generally con‑sidered to be the best. So Paul was sent away to Caen. He said his goodbyes bravely, really quite pleased that he was going to live somewhere where he would have some friends of his own.

Madame Aubain resigned herself to her son going away, knowing that he must have a good education. Vir‑ginie quickly got used to being on her own, but Félicitéfound the house very quiet without him. Soon, however she had something else to occupy her mind. From Christ mas onwards she had to take Virginie to catechism every day.

3

Genuflecting as she went in through the door, Félicitéwalked up the aisle beneath the high ceiling of the nave opened the door of Madame Aubain’s pew, sat herself down and looked all around her.

The children were seated in the choir stalls, the boys on the right and the girls on the left. The priest stood in front of them beside the lectern. One of the stained‑ glass win dows in the apse showed the Holy Spirit looking down on the Virgin Mary. In another, the Virgin knelt before the infant Jesus and behind the tabernacle there was a carving in wood representing Saint Michael slaying the dragon.

The priest began with a summary of the Holy Scrip tures. Félicité’s mind was filled with images of Paradise the Flood, the Tower of Babel, cities consumed by flames peoples dying and idols cast down. This dazzling recita of events instilled in her a wholesome respect for the Almighty and a profound fear of his wrath. She wept at the story of Christ’s Passion. Why had they crucified a man who was so kind to children, fed the hungry, gave sight to the blind, and who had chosen, out of his own gentle nature, to be born amongst the poor on the rough straw of a stable? Seed‑ time and harvest, the fruits of the vine, all those familiar things mentioned in the gospels had their place in her life too. They now seemed sanctified by contact with God. Félicité loved lambs all the more because of her love for the Lamb of God, and doves now reminded her of the Holy Spirit.

She found it difficult to imagine what the Holy Spirit actually looked like because he was not only a bird but sometimes a fire and sometimes a breath. Perhaps it was the light of the Holy Spirit that she would see at night‑ time, flickering at the edge of the marshes, or his breath which drove the clouds across the sky, or his voice which made the church bells ring so beautifully. She sat rapt in adoration of these wonders, delighting in the cool‑ness of the stone walls and the peacefulness of the church.

Of church dogma she understood not a word and did not even attempt to understand it. As the curé stood explaining it all to the children and the children repeated what they had learnt, Félicité would drop off to sleep, to be woken suddenly by the clatter of wooden shoes on the stone floor as the children left the church. And so Félicité came to learn her catechism by dint of hearing the children recite it, for her own religious education had been neglected when she was young. From then on, she copied the religious obser‑vances of Virginie, fasting when she fasted and going to confession whenever she did. For the feast of Corpus Christi, Félicité and Virginie made an altar of repose together.

For days beforehand, Félicité fretted over the prepar ations for Virginie’s first communion. She worried about her shoes, her rosary, her missal and her gloves. Her hands trembled as she helped Madame Aubain to dress her.

All through the mass she was on tenterhooks. One half of the choir stalls was hidden from her sight by Monsieur Bourais, but straight in front of her she could see the flock of young girls all wearing white crowns over their lowered veils and looking like a field of snow. Even from a dis tance, she could recognize her beloved little Virginie by the delicate line of her neck and her attitude of reverent contemplation. The bell tinkled. They all bowed their heads and knelt in silence. Then, with a mighty flourish from the organ, the choir and congregation sang the Agnus Dei. After the boys had processed forwards, the girls stood up. With their hands joined in prayer, they moved slowly towards the candle‑ lit altar, knelt at the altar‑ step, received the Host one by one and returned in the same order to their place in the choir stalls. When it came to Virginie’s turn, Félicité leant further forwards so that she could see her and, with that singular imagination that is born of true love, she felt she was herself Virginie assuming her expression, wearing her dress and with her heart beating inside her breast. As Virginie opened her mouth, Félicité closed her eyes and almost fainted.

The next morning, bright and early, Félicité went to the sacristy and asked to be given communion. She received it with due reverence but did not experience the same rapture.

Madame Aubain wanted the best possible education for her daughter and, because Guyot was unable to teach her either English or music, she resolved to send her to the Ursuline convent school in Honfleur.

Virginie had no objection to this plan but Félicité was most unhappy and felt that Madame was being too strict. However, she came to accept that it was not really for her to decide and that her mistress probably knew best.

Then one day, an old carriage drew up outside the door. Out of it got a nun who had come to collect Mademois‑elle. Félicité loaded the luggage up on to the rack, issued some parting instructions to the driver and put six pots of jam, a dozen pears and a bunch of violets in the boot.

Just as they were about to leave, Virginie burst into tears. She clung to her mother, who kissed her on the forehead and kept telling her: ‘Come, come, we must be brave!’ The step was pulled up and the carriage drove away.

When it had gone, Madame Aubain broke down and that evening all her friends, Monsieur and Madame Lormeau, Madame Lechaptois, the two Rochefeuille sis‑ters, Monsieur de Houppeville and Bourais, came round to comfort her.

At first, the loss of her daughter left her feeling very sad. But she received letters from her on three days each week and on the other days she wrote back to her, walked in her garden, read a little and so managed to occupy her time.

Every morning, out of habit, Félicité would go into Virginie’s bedroom and gaze at the walls. She missed being able to comb her hair for her, tie her bootlaces and tuck her up in bed; she missed seeing her sweet little face always beside her and holding her hand when they went out for walks. For want of something to do, she tried to take up lace work. But she was too clumsy with her fingers and she kept breaking the threads. She could not put her mind to anything and was losing sleep. She was, in her own words, ‘all empty inside’.

In order to provide herself with ‘a bit of company’, she asked Madame Aubain if her nephew Victor might be allowed to visit her.

He would always arrive on Sundays, just after mass, rosy cheeked, his shirt unbuttoned and bringing with him the smells of the countryside through which he had travelled She straight away laid the table for him. They would eat lunch sitting opposite each other, Félicité taking care to eat as little as possible so as to save on expense and giving Victor so much to eat that he ended up falling asleep. As the first bell for vespers began to ring, she would wake him up, give his trousers a good brush, tie his tie, and make her way to church, leaning on his arm like a proud mother

His parents always told him to make sure he brought something back with him, a bag of sugar, a piece of soap a little brandy or even money. He brought with him any of his clothes that needed mending and Félicité always did the work willingly, glad of any opportunity of encour‑aging him to visit her again.

In August, Victor went to join his father on his sea trips along the coast.

It was the beginning of the school holidays and it was some consolation to Félicité to have the children back at home. But Paul had become rather temperamental and Virginie was now too grown‑ up to be treated as a little child, which created a sense of awkwardness and distance between them.

Victor’s travels took him to Morlaix, to Dunkirk and to Brighton and after each trip he brought back a present for Félicité. The first was a little box made out of shells, the second a coffee cup and the third a big gingerbread man. He was growing into a handsome young man, with a fine figure, the first signs of a moustache, a frank and open expression and a little leather cap which he wore perched on the back of his head like a sea pilot. He would entertain Félicité by telling her stories laced with all sorts of nautical jargon.

One Monday, 14 July 1819 (it was a date that Félicitéwas never to forget), Victor announced that he had been signed on to the crew of an ocean‑ going ship and that in two days’ time he would be taking the night ferry from Honfleur to join his schooner, which was due shortly to set sail from Le Havre. He might be away for two years.

The prospect of such a long separation left Félicitéfeeling very saddened. In order to say one final farewell to him, on the Wednesday evening, after Madame had finished her dinner, she put on her clogs and ran the ten miles from Pont‑ l’Evêque to Honfleur.

When she came to the Calvary, instead of turning left she turned right, got lost in the shipyards and had to retrace her steps. She asked directions from some passers‑ by, who told her she would have to hurry. She walked all the way round the harbour, which was full of boats, getting caught up in the moorings as she went Suddenly the ground seemed to fall away beneath her beams of light criss‑ crossed before her eyes and she thought she must be losing her senses when she saw some horses in the sky overhead.

On the quayside, more horses were neighing, frightened by the sea. They were being hoisted into the air by a der rick and then lowered into a boat which was already crammed with passengers trying to squeeze their way between barrels of cider, baskets of cheese and sacks of grain. Hens were cackling and the captain was swearing One of the deck‑ hands, apparently oblivious to everything around him, stood leaning against the cat‑ head. Félicitéhad not recognized him and was calling out ‘Victor!’ again and again. He looked up and she rushed forward, but just at that moment the gangway was suddenly pulled ashore.

The boat moved out of the harbour, hauled along by a group of women who sang in chorus as they went about their work. Its ribs creaked and heavy waves lashed its bows. The sail swung round and hid everyone from view. The surface of the sea shone like silver in the moonlight and on it the ship appeared as a black spot, growing paler as it moved away. Eventually it was swallowed up in the distance and vanished from sight.

Returning home, Félicité passed by the Calvary and was taken by a sudden desire to commend to God’s mercy all that she held dear. She stood there praying for a long time, with tears running down her cheeks and her eyes fixed on the clouds above. The town was fast asleep; the only people about were the customs men. Water could be heard gushing through the holes in the lock‑ gate like a running torrent. A clock struck two.

The convent would not be open to visitors before day‑break and Félicité knew that, if she arrived back late, Madame was sure to be annoyed. So, although she would have loved just one small kiss from Virginie, she set off back home. The maids at the inn were just waking up as she walked into Pont‑ l’Evêque.

So poor little Victor was to spend months on end being tossed around on the waves! His previous trips at sea had not bothered her. England and Brittany were places one came back from. But America, the colonies and the Antil‑les were lost in some unknown region on the other side of the world.

From the day he left, Félicité could not stop thinking about her nephew. When it was hot and sunny, she wor‑ried that he might be thirsty and when there was a storm, she feared he might be struck by lightning. As she listened to the wind howling in the chimney and blowing slates off the roof, she pictured him buffered by the same storm clinging to the top of a broken mast and being flung backwards into a sheet of foam. At other times, prompted by her recollection of the pictures in the geography book she imagined him being eaten by savages, captured by monkeys in a forest or dying on some deserted beach But she never spoke about these worries to anyone.

Madame Aubain had worries of her own about her daughter.

The sisters at the convent said that she was an affec tionate child, but over‑ sensitive. The slightest emotion unsettled her and she had to give up playing the piano.

Her mother insisted that she wrote home regularly. One morning, when the postman had failed to appear, she could scarcely contain her impatience and kept pacing backwards and forwards in her room between her arm chair and the window. This really was extraordinary! No news for four days!

Thinking that her own situation might serve as some comfort to her mistress, Félicité ventured:

‘But Madame, I haven’t received any news for six months!’

‘News from whom?’

‘Why, news from my nephew,’ Félicité gently replied.

‘Oh, your nephew!’ And with a shrug of her shoulders, Madame Aubain began pacing about the room again, as if to say, ‘I hadn’t given him a thought! And in any case, he’s no concern of mine! A mere ship’s boy, a scrounger; he’s not worth bothering about! But someone like my daughter . . . Really!’

Although Félicité had been fed such rough treatment since she was a child, she felt very offended by Madame Aubain. But she soon got over it.

After all, it was to be expected that Madame should get upset about her own daughter.

For Félicité, the two children were of equal importance; they were bound together by her love for them and it seemed right that they should share the same fate.

Félicité learnt from the chemist that Victor’s ship had arrived in Havana. He had read the announcement in a newspaper.

Because of its association with cigars, Félicité imagined Havana to be a place in which the only thing people did was to smoke and she pictured Victor walking amongst crowds of Negroes in a cloud of tobacco smoke. Was it possible to return from Havana by land, ‘if need be’? How far was it from Pont‑ l’Evêque? In order to find out, she went to consult Monsieur Bourais.

He reached for his atlas and launched into a disquisition on lines of longitude. Félicité was utterly bewildered. Bourais sat in front of her, beaming smugly to himself, like the know‑ all he was. Eventually, he picked up his pencil and pointed to an almost invisible black dot in one of the little indentations in the contour of an oval‑ shaped patch on the map. ‘Here it is,’ he said. Félicité peered closely at the map. The network of coloured lines was a strain on her eyes, but it told her nothing. Bourais asked her what was puzzling her and she asked him if he would show her the house in which Victor was living. Bourais raised his arms in the air, sneezed and roared with laugh ter, delighted to come across someone so simple‑ minded Félicité, whose understanding was so limited that she probably even expected to see a picture of her nephew could not understand what he found so funny.

It was a fortnight after this, at his usual time on market day, that Liébard came into the kitchen and handed Féli cité a letter which he had received from her brother‑ in‑ law As neither of them could read, Félicité showed the letter to her mistress.

Madame Aubain, who was counting the stitches on a piece of knitting, put her work to one side, opened the letter, gave a sudden start and then, lowering her voice and looking very serious, she said, ‘They are sending you . . . bad news. Your nephew . . .’

Victor was dead. That was all the letter said.

Félicité sank down on to a chair and leant her head against the wall. Her eyelids closed and suddenly flushed pink. She remained there, her head bowed, her hands hang ing limply at her side, staring in front of her and repeating over and over again, ‘The poor boy! The poor boy!’

Liébard stood looking at her and sighing. Madame Aubain was shaking slightly.

She suggested that Félicité might go and see her sister at Trouville.

Félicité gave a wave of her hand to indicate that it was not necessary.

There was a silence. Old Liébard thought it best to leave.

When he had gone, Félicité said, ‘It doesn’t matter a bit, not to them it doesn’t.’

She lowered her head again and sat there, now and then toying distractedly with the knitting needles that lay on the work‑ table.

A group of women passed by in the yard, wheeling a barrow‑ load of dripping linen.

Félicité caught sight of them through the window and suddenly remembered that she had washing to do herself. She had passed the lye through it the day before and today it needed rinsing. She got up and left the room.

Her washing board and her tub were on the bank of the Toucques. She flung her pile of chemises on to the ground beside the river, rolled up her sleeves and seized her battledore. The drubbing could be heard in all the neighbouring gardens. The fields lay deserted and the wind rippled the surface of the river. On the river‑ bed, long strands of weed drifted with the current, like the hair of corpses floating downstream in the water. Félicité man‑aged to restrain her grief and was very brave until the evening, but when she was alone in her room she gave in to it, lying prone on her mattress with her face buried in the pillow and pressing her fists to her temples.

Much later, she came to learn the circumstances of Vic tor’s death from the captain of his ship. He had caught yellow fever and had been bled too much in the hospital Four separate doctors had given him the same treatment and he had died immediately. The chief doctor’s comment was, ‘Good, that’s one more to add to the list!’

Victor had always been treated cruelly by his parents and Félicité preferred not to see them again. They did not get in touch with Félicité either; perhaps they had simply forgotten about her or perhaps poverty had hardened their hearts.

Virginie was now growing weaker.

Difficulty in breathing, a persistent cough, a constant high temperature and pale blotches on her cheeks all pointed to some underlying disorder. Monsieur Poupart had advised a holiday in Provence. Madame Aubain decided to follow his advice and would have brought Virginie back home immediately, had it not been for the weather at Pont‑ l’Evêque.

She had a standing arrangement with a job‑ master, who drove her to the convent every Tuesday. In the convent garden there was a terrace overlooking the Seine where Virginie would walk up and down over the fallen vine leaves, leaning on her mother’s arm. She would look out at the sails in the distance and the whole sweep of the estuary from the chateau at Tancarville to the lighthouses at Le Havre. Sometimes the sun would suddenly break through the clouds and make her blink. Afterwards, they would rest under the arbour. Her mother had procured a little flask of the choicest Malaga wine, from which Virginie would take just two tiny sips, laughing at the thought of making herself tipsy.

She began to recover her strength. Autumn gradually slipped by. Félicité did all she could to reassure Madame Aubain. But one evening, on her way back from an errand in the town, she noticed Monsieur Poupart’s gig standing at the front door. Monsieur Poupart himself was in the entrance hall and Madame Aubain was fastening her bonnet.

‘Bring me my foot‑ warmer, my purse and my gloves! Hurry!’

Virginie had pneumonia and Madame feared she was beyond recovery.

‘I’m sure it’s not that bad,’ said the doctor, and the two of them climbed into his carriage, with the snowflakes falling in great flurries around them. Night was drawing on and it was bitterly cold.

Félicité dashed into the church to light a candle and then began to run after Monsieur Poupart’s gig. It was a full hour before she caught up with it. She jumped up behind it and clung to the fringe. Suddenly a thought occurred to her. ‘The gate to the courtyard was not locked! What if thieves should break in!’ She jumped back down on to the road.

The next day, at the very first sign of daylight, she went to the doctor’s house. The doctor had returned but had already left again to visit patients in the country. She waited at the inn, thinking that someone or other might arrive with a letter. Eventually, in the half‑ light of morn ing, she boarded the Lisieux stagecoach.

The convent was situated at the foot of a steep narrow street. When she was about half‑ way down the street, she began to make out strange sounds coming from the con vent; it was the tolling of a death bell. ‘It must be for someone else’, she thought, and gave the door‑ knocker a loud rap.

After some considerable time, she heard the shuffle of foot steps, the door was inched open and a nun appeared

The good sister solemnly announced that ‘she had just passed away’. At precisely the same moment, the bell of Saint‑ Léonard’s began to toll even more strongly.

Félicité went up to the second floor.

She stood in the doorway of the bedroom and could see Virginie laid out on her back, her hands clasped together, her mouth open and her head tilted backwards Above her head and inclined towards her was a black crucifix; her face was whiter than the drapes which hung stiffly around her. Madame Aubain lay hugging the foot of the bed and sobbing wildly. The Mother Superior stood beside her on the right. On the chest of drawers three candlesticks gave out little circles of red light; out side, the fog whitened the window panes. Some nuns came and led Madame Aubain away.

Félicité did not leave Virginie’s bedside for two whole nights. She sat there, repeating the same prayers over and over again; she would get up to sprinkle holy water on the sheets, then come back to her chair and continue to gaze fixedly at the dead girl. At the end of her first night’s vigil, she noticed that her face was beginning to turn yellow, her lips were turning blue, her nose had grown thinner and her eyes had become sunken. More than once she kissed her eyes and would not have been in the least surprised if Virginie had opened them again; to minds like hers, the supernatural appears perfectly ordinary. She laid her out, wrapped her in her shroud, put her in her coffin, placed a wreath upon her and spread out her hair. Her hair was fair and amazingly long for a girl of her age. Félicité cut off a large lock of it and slipped half of it into her bosom, resolv‑ing that it would never be separated from her.

The body was brought back to Pont‑ l’Evêque, accord‑ing to Madame Aubain’s instructions. Madame Aubain followed the hearse in a closed carriage.

After the funeral mass, it took another three‑ quarters of an hour to get to the cemetery. Paul led the procession, sobbing. Monsieur Bourais walked behind him, followed in turn by various dignitaries from Pont‑ l’Evêque, the women, all wearing black veils, and lastly Félicité. Félicitécould not help thinking of her nephew and, having been unable to offer him these last honours, she now felt an added grief, as if he were being buried along with Virginie.

Madame Aubain’s despair knew no bounds.

At first she rebelled against God, thinking it was unjust that He should take her daughter from her when she had never done any wrong and when there was nothing for her to feel guilty about. But perhaps there was. She should have taken her to the South. Other doctors would have cured her. She blamed herself, wished she could follow her daughter to the grave and called out in anguish in the middle of her dreams. One dream in particular tormented her. Her husband, dressed like a sailor, had returned from a long voyage and, choking back his tears told her that he had received an order to take Virginie away. They then both racked their brains to think of a hiding place for her.

On one occasion she came in from the garden dis traught. Just a moment before (and she pointed to the spot), the father and daughter had appeared in front of her, one after the other. They were not doing anything; they were just staring at her.

For several months she remained in her room, totally listless. Félicité gently admonished her, telling her that she should look after herself for the sake of her son and her late husband and in memory of ‘her’.

‘Her?’ said Madame Aubain as though waking from sleep. ‘Oh yes, of course. You haven’t forgotten her, have you!’ This was a reference to the cemetery, which Madame Aubain had been expressly forbidden to visit.

Félicité went there every day.

On the stroke of four, she would walk past the row of houses, climb the hill, open the gate and approach Virginie’s grave. There was a little column of pink marble standing on a stone base, with a small garden surrounded by chains. The separate beds could hardly be seen beneath the covering of flowers. Félicité would water the leaves, place fresh sand on the garden and get down on her hands and knees to make sure the ground was properly weeded. When Madame Aubain was eventually able to come to see the grave, she found it a source of comfort, a kind of consolation for her loss.

The years passed, one very much like another, marked only by the annual recurrence of the church festivals: Easter, the Assumption, All Saints’ Day. It was only little incidents in their daily lives that, in later years, enabled them to recall a particular date. Thus in 1825 two glaziers whitewashed the entrance hall; in 1827 a part of the roof fell into the courtyard and nearly killed a passer‑ by. In the summer of 1828 it was Madame’s turn to distribute consecrated bread to the parishioners. This was also about the same time that Bourais mysteriously left the town. One by one, all their old acquaintances went away: Guyot, Liébard, Madame Lechaptois, Robelin and old Uncle Gremanville, who had been paralysed for many years.

One night, the driver of the mail‑ coach arrived in Pont‑ l’Evêque with news of the July Revolution. A few days later, a new subprefect was appointed: the Baron de Larsonnière, who had previously been a consul in Amer‑ica. He arrived in Pont‑ l’Evêque accompanied not only by his wife but also by his sister‑ in‑ law and three young girls, all of them already quite grown up. They were often to be seen on their lawn, dressed in long, flowing smocks They also had a Negro servant and a parrot. They called on Madame Aubain to pay their respects and she made a point of doing likewise. As soon as she spotted them approaching in the distance, Félicité would come running in to tell Madame Aubain that they were on their way But there was only one thing that could really awaken her interest and that was her son’s letters.

Paul seemed unable to settle down to a career and spent much of his time in the tavern. Madame Aubain would pay off his debts, but he immediately ran up new ones She would sit at her knitting by the window and heave sighs that Félicité could hear even in the kitchen, where she was working at her spinning wheel.

The two women would often take a stroll together alongside the trellised wall of the garden. They still talked constantly about Virginie, wondering whether she would have liked such and such a thing or trying to imagine what she would have said on such and such an occasion.

All her belongings were still in a cupboard in the chil dren’s bedroom. Madame Aubain had avoided looking inside it as much as possible. Then, one summer day, she resigned herself. Moths came flying from the cupboard.

Virginie’s frocks hung in a row beneath a shelf upon which there were three dolls, some hoops, a set of doll’s furniture and her own hand‑ basin. The two women took out all the petticoats, stockings and handkerchiefs and spread them out on the two beds before folding them again. This sorry collection of objects lay there, caught in a beam of sunlight which brought out all the stains and the creases that had been made by the movements of Virginie’s body. The air was warm, the sky was blue, a blackbird sang out‑side and the world seemed to be utterly at peace. They found a little chestnut‑ coloured hat made of long‑ piled plush, but it had been completely destroyed by the moths. Félicité asked if she might have it as a keepsake. The two women looked at each other and their eyes filled with tears. Madame Aubain opened her arms and Félicité threw herself into them. Mistress and servant embraced each other, unit‑ing their grief in a kiss which made them equal.

It was the first time that this had ever happened, Mad‑ame Aubain being, by nature, very reserved. Félicité could not have been more grateful if she had been offered a priceless gift and from then on she doted on her mistress with dog‑ like fidelity and the reverence that might be accorded to a saint.

As time went by, Félicité’s natural kind‑ heartedness increased.

One day she heard the sound of drums from a regiment marching along the street and she stood at the door with a jug of cider, handing out drinks to the soldiers. She helped to nurse cholera victims and to look after the refu‑gees from Poland. One of the Poles even said he would like to marry her, but they had a serious argument when she came back one morning from the angelus to find him ensconced in her kitchen, calmly helping himself to a salad which she had prepared for lunch.

After the Poles had left, she turned her attention to an old man by the name of Colmiche, who was rumoured to have committed terrible atrocities in ’93. He now lived down by the river in a ruined pigsty. The boys in the town used to spy on him through the cracks in the wall and throw stones at him as he lay coughing and choking on his straw bed. He had long, straggling hair, his eyelids were inflamed and on one arm there was a swelling bigger than his head. Félicité provided him with linen and did what she could to keep his hovel clean; she even hoped she might be able to install him in the outhouse, where he would not disturb Madame. When the tumour burst she changed his dressing every single day. Sometimes she would bring him a small piece of cake or help him outside on to a bundle of straw, where he could lie in the sun The poor old wretch would splutter and shake and thank her in a barely audible whisper, saying he could not bear to lose her and stretching out his hands the minute he saw her preparing to leave him. He died and Félicité had a mass said for the repose of his soul.

On the same day, she received the most wonderful sur prise. Just as she was serving dinner, Madame de Larsonnière’s Negro servant arrived, carrying the parrot in its cage, along with its perch, chain and padlock. There was a note from the Baroness, informing Madame Aubain that her husband had been promoted to a Préfecture and that they were leaving Pont‑ l’Evêque that very evening. She asked Madame Aubain if she would be kind enough to accept the parrot as a memento of their friendship and as a token of her respect.

The parrot had been a source of wonder to Félicité for a long time, for it came from America, a word which always reminded her of Victor. She had already questioned the servant about it and, on one occasion, had even said that ‘Madame would be delighted to look after it!’

The Negro had mentioned this to his mistress and, because she could not take it away with her, she readily seized this opportunity of getting it off her hands.

4

The parrot was called Loulou. His body was green, the tips of his wings were pink, the top of his head was blue and his breast was gold‑ coloured.

Unfortunately, he had the tiresome habit of chewing his perch and he kept plucking out his feathers, scattering his droppings everywhere and splashing the water from his bath all over his cage. He thoroughly irritated Madame Aubain and so she gave him to Félicité to look after.

She decided she would teach him to speak and he was very soon able to say, ‘Pretty boy!’, ‘Your servant, sir!’and ‘Hail Mary!’ She put him near the front door and a number of visitors were surprised that he would not answer to the name ‘Polly’, which is what all parrots are supposed to be called. Some people said he looked more like a turkey or called him a blockhead. Félicité found their jibes very hurtful. There was a curious stubborn streak in Loulou which never ceased to amaze Félicité; he would refuse to talk the minute anyone looked at him!

Even so, there was no doubt that he appreciated com pany. On Sundays, when the Rochefeuille sisters Monsieur de Houppeville and some of Madame Aubain’s new friends – the apothecary Onfroy, Monsieur Varin and Captain Mathieu – came round to play cards, Loulou would beat on the window panes with his wings and make such a furious commotion that no one could hear them selves speak.

He obviously found Bourais’s face a source of great amusement. He only had to see it and he would break into fits of uncontrollable laughter. His squawks could be heard echoing round the yard. The neighbours would come to their windows and start laughing too. To avoid being seen by the parrot, Bourais would slink past the house along the side of the wall, hiding his face behind his hat. He would go down to the river and come into the house by way of the back garden. The looks he gave the bird were not of the tender variety.

The butcher’s boy had once flipped Loulou on the ear for trying to help himself to something from his basket and, since then, Loulou always tried to give him a peck through his shirt. Fabu threatened to wring his neck although he was not cruel by nature, despite what the tattoos on his arms and his long side whiskers might have led one to believe. In fact, he was rather fond of the parrot and, just for the fun of it, he had even tried to teach him a few swear words. Félicité was alarmed at the thought of his acquiring such bad habits and moved him into the kitchen. His chain was removed and he was allowed to wander all over the house.

When he came down the stairs, he would position the curved part of his beak on the step in front of him and then raise first his right foot, followed by his left. Félicitéwas always worried that these weird acrobatics would make the parrot giddy. He fell ill and could not talk or eat due to an ulcer under his tongue, such as chickens sometimes have. Félicité cured him herself, extracting the lump in his mouth with her fingernails. One day, Mon‑sieur Paul was silly enough to blow cigar smoke up his nose. On another occasion, when Madame Lormeau was teasing him with the end of her parasol, he bit off the metal ferrule with his beak. Then there was the time he got lost.

Félicité had put him out on the grass to get some fresh air. She went indoors for a minute and, when she came back, the parrot had disappeared. She searched for him in the bushes, by the river and even on the rooftops, oblivi‑ous to her mistress’s shouts of ‘Do be careful! You must be mad!’ She then hunted through every single garden in Pont‑ l’Evêque and stopped all the people in the street, asking, ‘You don’t happen to have seen my parrot by any chance?’ Those who did not already know the parrot were given a full description. Suddenly, she thought she saw something green flying about behind the mills at the bot tom of the hill. But when she got to the top of the hill there was nothing to be seen. A pedlar told her he had definitely seen the bird only a short while ago in old Mad ame Simon’s shop at Saint‑ Melaine. Félicité ran all the way there, but nobody knew what she was talking about In the end she came back home, utterly exhausted, her shoes torn to shreds and feeling sick at heart. She sat down on the middle of the garden bench, next to Madame, and she was telling her everything that she had done when she suddenly felt something drop gently on to her shoulder It was Loulou! What on earth had he been up to? Perhaps he had just gone for a little walk around the town!

It took Félicité quite a while to recover from this shock If the truth were known, she never really recovered from it completely.

She caught tonsillitis, as a result of getting thoroughly chilled, and shortly afterwards developed pains in her ears. Within three years she was completely deaf and spoke in a very loud voice, even in church. Even though her sins could have been proclaimed in every corner of the diocese without bringing any discredit to her or caus ing offence to others, the curé decided that it would now be best to hear her confession in the sacristy.

Imaginary buzzing noises in her head added to her troubles. Her mistress would often say, ‘Goodness me! You’re just being silly!’ Félicité would answer, ‘Yes, Mad‑ame,’ still looking around her to see where the noises were coming from.

She became enclosed in an ever‑ diminishing world of her own; gone for ever was the pealing of church bells and the lowing of cattle in the fields. Every living thing passed by her in ghostly silence. Only one sound now reached her ears, and that was the voice of her parrot.

Almost as if he were deliberately trying to entertain her, he would imitate the clicking of the turnspit, the shrill cry of the fishmonger or the sound of sawing from the joiner’s shop on the other side of the street. Whenever the front door bell rang, he would imitate Madame Aubain: ‘Félicité! The door, the door!’

They would hold conversations with each other, the parrot endlessly repeating the three stock phrases from his repertory and Félicité replying with words that made very little sense but which all came straight from the heart. In her isolation, Loulou was almost a son to her; she simply doted on him. He used to climb up her fingers, peck at her lips and hang on to her shawl. Sometimes she would put her face close to his and shake her head in the way a nurse does to a baby, with the wings of her bonnet and the bird’s wings all fluttering together.

When storm clouds gathered and thunder rumbled, the bird would squawk loudly, no doubt remembering the sudden cloud‑ bursts of his native forests. The sound of falling rain would send him into a frenzy. He would fly madly about the house, shooting up to the ceiling, knock ing everything over and finally escaping through the window into the garden to splash around in the puddles But he would soon come back, perch on one of the fire‑ dogs, jump up and down to dry his feathers and then proudly display his tail or his beak.

One morning in the terrible winter of 1837, when she had put him near the fireplace because of the cold, she found him dead in his cage, hanging head downwards with his claws caught in the metal bars. He had probably died of a stroke, but the thought crossed Félicité’s mind that he might have been poisoned with parsley and, although there was no definite proof, her suspicions fell on Fabu.

She wept so much that her mistress eventually said,‘Well, why don’t you have him stuffed?’

Félicité went to consult the chemist, who had always been kind to the parrot.

He wrote to Le Havre and a man by the name of Fel‑lacher agreed to do the job. But, knowing that the mail‑ coach sometimes mislaid parcels, Félicité decided that she would take the parrot as far as Honfleur herself.

The road ran between endless lines of apple trees, bare and leafless. Ice lay in the ditches. Dogs barked as she walked past the farms. With her hands tucked under her mantlet and her basket on her arm, Félicité walked briskly along the middle of the road in her little black clogs.

She followed the road through the forest, passed Le Haut‑ Chêne and eventually reached Saint‑ Gatien.

On the road behind her, in a cloud of dust and gather‑ing speed on its way down the hill, a mail‑ coach at full gallop came rushing towards her like a whirlwind. The coachman, seeing that this woman was making no attempt to get out of the way, stood up and looked out over the roof of the carriage and both he and his postilion shouted at her for all their worth. The four horses, which he was vainly trying to rein in, galloped faster and faster towards her and the leading pair struck her as they went by. With a sharp tug on the reins, the coachman forced them to swerve on to the side of the road. In his rage, he raised his arm and lashed out at her with his long whip as the coach lurched past. The blow struck Félicité full across her face and the upper part of her body, and with such force that she fell flat on her back.

The first thing she did when she regained consciousness was to open her basket. Fortunately, Loulou had come to no harm. She felt a burning sensation on her right cheek. She put her hand to her face and saw that her hand was red. She was bleeding.

She sat down on a pile of stones and dabbed her face with her handkerchief. Then she ate a crust of bread which she had brought with her in case she needed it and tried to take her mind off her wound by looking at the parrot.

As she came to the top of the hill at Ecquemauville, she saw the lights of Honfleur twinkling in the night like clusters of stars and, beyond them, the sea, stretching dimly into the distance. She was suddenly overcome with a fit of giddiness and her wretched childhood, the disap pointment of her first love affair, the departure of her nephew and the death of Virginie all came flooding back to her like the waves of an incoming tide, welling up inside her and taking her breath away.

She insisted on speaking personally to the captain of the ship and, although she did not tell him what was in her parcel, she asked him to look after it carefully.

Fellacher kept the parrot for a long time. He kept prom ising that it would arrive the following week. After six months, he announced that a box had been dispatched but that was the last they heard of it. Félicité began to fear that Loulou would never come back. ‘He has been stolen, I know it!’ she thought to herself.

But at last he arrived. And quite magnificent he looked too, perched on a branch which was screwed on to a mahogany plinth, with one foot held raised, his head cocked to one side and holding in his beak a nut which the taxidermist, in order to add a little touch of grandeur had gilded.

Félicité installed him in her room.

This room, which few were allowed into, was filled with a mixture of religious knick‑ knacks and other miscellan eous bits and pieces and resembled something between a chapel and a bazaar.

A large wardrobe made it awkward to open the door fully. Opposite the window that looked out on to the gar den was a smaller circular window which looked out on to the courtyard. There was a plain, unsprung bed and beside it a table with a water jug, two combs and a small cake of blue soap on a chipped plate. Fixed to the walls were rosa‑ries, medals, several pictures of the Virgin and a holy‑ water stoop made out of a coconut shell. On the chest of drawers, which was draped with a cloth like an altar, was the shell box that Victor had given her, a watering can and a ball, some handwriting books, the illustrated geography book and a pair of little ankle boots. Hanging by its two ribbons from the nail which supported the mirror was the little plush hat! These keepsakes meant so much to Félicité. She had even kept one of Monsieur’s frock‑ coats. If there was anything that Madame Aubain wanted to get rid of, she would find a place for it in her room, like the artificial flowers beside her chest of drawers and the portrait of the Comte d’Artois in the window recess.

Loulou was placed on a little shelf made especially for the purpose and fixed to a chimney breast which pro‑truded into the room. Every morning, as she woke, she would catch sight of him in the early morning light and would recall the days gone by, trivial incidents, right down to the tiniest detail, remembered not in sadness but in perfect tranquillity.

Being unable to hold a conversation with anyone, she lived her life as if in a sleepwalker’s trance. The only thing that seemed capable of bringing her back to life was the Corpus Christi procession, when she would visit all the neighbours, collecting candlesticks and mats to decorate the altar of repose that was always set up outside in the street.

When she went to church, she would sit gazing at the picture of the Holy Spirit and it struck her that it looked rather like her parrot. The resemblance was even more striking in an Epinal colour print depicting Our Lord’s baptism. The dove had wings of crimson and a body of emerald‑ green and it looked for all the world like Loulou Félicité bought the picture and hung it in place of the por trait of the Comte d’Artois, so that she could see them both together at the same time. In her mind, the one became associated with the other, the parrot becoming sanctified by connection with the Holy Spirit and the Holy Spirit in turn acquiring added life and meaning. Surely it could not have been a dove that God had chosen to speak through since doves cannot talk. It must have been one of Loulou’s ancestors. Félicité would say her prayers with her eyes turned towards the picture but every now and then she would turn her head slightly to look at the parrot.

She thought of entering the sisterhood of the Ladies of the Virgin but Madame Aubain persuaded her not to

There now occurred an event of considerable importance – Paul’s wedding.

Having worked first as a lawyer’s clerk, Paul had sub sequently tried his hand at business, worked for the Customs and for the Inland Revenue and had even con sidered joining the Department of Forests and Waterways. Now, at the age of thirty‑ six, as if by divine inspiration he had suddenly discovered his vocation – the Registry Office! Indeed, he had displayed such a talent for the job that one of the inspectors had offered him his daughter’s hand in marriage and had promised to use his influence to advance his career.

By now, Paul took his responsibilities seriously and he brought his intended to see his mother.

Not a thing at Pont‑ l’Evêque met with her approval. She expected to be treated like royalty and she hurt Félicité’s feelings badly. Madame Aubain was relieved to see her go.

The following week, they learned of the death of Mon‑sieur Bourais in an inn somewhere in Lower Brittany. Rumour had it that he had committed suicide. This turned out to be true and questions were raised about his honesty. Madame Aubain went through her accounts and the catalogue of his misdeeds soon became apparent: embez‑zlement of arrears of rent, undeclared sales of wood, forged receipts, and so forth. It was also discovered that he was the father of an illegitimate child and that he was having ‘an illicit relationship with someone from Dozulé’.

This sordid business was a source of great distress to Madame Aubain. In March 1853, she began to feel pains in her chest. A grey coating covered her tongue. She was treated with leeches but this failed to improve her breath‑ing. On the ninth evening of her illness, she died, aged just seventy‑ two.

People took her to be younger than this because of her dark hair, which she had always worn in bandeaux round her pale, pockmarked face. She had very few friends to lament her death; there was a certain haughtiness about her that had always kept people at a distance.

Félicité wept for her in a way that servants rarely weep for their masters. That Madame should die before her disturbed her whole way of thinking; it seemed to go against the natural order of things; it was something unacceptable and unreal.

Ten days later, just as soon as they could get there from Besançon, the heirs arrived on the scene. Madame Aubain’s daughter‑ in‑ law went through all the drawers chose a few pieces of furniture for herself and sold what was left. Then they all went back to the Registry Office.

Madame’s armchair, her little table, her foot‑ warmer and the eight chairs had all gone! On the walls, yellow patches marked the places where pictures had once hung They had taken away the children’s beds, along with their mattresses, and the cupboard had been cleared of all Virginie’s things. Félicité went from room to room heartbroken.

The following day, a notice appeared on the front door. The apothecary shouted into Félicité’s ear that the house was for sale.

Félicité’s head began to swim and she had to sit down

What most upset her was the thought of having to move out of her own room; it was the perfect place for poor Loulou. In her anguish she would gaze at him and beg the Holy Spirit to come to her aid. She developed the idolatrous habit of kneeling in front of the parrot to say her prayers. Sometimes the sun would catch the parrot’s glass eye as it came through the little window, causing an emanation of radiant light that sent her into ecstasies.

Félicité had been left a pension of three hundred and eighty francs by her mistress. The garden provided her with vegetables. As for clothes, she had sufficient to last her her lifetime and she saved on lighting by going to bed as soon as it began to get dark.

She hardly ever went out, because she disliked walking past the secondhand dealer’s shop, where some of the old furniture was on display. Ever since her fit of giddiness, she had been dragging one leg and, as she was now grow‑ing frail, old Madame Simon, whose grocery business had recently collapsed, used to come round every morning to chop her firewood and draw her water.

Her eyes grew weaker. The shutters were no longer opened. Many years passed. Nobody came to rent the house and nobody came to buy it.

Félicité never asked for any repairs to be done, because she was frightened she might be evicted. The laths in the roof rotted and for one whole winter her bolster was per‑manently wet from the rain. Shortly after Easter, she coughed blood.

Madame Simon called for a doctor. Félicité wanted to know what was wrong with her. But by now she was too deaf to hear what was said and she only managed to catch one word: ‘pneumonia’. It was a word she knew and she quietly answered, ‘Ah! Like Madame’, finding it quite nat ural that she should follow in her mistress’s footsteps.

The time for preparing the altars of repose was drawing near.

The first of them was always placed at the foot of the hill, the second outside the post office and the third about half‑ way up the street. The exact position of this last altar was a matter of some rivalry, but the women of the parish eventually agreed that it should be placed in Madame Aubain’s courtyard.

Félicité’s breathing was getting worse and she was becom‑ing more feverish. She fretted at not being able to do anything for the altar. If only there were at least something that she could put on it! And then she thought of the par rot. The neighbours objected, saying that it was not really suitable. But the curé gave his permission and this made Félicité so happy that she asked him to accept Loulou, the one treasure she possessed, as a gift from her when she died.

From Tuesday to Saturday, the eve of Corpus Christi her coughing increased. By the evening, her face looked drawn, her lips were sticking to her gums and she began vomiting. The following morning, at first light, feeling very low, she sent for a priest. Three good women stood round her as she was given extreme unction. She then announced that she needed to speak to Fabu.

Fabu arrived dressed in his Sunday best and feeling very ill at ease in such sombre surroundings.

‘Please forgive me,’ she said, summoning all her strength to extend her arm towards him, ‘I thought it was you who had killed him.’

What was all this nonsense? How could she suspect someone like him of having committed a murder! Fabu was most indignant and was on the point of losing his temper.

‘Her mind is wandering,’ they said. ‘Surely you can see that.’

From time to time Félicité seemed to be speaking to phantoms. The women went away. Madame Simon ate her lunch.

A little later she went to fetch Loulou and held him close to Félicité. ‘Come on,’ she said. ‘Say goodbye to him.’

Although Loulou was not a corpse, he was being eaten away by maggots. One of his wings was broken and the stuffing was coming out of his stomach. But Félicité was now blind. She kissed him on his forehead and held him against her cheek. Madame Simon took him from her and went to replace him on the altar.

5

The smells of summer drifted in from the meadows. The air was filled with the buzzing of flies. The sun glinted on the surface of the river and warmed the slates of the roof. Madame Simon had come back into the room and was gently nodding off to sleep.

She was awoken by the sound of bells; they were com ing out of vespers. Félicité grew suddenly calmer. She thought of the procession and saw everything as clearly as if she were there.

All the schoolchildren, the choristers and the firemen were walking along the pavements. In the middle of the street, at the head of the procession, came the church officer with his halberd, the beadle carrying the great cross, the schoolmaster in charge of the boys and the nun keeping a motherly eye on the girls. Three of the prettiest looking like curly headed angels, were throwing rose pet als in the air. They were followed by the deacon conducting the band with arms outstretched and two censer‑ bearers turning round at every step to face the Holy Sacrament which was carried by Monsieur le Curé, clad in his mag nificent chasuble and protected by a canopy of bright red velvet held aloft by four churchwardens. A great throng of people followed on behind as the procession made its way between the white sheets which draped the walls of the houses and eventually arrived at the bottom of the hill.

Félicité’s forehead was bathed in a cold sweat. Madame Simon sponged it with a cloth, telling herself that one day she would go the same way.

The noise of the crowd gradually increased, at one point becoming very loud and then fading away.

A sudden burst of gunfire rattled the window panes The postilions were saluting the monstrance. Félicitérolled her eyes and, trying to raise her voice above a whis‑per, she asked, ‘Is he all right?’ She was still worrying about the parrot.

Félicité was now entering her final moments. Her breath came in short raucous gasps, making her sides heave. Beads of froth gathered in the corners of her mouth and her whole body began to shake.

From the street outside came the blaring of ophicleides, the high‑ pitched voices of the children and the deeper voices of the men. There were moments when all was quiet and all that could be heard was the tread of feet, cush‑ioned by the scattered petals and sounding like a flock of sheep crossing a field.

The group of clergy entered the courtyard. Madame Simon climbed up on to a chair to look out of the little window and was able to see the altar directly below.

It was hung with green garlands and covered with a flounce in English point lace. Standing in the centre was a little square frame containing some relics and at each end there was an orange tree. Along the length of the altar there was a row of silver candlesticks and china vases containing a vivid display of sunflowers, lilies, peonies, foxgloves and bunches of hydrangea. A cascade of bright colours fell from the top of the altar down to the carpet spread out on the cobblestones beneath it. In amongst the flowers could be seen a number of other treasured ornaments: a silver‑ gilt sugar‑ bowl decorated with a ring of violets, a set of pendants cut from Alençon gemstones glittering on a little carpet of moss, two Chinese screens with painted landscapes. Loulou lay hidden beneath some roses and all that could be seen of him was the spot of blue on the top of his head, like a disc of lapis lazuli.

The churchwardens, the choristers and the children took up their places around three sides of the courtyard The priest slowly walked up the steps and placed his great shining orb on the lace altar cloth. Everyone fell to their knees. There was a deep silence in which all that could be heard was the sound of the censers sliding on their chains as they were swung backwards and forwards.

A blue haze of incense floated up into Félicité’s room She opened her nostrils wide to breathe it in, savouring it with mystical fervour. Her eyes closed and a smile played on her lips. One by one her heartbeats became slower, growing successively weaker and fainter like a fountain running dry, an echo fading away. With her dying breath she imagined she saw a huge parrot hover ing above her head as the heavens parted to receive her.

竹林中

樵夫答典史问

是啊，发现那具尸体的正是我。今天早晨，我跟往常一样去砍伐后山的杉树。没料到山后的竹林里，竟有这么一具尸体。地点在哪儿？离山科的驿路有那么四五町[1]光景。竹子当中夹杂着细小的杉树，那地方连个人影儿也没有。

尸体上身穿淡蓝色短褂，头上戴着有皱纹的京式乌帽，脸朝天倒在那里。想想看，这一刀刚好戳在胸口上，尸体周围竹子的落叶简直就像是浸透了苏枋[2]水般地染红了。不，已经不再流血了，伤口好像早就凝固了。那里一只马蝇紧紧地叮在伤口上，似乎连我的脚步声都没理会。

没有看见什么凶器吗？没有，啥都没有。只是旁边的杉树底下丢着一根绳子。另外——对，除了绳子还有一把梳子。尸体旁边只有这两样东西。可是周围的草和竹叶给踩得很厉害，看来那个汉子被害以前，还曾拼命搏斗过一番。什么，有马没有？那里根本进不去马，竹林后面的路才能够走马呢！

云游僧答典史问

不错，昨天我碰见过那个如今成了尸体的汉子。昨天晌午，地点是从关山到山科的路上。那个人跟着一个骑马的妇女朝关山这边走来。女人遮着面纱，我看不见她的脸，只看见了她身上那件夹衣的颜色——好像是红面蓝里子。马是桃花马，记得马鬃是剃光了的[3]。马有多高吗？总有四尺四寸吧。……不过我是沙门，不大懂得这种事。那个男子——不，既佩着大刀，也带着弓箭，而且在上了黑漆的箭囊里插着二十来支箭，这我至今还清清楚楚地记得。

我做梦也想不到那个汉子会落到这么个下场。人生诚然是如过眼浮云。哎呀呀，我简直不知道怎么说才好，多么可怜！

捕役[4]答典史问

我抓到的那个人吗？他确实是个臭名昭著的强盗，名叫多襄丸。不过我逮他的时候，他正在粟田口的石桥上嗯嗯地呻吟着呢，大概是从马上摔下来的吧。时间吗？是昨天晚上初更光景。上回我差点捉住了他，被他逃掉了。那一回他穿的也是藏青短褂，腰里插着大刀。您瞧，如今他除了刀以外，还带着弓箭呢。啊？原来那个被害的人携带的也是这些……那么杀人的无疑就是这个多襄丸了。缠着皮的弓，黑漆的箭囊，鹰翎的箭十七支——这都是那个被害人随身带的吧。对，正如您说的，马也正是那匹剃光了鬃毛的桃花马。准是因果报应，被这畜生甩下来啦。它就在石桥过去一点儿的地方，拖着长长的缰绳，在吃路旁的青芒呢。

在洛中出没的强盗当中，多襄丸这家伙也是个好色之徒。去年秋天，有个好像是来进香的妇女和丫头一道在鸟部寺宝头卢的后山被杀，据说就是这家伙干的。男的被他杀了，骑桃花马的那个女人也不知道给带到什么地方去，后来怎样了呢。也许我不该多嘴，这一点也请您调查一下吧。

老媪答典史问

没错，这就是我闺女嫁的那个男人的尸体。他不是京城的人，是若狭国府的武士。名字叫金泽武弘，二十六岁。不，他性情温和，绝不会招人忌恨的。

女儿吗？女儿叫真砂，今年十九岁。她性格刚强，几乎赛过男子。除了武弘以外，她不曾跟别的男人好过。小小的瓜子儿脸，肤色微黑，左眼角上有颗痣。

武弘昨天跟我女儿一道动身到若狭去，竟出了这样的事，真不知前世造了什么孽！女婿已然这样，也只好认命了，可我女儿怎样了呢？真把我急坏了。我这苦老婆子求求您啦，一辈子也忘不了您，哪怕上天入地，也恳求您务必找到我女儿的下落。不管怎么说，可恨的是那个叫作什么多襄丸的强盗。他不但害了我女婿，连我女儿也……（老媪泣不成声）

多襄丸的供词

那个男人是我杀死的，可我没杀女的。她到哪儿去啦？这我可不知道。喏，慢着。再怎么拷问，不知道的也说不出来呀！而且事到如今，我不打算卑鄙地隐瞒什么了。

昨天刚过晌午，我碰见了那对夫妇。那时候碰巧刮了一阵风，撩起了那女人长长垂下的面纱，我瞅见了她的脸。可一眨眼的工夫，就又看不见了。一方面也是由于这个缘故吧，我只觉得那个女人长得像菩萨一样标致。我一时打定了主意，即使杀了那个男的，也非把女的抢到手不可。

咳，杀死个把男人，并不是像你们想的那样了不起的事。要抢女人，男人横竖是要给杀死的。只不过我杀人是用腰间佩的大刀，而你们杀人不用刀，单凭权力，凭金钱，往往还仅仅凭了那张伪善的嘴巴就够了。不错，血是不会流的，人还活得好好的——然而还是给杀了。想想有多么罪孽呀！谁知道究竟是你们坏还是我坏呢？（嘲讽的微笑）

不过，要是能够不杀男人就把女人抢到手，倒也没什么不好。哦，那时候原是想尽量避免杀男人而把女人抢到手的。但在那山科的驿路上，说什么也办不到。所以我就想方设法把那对夫妇引到山里去。

这也不费什么事。我跟那对夫妇搭伴走，跟他们说，对面山上有个古冢，我一挖，挖出了许许多多镜子和大刀，我悄悄地给埋在山后的竹林里了。谁要是想买，随便哪样，出几个钱就成。那个男的听了我这话，不知不觉地动了心——您瞧，贪欲有多么可怕啊。不到半个时辰，那对夫妇就跟我一道走上了山路。

到了竹林前面我就说，宝贝埋在这里呢，来看吧。男的利欲熏心，自然同意。可是那个女人连马都没下，说是就在那儿等着。看到竹林那么密，也就难怪她会这么说了。说实在的，这正合我意，就把女人留在那儿，跟男的一块儿走进了竹林。

竹林里起初净是竹子。走了十六七丈，才是一簇疏疏朗朗的杉树——为了达到我的目的，没有比这地方更便当的了。我扒开竹枝，撒了个听起来好像很有道理的谎，说宝贝就埋在杉树底下。听我这么一说，男的就拼命朝着透过竹叶已经能够看到细小杉树的那个方向走去。这当儿竹子稀疏起来，并立着好几棵杉树——刚走到这儿，我就马上把对方按倒。那人不愧是个佩刀的，好像相当有力气。无奈我给他个措手不及，他怎么也招架不住，马上就给捆到一棵杉树脚下了。绳子吗？这是做贼的妙处，随时得翻墙越壁，所以腰间早就准备好了。当然，为了不让他喊出声来，就用竹子的落叶堵上他的嘴，此外就没什么麻烦了。

我把男的安排停当后，就又到女人那里去说，那个男的好像得了急病，要她快去看看。不用说，这一次也达到了目的。女的已经摘掉那个垂着面纱的市女笠，就那样被我拉着手走到竹林深处来了。到这儿一看，男的给捆在杉树脚上呢——女人一看到这幅情景，不知什么工夫从怀里掏出了小刀，闪亮亮地拔出了鞘。我从来还没见过那么烈性子的女人呢。这当儿只要稍微一大意，就会被她一刀戳破了肚皮。不，即使躲过了这一下，在她的乱刀下面，指不定会受什么样的伤呢。我毕竟是多襄丸啊，好歹连大刀也没拔，到底把她的小刀打落了。再怎么刚强的女人，没有了武器也就没办法了。我终于照原来想的那样，不杀害男人，就把女人弄到了手。

不杀害男人——是的，只要把女人弄到手，我并不曾打算要男人的命。可是正当我丢下伏在地上哭泣的女人，往竹林外头逃去的时候，那个女人突然像疯子一样抓住了我的胳膊，而且她断断续续地喊道，你也罢，我丈夫也罢，你们之间总得死一个。在两个男人面前丢丑，比死还痛苦。后来还气喘吁吁地说，不管是你们哪个活下来，我就情愿跟他。这时我猛地对那个男人动了杀机。（阴郁的兴奋）

我这么一说，你们一定会认为我比你们还要残酷。那是因为你们不曾看见那个女人的脸，尤其是一瞬间她那烈火般的眸子。我和这个女人眼光相遇时，心想就是天打雷劈，也要把她娶到手。我只有娶她为妻这么一个念头。这不是像你们所想象的那种下流的色欲。假若当时除了色欲之外什么愿望也没有，我就是把女人踢倒了，也非逃跑不可。这样，我的大刀也就不至于沾上男人的血了。但是我在阴暗的竹林中定睛看了看女人的脸。当时我就打定主意，不杀死男人，绝不离开这里。

但是杀男人嘛，我也不想用卑鄙的手段。我给他松了绑，要求跟他用大刀来决斗。（丢在杉树脚下的绳子，就是那时忘了扔掉的）那个男人依然煞白着脸，马上把大刀拔出了鞘。一眨眼的工夫，一声不响气冲冲地向我扑来——交手的结果怎样，那就不用多说了。第二十三个回合，我的大刀把对方的胸膛刺透了。请不要忘记——是第二十三个回合啊。直到现在，我对他这一点还是佩服的。因为他是天下唯一和我交手到二十回合以上的。（快活的微笑）

男人刚一倒下，我就提着血淋淋的大刀，回头去看女人。可哪里想到，女人已经无影无踪了。她逃到哪儿去了呢？我在那簇杉树中找了找，可是竹子的落叶上，连点可疑的痕迹也没有。竖起耳朵听了听，只传来了男子喉间发出的断气声。

也许我刚开始抡刀的时候，那个女人为了呼救，就钻出竹林逃跑了——想到这里，这下子我为了保全自己的性命，就拿了大刀和弓箭，立即又回到原来的山路上去。女人的马还在那儿静静地吃草呢。以后的事情就用不着去说了。只是在进京之前，我已经把大刀卖掉了——我的口供完啦。我这颗脑袋总有挂在苦楝树梢[5]上的一天，请处我以极刑吧。（气概昂然）

来到清水寺的女人的忏悔

那个穿藏青短褂的人把我污辱以后，就瞧着我那被绑起来的丈夫嘲笑起来。我丈夫该是多么气愤啊。可他不管怎么挣扎，浑身绑着的绳子只是越勒越紧。我不由得滚也似的跑到丈夫身边去——不，是想要跑过去。可是那个人马上一脚把我踢倒了。就在这当儿，我觉察到丈夫眼里有一种难以形容的光。难以形容的——直到现在，我一想起他那眼神还不禁发抖。丈夫一句话也说不出来，在这一刹那间，用眼睛把他整个儿的心意传给我了。可闪烁在他眼睛里的，既不是愤怒也不是悲哀——只是蔑视我的冷冰冰的光呀！与其说是被那个人踢的，毋宁说是由于受了这眼光的刺激，我不由得喊了一句什么，就终于昏倒了。

后来我总算恢复了知觉。一看，那个穿藏青短褂的人已经不知去向。只剩下我丈夫被绑在杉树脚下。我从落满竹叶的地上勉勉强强撑起身来，看了看丈夫的脸。但是丈夫的眼神跟方才丝毫没有两样。在冷冰冰的轻蔑之下，蕴藏着憎恶的光。羞耻，悲哀，愤怒——简直不知道怎么形容当时我心里的感觉才好。我摇摇晃晃地站起来，走到丈夫身边。

“你呀，事情已经是这样了，我再也不能跟你在一块儿啦。我打算一死了之。可是……可是请你也死掉。你看到了我的耻辱，我不能让你一个人就这样活下去。”

我拼命地说了这么几句。然而丈夫只是厌恶地盯着我。我按捺住几乎要破裂的胸膛，搜寻丈夫的大刀。大概是给强盗抢去了，大刀自不用说，竹丛里连弓箭也没有了。可是幸亏小刀还掉在我脚底下。我举起小刀，又对丈夫说了一遍：“那么，请允许我先要了你的命，我随后就来。”

丈夫听了我这话，好容易才动了动嘴唇。他嘴里塞满了竹子的落叶，声音当然是一点也听不见的。但是我一看见他的嘴动，马上就明白了他在说什么。他依然对我抱着轻蔑的态度，说了句：“杀吧。”我几乎像做梦一般朝着丈夫那穿着淡蓝色短褂的胸口扑哧一声把小刀戳了进去。

我这时大概又昏过去了。好歹恢复知觉后，四下里打量了一下，丈夫仍旧绑在那里，早已咽了气。透过交错的竹子和杉树，一道夕阳从天空里射到他那苍白的脸上。我忍着哭声，给尸体松了绑。于是……于是我怎样了呢？唯独这一点，我已经没有力气来说明了。横竖我怎样也没有能耐去死。把小刀往喉咙里戳也罢，投身到山脚下的池子里也罢，种种办法都试过了，可就是死不了。现在还这么活着，这也不是什么光彩的事。（淡淡的惨笑）像我这样没有骨气的人，说不定连大慈大悲的观音菩萨也不屑睬一眼了。可是，杀了丈夫的我，被强盗糟蹋了的我，究竟该怎么办才好呢？我究竟……我……（突然激烈地抽搭）

鬼魂借巫女之口所说的话

——强盗奸污完了我的妻子，就在那儿坐下来，用种种话来安慰她。我当然说不出话来，身子也给绑在杉树脚下，可是我多次给妻子使眼色，想暗示她，不要把这个人的话信以为真。要知道，不管他说什么都是一派谎言。可是我妻子沮丧地坐在竹子的落叶上，一个劲儿地望着自己的膝头。怎么看也像是在专心听强盗的话哪。我嫉妒得浑身发抖，可是强盗花言巧语地变着法儿讲下去，最后竟大胆地说出了这样的话：即便就被糟蹋这么一回，反正跟丈夫也很难再圆满相处了。与其跟这样的丈夫过下去，你有没有做我妻子的打算呢？我正因为疼你，才干出了这样一桩无法无天的事来。

听强盗这么一说，妻子竟然就心荡神驰地仰起脸来。我还从来没看到妻子像那个时刻那么美丽过。可是那个美丽的妻子，当着像这样被绑起来的我的面，怎么回答了强盗呢？尽管魂游冥世，每逢想起妻子的回答，就怒火中烧。妻子确实是这样说的：“那么，请你随便把我带到哪儿去吧。”（沉默良久）

妻子的罪过，还不止于此。要仅仅是这样，我也不至于在冥冥之中这么痛苦了。可是妻子犹如做梦一般被强盗牵着手往竹林外面走去的当儿，脸色忽然变得刷白，指着杉树脚下的我，像发了疯般地喊了好几遍：“请你把那个人杀掉。只要他活着，我就不能跟你在一块儿。”“请你把那个人杀掉”——这句话像一股狂风，即使现在也好像要把我头朝下刮落到遥远、黑暗的深渊底下去。哪怕是一次，难道人的嘴巴曾吐出过这样可憎恶的话吗？哪怕是一次，难道人的耳朵曾听到过这样可诅咒的话吗？哪怕是一次，难道……（突然一阵冷笑）听了这话，连强盗也煞白了脸。“请你把那个人杀掉。”妻子边这么喊着，边拉住强盗的胳膊。强盗定睛看着我的妻子，不说杀也不说不杀……我刚这么一想，妻子一脚就给踢倒在竹子的落叶上了。（又迸发出一阵冷笑）强盗安详地抱起胳膊，向我看了看：“那个女人你打算怎么处置？是杀掉，还是饶她一条命？点一下头吧：杀掉吗？”——单凭这句话，我就想赦免强盗的罪孽。（再度沉默良久）

趁着我迟疑的工夫，妻子喊叫了一句什么，立即逃到竹林深处去了。强盗马上扑奔过去，可是好像连袖子也没抓着。我仿佛是在梦幻中看到了这幅情景。

妻子逃掉以后，强盗夺过我的大刀弓箭，把我身上绑的绳子割断一处。我记得强盗消失在竹林外面的时候，喃喃地说了句：“这回该轮到我了。”以后，周围寂静下来。不，还有什么人的哭声哩。我一边解开绳子，一边侧耳细听。呃，这不是我自己的哭声吗？（第三次沉默良久）

我很吃力地从杉树脚下抬起我那精疲力竭的身子。妻子落下的小刀就在我跟前闪着光。我把它拿在手里，朝着胸口一戳。一块带着腥味的玩意儿涌到嘴里来。我丝毫不觉得痛苦，只是胸口凉了以后，四下里越发寂然无声。哎呀，多么凄凉啊！连只小鸟也不飞到这山后的竹林上空来啁啾，唯有几抹阳光寂寥地飘在竹子和杉树梢头。就连这阳光也逐渐暗淡下来，杉树和竹子都再也看不见了。我倒在那儿，笼罩在深沉的静穆之中。

这当儿有谁蹑手蹑脚地走到我身边来了。我想掉过头去看一看，但是不知什么时候我周围已经昏暗下来了。什么人——不知是谁，用看不见的手悄悄地拔掉了我胸口上的小刀。同时，鲜血又涌到我嘴里来。从此，我就永远沉沦在冥世的黑暗中了……

一九二一年十二月

（文洁若 译）

[1] 町是日本长度单位，一町约合109米。（说明：书中脚注均为译者注。）

[2] 苏枋，也叫苏木、苏方，是一种常绿小乔木，心材浸液可做红色染料。

[3] 原文为剃有法师发的马，即将马鬃像和尚头那样剃光。

[4] 原文为放免一词，即日本古代对一些犯人免除徒刑，利用他们来追捕罪犯。

[5] 日本古代在牢狱门口植以苦楝树，以便将犯人枭首示众。

点鬼簿

一

我母亲是个狂人。我从未对母亲有过骨肉之情。我母亲用梳子把头发卷在头顶上，总是独自坐在位于芝[1]的娘家，咕噜咕噜地吸烟袋[2]。她的脸小，身体也小。不知为什么，那张脸是灰色的，没有朝气。我曾经读过《西厢记》，读到“土气息，泥滋味”一语时，一下就想起了我母亲那张脸——消瘦的侧脸。

说这番话的我，从未被母亲照料过。有一次，养母带着我，特意到楼上去问候母亲，她竟然冷不防用烟袋打了我的脑袋。我对此事记忆犹新。不过，总的来说，我母亲是一位实在文静的狂人。我或我的姐姐迫使她画画的时候，她就在折成四折的日本纸[3]上为我们画。非但用墨笔画，还把我姐姐的水彩画颜料涂在她自己所画男男女女的衣服啦、草木和花上面。只不过这些画上的人物个个都长着活脱儿是狐狸的脸。

我十一岁那一年的秋天，我母亲去世了。与其说是生病而死，毋宁说是衰弱而死的吧。唯独她逝世前前后后的记忆却比较清晰地留在我的记忆里。

大概是由于接到了病笃的电报吧。在一个无风的深夜，我和养母同乘一辆人力车，从本所[4]赶到芝。迄今我还没使用过叫作围巾的玩意儿。然而，特别在这个夜晚，我记得围了一条画了南画[5]里一些山水风景的薄绸手绢儿。也记得那条手绢儿发出的叫作“蝴蝶花”的香水气味。

我母亲躺在二楼下方那间八榻榻米[6]的客厅里。我和比我大四岁的姐姐跪在母亲的枕畔，两个人都不断地号啕大哭。尤其是有人在我后边念诵“驾鹤西去，驾鹤西去”，当时我越发感到悲伤不禁涌上心头。然而，一直闭着眼睛、几乎是死者的母亲突然睁开双目，说了些话。我们尽管凄怆，却小声哧哧地笑起来了。

次日晚上，我依然在母亲的枕边坐到将近拂晓。不过，不知为何，这一晚我一滴眼泪也流不出来。我在几乎不停地嚎哭的姐姐面前觉得丢脸，于是拼命地假装哭泣。同时，我又相信既然自己哭不出来，母亲必定不会死。

第三天的夜晚，我母亲几乎没怎么痛苦就咽了气。死前大概清醒过来了，凝视着我们的面孔，扑簌簌地落泪。不过，依然像平素那样什么话也不说。

入殓之后，我也不禁经常哭泣。有一位叫作“王子[7]的姑妈”的远亲说：“实在使人钦佩。”我当时唯一的想法就是，她是那种对玄妙的事感到钦佩的人。

我母亲出殡的那一天，姐姐拿着灵牌，我跟在后边，拿着香炉。两个人都是乘人力车去的。我有时打盹儿，总会在险些要把香炉掉下去的时候，突然惊醒。一直就这样，我们好像永远也到不了谷中[8]似的。相当长的送葬行列静悄悄地沿着秋季那总是晴朗的东京的大街前进。

我母亲的忌辰是十一月二十八日，戒名是“归命院妙成日进大师”。可是二十年后，我却不记得自己的亲生父亲的忌辰与戒名。多半是因为对十一岁的我而言，记住忌辰与戒名也是值得夸耀的一件事吧。

二

我有一位姐姐。尽管她身体多病，却成了两个孩子的母亲。想添加在我《点鬼簿》中的，当然不是这位姐姐的事，而是那位恰好在我出生前，突然夭折了的姐姐的事。据说，我们三姐弟中，她最聪明。

这位姐姐叫作初子，或许是由于她生为长女。我家的佛盒上至今有一张“小初”的相片，装在小小的镜框里。“小初”一点也不像是衰弱的孩子。长着小酒窝儿的两颊，就像熟杏子一般，圆溜溜的……

被父母过多地宠爱的终究是“小初”。他们把“小初”从芝的新钱座特意带到位于筑地[9]的萨姆纳夫人担任园长的幼儿园。然而，星期六至星期日，必定到我母亲的娘家——坐落在本所的芥川家过夜。像这样出门的时候，“小初”穿的是就连在明治二十年代[10]都够时兴的西装。我记得上小学的时候，得到了给“小初”做西装的下脚布料。我把它们裹在人造橡胶玩具娃娃身上。那些下脚布料无一例外，全都是进口的平纹细白棉布，上面点缀着细碎的印花或乐器花样。

一个早春的星期日下午，“小初”一边在院子里踱来踱去，一边跟坐在房间里的伯妈说话。（我当然想象着当时姐姐依然穿着西装）

“伯妈，这棵树叫什么呀？”

“哪一棵树？”

“这棵有花骨朵的树。”

我外婆家的院子里有一棵低矮的木瓜树。树枝耷拉到一口古老的井里。估计梳着小辫儿的“小初”杏眼圆睁，当时正凝视着枝子带刺儿的木瓜树吧。

“这棵树的名字跟你的一样。”

偏巧“小初”未能理解伯妈的戏谑语。

“那么，这棵树就叫作‘傻瓜树’喽。”

至今，只要有人提到“小初”，伯妈就反复地说她们之间曾经怎样一问一答。实际上，此外，“小初”说过的话，一句也没留存。大概这之后没过几天她就进了棺材。我不记得刻在小小的灵牌上的“小初”的戒名。然而，“小初”的忌辰是四月五日。玄妙的是，我对此记忆犹新。

不知为什么，我对这位姐姐——素昧平生的姐姐，有一种亲密感情。倘若“小初”至今健在，已经四十多岁了吧。过了不惑之年的“小初”那张脸也许活脱儿像是在坐落于芝的娘家二楼茫然地抽烟的母亲的脸吧。我时常宛若幻想一般觉得：弄不清是我母亲还是姐姐的一位四十来岁的女人，不知从何处守望着我的一生。难道这是喝咖啡啦、抽烟啦搞得疲惫不堪的我，神经遭到摧残了吗？抑或是超自然的力量借着什么机会出现在真实的世界，并干出了这样的勾当吧？

三

由于母亲疯了，我刚生下来就到收养我的家来啦（那是舅父的家），所以对亲生父亲也冷淡。我父亲经营牛奶铺，似乎是一位有些成功的人。教给我认识在当时而言还蛮时髦的水果与饮料的也统统是父亲。香蕉、冰激凌、菠萝、朗姆酒——或许还有其他的。我记得曾在当时坐落于新宿的牧场外边那棵槲树的树叶阴影下喝朗姆酒的往事。朗姆酒是酒精极少、橙黄色的饮料。

我父亲劝幼小的我吃喝如此新奇的东西，试图把我从收养我的家庭弄回来。我还记得有一天晚上，在大森[11]的鱼荣餐馆，父亲一边劝我吃冰激凌，一边露骨地说服我逃回到自个儿家来。说这番话的时候，我父亲发挥了巧言令色的本事。然而，遗憾的是他的劝说诱导一次也未奏效。因为我爱收养我的那一家的父母——尤其是舅妈。

我父亲还性急，屡次跟随便什么人吵架。我在中学三年级时，与父亲玩相扑，我用现代柔道的特殊招数巧妙地把他摔倒了。我父亲刚站起来就说“再来个回合”，并朝着我走过来。我再度没费什么力气就把他摔倒了。我父亲第三次一边说“再来个回合”，一边勃然变色猛扑过来。我的后母在观看——她是我母亲的妹妹，又是我父亲的继室——朝我使了两三个眼神。我与父亲较量了一番，故意摔了个四仰八叉。然而，倘若那时我没败给父亲，他必定要揪住我吧。

我二十八岁时——那时还在当教师，接到了“父住进医院”的电报，遂仓皇地从镰仓[12]直奔东京。我父亲是由于患流行性感冒而住进东京医院的。我与收养我的舅妈和后母在病房的角落住宿了约莫三天。这当儿我逐渐感到郁闷了。正在此时，跟我有交情的一位爱尔兰新闻记者打电话来邀请我到筑地的一家酒馆去吃饭。我以那位新闻记者最近要赴美国为借口，丢下奄奄一息的父亲，前往筑地的那家酒馆。

我们跟四五位艺伎一道，愉快地吃了日本风味的饭。大概是十点左右吃完的。有人从背后招呼我：“先生。”我在中段止步，回头朝宽踏板的楼梯上边望着。一位恰好在场的艺伎聚精会神地俯视着我。我一言不发地走下楼梯。坐上停在正门外边的出租汽车。出租汽车立即开动了。然而，出现在我的脑海中的与其说是父亲，毋宁说是绾着娇艳的西式发髻的她的脸——尤其是她的眼睛。

我回到医院，只见父亲正等得不耐烦。不但如此，他让其他人全都离开，到两扇的屏风外边去。要么握住我的手，要么就抚摸它；谈起我不知道的往事——当年跟我母亲结婚时的事。左不过是与我母亲出门去买衣柜啦，购买了寿司啦，一些琐碎的事罢了。不过，正说着的时候，我的眼睑不知不觉地灼热起来了。眼泪也沿着我父亲那消瘦的脸蛋流下来。

我父亲在次日早晨没怎么痛苦地驾鹤西去，死前好像发疯了，说什么：“来了一艘军舰，瞧那些飘扬着的旗子！大伙儿都喊万岁吧！”我压根儿不记得自己父亲的丧礼情况。不过，依然记得把父亲的遗体护送到他本人之家时，春季的一轮大月亮的光照耀在灵柩车上。

四

今年三月中旬我还揣着怀炉时，隔了好久才第一次跟妻子一道去上坟。已经过去了这么久——然而，小小的坟墓自不待言，就连将枝子伸到坟墓上的一株赤松也没有变化。

添加在《点鬼簿》里的三个人的骸骨都埋在谷中墓地的角落里——而且在同一座墓碑下面。我想起了母亲的棺材被静悄悄地降下到这座墓碑下边时的往事。“小初”大概也是这样的。唯独我父亲——我记得父亲的骸骨发白、细碎，夹杂着金牙……

我并不喜欢上坟。倘若能忘掉，巴望把双亲与姐姐也忘记。然而，尤其是那一天，或许是身体衰弱的缘故，一边眺望早春的阳光中那座发黑的墓碑，一边思索：究竟他们三个人当中，谁幸福呢？

升腾起阳气

我独自住在

坟地外边

说实在的，我从来没有像这时那样，感到这么写的丈草[13]的心境逼近自己过。

（文洁若译于二〇一八年二月十四日）

[1] 芝是东京都港区的一个街区。

[2] 烟袋是一种吸烟用具，一般在细竹管的一端安着烟袋锅儿，可以装烟，另一端安着玉石、翡翠等制成的嘴儿，可以衔在嘴里吸。

[3] 原文为“半纸”，习字、写信用的日本纸，长24厘米，宽34厘米左右。

[4] 本所是东京都墨田区的一个街区。

[5] 南画也叫文人画。是18、19世纪很多日本画家采用的一种绘画风格。在江户中期和后期，一些具有独特创作能力的画家属于这一画派。其画风是依据17至18世纪具有个性的中国清代绘画形成的。同时，南画画家们在构图及笔法上改变了中国文人画的夸张手法，作品中常带有一种幽默感。

[6] 也称“叠”“帖”，榻榻米为音译，指铺在和式房间地板上的草垫子，呈长方形，尺寸大小各地不尽相同。一般宽90厘米，长180厘米，厚约6厘米。

[7] 东京都北区内的一个街区。

[8] 东京都台东区内的一个街区。

[9] 东京都中央区的一个街区。

[10] 明治二十年至二十九年是1887年至1896年。

[11] 是东京都大田区的一个街区。

[12] 神奈川县南部城市。

[13] 内腾丈草（1662—1704），江户前期的俳句诗人，“和歌”诗人。

傻子的一生

久米正雄君[1]：

此稿可否发表，什么时候在哪儿发表，我愿意完全委托给你。

稿中所出现的人物你大概都知道。但是发表之际，希望你不要加上注解。

我目前生活在最不幸的幸福当中。但奇怪的是我并不懊悔。我只是对有了我这样的恶夫、恶子、恶父的亲人感到遗憾。那么，再见了。在此稿中，我至少还不曾有意识地替自己辩护。

最后再说一句：我之所以特地将此稿委托给你，乃是因为我相信你恐怕比任何人都更了解我。（一旦揭掉我这张城里人的皮）我在此稿中表现出的傻劲儿供你一笑。

昭和二年六月二十日

芥川龙之介

一 时代

那是某书店的二楼。年方二十的他登上靠在书架上的西式梯子，寻找新书。莫泊桑、波德莱尔[2]、斯特林堡、易卜生、萧伯纳、托尔斯泰……

天色逐渐黑下来了。他却还热心地继续读书脊上的字。那里陈列的，与其说是书籍，毋宁说是这个时代[3]本身。尼采、魏尔伦、龚古尔兄弟[4]、陀思妥耶夫斯基、霍普特曼[5]、福楼拜……

他在薄暮中挣扎，数着他们的名字，可是书籍自然而然地淹没在阴郁的暮色中。他终于失去耐性，想从西式梯子上下来。他头上刚好悬着个秃灯泡，忽然亮了。他就立在梯子上，俯视在书籍之间移动的店员和顾客。他们显得怪渺小的，而且非常寒碜。

人生还不如波德莱尔的一行诗。

他立在梯子上，朝着这些人望了片刻。

二 母亲

疯子们都清一色地穿着灰衣服。宽阔的屋子因而越发显得忧郁。其中的一个对着风琴，热衷于弹赞美歌。同时，另外一个站在屋子正中间，与其说是跳舞，不如说是乱蹦着。

他和红光满面的医生一起看着这样的情景。十年前，他母亲也跟他们毫无二致。毫无——说实在的，他从他们的气味中嗅到了母亲的气味。

“那么，走吧？”

医生走在他的前面，沿着走廊进入一个房间。房间的角落里有个装满酒精的大玻璃瓶，里面浸着几副脑髓。他在其中的一副上发现了略微发白的东西，有些像是撒上了点蛋白。他同医生站着谈话，又想起了自己的母亲。

“这是××电灯公司的一个技师生前的脑髓。他一直认定自己是黑油油的大发电机。”

为了避开医生的视线，他就朝玻璃窗外面望去。除了插着空瓶碎片的砖墙以外，那里什么也没有。不过砖墙上长的薄薄青苔斑驳地泛着白色。

三 家

他住在郊外的一个二楼的房间里。由于地基松软了，这座房子的二楼有些倾斜。

他的姑妈常常跟他在楼上吵架。他的养父养母有时出面调解。可是他最爱这位姑妈。姑妈终身未嫁，当他二十岁的时候，她已接近六十岁了。

他在某郊外的楼上屡屡思索：莫非相爱的人就得彼此折磨吗？这当儿，他感到二楼歪斜得有点可怖。

四 东京

隅田川阴沉沉的。他从行驶中的小汽船窗口眺望向岛的樱树。在他眼里，盛开的樱花恍若一片败絮般令人忧郁。可是他在那些樱树中——江户时代以来的向岛的樱树中发现了他自己。

五 自我

他和他的前辈一起坐在某咖啡馆的桌边，不断地吸着纸烟。他不大开口讲话，却热心地听着前辈的话。

“今天乘了半天汽车。”

“有什么事情吗？”

他的前辈手托着腮，漫不经心地回答说：“没有什么事，只不过想坐坐罢了。”

这句话把他自己解放到不可知的世界——接近诸神的“自我”的世界。他觉得有点痛苦，同时也感到欢乐。

那个咖啡馆很小。牧羊神的相框下面却有一棵栽在赭色盆中的橡树，肥厚的叶片耷拉着。

六 病

潮风不断刮来，他摊开《英语大辞典》，手指划着找词条。

Talaria：生了翼的鞋，或作Sandal。

Tale：故事。

Talipot：印度东部产的椰子。树干高达五十英尺至一百英尺，叶子可用于制伞、扇子、帽子等。七十年开花一次……

他凭想象清晰地描绘出这种椰子的花。他的喉咙从来没这么痒过，不由得往辞典上吐了口痰。痰？——那却不是痰。他想到短暂的生命，又一次想象着椰子花——在遥远的大海彼岸高高耸立的椰子花。

七 画

他突然地——实在是突然地……站在某书店的店头翻阅梵·高的画集时，他突然地领悟了画这个东西。当然，梵·高的画集无疑是影印版。他从影印版中也感到了鲜明地浮现的大自然。

对这幅画的热情使他的眼界一新。他不知不觉间密切注意着树枝的弯曲和女人面颊的丰腴。

在一个下雨的秋日傍晚，他走过郊外的陆桥下面。陆桥对面的堤坝下停着一辆货运马车。他经过那里时，感到有人曾走过这条路。是谁呢？——无须问他本人。二十三岁的他，心目中浮现出一个割去了耳朵的荷兰人，叼着长烟斗，锐利的目光注视着这幅忧郁的风景画……

八 火花

他淋着雨，在柏油路上行走。雨下得相当大。在飞溅的雨水中，他嗅到了橡胶雨衣的气味。

眼前的一根架空线冒出紫色火花。他格外感动。他的上衣口袋里藏着准备在同人杂志上发表的原稿。他冒雨走着，再次仰望了一下后面的架空线。

架空线依然放出耀眼的火花。他展望人生，并没有特别稀罕的东西。但是只有这紫色的火花——只有这可怕的空中的火花，哪怕用生命来换取，他也想把它抓住。

九 尸体

那些尸体的拇指上都挂着穿上铁丝的牌子，上面记着姓名、年龄等等。他的朋友弯着腰，灵活地运用解剖刀，开始剥一具尸体脸上的皮。皮下布满了美丽的黄色脂肪。

他望着那具尸体。为了完成一个短篇——以王朝时代为背景的一个短篇，他非这么做不可。可是，像腐烂了的杏子一样的尸臭是难闻的。他的朋友皱起眉头，静静地动着解剖刀。

“近来尸体也不够用。”他的朋友说。

不知什么时候，他早已准备好了答复：“如果尸体不够用，我就会没有任何恶意地去杀人。”可是他当然只把这话放在心里。

十 先生

他在一棵大槲树下读着先生的书。槲树沐浴在秋天的阳光下，连一片叶子也不动。远处的空中有一架吊着玻璃秤盘的天平，刚好保持平衡——他边读着先生的书，边遐想着这样的情景……

十一 拂晓

天逐渐亮了。有一次，他在某街的拐角望着广阔的市场。市场上熙熙攘攘的人和车子都染成了玫瑰色。

他点燃一支纸烟，安详地走进市场。一条黑色瘦狗突然向他吠起来。可是他不惊慌。他甚至爱起那条狗来。

市场正中有一棵法国梧桐树，树枝向四面挓挲着。他站在树干下，透过树枝仰望高空。正好在他头顶上空，闪烁着一颗星星。

这是他二十五岁的时候——会见先生以后的第三个月。

十二 军港

潜水艇内部是阴暗的。周围都是机器，他弯着腰，透过小小的方镜望去。映在方镜里的是明亮的军港风光。

“那边还可以看到‘金刚’呢。”一个海军高级军官对他说。

他看着方镜上的小军舰，不知怎的，忽然想起了荷兰芹菜——每份三毛钱的牛排上也有荷兰芹菜，散发着清香。

十三 先生之死

雨后起了风，他在一个新车站的站台上走着。天刚蒙蒙亮。站台那面，三四名铁路工人一齐抢着镐，高声唱着什么。

雨后的风吹散了工人的歌声和他的感情。他拿着没有点燃的香烟，感到近于欢乐的痛苦。“先生病危”的电报揣在大衣兜里……

这时，从对面松山的背阴处，早上六点的上行列车拖着一缕轻烟，蜿蜒向这边驶来。

十四 结婚

婚后第二天他就数落妻子道：“刚来就浪费可不行啊。”然而，这种数落的话，与其说是他自己要说的，不如说是他的姑妈叫他“说”的。当然，他的妻子不但向他本人，也向他的姑妈赔了不是。为他买来的那钵黄水仙花就摆在她前面……

十五 他们

在大芭蕉叶的宽阔阴影下，他们和平地生活着——他们的家在从东京乘火车要足足一小时的海滨某镇上。

十六 枕头

他枕着散发玫瑰叶香的怀疑主义，读着阿纳托尔·法朗士的书。可是，他没有注意到枕中还有半人半马神。

十七 蝴蝶

在充满海藻气味的风中，一只蝴蝶在蹁跹飞舞。一眨眼的工夫，他感到这只蝴蝶的翅膀碰了一下他那干燥的嘴唇。可是沾在他嘴唇上的翅粉却在几年后还闪着光。

十八 月

他在某饭店的台阶上偶然遇见了她。就连在这样的白昼，她的脸也跟在月光下一样。他目送着她（他俩素昧平生），感到从来没有过的寂寞……

十九 人工翼

他从阿纳托尔·法朗士转向十八世纪的哲学家去了，但是他没有接近卢梭。那或许是他本人的一面——容易感情用事的一面跟卢梭相近之故。他却去接近跟他本身的另一面——富于冷静的理智的一面——相近的《天真汉》[6]的哲学家了。

对二十九岁的他来说，人生已经一点也不光明了。可是伏尔泰给了这样的他以人工翼。

他张开这人工翼，轻而易举地飞上天空。同时，理智之光照耀的人生的悲欢沉沦在他的眼底下。他向穷街陋巷投以讽刺与微笑，穿过一无遮拦的太空，径直飞向太阳。他似乎忘记了古代希腊人因这样的人工翼被阳光晒化而终于落进海里死去的事[7]……

二十 桎梏

由于他要到某报社去工作，他们夫妇就跟他的养父养母同住在一座房子里了。他依靠的是写在黄纸上的合同。后来才知道，报社对这份合同不承担任何义务，只由他承担义务。

二十一 狂人的女儿

两辆人力车在冷冷清清的阴天的乡间道路上跑着。海风习习，这条路显然通向海边。他坐在后面这辆人力车上，边纳闷着为什么自己对这次的幽会兴致索然，边思索是什么把他引到这里来的。这绝不是恋爱。倘若不是恋爱——他为了回避这个答复，不得不想：总之，我们是平等的。

坐在前面那辆人力车上的是一个狂人的女儿。不仅如此，她的妹妹是因嫉妒而自杀的。

——事到如今，怎么也没办法了。

他对这个狂人的女儿——她只有强烈的动物本能——已经感到某种憎恶了。

这当儿，两辆人力车经过有咸腥气味的墓地外面。粘着蚝壳的矮树篱里面，有几座黑黝黝的石塔。他眺望着在那些石塔后面微微闪烁的海洋，不知怎的，忽然对她的丈夫——没能抓住她的心的丈夫，感到蔑视……

二十二 某画家

那是某杂志的插图。一只公鸡的水墨画表现出明显的个性。他向某友人打听这位画家的情况。

大约一周后，这位画家访问了他。在他的一生中，这是一件颇不寻常的事情。他在这位画家身上发现了谁都不知道的那一面。不但如此，还发现了连画家本人也一直不知道的画家的灵魂。

在一个微寒的秋日傍晚，他因看到一株玉米，蓦地联想起这位画家。长得高高的玉米，披着粗糙的叶子，培在根部的土里露出像神经那样纤细的根须。这无疑又是容易受伤的他的自画像。可是这样的发现只有使他忧郁罢了。

——已经晚了。可是到了节骨眼儿上……

二十三 她

某广场前面，暮色苍茫。他的身体发着低烧，在广场上踱步。晴空略呈银色，大厦林立，窗口灯火辉煌。

他在路边停下脚步，等候她到来。大约过了五分钟，她好像有些憔悴似的向他走来。她看到了他的脸，就微笑着说：“累啦。”他们并肩在依稀有些亮光的广场上走着。对他们来说，这是第一次。为了跟她在一起，他无论抛掉什么都在所不惜。

他们乘上汽车后，她凝视着他的脸说：“你不后悔吗？”他斩钉截铁地说：“不后悔。”她按着他的手说道：“我也不后悔。”这样讲的时候，她的脸好像沐浴在月光下。

二十四 分娩

他伫立在纸隔扇旁边，俯视着穿白色手术衣的一名接生婆在给婴儿洗澡。每当肥皂浸进眼里，婴儿就可爱地反复皱起眉头，还不断地大声哭。他一面觉得婴儿的气味有点像鼠崽子，一面不由得深刻地想道：“为什么这娃娃也出生了呢？生到这个充满俗世之苦的世界上来——为什么他命中注定要有我这个爸爸呢？”

而且这是他的妻子头胎生的男孩。

二十五 斯特林堡

他站在房间门口，看着开着石榴花的月光底下几个衣冠不整的中国人在打麻将。然后回到房间里，在矮矮的油灯下开始读《痴人的告白》。可是还没有读上两页，就不知不觉苦笑起来——斯特林堡在给情妇伯爵夫人的信中，写着和他差不离的谎言……

二十六 古代

彩色剥落了的佛像、天人、马和莲花座几乎使他为之倾倒。他仰望着它们，把一切抛在脑后。甚至忘记了他本人侥幸得以摆脱狂人的女儿……

二十七 斯巴达式训练

他同他的朋友在一条巷子里走着。一辆上篷的人力车径直迎面跑来。而且出人意料的是车上坐的正是昨晚的她。在这样的白昼，她的面容恍若沐浴在月光下。当着他朋友的面，他们当然连招呼也没打。

“真漂亮。”他的朋友这样说。

他望着巷子尽头的春天的山，毫不犹豫地回答说：“是啊，真漂亮。”

二十八 杀人

乡间道路沐浴在阳光下，散发着牛粪的臭气。他揩着汗，踏着上坡路走去。道路两旁飘着熟麦的香气。

“杀吧，杀吧……”他不知不觉间嘴里反复嘟囔着。杀谁呢？——这他是清楚的。他想起一个极卑鄙的留平头的男子。

黄色麦地的那面，不知何时露出了一座天主教堂的圆屋顶……

二十九 形象

那是一把铁制酒壶。这把细纹酒壶使他懂得了“造型”的美。

三十 雨

他在大床上同她聊着天。寝室窗外下着雨。在这场雨中，木棉花说不上什么时候就会烂掉吧。她的面容仍像是沐浴在月光下。可是同她交谈，他不免感到无聊。他匍匐着，静静地点起一支纸烟，想起同她一起生活已有七年了。

“我爱着这个女人吗？”他问他自己道。

“我还爱着。”——这个答复使注视着自己的他也感到意外。

三十一 大地震

那种气味和熟透了的杏子差不多。他在火灾后的废墟上走着，微微嗅到这样的气味，于是想道：炎天的腐尸，气味居然也不太难闻。可是当他站在尸骸累累的池畔望去的时候，才发现“鼻子发酸”这句话在感觉上绝不是夸张的。尤其使他动情的是十二三岁的小孩的尸体。他看着那具尸体，有点觉得羡慕。他想起“上帝所爱者不长命”这句话。他的姐姐和异母兄弟的家都焚毁了，而且他的姐夫是犯了伪证罪而缓期服刑的……

他站在灰烬中，不由得深深地想道：人人都死掉才好呢。

三十二 打架

他同异母兄弟扭打起来了。他弟弟无疑由于他的缘故经常受到压迫。同时，他也因为弟弟而失掉了自由。他的亲戚一个劲儿地对他的弟弟说：“你要学他。”然而这不啻是把他本人的手脚都绑了起来。他们扭作一团，终于滚到廊子上了。他还记得，廊外的庭院中有一棵百日红，在酝酿着一场雨的天空下开着红彤彤的花。

三十三 英雄

不知什么时候，他从伏尔泰家的窗口仰望着高山。那挂着冰河的山上，连秃鹰的影子也看不见。可是有一个身材矮小的俄罗斯人在顽强地沿着山路攀登。

夜幕降临到伏尔泰家后，他在明亮的灯光下回忆着攀登山路的俄罗斯人的身姿，写了这样一首有教化目的的诗：

你比谁都恪守十诫，

又比谁都违反十诫。

你比谁都爱护民众，

又比谁都轻视民众。

你比谁都富于理想，

又比谁都了解现实。

你是我们东洋诞生的，

散发草花香气的电气机车。

三十四 色彩

三十岁的他不知什么时候爱上了某块空地。那里，长着青苔的地面上只散着一些残砖碎瓦。可是在他眼里这与塞尚[8]的风景画没有什么两样。

他忽然想起了七八年前他的激情。同时发现他在七八年前是不懂得色彩的。

三十五 假人

他打算过一种激烈到不论何时死去也不会后悔的生活。可是在养父养母和姑妈面前，他的日子依然过得很拘谨。这就使他的生活形成了阴阳两面。他看见立在某西服店里的一个人体模型，就想到究竟他自己在多大程度上像这个模型。但是意识之外的他——可以说是第二个他，早已把这样的心情写入一篇短篇小说里了。

三十六 倦怠

他同一个大学生在长满狗尾草的野地上行走。

“你们仍有旺盛的生活欲吧？”

“嗯……可是你也……”

“可是我没有了。只是有创作欲罢了。”

这是他的真情。说实在的，他不知不觉间已对生活失去了兴趣。

“创作欲也是生活欲吧。”

他没有回答。曾几何时，野地的红穗上清晰地映现出一座喷火山。他觉得有些羡慕这座喷火山。可是他自己也莫名其所以然……

三十七 过来人

他遇到了在才力上也能够同他匹敌的女人。可是他写了《过来人》等抒情诗，才摆脱了这个危机。这是一种百无聊赖的心情，宛如把冻在树干上的闪闪发光的雪拍了下来。

草笠随风舞，

飘摇落道旁；

我名何所惜，

但愿君名扬。

三十八 复仇

那是某饭店的阳台，周围满是刚萌芽的树木。他在那里画着画，哄一个少年玩。这是七年前分手的狂人的女儿的独生子。

狂人的女儿点燃纸烟，看着他们玩。他在心情沉重地继续描绘火车和飞机。幸亏这个少年不是他的儿子。可是，使他感到痛苦的莫过于这个少年叫他“叔叔”。

少年不知跑到哪儿去了，狂人的女儿边抽着烟，边带点媚态地对他说：“那孩子不像你吗？”

“不像。第一……”

“可是，还有胎教的说法呢。”

他默不作声，眼睛望着一旁。可是他心里并非没有残忍的愿望，恨不得把他掐死……

三十九 镜子

他在某咖啡馆的一个角落里同朋友谈话。他的朋友吃着烤苹果，谈论着近来天气寒冷之类的话。他突然感到这样的话里有矛盾。

“你还是独身呀。”

“不，下个月就结婚。”

他不由得默不作声了。嵌在咖啡馆墙壁上的镜子映出他无数的形象。冷冰冰的，像威胁什么似的……

四十 问答

你为什么要攻击现代的社会制度？

因为我看到了资本主义所产生的罪恶。

罪恶？我还只当你分辨不出善恶的差别呢。那么，你的生活呢？

——他就这样同天使一问一答。当然是体体面面地戴着大礼帽的天使……

四十一 病

他患了失眠病，并且体力也开始衰弱了。好几位医生各自给他的病做了两三种诊断：胃酸过多、胃弛缓、干性肋膜炎、神经衰弱、慢性结膜炎、脑疲劳……

可是他知道自己的病源。那就是对他自己感到羞愧，同时又害怕他们的心情。害怕他们——害怕他所蔑视的社会！

在一个要下雪的阴沉的下午，他在某咖啡馆的一个角落里衔着点燃了的雪茄烟，倾听对面留声机放出的音乐。乐声沁人心脾。等到那段音乐结束后，他就走到留声机前，看看唱片上贴的说明：《魔笛》——莫扎特。[9]

他顿时领悟了。破了十诫的莫扎特也还是有过苦闷的。可是，该不至于像他这样……他垂着头，静静地回到自己的桌边。

四十二 众神的笑声

在春光明媚的松林中，三十五岁的他边踱步边回忆着自己两三年前写过的话：

我最同情的是神不能自杀。

四十三 夜

夜幕又快降临了。要闹天气了，半明半暗中，海上浪花滚滚。在这样的天空下，他同妻子第二次结婚了。这给他们带来了欢乐，同时又带来痛苦。三个孩子和他们一起看着海上的闪电。他的妻子抱着一个孩子，好像忍着眼泪。

“那边有一只船。”

“嗯。”

“樯杆断了的船。”

四十四 死

他趁着独自睡觉的机会，把腰带挂在窗棂子上想自缢。可是把脖子伸进带子时忽然又怕死了。并不是害怕死的那一瞬间的痛苦。他第二次自缢时拿着怀表测试缢死的时间。稍感痛苦以后，神志就有些恍惚了。只要过了这一关，准会进入死境。他看了看表针，发现感到痛苦的过程为一分二十几秒。窗棂子外一片漆黑。从黑暗中传来了粗犷的鸡鸣。

四十五 Divan[10]

Divan即将再次给他的心灵倾注以新的力量。那是他所不知道的“东洋的歌德”。他看见超脱一切善恶，悠然站在彼岸的歌德，感到近乎绝望的羡慕。在他眼里，诗人歌德比诗人基督更伟大。在这位诗人的心中，除了阿克罗波利斯[11]和各各他[12]之外，还有阿拉伯玫瑰花在怒放。倘若多少有力量追踪这位诗人的足迹的话……他读完诗集，当极为激动的情绪平息以后，不禁深深蔑视自己，因为他在生活中就像宦官一样。

四十六 谎言

他姐夫的自杀猝然使他受了打击。今后连姐姐一家人也得由他来照顾了。至少对他来说，未来就像日暮那样昏暗。他对自己精神上的破产有一种近乎冷笑的感觉（他完全明白自己的罪孽和弱点），继续阅读各种书籍。可是连卢梭的《忏悔录》也充满英雄的谎言。尤其是《新生》[13]——他从来没有遇见过像《新生》的主人公那样老奸巨猾的伪善者。可是只有弗朗索瓦·维庸[14]浸透了他的心。他在几篇诗里发现了“美丽的男性”。

等待绞刑的维庸的形象出现在他的梦里。他几次差点儿像维庸那样坠入人生的底层。但是他的境遇和体力不允许这样。他渐渐衰弱下去，恰似从前斯威夫特[15]见到过的从树梢枯萎起来的树木那样……

四十七 玩火

她容光焕发，犹如晨光照耀下的薄冰似的。他对她抱有好感，但是没有恋爱的感觉，而且连碰也没碰过她的身体。

“听说你想死。”

“是——不，与其说想死，不如说活腻了。”

他们这样一问一答，约好一起死。

“这是精神自杀。”

“双双精神自杀。”

他对他自己这样镇静自若，不由得感到奇怪。

四十八 死

他没有同她一起死。至今连碰也没碰过她的身体这一点，似乎使他感到满意。她若无其事地时常同他谈，并且把她带着的一瓶氰化钾递给他，还说：“有了这个，彼此心里都有仗势了。”

那确实使他心里有了仗势。他独自坐在藤椅上，看着柯树的嫩叶，不由得反复思索死亡将给予他的和平。

四十九 剥制的天鹅

他想尽最后的力量写自传。可是这对他来说竟然并不容易。那是由于他还残留着自尊心、怀疑主义和利害打算。他不得不轻蔑这样的自己。可是另一方面，他又不由自主地想：如果剥开一层皮来看，谁都是一样的。他总是想，《诗与真实》这个书名好像是一切自传的书名。他还清楚地知道，文艺作品不一定使人人都感动。他还产生了这样的念头：只有那些与他的生涯相近并且和他相似的人们才会为他的作品所感动。因此，他决定简短地把自己的《诗与真实》写出来。

他写完《傻子的一生》后，偶然在某旧家具店看见了剥制的天鹅。它伸长了颈立着，连发黄的羽毛也被蛀蚀了。他回想自己的一生，不禁热泪盈眶，发出冷笑。他的前途不是发疯就是自杀。他独自在日落的街上走着，决心等待慢慢把他毁灭的命运的到来。

五十 俘虏

他的朋友之一发疯了。他对这个朋友一向有某种亲近的感觉。因为他比别人更深刻地理解这个朋友的孤独——快活的假面掩盖下的孤独。这个朋友发疯后他去看望过两三次。

“你和我都给恶魔附体了——给所谓世纪末的恶魔附体了。”

这位朋友曾低声对他这样说。听说两三天以后，这位朋友在去某温泉旅馆的途中，甚至吃起玫瑰花来了。这个朋友住院后，他想起了过去曾送给这个朋友一座赤陶半身像。那是这个朋友所喜欢的《钦差大臣》一书的作者的半身像。他想起果戈理也是发疯而死的，不由得感到冥冥之中有一股力量在支配他们。

他已筋疲力竭之际，偶尔读到拉迪盖[16]临终的话，又一次觉得听见了众神的笑声。那句话说：“神兵来捉我。”他想与他的迷信和感伤主义做斗争。可是从肉体上来说，他已经不可能进行任何斗争了。“世纪末的恶魔”无疑正在摧残他。他对虔信神的中世纪的人们感到羡慕。可是他终究不可能信神——信仰神的爱。连科克托[17]都是信神的啊！

五十一 败北

他执笔的手颤抖起来了，甚至还流了口水。除非服用零点八毫克的佛罗那[18]，他的头脑没有一次清醒过，而且清醒也不过半小时或一小时。他只有在幽暗中挨着时光，直好像是将一把崩了刃的细剑当拐杖拄着。

一九二七年六月，遗稿

（文学朴 译）

[1] 久米正雄（1891—1952），日本小说家、剧作家。

[2] 波德莱尔（1821—1867），法国诗人。诗中歌咏死亡，充满悲观厌世情绪。

[3] 文中所指为19世纪末，颓废派的时期。

[4] 指埃德蒙·德·龚古尔（1822—1896）和茹尔·德·龚古尔（1830—1870），法国小说家，文学史上称“龚古尔兄弟”。

[5] 霍普特曼（1862—1946），德国剧作家。

[6] 《天真汉》是法国启蒙思想家、哲学家、作家伏尔泰（1694—1778）的哲理小说。

[7] 见希腊神话中的故事《代达罗斯和伊卡洛斯》。伊卡洛斯和他的父亲代达罗斯一起逃离克瑞忒，伊卡洛斯不听父亲的话，飞近太阳，人工翼上的蜡被晒化，坠海而死。

[8] 塞尚（1839—1906），法国画家，后期印象派的代表人物。

[9] 原文为英文。

[10] 英语：诗集（尤指用波斯文或阿拉伯文写的个人诗集）。

[11] 阿克罗波利斯是雅典的卫城。

[12] 各各他是耶稣被钉上十字架的地方。

[13] 《新生》（1918—1919）是岛崎藤村的自传体长篇小说，描写作者做出了背离社会道德的事情后，交代了事实经过，从而获得“新生”。

[14] 弗朗索瓦·维庸（1431—约1463），法国抒情诗人，贫民出身，一生颠沛流离。

[15] 斯威夫特（1667—1745），英国讽刺作家，生于爱尔兰贫苦家庭，著有《格列佛游记》。他曾参加爱尔兰人民反抗英国统治者的斗争，晚年发疯。

[16] 拉迪盖（1903—1923），法国小说家、诗人。

[17] 科克托（1889—1963），法国诗人、小说家。

[18] 佛罗那是一种安眠药。

Death Register

1

My mother was a madwoman. I never did feel close to her, as a son should feel toward his mother. Hair held in place by a comb, she would sit alone all day puffing on a long, skinny pipe in the house of my birth family in Tokyo’s Shiba Ward. She had a tiny face on a tiny body, and that face of hers, for some reason, was always ashen and lifeless. Once, reading The Story of the Western Wing, I came upon the phrase ‘smell of earth, taste of mud’, and thought immediately of my mother – of her emaciated face in profile.

And so I never had the experience of a mother’s care. I do seem to recall that one time, when my adoptive mother made a point of taking me upstairs to see her, she suddenly conked me on the head with her pipe. In general, though, she was a quiet lunatic. I or my elder sister would sometimes press her to paint a picture for us, and she would do it on a sheet of paper folded in four. And not just with black ink, either. She would apply my sister’s watercolors to blossoming plants or the costumes of children on an outing. The people in her pictures, though, always had fox faces.

My mother died in the autumn of my eleventh year, not so much from illness, I think, as from simply wasting away. I have a fairly clear memory of the events surrounding her death.

A telegram must have arrived to alert us. Late on a windless night, I climbed into a rickshaw with my adoptive mother and sped across the city from Honjo to Shiba. Otherwise in my life I have never used a scarf, but I do recall that on that particular night I had a thin silk handkerchief wrapped around my neck. I also recall that it had some kind of Chinese landscape motif, and that it smelled strongly of Iris Bouquet.

My mother lay on a futon in the eight- mat parlor directly beneath her upstairs room. I knelt beside her, wailing, with my four- year- older sister. I felt especially miserable when I heard someone behind me say, ‘The end is near.’ My mother had been lying there as good as dead, but suddenly she opened her eyes and spoke. Sad as everyone felt, we couldn’t help giggling.

I stayed up by my mother through the following night as well, but that night, for some reason, my tears simply wouldn’t flow. Ashamed to be so unfeeling while right next to me my sister wept almost constantly, I struggled to pretend. Yet I also believed that as long as I was unable to cry, my mother would not die.

On the evening of the third day, though, she did die, with very little suffering. A few times before it happened, she would seem to regain consciousness, look us all in the face, and release an endless stream of tears, but as usual she said not a thing.

Even after her body had been placed in the coffin, I couldn’t keep from breaking down time and again. The old woman we called our ‘Ōji Auntie’, a distant relative, would say, ‘I’m so impressed with you!’ My only thought was that here was a person who let herself be impressed by very strange things.

The day of my mother’s funeral, my sister climbed into a rickshaw holding the memorial tablet, and I followed her inside, holding the censer. I dozed off now and then, waking with a start each time the censer was about to drop from my hand. Still, we seemed never to reach Yanaka. Always I would wake to find the long funeral procession still winding its way through the streets of Tokyo in the autumn sunlight.

The anniversary of my mother’s death is 28 November. The priest gave her the posthumous name of Kimyōin Myōjō Nisshin Daishi. I can remember neither the anniversary of my birth father’s death two decades later nor his posthumous name. Memorizing such things had probably been a matter of pride for me at the age of eleven.

2

I have just the one elder sister. Not very healthy, she is nevertheless the mother of two children. She is not, of course, one of those I want to include in this ‘Death Register.’ Rather, it is the sister who died suddenly just before I was born. Among us three siblings, she was said to be the smartest.

She was certainly the first – which is why they named her ‘Hatsuko’ (First Daughter). Even now a small framed portrait of ‘Little Hatsu’ adorns the Buddhist altar in my house. There is nothing at all sickly- looking about her. Her cheeks, with their little dimples, are as round as ripe apricots.

Little Hatsu was by far the one who received the greatest outpouring of love from my parents. They made a point of sending her all the way from Shiba Shinsenza to attend the kindergarten of a Mrs Summers – I think it was – in Tsukiji. On weekends, though, she would stay with my mother’s family, the Akutagawas, in Honjo. On these outings of hers, Little Hatsu would probably wear Western dresses, which still, in the Meiji twenties, would have seemed very modish. When I was in elementary school, I remember, I used to get remnants of her clothes to put on my rubber doll. Without exception, all the cloth patches were imported calico scattered with tiny printed flowers or musical instruments.

One Sunday afternoon in early spring, when Little Hatsu was strolling through the garden (wearing a Western dress, as I imagine her), she called out to our aunt Fuki in the parlor, ‘Auntie, what’s the name of this tree?’

‘Which one?’

‘This one, with the buds.’

In the garden of my mother’s family, a single low boke[1] trailed its branches over the old well. Little Hatsu, in pigtails, was probably looking up at its thorny branches with big round eyes.

‘It has the same name as you,’ my aunt said, but before she could explain her joke, Hatsu made up one of her own:

‘Then it must be a “dummy” tree.’

My aunt always tells this story whenever the conversation turns to Little Hatsu. Indeed, it’s the only story left to tell about her. Probably not too many days later, Little Hatsu was in her coffin. I don’t remember the posthumous name engraved on her tiny memorial tablet. I do have a strangely clear memory of her death date, though: 5 April.

For some unknown reason, I feel close to this sister I never knew. If ‘Little Hatsu’ were still living, she would be over forty now. And maybe, at that age, she would look like my mother as I recall her upstairs in the Shiba house, blankly puffing away on her pipe. I often feel as if there is a fortyish woman somewhere – a phantom not exactly my mother nor this dead sister – watching over my life. Could this be the effect of nerves wracked by coffee and tobacco? Or might it be the work of some supernatural power giving occasional glimpses of itself to the real world?

3

Because my mother lost her mind, I was adopted into the family of her elder brother shortly after I was born, and so my real father was another parent for whom I had little feeling. He owned a dairy and seems to have been a small- scale success. That father was the person who taught me all about the newly imported fruits and drinks of the day: banana, ice cream, pineapple, rum – and probably much more. I remember once drinking rum in the shade of an oak tree outside the pasture, which was then located in Shinjuku. Rum was an amber- colored drink with little alcohol.

When I was very young, my father would try to entice me back from my adoptive family by plying me with these rare treats. I remember how he once openly tempted me into running away while feeding me ice cream in the Uoei restaurant in Ōmori. At times like this he could be a smooth talker and exude real charm. Unfortunately for him, though, his enticements never worked. This was because I loved my adoptive family too much – and especially my mother’s elder sister, Aunt Fuki.

My father had a short temper and was always fighting with people. When I was in the third year of middle school, I beat him at sumo wrestling by tripping him backwards using a special judo move of mine. He got up and came right after me saying ‘One more go.’ I threw him easily again. He came charging at me for a third time, again saying ‘One more go,’ but now I could see he was angry. My other aunt (Aunt Fuyu, my mother’s younger sister – by then my father’s second wife) was watching all this, and she winked at me a few times behind my father’s back. After grappling with him for a little while, I purposely fell over backwards. I’m sure if I hadn’t lost to him, I would have ended up another victim of my father’s temper.

When I was twenty- eight and still teaching, I received a telegram saying ‘Father hospitalized,’ and I rushed from Kamakura to Tokyo. He was in the Tokyo Hospital with influenza. I spent the next three days there with my Aunts Fuyu and Fuki, sleeping in a corner of the room. I was beginning to feel bored when a call came for me from an Irish reporter friend inviting me out for a meal at a Tsukiji tea house. Using his upcoming departure for America as an excuse, I left for Tsukiji even though my father was on the verge of death.

We had a delightful Japanese dinner in the company of four or five geisha. I think the meal ended around ten o’clock. Leaving the reporter, I was headed down the steep, narrow stairway when, from behind, I heard a soft feminine voice calling me ‘ Ah- san’ in that playful geisha way. I stopped in mid- descent and turned to look up toward the top of the stairs. There, one of the geisha was looking down, her eyes fixed on mine. Wordlessly, I continued down the stairs and stepped into the cab waiting at the front door. The car moved off immediately, but instead of my father what came to mind was the fresh face of that geisha in her Western hairstyle – and in particular her eyes.

Back at the hospital, I found my father eagerly awaiting my return. He sent everyone else outside the two- panel folding screen by the bed, and, gripping and caressing my hand, he began to talk about long- ago matters that I had never known – things from the time when he married my mother. They were inconsequential things – how he and she had gone to shop for a storage chest, or how they had eaten home- delivered sushi – but before I knew it my eyelids were growing hot inside, and down my father’s wasted cheeks, too, tears were flowing.

My father died the next morning without a great deal of suffering. His mind seemed to grow confused before he died, and he would say things like ‘Here comes a warship! Look at all the flags it has flying! Three cheers, everybody!’ I don’t remember his funeral at all. What I do remember is that when we transported his body from the hospital to his home, a great big spring moon was shining down on the hearse.

4

In mid- March of this year, when it was still cold enough for us to carry pocket warmers, my wife and I visited the cemetery for the first time in a long while – a very long while. Still, however, there was no change at all in either the small grave itself (of course) nor in the red pine stretching its branches above it.

The bones of all three people I have included in this‘Death Register’ lie buried in the same corner of the cemetery in Yanaka – indeed, beneath the same gravestone. I recalled the time my mother’s coffin was gently lowered into the grave. They must have done the same with Little Hatsu. In my father’s case, though, I remember the gold teeth mixed in with the tiny white shards of bone at the crematorium.

I don’t much like visiting the cemetery, and I would prefer to forget about my parents and sister if I could. On that particular day, though, perhaps because I was physically debilitated, I found myself staring at the blackened gravestone in the early spring afternoon sunlight and wondering which of the three had been the most fortunate.

　　　　A shimmering of heat –

　　　Outside the grave

　　　　Alone I dwell.

Never before had I sensed these feelings of Jōsō’s pressing in upon me with the force they truly had for me that day.

[1] boke: The name of the tree, known as a Japanese quince (Pyrus japon ica) in English, is a homonym for ‘dimwit’. Before the aunt can joke with her that both she and the tree are ‘boke’, Hatsu cleverly makes up her own remarkably similar word play using ‘baka’ (dummy).

The Life of a Stupid Man

To my friend, Kume Masao:

I leave it to you to decide when and where to publish this manuscript – or whether to publish it at all.

You know most of the people who appear here, but if you do publish this, I don’t want you adding an index identifying them.

I am living now in the unhappiest happiness imaginable. Yet, strangely, I have no regrets. I just feel sorry for anyone unfortunate enough to have had a bad husband, a bad son, a bad father like me. So goodbye, then. I have not tried –consciously, at least – to vindicate myself here.

Finally, I entrust this manuscript to you because I believe you probably know me better than anyone else. I may wear the skin of an urbane sophisticate, but in this manuscript I invite you to strip it off and laugh at my stupidity.

Akutagawa Ryūnosuke

20 June 1927

1. The era

He was upstairs in a bookstore. Twenty years old at the time, he had climbed a ladder set against a bookcase and was searching for the newly- arrived Western books: Maupassant, Baudelaire, Strindberg, Ibsen, Shaw, Tolstoy . . .

The sun threatened to set before long, but he went on reading book spines with undiminished intensity. Lined up before him was not so much an array of books as the fin de siècle itself. Nietzsche, Verlaine, the Goncourt brothers, Dostoevsky, Hauptmann, Flaubert . . .

He took stock of their names as he struggled with the impending gloom. The books began to sink into the somber shadows. Finally his stamina gave out and he made ready to climb down. At that very moment, directly overhead, a single bare light bulb came on. Standing on his perch on top of the ladder, he looked down at the clerks and customers moving among the books. They were strangely small – and shabby.

Life is not worth a single line of Baudelaire.

He stood on the ladder, watching them below . . .

2. moTher

All the lunatics had been dressed in the same gray clothing, which seemed to give the large room an even more depressing look. One of them sat at an organ, playing a hymn over and over with great intensity. Another was dancing – or, rather, leaping about – in the very center of the room.

He stood watching this spectacle with a doctor of notably healthy complexion. Ten years earlier, his mother had been in no way different from these lunatics. In no way. And in fact in their smell he caught a whiff of his own mother’s smell.

‘Shall we go, then?’

The doctor led him down a corridor to another room. In a corner there were several brains soaking in large jars of alcohol. On one of the brains he noticed something faintly white, almost like a dollop of egg white. As he stood there chatting with the doctor, he thought again of his mother.

‘The man who had this brain here was an engineer for the XX lighting company. He always thought of himself as a big shiny black dynamo.’

To avoid the doctor’s eyes, he kept looking out the window. There was nothing out there but a brick wall topped with embedded broken bottles. It did, though, have thin growths of moss in dull white patches.

3. The house

He was living in the upstairs room of a house in the suburbs. The second story tilted oddly because the ground was unstable.

In this room, his aunt would often quarrel with him, though not without occasional interventions from his adoptive parents. Still, he loved this aunt more than anyone. She never married, and by the time he was twenty, she was an old woman close to sixty.

He often wondered, in that suburban second story, if people who loved each other had to cause each other pain. Even as the thought crossed his mind, he was aware of the floor’s eerie tilt.

4. ToKyo

A thick layer of cloud hung above the Sumida River. From the window of the little steamer, he watched the Mukōjima bank drawing closer. To his eyes, the blossoming cherry trees there looked as dreary as rags in a row. But almost before he knew it, in those trees – those cherry trees that had lined the bank of Mukōjima since the Edo Period –he was beginning to discover himself.

5. ego

He and an elder colleague sat at a café table puffing on cigarettes. He said very little, but he paid close attention to his companion’s every word.

‘I spent half the day riding around in an automobile.’

‘Was there something you needed to do?’

Cheek resting on his hand, the elder colleague replied with complete abandon, ‘No, I just felt like riding around.’

The words released him into a world of which he knew nothing – a world of ‘ego’ close to the gods. He felt a kind of pain but, at the same time, a kind of joy.

The café was extremely small. Beneath a framed picture of the god Pan, however, a rubber tree in a red pot thrust its thick leaves out and down.

6. illness

In a steady ocean breeze, he spread out the large English dictionary and let his fingertip find words for him.

Talaria: A winged sandal.

Tale: A story.

Talipot: A coconut palm native to the East Indies. Trunk from 50 to 100 feet in height, leaves used for umbrellas, fans, hats, etc. Blooms once in 70 years . . .

His imagination painted a vivid picture of this bloom. He then experienced an unfamiliar scratchy feeling in his throat, and before he knew it he had dropped a glob of phlegm on the dictionary. Phlegm? But it was not phlegm. He thought of the shortness of life and once again imagined the coconut blossom – the blossom of the coconut palm soaring on high far across the ocean.

7. PicTure

It happened for him suddenly – quite suddenly. He was standing outside a bookstore, looking at a Van Gogh volume, when he suddenly understood what a ‘picture’was. True, the Van Gogh was just a book of reproductions, but even in the photographs of those paintings, he sensed the vivid presence of nature.

This passion for pictures gave him a whole new way of looking at the world. He began to pay constant attention to the curve of a branch or the swell of a woman’s cheek.

One rainy autumn evening, he was walking beneath an iron railroad bridge in the suburbs. Below the bank on the far side of the bridge stood a horse cart. As he passed it, he sensed that someone had come this way before. Someone? There was no need for him to wonder who that‘someone’ might have been. In his twenty- three- year- old heart, a Dutchman with a cut ear and a long pipe in his mouth was fixing his gaze on this dreary landscape.

8. sParKs: floWers of fire

Soaked by the rain, he trod along the asphalt. It was a heavy downpour. In the enveloping spray, he caught the smell of his rubberized coat.

Just then he saw the overhead trolley line giving off purple sparks and was strangely moved. His jacket pocket concealed the manuscript of the piece he was planning to publish in their little magazine. Walking through the rain, he looked back and up once again at the trolley line.

The cable was still sending sharp sparks into the air. He could think of nothing in life that he especially desired, but those purple sparks – those wildly- blooming flowers of fire – he would trade his life for the chance to hold them in his hands.

9. cadavers

A tag on a wire dangled from the big toe of each cadaver. The tags were inscribed with names, ages, and such. His friend bent over one corpse, peeling back the skin of its face with a deftly wielded scalpel. An expanse of beautiful yellow fat lay beneath the skin.

He studied the cadaver. He needed to do this to finish writing a story – a piece set against a Heian Period background – but he hated the stink of the corpses, which was like the smell of rotting apricots. Meanwhile, with wrinkled brow, his friend went on working his scalpel.

‘You know, we’re running out of cadavers these days,’his friend said.

His reply was ready: ‘If I needed a corpse, I’d kill someone without the slightest malice.’ Of course the reply stayed where it was – inside his heart.

10. The masTer

He was reading the Master’s book beneath a great oak tree. Not a leaf stirred on the oak in the autumn sunlight. Far off in the sky, a scale with glass pans hung in perfect balance. He imagined such a vision as he read the Master’s book . . .

11. daWn

Night gradually gave way to dawn. He found himself on a street corner surveying a vast market. The swarming people and vehicles in the market were increasingly bathed in rose light.

He lit a cigarette and ambled into the market. Just then a lean black dog started barking at him, but he was not afraid. Indeed, he even loved this dog.

In the very center of the marketplace, a sycamore spread its branches in all directions. He stood at the foot of the tree and looked up through the branches at the sky. A single star shone directly above him.

It was his twenty- fifth year – the third month after he first met the Master.

12. naval PorT

Gloom filled the interior of the miniature submarine. Crouching down amid all the machinery, he peered into a small scope. What he saw there was a view of the bright naval port.

‘You should be able to see the Kongō, too,’ the naval officer explained to him.

As he was looking at the small warship through the square eyepiece, the thought of parsley popped into his mind for no reason – faintly aromatic parsley on top of a thirty- yen serving of beefsteak.

13. The masTer’s deaTh

In the wind after the rain, he walked down the platform of the new station. The sky was still dark. Across from the platform three or four railway laborers were swinging picks and singing loudly. The wind tore at the men’s song and at his own emotions.

He left his cigarette unlit and felt a pain close to joy.‘Master near death,’ read the telegram he had thrust into his coat pocket.

Just then the 6 a.m. Tokyo- bound train began to snake its way toward the station, rounding a pine- covered hill in the distance and trailing a wisp of smoke.

14. marriage

The day after he married her, he delivered a scolding to his wife: ‘No sooner do you arrive here than you start wasting our money.’ But the scolding was less from him than from his aunt, who had ordered him to deliver it. His wife apologized to him, of course, and to the aunt as well – with the potted jonquils she had bought for him in the room.

15. he and she

They led a peaceful life, surrounded by the garden’s broad green bashō leaves.

It helped that their house was located in a town by the shore a full hour’s train ride from Tokyo.

16. PilloW

Pillowing his head on his rose- scented skepticism, he read a book by Anatole France. That even such a pillow might hold a god half- horse, he remained unaware.

17. buTTerfly

A butterfly fluttered its wings in a wind thick with the smell of seaweed. His dry lips felt the touch of the butterfly for the briefest instant, yet the wisp of wing dust still shone on his lips years later.

18. moon

He happened to pass her on the stairway of a certain hotel. Her face seemed to be bathed in moonglow even now, in daylight. As he watched her walk on (they had never met), he felt a loneliness he had not known before.

19. man- made Wings

He moved on from Anatole France to the eighteenth- century philosophers, though not to Rousseau. Perhaps this was because one side of him – the side easily moved by passion – was too close to Rousseau. Instead, he approached the author of Candide, who was closer to another side of him – the cool and richly intellectual side.

At twenty- nine, life no longer held any brightness for him, but Voltaire supplied him with man- made wings.

Spreading these man- made wings, he soared with ease into the sky. The higher he flew, the farther below him sank the joys and sorrows of a life bathed in the light of intellect. Dropping ironies and smiles upon the shabby towns below, he climbed through the open sky, straight for the sun – as if he had forgotten about that ancient Greek who plunged to his death in the ocean when his man- made wings were singed by the sun.

20. shacKles

He and his wife came to live with his adoptive parents when he went to work for a newspaper. He saw his contract, written on a single sheet of yellow paper, as a great source of strength. Later, however, he came to realize that the contract saddled him with all the obligations and the company with none.

21. crazy girl

Two rickshaws sped down a deserted country road beneath overcast skies. From the sea breeze it was clear that the road was headed toward the ocean. Puzzled that he felt not the slightest excitement about this rendezvous, he sat in the second rickshaw thinking about what had drawn him here. It was certainly not love. And if it was not love, then . . . but to avoid the conclusion, he had to tell himself, At least we are in this as equals.

The person riding in the front rickshaw was a crazy girl. And she was not alone in her madness: her younger sister had killed herself out of jealousy.

There’s nothing I can do about this anymore.

He now felt a kind of loathing for this crazy girl – this woman who was all powerful animal instinct.

The two rickshaws soon passed a cemetery where the smell of the shore was strong. Several blackened, pagoda- shaped gravestones stood within the fence, which was woven of brushwood and decorated with oyster shells. He caught a glimpse of the ocean gleaming beyond the gravestones and suddenly – inexplicably – he felt contempt for the woman’s husband for having failed to capture her heart.

22. a PainTer

It was just a magazine illustration, but the ink drawing of a rooster showed a remarkable individuality. He asked a friend to tell him about the painter.

A week later, the painter himself came to pay him a visit. This was one of the most remarkable events in his entire life. He discovered in this painter a poetry of which no one else was aware. In addition, he discovered in himself a soul of which he himself had been unaware.

One chilly autumn evening, he was reminded of the painter by a stalk of corn: the way it stood there armed in its rough coat of leaves, exposing its delicate roots atop the mounded earth like so many nerves, it was also a portrait of his own most vulnerable self. The discovery only served to increase his melancholy.

It’s too late now. But when the time comes . . .

23. The Woman

From where he stood, the plaza was beginning to darken. He walked into the open space feeling slightly feverish. The electric lights in the windows of several large office buildings flashed against the clear, faintly silvery sky.

He halted at the curb and decided to wait for the woman there. Five minutes later she came walking toward him looking somewhat haggard. ‘I’m exhausted,’ she said with a smile when she caught sight of him. They walked through the fading light of the plaza side- by- side. This was their first time together. He felt ready to abandon anything and everything to be with her.

In the automobile she stared at him and asked, ‘You’re not going to regret this?’

‘Not at all,’ he answered with conviction.

She pressed her hand on his and said, ‘I know I won’t have any regrets.’

Again, as she said this, her face seemed to be bathed in moonlight.

24. The birTh

He stood by the sliding screen, looking down at the midwife in her white surgical gown washing the baby. Whenever soap got in its eyes, the baby would wrinkle up its sad little face and let out a loud wail. It looked like a baby rat, and its odor stirred him to these irrepressible thoughts –

Why did this one have to be born – to come into the world like all the others, this world so full of suffering? Why did this one have to bear the destiny of having a father like me?

This was the first son his wife bore him.

25. sTrindberg

He stood in the doorway, watching some grimy Chinese men playing Mahjongg in the moonlight where figs bloomed. Back in his room, he started reading The Confessions of a Fool beneath a squat lamp. He had barely read two pages when he caught himself with a sour smile. So – the lies that Strindberg wrote to his lover, the Countess, were hardly different from his own.

26. anTiQuiTy

He was nearly overwhelmed by peeling Buddhas, heavenly beings, horses and lotus blossoms. Looking up at them, he forgot everything – even his good fortune at having escaped the clutches of the crazy girl.

27. sParTan disciPline

He was walking down a back street with a friend when a hooded rickshaw came charging in their direction. He was surprised to recognize the passenger as the woman he had been with the night before. Her face seemed to be bathed in moonglow even now, in the daylight. With his friend present, they could not exchange even ordinary greetings.

‘Pretty woman,’ his friend said.

Eyes on the spring hills at the end of the street, he answered without the slightest hesitation:

‘Yes, very.’

28. murder

The country road stank of cow manure in the sun. Mopping his sweat, he struggled up the steep hill. The ripened wheat on either side of the road gave off a pleasant scent.

‘Kill him, kill him . . .’

Before he knew it, he was muttering this aloud to himself over and over. Kill whom? It was obvious to him. He recalled the cringing fellow with close- cropped hair.

Just then, the domed roof of a Catholic church appeared beyond the yellow wheat.

29. form

It was a cast- iron saké bottle. With its finely incised lines, it had managed at some point to teach him the beauty of‘form’.

30. rain

In the big bed he talked with her about many things. Beyond the bedroom window it was raining. The blossoms of the crinum tree had begun to rot in the rain, it seemed. Her face, as always, looked as if it were in moonlight, yet talking with her was not entirely free of boredom. He lay on his stomach, had himself a quiet smoke, and realized he had now been with her for seven years.

Do I still love this woman? he asked himself. He was in the habit of observing himself so closely that the answer came as a surprise to him: I do.

31. The greaT earThQuaKe

The odor was something close to overripe apricots. Catching a hint of it as he walked through the charred ruins, he found himself thinking such thoughts as these: The smell of corpses rotting in the sun is not as bad as I would have expected. When he stood before a pond where bodies were piled upon bodies, however, he discovered that the old Chinese expression, ‘burning the nose’, was no mere sensory exaggeration of grief and horror. What especially moved him was the corpse of a child of twelve or thirteen. He felt something like envy as he looked at it, recalling such expressions as ‘Those whom the gods love die young.’ Both his sister and his half- brother had lost their houses to fire. His sister’s husband, though, was on a suspended sentence for perjury.

Too bad we didn’t all die.

Standing in the charred ruins, he could hardly keep from feeling this way.

32. fighT

He had a quarrel with his half- brother that ended in a physical brawl. True, he was a constant source of pressure for this younger brother, who in turn cost him a good deal of freedom. Relatives were always telling the young man, ‘be like your brother’, but for him, this was like being bound hand and foot. Locked in each other’s grip, they fell near the edge of the veranda. He still remembers the one crape myrtle bush in the garden by the veranda – its load of brilliant red blossoms beneath a sky about to drop its rainy burden.

33. hero

From the window of Voltaire’s house, he found himself looking up toward a high mountain. There was nothing to be seen on the glacier- topped mountain, not even a vulture. There was, however, a short Russian man doggedly climbing the trail.

After night fell, beneath the bright lamp in Voltaire’s house, he wrote this didactic poem (still picturing that Russian man climbing the mountain).

You who more than anyone obeyed the Ten Commandments

Are you who more than anyone broke the Ten Commandments.

You who more than anyone loved the masses

Are you who more than anyone despised the masses.

You who more than anyone burned with ideals Are you who more than anyone knew reality.

You are what our Eastern world has bred –An electric locomotive that smells of flowering grasses.

34. color

At thirty he found himself loving a piece of vacant land. It contained only some moss and scattered bits of brick and tile. To his eyes, however, it was exactly like a Cezanne landscape.

He suddenly recalled his passions of seven or eight years earlier. And when he did so, he realized that seven or eight years earlier he had known nothing about color.

35. comic PuPPeT

He wanted to live life so intensely that he could die at any moment without regrets. But still, out of deference to his adoptive parents and his aunt, he kept himself in check. This created both light and dark sides to his life. Seeing a comic puppet in a Western tailor’s shop made him wonder how close he himself was to such a figure. His self beyond consciousness, however – his ‘second self’ – had long since put such feelings into a story.

36. Tedium

He was walking through a field of plume grass with a university student. ‘You fellows still have a strong will to live, I suppose?’

‘Yes, of course, but you, too . . .’

‘Not any more,’ he said. He was telling the truth. At some point he had lost interest in life. ‘I do have the will to create, though.’

‘But surely the will to create is a form of the will to live . . . ?’

To this he did not reply. Above the field’s red plumes rose the sharp outline of an active volcano. He viewed the peak with something close to envy, though he had no idea why this was so . . .

37. ‘Woman of hoKuriKu’

He met a woman he could grapple with intellectually. He barely extricated himself from the crisis by writing a number of lyric poems, some under the title ‘Woman of Hokuriku’. These conveyed a sense of heartbreak as when one knocks away a brilliant coating of snow frozen onto a tree trunk.

Hat of sedge dancing in the wind:

How could it fail to drop into the road?

What need I fear for my name?

For your name alone do I fear.

38. PunishmenT

They were on the balcony of a hotel surrounded by trees in bud. He was drawing pictures to amuse a little boy –the only son of the crazy girl, with whom he had broken off relations seven years earlier.

The crazy girl lit a cigarette and watched them play. With an oppressive feeling, he went on drawing trains and airplanes. Fortunately, the boy was not his, but it still pained him greatly when the child called him ‘uncle’.

After the boy wandered off, the crazy girl, still smoking her cigarette, said suggestively:

‘Don’t you think he looks like you?’

‘Not at all. Besides –’

‘But you do know about “prenatal influence”, I’m sure.’

He looked away from her in silence, but in his heart he wanted to strangle her.

39. mirrors

He was in the corner of a café, chatting with a friend. The friend was eating a baked apple and talking about the recent cold weather when he himself began to sense a certain contradiction in the conversation.

‘Hey, wait a minute – you’re still a bachelor, right?’

‘Not exactly: I’m getting married next month.’

That silenced him. The mirrors set in the café walls reflected him in endless numbers. Coldly. Menacingly.

40. dialogue

Why do you attack the present social system?

Because I see the evils that capitalism has engendered.

Evils? I thought you recognized no difference between good and evil. How do you make a living, then?

He engaged thus in dialogue with an angel – an angel in an impeccable top hat.

41. illness

He suffered an onslaught of insomnia. His physical strength began to fade as well. The doctors gave him various diagnoses – gastric hyperacidity, gastric atony, dry pleurisy, neurasthenia, chronic conjunctivitis, brain fatigue . . .

But he knew well enough what was wrong with him: he was ashamed of himself and afraid of them – afraid of the society he so despised.

One afternoon when snow clouds hung over the city, he was in the corner of a café, smoking a cigar and listening to music from the gramophone on the other side of the room. He found the music permeating his emotions in a strange new way. When it ended, he walked over to the gramophone to read the label on the record.

‘Magic Flute – Mozart.’

All at once it became clear to him: Mozart too had broken the Ten Commandments and suffered. Probably not the way he had, but . . .

He bowed his head and returned to his table in silence.

42. The laughTer of The gods

At thirty- five, he was walking through a pinewood with the spring sun beating down on it. He was recalling, too, the words he had written a few years earlier: ‘It is unfortunate for the gods that, unlike us, they cannot commit suicide.’

43. nighT

Night closed in again. The rough sea sent up spray in the fading light. Beneath these skies, he married his wife anew. This brought them joy, but there was suffering as well. With them, their three sons watched the lightning over the open sea. His wife, holding one of the boys in her arms, seemed to be fighting back tears.

‘See the boat over there?’ he asked her.

‘Yes . . .’

‘That boat with the mast cracked in two . . .’

44. deaTh

Taking advantage of his sleeping alone, he tried to hang himself with a sash tied over the window lattice. When he slipped his head into the sash, however, he suddenly became afraid of death. Not that he feared the suffering he would have to experience at the moment of dying. He decided to try it again, using his pocket watch to see how long it would take. This time, everything began to cloud over after a short interval of pain. He was sure that once he got past that, he would enter death. Checking the hands of his watch, he discovered that the pain lasted one minute and twenty- some seconds. It was pitch dark outside the lattices, but the wild clucking of chickens echoed in the darkness.

45. divan

Divan was giving him new inner power. This was an‘Oriental Goethe’ he had not known before. He saw the author standing with quiet confidence on the Other Shore, far beyond good and evil, and he felt an envy close to despair. In his eyes, the poet Goethe was even greater than the poet Christ. For in the heart of the poet Goethe, there bloomed not only the roses of the Acropolis and Golgotha but the rose of Arabia as well. If only he had the least ability to follow in this poet’s footsteps!

Once he had finished reading Divan and recovered somewhat from its terrifying emotional impact, he could only despise himself for having been born such a eunuch in life!

46. lies

He felt the suicide of his sister’s husband as a terrible blow. Now he was responsible for his sister’s family as well. To him at least, his future looked as gloomy as the end of the day. He felt something like a sneer for his own spiritual bankruptcy (he was aware of all of his faults and weak points, every single one of them), but he went on reading one book after another. Even Rousseau’s Confessions, though, was full of the most heroic lies. And when it came to Tōson’s New Life, he felt he had never met such a cunning hypocrite as that novel’s protagonist. The one who truly moved him, though, was François Villon. He found in that poet’s many works the ‘beautiful male’.

Sometimes in his dreams the image would come to him of Villon waiting to be hanged. Like Villon, he had several times nearly fallen to the ultimate depths of life, but neither his situation nor his physical energy would permit him to keep this up. He grew gradually weaker, like the tree Swift saw so long ago, withering from the top down.

47. Playing WiTh fire

She had a radiant face, like the morning sun on a thin sheet of ice. He was fond of her, but he did not love her, nor had he ever laid a finger on her.

‘I’ve heard you want to die,’ she said.

‘Yes – or rather, it’s not so much that I want to die as that I’m tired of living.’

This dialogue led to a vow to die together.

‘It would be a Platonic suicide, I suppose,’ she said.

‘A Platonic double suicide.’

He was amazed at his own sangfroid.

48. deaTh

He did not die with her, but he took a certain satisfaction in his never having touched her. She often spoke with him as though their dialogue had never happened. She did once give him a bottle of cyanide with the remark,‘As long as we have this, it will give us both strength.’

And it did indeed give him strength. Sitting in a rattan chair, observing the new growth of a shii tree, he often thought of the peace that death would give him.

49. sTuffed sWan

With the last of his strength, he tried to write his autobiography, but it did not come together as easily as he had hoped. This was because of his remaining pride and skepticism, and a calculation of what was in his own best interest. He couldn’t help despising these qualities in himself; but neither could he help feeling that ‘Everyone is the same under the skin.’ He tended to think that Goethe’s title ‘Poetry and Truth’ could serve for anyone’s autobiography, but he knew that not everyone is moved by literature. His own works were unlikely to appeal to people who were not like him and had not lived a life like his – this was another feeling that worked upon him. And so he decided to write his own brief ‘Poetry and Truth’.

Once he had finished writing ‘The Life of a Stupid Man’, he happened to see a stuffed swan in a secondhand shop. It stood with its head held high, but its wings were yellowed and moth- eaten. As he thought about his life, he felt both tears and mockery welling up inside him. All that lay before him was madness or suicide. He walked down the darkening street alone, determined now to wait for the destiny that would come to annihilate him.

50. caPTive

One of his friends went mad. He had always felt close to this man because he understood far more deeply than anyone else the loneliness that lurked beneath his jaunty mask. He visited him a few times after the madness struck.

‘You and I are both possessed by a demon,’ the friend whispered, ‘the demon of the fin de siècle.’

Two or three days later, he heard, the man ate roses on the way to a hot- spring resort. When the friend was hospitalized, he recalled once sending him a terra cotta piece. It was a bust of the author of The Inspector General, one of the friend’s favorite writers. Thinking how Gogol, too, had gone mad, he could not help feeling that there was a force governing all of them.

Just as he reached the point of utter exhaustion, he happened to read Raymond Radiguet’s dying words,‘God’s soldiers are coming to get me,’ and sensed once again the laughter of the gods. He tried to fight against his own superstitions and sentimentalism, but he was physically incapable of putting up any kind of struggle. The ‘demon of the fin de siècle’ was preying on him without a doubt. He envied medieval men’s ability to find strength in God. But for him, believing in God – in God’s love –was an impossibility, though even Cocteau had done it!

51. defeaT

The hand with the pen began to tremble, and before long he was even drooling. The only time his head ever cleared was after a sleep induced by eight- tenths of a gram of Veronal, and even then it never lasted more than thirty minutes or an hour. He barely made it through each day in the gloom, leaning as it were upon a chipped and narrow sword.

萎缩的胳膊

一 遭遗弃的挤奶姑娘

这是一个有八十头奶牛的牛奶场，一群挤奶工，正式的和临时的，都在干活儿；季节虽然还不过是四月初的春天，可放牧全在那些水浇地牧场上，所以那些奶牛个个都是“满桶奶的”。时间大约到了傍晚六点钟，那些大个头、红颜色、长方块的畜生，有四分之三已经挤完了奶，这样大家就有机会聊聊天了。

“我听说，他明天真要把新娘子带回家来啦。他们今天已经从安格伯瑞动身了。”

声音仿佛发自那头叫作樱桃的母牛的肚子，不过说话的人可是一个挤奶妇，她的脸埋在那头一动不动的母牛肋条上。

“有谁瞧见过她吗？”另一个人问。

先说话的那个人说，没有。“可他们说，她真够得上是玫瑰脸蛋儿，樱草花球小身段儿。”她又这样加了一句。这个挤奶妇一边说，一边转过脸去，这样，她就可以隔着她那头母牛的尾巴对场院的那一边瞟上一眼。那里有一个姿容憔悴的瘦削女人，大约三十岁模样，和别人多少分开了一点，正在挤奶。

“他们说，比他小好些岁呢。”第二个人接着说，也对那个方向投去若有所思的一瞥。

“那么，你说他多大岁数了？”

“三十上下吧。”

“更像四十岁。”旁边一个年岁大的挤奶男工插了一句，他罩了一件大白围裙或者说“工作罩衣”，帽檐向下耷拉着，看起来像是一个女人。“他出世的时候，水坝还没筑，我在那里提水的时候，还没拿大人的工资呢。”

议论越来越热闹，牛奶往下流的声音变得断断续续的了，这时从另一头母牛肚子那儿传来颇有权威的声音：“嗨，嗨，农场主洛吉的年纪，或者洛吉的新太太，究竟和咱们有啥关系？不管他或者她是多大岁数，反正我租他的这些奶牛，每头牛每年都得交他九镑。接着干你们的活儿吧，要不，咱们干不完天就黑了。晚霞已经把天都照红啦。”说这话的人是牛奶场的老板，这些挤奶的女工和男工都是他雇的。

谁也没有再公然大声议论农场主洛吉的婚事了，不过第一个说话的女工仍在她那头牛下面对她的近邻嘀咕：“她可不好受啦。”她指的是刚才提到的那个瘦削憔悴的挤奶女工。

“啊，不会的，”第二个说，“他已经有几年没跟若达·布茹克说话了。”

挤完了奶，他们刷净了自己的奶桶，把它们挂在奶桶架上。它像通常的奶桶架一样，是用一根剥了皮的橡树枝做的，上面装着许多钩子，直直地竖在地上，像一盘巨大的鹿角。大多数人都朝着四面八方回家去了。那个一言未发的瘦女人，和一个大约十二岁的男孩走到一起，他们俩也顺着那块场地走上去了。

他们走的路和别人不同，通向水浇牧场上面一块高出来的孤零零的地方，离爱敦荒原的边缘不远，当他们走到家门附近的时候，可以远远看见荒原那黑乎乎的影子。

“他们刚才在场院里说，你爸爸明天要把他那个年轻的媳妇从安格伯瑞带回来了，”那个女人说，“我想打发你到市场上去干点事，你准保可以碰见他们。”

“好吧，妈妈，”男孩说，“那么爸爸结婚了吗？”

“是……你可以看她一眼。要是你真看到她了，就告诉我她什么样。”

“好吧，妈妈。”

“她是长得黑还是白，个儿高不高——是不是跟我一样高。还有，她看起来是不是像一个靠干活儿吃饭的女人，或者是一个富裕惯了的人，从来没有干过什么活儿，显出一副太太的样子，就像我想的那样。”

“好。”

他们在苍茫暮色中爬上那座小山，走进自己的农舍。农舍四面是土墙，多次雨水冲刷，已经把墙面冲出一道道的沟纹和凹洼，原来那种平整的墙面，一点也看不见了，而上面铺草的房顶，时而露出一根椽子，像是一根骨头戳破了皮肤露在外面。

她跪在炉灶旁边，两块泥煤架在前面，煤块中间放着石楠的干枝，她用力吹那堆红热的余烬，一直吹到泥煤燃起了火苗。火光照亮了她苍白的脸颊，使她那对曾经看起来很漂亮的眼睛，好像又漂亮起来了。“是的，”她接着又说起来，“看她长得是黑还是白，还有，要是能够看得到，留神一下她那双手白不白，要是不白，就看看它们是不是做过家务活儿，或者是像我这双挤奶的手。”

男孩照样答应了，这次有点心不在焉，他母亲没有注意到，他正在用一把小刀，在山毛榉木靠背椅上刻一道凹痕。

二 年轻媳妇

从安格伯瑞到霍姆斯托克的大道，基本都是平路，只有一个地方有个很陡的上坡道，使它显得不那么单调。赶集回家的农夫，都是一路让马小跑着，到了这段短短的陡坡，才赶着马缓慢爬坡。

第二天黄昏，太阳还挺亮，一辆崭新漂亮的轻便双轮马车，由一匹健壮的牝马拉着，沿着那条平川大道向西飞跑。这辆车车身是柠檬色的，车轮是红色的。赶车人是个年富力强的自耕农，胡子刮得干干净净，像个演戏的，脸色红里透青。一个兴旺发达的农夫，在镇上做了几笔顺手的买卖回家，常常就是这样满面生辉。他身旁坐着一个女人，比他年轻得多，简直可以说还是一个女孩儿。她的脸色也很光鲜，但那完全是另外一种性质——柔媚缥缈，像是从一堆玫瑰花瓣透过来的光辉。

没有什么人这样赶路，因为这不是一条主要的大道。在这条沙砾铺成的白色长带上，他们前面空空荡荡，只有一个几乎并不活动的小黑点，它渐渐地变成了一个男孩的模样，好似一只蜗牛正在慢慢向上爬，而且不断地回过头来朝后面张望。他背的那个沉重的包，如果说不是他步履缓慢的理由，也可以说是某种借口。那辆欢腾跳跃的轻便马车，来到前面提到的那个陡坡下面，放慢了速度，这时那个步行的男孩在前面不过几码[1]的地方。他一只手放在屁股上托着那个大包，和马并排走着，同时回过头来，死死盯住农场主的媳妇，好像要把她仔仔细细琢磨个透似的。

夕阳迎面照在她的脸上，把她五官的每一个部分，从她那小巧鼻孔的曲线直到她那双眼睛的颜色都照得一清二楚。那个农场主，对男孩这样死乞白赖地盯着看，似乎感到恼火，可是并没有赶他走，吩咐他让路，因此这个小小子一直走在他们前面。他的眼睛一直死盯着她，等到他们到达坡顶，农场主脸上露出放下心来的神情，撒开马小跑起来——从外表上看，不再注意那个男孩究竟怎样了。

“看那可怜的男孩盯着我看的那副神情！”年轻媳妇说。

“是呀，亲爱的，我看见他是在盯着你瞧。”

“他是村里的人吧，我猜？”

“是附近的一个人。我想他是和他妈住在一两英里[2]远的地方。”

“毫无疑问，他知道我们是谁吧？”

“啊，是的，你一定得预料到，刚开始人家会盯着你瞧，我漂亮的格楚德。”

“我料到了——不过我以为，这个可怜的男孩盯着我们瞧，可能是想让我们帮他带一下他背的那个沉重的大包，而不是出于好奇。”

“啊，不对，”她丈夫脱口而出，“这些乡下小子，只要东西一上肩，就可以背上一英担[3]，再说，他那个包看起来很大，实际上并不那么重。好啦，再走上一英里，我就可以远远地指给你看我们住的那所房子——要是我们赶到那儿天还不太黑的话。”车轮滚滚向前，又像以前那样把砂土碾得向四周乱迸，终于出现了一所占地阔大的白房子，房后还有一些专为干农活儿用的房子和干草堆。

这时候，那个男孩加快了脚步，在离这所白色农庄还有差不多一英里半的地方，拐到一条小路上，向着那些比较贫瘠的草场爬上去，一直走到他母亲的那所村舍。

她干完了她当天在外面奶场上挤奶的活儿，已经回到家里，正借着渐渐昏暗的光线，在门洞里洗菜。“把这个网兜拿一会儿。”男孩刚一走进来，她没有先打招呼就这样说。

他赶忙扔下他那个大包袱，抓住盛菜网兜的边，她一边往兜里放正在滴水的卷心菜，一边继续说话：“怎么样，你看见她了吗？”

“嗯，挺清楚的。”

“她像个太太吗？”

“嘿，不单像，还是个不折不扣的太太呢。”

“她年轻吗？”

“嗯，她已经是个大人啦。她那神气，十足是个女人。”

“当然。她的头发和脸蛋儿是什么颜色？”

“她头发是浅色的，脸蛋儿就像一个活的玩具娃娃。”

“她的眼睛，那么，不是像我的眼睛这样深颜色的吧？”

“不，是浅蓝色的，她的嘴长得挺俏挺红，笑起来露出一口白牙。”

“她个儿高吗？”她酸溜溜地问道。

“我看不见。她坐着呢。”

“那么，明天早晨你到霍姆斯托克教堂去，她准会去那儿。早点去，看着她走进去，回家来告诉我，她是不是比我高。”

“那好吧，妈妈。可是你干吗不自己去看看呢？”

“我去看她！她就是这会儿从我窗户前面走过去，我也不会抬头去看她。当然，她是和洛吉先生在一起。他说了些什么？做了些什么？”

“和平常一样。”

“没有注意你？”

“没有。”

第二天，母亲给孩子穿了一件干净的衬衫，打发他到霍姆斯托克教堂去。他到达这座小小的古老建筑的时候正赶上开门，他就第一个走了进去。他在洗礼盘旁边找了个座位，看着教区所有的教民鱼贯而入。阔气的农场主洛吉几乎是最后一个走进来的，伴随他的那个年轻的媳妇，走进教堂走廊，脸上带着羞涩的神情，这对于一个第一次在众人面前露面的端庄淑静的女人来说，也是自然而然的事。大家的目光都盯着她，所以这个年轻人的注视，现在也就没有引起人们的注意了。

他到达家门口的时候，还没等走进屋子，他母亲就问了：“怎么样？”

“她个儿并不高，还有点矮呢！”他回答说。

“啊！”他母亲满意地叫了一声。

“可是她很漂亮——很漂亮。说实话，她挺可爱。”自耕农的媳妇那种年轻鲜艳的神情，甚至给这个秉性多少有点严峻的男孩，显然留下了深刻的印象。

“这就是所有我想要听到的。”他母亲很快地说，“好啦，把桌布铺上。你用铁丝网套住的兔子很嫩，可是要小心，别让谁抓住你——你一直还没告诉我，她的手是什么样的。”

“我根本没见到。她一直没有脱下手套。”

“她今天早晨穿戴的什么？”

“一顶白帽子和一身银灰色的袍子。袍子蹭到教堂条凳上刺啦刺啦地响，声音那么大，那位太太自己听到这声音感到不好意思，脸红得比原先更厉害了，她把衣服拉起来，好让它别再蹭，可是她猛一下坐到位子上，那刺啦声更大了。洛吉先生，他好像很得意，他的背心露着，他那几颗金晃晃的大印吊着，就像一个大老爷似的，可是他太太好像是希望她那件闹人的袍子放在哪里都成，就是别穿在她身上。”

“是吗？不管怎么说，现在这就够啦！”

以后，这个男孩每次偶然碰见这对新婚夫妇，他母亲都要他陆续把他们的情况再讲一遍。若达·布茹克固然只要走上一两英里就可以很容易地亲自见到年轻的洛吉太太，但是她从没打算走这一点路，到农庄房舍所在的地方去。牛奶场的场院就在洛吉这远处的第二个农场里，她每天在场院挤奶的时候，也从来不提最近办的这桩婚事。牛奶场老板租了洛吉的奶牛，对这个高挑挤奶姑娘的身世也知道得清清楚楚，他怀着男子汉的善意，总是不让奶场场院里的这些流言蜚语引起若达苦恼。但是洛吉太太到达以后最初那些日子，周围的环境老是充满这个话题。而若达·布茹克从她孩子的描述和其他挤奶工人偶尔露出的只言片语，也能够在心里描绘出对这个一无所知的洛吉太太的图像，就像照片那样逼真。

三 幻象

新人回家两三个星期后的一天晚上，男孩上床睡了，若达把泥煤灰扒出来放在面前，好让它们熄灭，她在那堆泥煤余火前面坐了很长时间。她就着那些余烬，按照她想象的模样，心里想着那个新媳妇，思考得那样聚精会神，竟忘记时间过去了多久，最后，由于一天工作的疲累，她也去睡觉了。

但是，这一天和前些天来一直萦回在她心中的形象，即使在夜晚也无法赶开。梦中，那个取代她的地位的格楚德·洛吉第一次来看她了。若达·布茹克在睡着以前确信自己真看见她了，而这是不足信的。她梦见这个年轻媳妇穿了一身浅灰色的衣服，戴着一顶白帽子，但是面容却歪歪扭扭，一塌糊涂，好像年纪很大，满脸皱纹。她躺在那儿，这个新媳妇就坐在她的胸脯上。洛吉太太的身体压得越来越重，那双蓝眼睛冷酷无情地死盯着她的脸，然后这个影子又嘲弄地向前伸出左手，好让她戴的那个结婚戒指在若达的眼前熠熠闪耀。睡觉的人精神狂乱，给压得几乎透不过气来，她拼命挣扎。一会儿压在她身上的那个梦魔退到床脚去了，可是仍然死盯着她，随后又逐渐移上前来，重新坐在她胸脯上，又像刚才那样晃着左手。

若达使劲喘着气，最后拼命挣扎，抽出自己的右手，猛地抓住面前这个影子伸出的左臂，迅速把它向后拧着朝地上摔，她自己一下坐起来，同时发出一声低沉的叫喊。

“啊，善心的老天爷呀！”她叫喊着，坐在床边，出了一身冷汗。“这不是做梦——她到这儿来过了！”

甚至到这时候，她都能感觉到那只胳膊在她紧握的手掌中挣扎——好像真是有骨头有肉似的。她看看地上，她曾经把鬼影摔在那儿，但是地上什么也看不见。

若达·布茹克那天夜里再也没睡。第二天清早她去挤牛奶的时候，大家注意到，她的脸色惨白，显得疲乏不堪。她挤出的牛奶颤颤悠悠地流进牛奶桶，她的手到那时还没有平静下来，仍然感觉得到那只胳膊。她回家吃早饭，就好像是到了吃晚饭的时候那样困。

“妈妈，昨天晚上你屋子里有声音，怎么啦？”她儿子问她，“你真从床上滚下来了吧？”

“你听见什么东西摔下来吗？什么时候？”

“刚好钟敲两点的时候。”

她无法解释，吃过早饭就一声不响地干起家务活儿来，男孩帮着她干，因为他讨厌到外面农场地里去，他不愿去，她也就惯着他。十一二点钟的时候，园子的门咔嚓一响，她抬头望着窗户，园子尽头门口站着她幻觉中的那个女人。若达好像一下子呆住了。

“啊，她说过她要来的！”男孩也看到了这个女人，大声喊着。

“这样说过——什么时候？她怎么知道我们？”

“我见过她，和她说过话。我昨天和她说过话。”

“我不是告诉过你了吗？”妈妈满脸通红愤怒地说，“不要和那所房子里的什么人说话，也不要走到那所房子跟前去。”

“我没和她说话，是她先和我说的。我也没有走到那所房子跟前，我在大路上碰到她的。”

“你告诉她什么啦？”

“什么也没有。她说：‘你就是那天从市场上背回那么重一包东西的那个可怜的孩子吗？’她看了看我的靴子，并且说，要是走在湿地上，这靴子没法儿让我的脚不湿，因为靴子都那么破了。我告诉她，我和妈妈一起过，我们为养活自己，已经做得够可以了，而且事实就是这样。那时候她就说了‘我给你带双好点的靴子来，并且看看你妈妈’。不光给我们，她还给牧场上别的人散东西呢。”

洛吉太太这时已经接近屋门口了——不是满身丝绸，像若达梦见在卧室里那样，而是戴了一顶晨帽，穿了一件普通薄料子的袍子，而这比丝绸更适合她。她胳膊上挎着一只篮子。

头天夜里所经历的事情，留下的印象仍然很强烈。布茹克差不多还以为可以从来访客人的脸上看到那些皱纹，那种蔑视，那种冷酷。如果能够躲开，她就会躲开，不和她见面。然而，这所房子并没有后门，洛吉太太轻轻一敲门，孩子就立刻把门闩拔开了。

“我说呢，我找这所房子是找对了。”她一边说，一边瞅了一眼这个小小子，满脸含笑，“可是不是你开门，我还没有把握呢。”

这种形象和举止同幻梦中的影子一模一样，但是她的声音那么难以言传的甜，她的一顾一盼都那么逗人喜欢，她的笑容那么温柔，完全不像若达夜半梦中那个来访的贵客，若达简直无法相信自己的感觉是否正确了。她本来因为非常讨厌而想一躲了事，这时她却真正感到高兴，她幸好没有躲开。洛吉太太篮子里带来了她原来答应给孩子的一双靴子，还有一些别的有用的东西。

面对这些说明洛吉太太对她和她的亲人亲切友善的感情，若达内心不觉在痛苦地责备自己。这个天真无辜的年轻人儿，应该得到她的祝福，而不是她的诅咒。她离开他们以后，屋子里好像少了一种光辉。两天以后，她又来了，想知道那双靴子是不是合脚；在那以后不到两个星期，她又来看了若达一次。这一次男孩不在家。

“我经常出来走走，”洛吉太太说，“你们的房子是我们自己那个教区以外离我们最近的了。我希望你身体很好。可是你看起来好像不太好。”

若达说她很好，的确，两个人比起来，她脸色比较苍白，可是她身体结实，身材高大，比起站在她面前的这位面容娇柔的年轻女人来，更有力量，更能耐劳。谈起谁强壮谁柔弱，谈话也就越来越亲密了。洛吉太太动身离开的时候，若达说：“我希望这里的空气对你合适，太太，希望水浇牧场的潮气对你没有害处。”

年纪轻的这位回答说，这倒没有多大的问题，她总的健康状况通常都是很好的。“不过，你现在提醒我了，”她又接着说下去，“我有点小毛病，叫我闹不明白。它也并不是什么大不了的事，可是我就是弄不清楚。”

她露出她的左手和左胳膊，若达一看，就是她在梦中看见过并且猛地抓住的那只胳膊的样子。胳膊粉红圆润的表皮上，现出的淡淡的颜色带有病态的痕迹，像是给猛力抓住过而留下的手印。若达的眼睛死盯在这些变了颜色的痕迹上。在想象中，她以为她从中辨认出来了她的四根手指头的形状。

“这是怎么弄的？”她不动声色地问。

“我也说不上来，”洛吉太太一边摇头，一边说，“有一天晚上，我睡得很熟，梦见我去到一个有些陌生的地方，突然我的胳膊猛地一疼，疼得很厉害，把我疼醒了。我想，大概是我白天里撞了一下，可是我也记不得这样撞过。”她笑着又加了一句，“我对我亲爱的丈夫开玩笑说，看起来好像是他突然大发雷霆，在那儿打了我一下。噢，我敢说，它很快就会没了的。”

“哈，哈！是呀……那是哪一天夜里有的？”

洛吉太太想了想，然后说，那是两个星期以前的一个夜晚。“我醒过来的时候，记不清我到过哪里。”她又加了一句，“一直到钟敲了两点，这才提醒了我。”

她说出了若达与幻影相遇的那天夜晚和具体钟点，布茹克觉得好像成了一个罪人。这样没有一点矫饰虚夸就透露了真情，使她大为惊恐，但她并不把它设想为奇怪的巧合：闹鬼那天夜里的一切景象，都更加生动地重现在她心里了。

“啊，难道说，”客人走了以后，她自言自语道，“我能违反自己的意愿，对别人施加邪恶的力量吗？”她知道，她失身以后，有人一直偷偷地把她叫作女巫；但是她从来不明白，为什么要把这恶名加在她头上，不去管它也就过去了。难道这就是原因吗？难道像这样的事果真以前也发生过吗？

四 建议

夏天越来越近了，若达·布茹克几乎害怕再见到洛吉太太，尽管她对这个年轻的媳妇差不多可以说很有感情了。若达个人品格上的某些东西似乎要把她自己判为有罪。然而出于命运安排，她有时离开家门不是为了上工，走着走着就走到霍姆斯托克附近去了；因此她们下一次会面也就到了户外。若达想避也避不开那个使她感到神秘的话题，说了不多几句话，她就吞吞吐吐地说：“我想，你的——胳膊已经复原了吧，太太？”其实她早已惊愕地发现，格楚德·洛吉的左胳膊有些直挺挺的。

“不，还没怎么见好。说实在的，根本就没有见好，倒不如说是更坏了。有时候痛得要命。”

“也许你最好还是去找个医生看看，太太。”

她回答说，她已经找过医生了。她丈夫坚持要她去找一个医生。但是那位外科大夫好像根本不懂那只有病的胳膊是怎么回事。他告诉她用热水浸泡，她也泡过了，但是这种治疗一点用处也没有。

“让我看看，好吗？”挤奶妇问道。

洛吉太太把袖子卷上去，露出那个地方，就在手腕上边几英寸[4]。若达·布茹克一看见它，几乎都无法保持镇静了。那并不是像伤口一样的什么东西，但是胳膊上那个地方现出干瘪的样子，那四根手指头的轮廓比前一次显得更清楚了。不仅如此，她还想象出，这些指印刚好就在她恍惚之间使劲抓住的位置：第一根指头朝着格楚德的手腕，第四根指头朝向她的胳膊肘。

格楚德自己在她们上次会面之后，好像也感到这些印痕和什么相像。“看起来几乎就像手指印。”她说，接着淡淡一笑，“我丈夫说，好像是什么女巫，或者魔鬼抓住过我这个地方，把肌肉掐干瘪了。”

若达打了一个冷战。“那是胡思乱想，”她急忙说，“我要是你，我就不会在乎它。”

“我本来不应该那样在乎它，”年轻的那位迟迟疑疑地说，“要是……要是我没有一种感觉，觉得它使我丈夫……不喜欢我，不，不那样爱我。男人都那样喜欢考虑一个人的外表。”

“有些人是那样的——他就是一个。”

“是的，而且起先，他对我的外表非常得意。”

“把你的胳膊遮着，别让他瞧见。”

“唉——他知道那儿变样了！”她竭力想不让人看见她那满眼泪水。

“好了，太太，我真心诚意希望这事马上就过去。”

就这样，这个挤奶妇回家的时候，又重新让一种可怕的魔力把自己的心同这件事情牢牢地拴在一起了。她装作嘲笑自己迷信，可是做了某种坏事的犯罪感还是增强了。若达在内心深处，并不完全反对她那位后任的花容月貌略微有点减损，不管是出于什么方式；但是也不希望使她遭受肉体上的痛苦，因为，虽然有了这个年轻漂亮的女人，洛吉再也不可能就他自己过去对若达的所作所为给予任何补偿，但是在这个较年长女人的心里，对别人完全出于无心的篡夺行为所怀有的任何愤恨，都早已烟消云散了。

如果这位甜美善良的格楚德·洛吉知道了卧房里的那场梦境，她会怎么想呢？和她保持友谊，而又不把这件事告诉她，好像就是不仁不义；但是她自己又不愿意主动地去告诉她——而且她也想不出什么补救的办法。

那天晚上她大部分时间都在思索这件事情。第二天，挤完了早晨那班牛奶之后，由于有一种可怕的魔力把她拉向洛吉太太那里，她就动身出去，想看看是不是能够再见格楚德·洛吉一面。挤奶姑娘从远处遥望那所房子，终于能够辨认出农场主的妻子独自一人骑马外出——大概是到远处的农场去和她丈夫会合。洛吉太太看见了她，就策马朝她这个方向慢慢跑来。

“早上好，若达！”格楚德跑过来的时候说，“我正要去看你呢。”

若达注意到，洛吉太太握住缰绳都有些困难。

“我希望——那只有毛病的胳膊……”若达说。

“他们告诉我，也许有一种办法，我可以找出它的原因，这样就可以把它治好，”另一位急匆匆地说，“那就是去找爱敦荒原上的一个什么聪明人。他们不知道他是否还活着——这会儿我一下想不起他的名字来了。但是他们说，你比附近不管谁都更了解他的动静，可以告诉我，是不是还可以找他请教。哎呀——他叫什么名字？你是知道的。”

“不是纯德法师吗？”她问着，瘦削的脸变得惨白了。

“纯德——对了。他还活着吗？”

“我相信他还活着。”若达勉勉强强地说。

“你为什么把他称作法师？”

“嗯——他们说……他们一直说，他是个……他有许多别人没有的能力。”

“唉，我们那些人怎么那样迷信，要介绍这种人？我原来以为他们说的是个什么行医的人呢。我不想再找他了。”

若达看来松了一口气，洛吉太太骑马走了。挤奶妇听说别人提出向她打听这个人，那时，她就从内心感到，工友中间一定有某种讥讽的看法，说一个女巫会知道那个魔法师的下落。那么，他们是在怀疑她。不久以前，这种事不会让她这个明理的女人在意。但是，现在她可有一个挥之不去让她迷信的理由了。她突然恐惧起来，害怕这个法师会指名道姓，说她是那个正在摧毁格楚德美貌的恶人，因而使她那位朋友永远恨她，把她看成是化作人形的魔鬼。

但是所有一切都还没有完结。过了两天，午后的太阳透过窗格子照进来，在若达·布茹克家的地上投下了一个黑影。这个女人立刻开了门，几乎都喘不过气来了。

“你一个人在家吗？”格楚德问道。她看来也同若达·布茹克本人一样焦虑急躁。

“是。”若达说。

“我胳膊上那块地方看来好像更糟了，这让我很苦恼！”这个年轻的农场主太太继续说，“它多么奇怪呀！我真希望它不会是一种不治之症。我一直又在考虑他们所说的纯德法师的事。我并不真信那种人，但是我觉得，只是去看看他并不碍事，出于好奇吧——不过绝不应该让我丈夫知道。到他住的地方去远吗？”

“是——有五英里地呢，”若达迟迟疑疑地说，“在爱敦荒原最里边。”

“嗯，我应该步行去。你能和我一起去，帮我带带路吗？——比如说，明天下午？”

“啊，我不行。那是——”挤奶妇低声咕哝着，心中一惊。她突然觉得很恐惧，害怕她在梦中采取那种猛烈行动的事会泄露出来，那样，在她这个平生最有益的朋友眼中，她的人格就完了，而且再也无可挽回了。

洛吉太太一再撺掇，若达虽然非常担心，最后还是同意了。这条道路对她说来固然很伤心，可是她的恩人那种奇怪的病有可能治好，她就不能蓄意挡她的道。最后两人商量好，为了避免别人对她们这种不可思议的意图产生怀疑，她们决定在荒原边沿一块人工林的角落上会合。从她们现在站着的地方就可以看见那个角落。

五 纯德法师

在第二天下午以前，若达本来可以做出一些事情来逃避这次探访，但是她已经答应了要去。不仅如此，如果真能有助于找到一种可能的方法，弄清究竟，也许可以发现她在那个神秘莫测的世界里还是一个人物，比她过去对她自己设想过的更加了不起，这本身有时就具有一种可怕的诱惑力。

快到她们约定的那个时间，她出发了，经过半小时轻快的步行，她走到了这一地带爱敦荒原的东南边缘，那里有一片枞树林。一个身材娇小的人，穿着外套，戴着面罩，早已到了那里。若达一看到洛吉太太用吊带把左胳膊吊着，几乎浑身打了一个哆嗦。

她们彼此几乎没有讲什么话，就立即开始爬坡，朝这片森严肃穆的荒野深处走去。这片地方居高临下，俯视她们半小时之前刚刚离开的那片冲积而成的富饶土地。这是一次长途跋涉。乌云使整个环境显得阴暗，虽然这时还不过刚到下午。风在荒原的斜坡上凄厉地嚎叫，这个荒原未必就不是那个目睹过威塞克斯国王伊那的痛苦的荒原，而后世则把伊那描述为李尔[5]。格楚德·洛吉说话多，若达只是用简单几个现成的字眼儿回答。她有一种奇怪的厌恶心理，不愿走在这个同伴吊着那条有毛病的胳膊的那一边，一不小心靠近那条胳膊了，她就转身走到另一边去。下坡走向一条车道的时候，她们的脚扫着了许多石楠。她们要寻找的那个人的房子就在路旁。

他并不承认他开业治病，或者关心与此相关的任何事情。他直接关心的是经营常青棘、泥煤、“粗砂”等土特产品。的确，他假装并不相信自己的能力，人们请他治疗瘊子，这些瘊子奇迹般地消失了——必须承认，的确是消失了——他会轻描淡写地说：“噢，我不过是对着那些瘊子喝了杯烈酒，也许是凑巧了吧。”而且马上就转换话题。

她们到达的时候，他正好在家，事实上是看着她们下到他这个山谷里来的。他胡须灰白，脸色红润。他一见到若达，就用一种奇特的眼神盯着她。洛吉太太告诉他，她是来干什么的。他一边嘴里叨唠着自己不行，一边又检查她的胳膊。

“药可治不了它，”他立刻说，“这是一个仇人干的。”

若达缩作一团，倒退了两步。

“一个仇人？什么仇人？”洛吉太太问道。

他摇摇头。“那你自己最容易弄清楚，”他说，“要是你愿意，我可以把那个人给你指出来。不过我自己并不会知道那是谁。别的我干不了，也不想干。”

她催着他干。于是他告诉若达，让她在外面她现在站的地方等着，然后把洛吉太太领进屋里。屋门马上开了，而且后来一直留着一道缝儿，因此若达没有跟他们在一起，也可以看见他们自始至终在干些什么。他从食具柜里拿出一只平底酒杯，装上大半杯水，并且拿出一个鸡蛋，用某种不让别人知道的办法摆弄了一番，然后就着玻璃杯的边缘把蛋敲破，让蛋清流进去，蛋黄留在蛋壳里。因为天越来越暗了，他就把酒杯和酒杯里的东西一起拿到窗前，告诉格楚德仔细地观察水里的东西。他们俩一起躬身靠近桌子，挤奶妇能够看见蛋清在水里下沉的时候形状不断变化泛起的乳白色，但是她离得不够近，看不出它成了什么形状。

“你看的时候，能够看得出像什么人的脸或者模样吗？”法师对年轻的女人说。

她小声回答，声音轻得若达听不见，并且还继续全神贯注地看着杯子里面。若达转过身去，向远处走了几步。

洛吉太太出来了，阳光照在她脸上，在荒原景物忧郁暗淡的色调衬托之下，她的脸显得特别惨白——和若达的脸一样惨白。纯德在她走出之后把门关上了，她们立刻一起回家。但是若达看得出来，她的同伴完全变了。

“他收费很多吗？”她探问道。

“啊，不——没花钱。他分文不取。”格楚德说。

“那么，你看到什么啦？”若达问道。

“什么……什么我也不乐意说。”她那种小心谨慎的样子很明显。她的脸板着，一下变老了，有点像若达卧室中的那张脸。

“是你首先建议到这里来的吗？”洛吉太太停了很久以后突然问道，“如果是你首先建议的，那该多怪呀！”

“不是。但是就目前的情况来看，我并不认为这个决定是错误的。”她回答道。她忽然第一次有了一种胜利感，她一点也不悔恨，她身边的这个小东西该知道，并不是她们自己，而是别的什么有影响力的东西，使她们不相容。

在回家去的这条漫长而又累人的路上，再也没有人提到这个话题了。但是，那年冬天在那片有很多牛奶场的低地上，以这种或那种方式悄悄流传着这样一个故事：洛吉太太的左胳膊慢慢不中用了，是因为若达·布茹克用“目光震慑”住了。若达对于那场梦魇保有她自己的想法，但是她的面容越来越愁苦，越来越消瘦。到了春天在霍姆斯托克附近就再也见不到她和她那个男孩了。

六 第二次尝试

六年过去了，洛吉先生和太太的婚后生活平淡乏味，而且更糟。农场主常常闷闷不乐，沉默寡言；而那个女人，以前由于优雅和美貌而受到他的热烈追求，这时左臂已经变形，不成样子。不仅如此，她也并没有给他生孩子，这就大有可能使他在大约二百年来占有这个河谷的家族中，成为末代子孙了。他想起若达·布茹克和她的儿子，害怕这可能就是上天对他的判决。

过去一向心情轻快、头脑开明的格楚德，逐渐变成了一个容易激动、思想迷信的女人，她全部时间都用来为治她的病痛做试验，采用她碰上的任何一个江湖医生的药方。她一心眷恋丈夫，还暗怀着痴心妄想至少挽回她身上原有的某些美貌，来赢得他的回心转意，因此她的私室里摆满了各式各样的瓶瓶、包包、药盒、药罐——不仅这些，还有一包包神秘的草药、种种符咒和宣讲巫术的书籍，要是在她的学生时代，她一定会嘲笑说这些东西都是愚蠢胡闹。

“见鬼。看吧，这些药店乱配的杂烩和巫婆胡掺和的东西，哪一天不把你自己毒死才怪呢。”她丈夫偶尔看到那一排又一排的玩意儿就这样说。

她并不回答，只是用那样一种痛心的责备神情，向他投去悲哀而又温情的一瞥，所以他显出对自己的话感到歉意的样子，又加了一句：“你知道，我这不过是为了你好，格楚德。”

“我要把这些劳什子一股脑儿都清理出来，全部毁掉，”她哑着嗓子说，“再也不试那种药方了！”

“你得有个什么人，让你高兴起来。”他说，“我曾经想抱养一个男孩，可是他现在岁数太大了，而且他走了，我也不知道现在他在什么地方。”

她猜到了他指的是谁，因为这些年来，若达·布茹克的事她已经知道了，虽然她丈夫从来没有就这件事和她交谈过一个字。她也从来没有对他说过，她曾经去拜访过纯德法师，也没说过那个孤零零地住在荒原上的人给她透露过什么，或者她以为给她透露过什么。

她现在二十五岁，但是看起来要老得多。“六年的婚姻，不过几个月的爱情。”有时她这样自言自语。于是她想到那个显而易见的原因，看看自己那条日益萎缩的胳膊，满怀悲哀地说：“要是我能够再变回原来的模样，就像他第一次见到过的那样，那该多好呀！”

她顺从地毁掉了那些丹方符咒，但是仍然保留着一种热切的愿望，想试试另外的东西——完全不同的另一种疗法。自从若达勉为其难地领着她去拜访过那位离群索居的人以后，她再也没有重访纯德。但格楚德现在突然想起，她可以再做孤注一掷的努力，来消除这种看来像是受到诅咒的灾祸，如果他还活着，就再去找找他。他应该是可信的，因为他在酒杯中造出的那个不大清晰的形象，毫无疑问是和一个女人相像，虽然那时她还不知道，可是她现在知道了，世界上只有那个女人有理由对她不怀好意。是应该再去拜访一次。

这一次她是一个人去的，不过她在荒原上几乎迷了路，比她应该走的路多绕了很远的一段。然而，最后总算到了纯德的那所房子，他不在家，没有在屋子里等她。远处他那伛偻的身影，指明他在那个地方干活儿，她走了过去。纯德还记得她。他把他收集的常青棘根放下，堆成一堆，提出要陪着她朝她回家的路上走走，因为路程很远，而白天又很短。这样他们就一起走着，他的头低得几乎都要触到地面了，而且他的外表和地面是一个颜色。

“我知道，你可以把瘊子、瘤子消掉，”她说，“为什么不能把这个消掉呢？”她说着就露出了胳膊。

“你把我的力量想得太大了！”纯德说，“我现在是年纪又老，身体又弱。不行，不行。我亲自干，干不了。你试过些什么办法？”

她时时变换，用过上百种治病的药物和驱邪的符咒，她给他举出了几种，他摇了摇头。

“有一些是够好的，”他用赞成的口气说，“可是其中有许多并非如此。这种病是一种萎缩性的，不是创伤性的，而且只要你一下把它摆脱了，那马上就会完全好了。”

“要是我能那样该多好！”

“我所知道的，只有唯一一种机遇能行。治疗类似的病痛，这个办法从来没有不灵的——我敢这样说。不过做起来难，特别是一个女人。”

“告诉我吧！”她说。

“你必须用那条胳膊去摸上过绞刑的人的脖子。”

他讲的这种景象把她吓了一跳。

“要在刚从绞刑架上放下来尸体还没有冰凉的时候。”法师不动声色地继续说。

“那样做有什么好处呢？”

“它可以调理血脉，改变体质。不过，我刚说过，做起来很难。你得在有绞刑的时候到监狱去，在那里等着把人从绞刑架上放下来，好多人都那样干过，不过也许没有像你这样漂亮的女人。我一向打发皮肤有毛病的人去，总有几十人了。不过，那都是以前的事，我打发去的最后一个人，是在一八一三年——都差不多有十二年啦。”

他再没有对她说什么，然后把她送上一条回家去的直路，就转身离开了她，和第一次一样，一文钱也不肯收。

七 骑马赶路

这番话深深地印在格楚德的心里了。她的性格属于有点怯弱的那种，大概这个善心的术士所能够推荐的一切疗法中，没有任何一种能像这种办法那样，使她充满反感，更不用说实行起来会遇到的不计其数的障碍了。

到郡城所在地卡斯特桥有十二英里或十五英里。虽然在那个犯盗马罪、纵火罪、夜盗罪的人都要处死刑的年月，一场巡回审判过后很少有不判绞刑的，但是，没有别人帮忙，她大概没法儿接近犯人的尸体。而她又害怕她丈夫会大发雷霆，所以不愿意把纯德的建议向他或他周围的人透露一个字。

她等了几个月，什么也没做，只是像以前一样，耐心地忍受着破相的痛苦。但是，她毕竟是一个女人，从天性来说，总想恢复自己的秀美姿容，重新得到爱情（她还不过二十五岁呀），这种渴望不断地刺激她，要她尝试一下这种无论如何也不大可能使她受到任何伤害的办法。“用魔法降临的，也一定得用魔法赶走。”她常这样说。可是她的想象里一出现这种行动，她就恐惧退缩，不敢正视这种可能性。随后，法师讲的“它可以调理血脉”这句话又来了，好像它能够变成一种符合科学的解释，而不是一派胡言乱语。同时那种难以抑制的想克服病痛的愿望也催促她再去尝试尝试。

那个时候，郡里只有一家报纸，她丈夫也只是偶尔借阅一下。但是过去也有过去的办法。人们广泛用口舌传递消息，从一个市场到另一个市场，从一个集市到另一个集市，所以一有执行死刑这类事情快要发生，方圆二十英里之内，几乎没有人不知道这种马上要来的光景，哪怕远在霍姆斯托克，也有些热心的人，据大家所知道的，步行去到卡斯特桥，一天之内走个来回，就是为了亲眼看看那场热闹。下一次巡回审判定在三月；格楚德·洛吉听说审判已经举行了，一找到机会就偷偷地向酒馆、客店打听审判的结果。

然而，她已经太迟了。行刑的时间已经到了，走那么一段路，还要在那样短的时间内就能获准进去，那至少要得到她丈夫的帮助。她可不敢告诉他，因为她刚稍微一试探就已经发现，农村中此类迷信的念头，只要一提就使他火冒三丈，一半原因是他自己对这类念头也半信半疑，因此她只好再等另一次机会。

她听说，就在霍姆斯托克的这个村子里，多年以前有两个患癫痫病的孩子曾经去过，而且效果很好，尽管附近的教会人士强烈谴责这种做法，这种事情还是使她的决心得到鼓舞。四月、五月、六月都过去了，可以毫不夸张地说，到了六月底的时候，格楚德简直是在热切希望把什么人处死了。她平时每天晚上都做常规的祈祷，这时她却不知不觉地这样祈祷起来了：“啊，上帝，快把一个什么人绞死吧，管他有罪还是无辜！”

这一次她更早就开始打听，她的做法也更加按部就班。不仅如此，当时正是夏季，处在储草和收获之间，她丈夫有空闲时间，常常离家在外度假。

巡回审判是在七月份，她又像以前那样到客店去打听。只判了一个死刑——仅仅一个——罪名是纵火。

她最大的问题倒不是如何去卡斯特桥，而是采用什么办法可以获准进入监狱。虽然为了这种目的而提出进入监狱，这种申请以前从来没有遭到过拒绝，可是这种习俗现在已经不时兴了。她考虑到可能遇到的困难，差不多又要迫不得已回过头来去依靠她丈夫了。但是，她对巡回审判的事情稍微一试探，他就显得那么不愿谈论，甚至比以前更加冷淡，所以她没往下再说，决定不管要做什么，她都自己一个人去做。

一向冷酷无情的命运，于她来说出乎意料地好转了。死刑定在星期六，星期四的时候，洛吉先生对她说，他要再离家一两天，到集市上去做点生意，并且说他很抱歉，不能带她一起去。

这次她表示非常乐意留在家里，这使他感到惊讶，盯着她直看。她以前对于失去这种短途旅游的机会，总是表现出强烈失望的。然而，他慢慢恢复了他一向沉默寡言的态度，到了所说的那一天，就离开了霍姆斯托克。

现在该轮到她了。她最初想赶车去，可是仔细一想，又打住了，因为那样她就得走税卡路，她那鬼鬼祟祟的使命让人发觉的可能性就要增加十倍了。本来在结婚之前，她丈夫答应过要经常留一匹牝马供她骑用，而这时在她丈夫的几个马厩里，无论想象多么出格，也找不到一匹适合女人的坐骑；尽管如此，她还是决心骑马，并且避开人们常走的路。她丈夫有许多拉车的马，很好的驭马，留下的马匹中间有一匹可以使唤。这是一匹体形高大的亚马逊牝马，马背宽得像一只沙发，她小有不适的时候，偶尔也骑出去换换空气。她挑上了这匹马。

星期五下午，一个伙计把它溜熟了。她已经穿戴停当，临走前她看着那条干瘪的胳膊。“哎呀！”她说，“如果不是为了你，我就不会去受这一趟可怕的罪啦！”

她带了几件衣物，打了一个小包，趁这个机会对仆人说：“我去看一个朋友，怕今天晚上回不来，所以带了这些东西。要是我十点钟还没回来，不要惊慌，像平日一样把家门关好。明天我肯定会回来。”她打算以后再私下告诉她丈夫，做完了的事不像计划要做的事，他差不多肯定会宽恕她的。

于是，这个颇为忐忑的格楚德·洛吉离开了丈夫的宅院。但是，尽管她的目的地是卡斯特桥，她却没有走直路经过斯蒂克福到那里去。她耍花招最初走的路刚好是相反的方向。然而，她一走到人们看不见她的地方，就向左拐，走上去爱敦荒原的路。刚要走上荒原的时候，又拐一个弯，走上真正要走的路，向正西方走去。很难想象出，到郡城去还有比这更隐秘的路了；至于方向，她只需要把马头牢牢对准太阳右边一点就行。她懂得，她随时可以碰到砍常青棘的或者村舍里的什么人，问问他们就不会走错了路。

虽然说来那时离现在还不太久远，可是爱敦远远不像现在这个样子把地面都分成了小块小块的，人们想在低坡上开垦，不管结果是成功还是失败，都把原来的荒原分割成了许多互不相连的小荒原。而那时候，这些还不太盛行，还没实现圈地法，田埂和树篱都还没建立起来。不像现在这样：村民的牲口不能享有从前在公有地上放牧的权利，那些享有泥煤开采特权的人自己的大车也不能随便到处走，保证他们一年到头都有东西烧。因此格楚德骑马走去，除了带刺的常青棘丛、一片片石楠、白色的水沟、地表上自然的悬崖和斜坡以外，并没有别的什么障碍。

她那匹马如果大踏步、慢慢走很稳当，虽然是一匹挽马，走得却从容不迫。如果不是这样，她就不敢端着一条半死不活的胳膊，骑上它走这样一片村野荒地了。因此，她快要离开荒原下到满是耕地的山谷之前，走到了荒原通向卡斯特桥的路上最后一块边远的高地，勒住缰绳让她的坐骑喘口气，这时候，已经快到八点钟了。

她停在一个叫作灯草池的水塘边，池子两侧是两道树篱的尽头，一道栏杆通过池子中心，把水池分为两半。从栏杆上面望过去，是乡间的低绿地，越过绿树，是市镇的房项，越过房顶有一道房子平平的白色前脸儿，那就是郡监狱的入口。这道房子前脸儿的房顶上，有几个小黑点在来回挪动；看来他们像是几个工人在竖一个什么东西。她觉得毛骨悚然。她缓慢地往下走，不久就走到玉米地和牧场中间了。又过了半小时以后，格楚德走到城市这一边的第一个客店白鹿客栈，这时差不多已是暮色苍茫了。

她到达这里并没有激起什么人的惊讶。那个年月，农夫的妻子骑马赶路，比现在要多，不过，此情此景别人也根本想象不出洛吉太太已经身为人妻了。客栈老板以为她是一个轻率莽撞的年轻女人，到这里来看第二天的“绞刑盛会”。她丈夫和她本人都没有在卡斯特桥市场上做过买卖，所以没有人认识她。下马的时候她看到一群男孩就在客栈前面围在一个马具店的大门口，兴趣盎然地在朝里面看。

“那儿在干什么？”她问客栈的马夫。

“搓绳子明天好用。”

她会意地心头一悸，并且把胳膊缩回来了。

“事情完了以后，这根绳子要一寸一寸地卖，”那个马夫接着说，“要是你想要，小姐，我可以给你弄一段，免费的。”

她赶紧打消了任何这类念头，主要是因为她不知道怎么忽然有了一种奇怪的感觉，好像那个判了死刑的可怜人的命运，和她自己的命运交织在一起了。她订了一个房间准备过夜，然后坐下寻思。

究竟应该用什么办法获得允许进入监狱，一直到现在她连哪怕是最模糊的一点主意也没有。她忽然想起那个神通广大的人说过的那番话。他曾经暗示过，她可以利用她的美貌——尽管遭到了损害，作为通关的钥匙。她没有经验，狱卒、狱吏她都不认识。她曾经听说过一个郡长和副郡长，但是也只是模糊地提到。然而她知道，一定有一个绞刑吏，于是她决定去求绞刑吏。

八 水边隐士

在那个年月以及几年以后，几乎每个监狱都有一个绞刑吏。格楚德经过打听才知道，卡斯特桥的那个小吏住在悬崖下面那条很深、很缓的河流旁边一个孤零零的村舍里，悬崖上面就是监狱那些房子的所在。而那条河，虽然她并不知道，就是灌溉下游斯蒂克福德和霍姆斯托克那一带草场的同一条河。

格楚德换了衣服，没吃没喝就出发了，因为不把某些具体事情定下来，她就是无法让自己安下心来。她沿着河边的一条小路走向所说的那所房子。走过监狱附近，在天空的映衬下，可以看得出来，在门道上面的平房顶上，有三个长方形的框子，她远远望去，有几个黑影在那里活动，她认出了竖起的东西是什么，于是快步走过去。再走了一百码，她就到了行刑人的房子，这是一个男孩指给她的。房子就在同一条河流的旁边，紧靠一座排闸，河水流过不断发出轰隆的声响。

她站在那儿犹豫不决，这时门开了，一个老人走了出来，用一只手遮住一根蜡烛。他从外面把门锁上，转身登上一座木踏板楼梯，楼梯安在那所房子的边上，他开始上楼，显然这是通往他卧室的楼梯。格楚德赶忙上前，但是等赶到楼梯下面，他已经上到楼梯顶上了。她朝着他高声叫喊，声音足可以盖过排闸那边的轰鸣，让他听见，他往下看着问道：“你来这儿干啥？”

“和你说一分钟。”

烛光总算还照在了她仰面朝上颜色惨白而且带着乞求神情的脸上，戴维斯（大家都这样称呼这个绞刑吏）又走下楼梯。“我正要睡觉去了，”他说，“‘早睡早起’嘛，可是为了像你这样的一位女士，耽搁一分钟我是不会在乎的。进屋里来吧。”他重新打开门，把她领到屋子里面。

他平常干活的工具，也就是短工花匠的工具，摆在墙角，他大概看出了她像个乡下人，于是说道：“要是你想找我去干乡下的活儿，我可不能去，因为我从来没有离开过卡斯特桥，为高贵的或是低微的人去干事儿——别找我吧。尽管有的时候我会让别人“离开”这里。”他正式地加了一句。

“是呀，是！是那样。明天！”

“啊，我想是这么回事。好吧，那又怎么样啦？关于绳结的事，到这儿来没有用——人们不断到这儿来，可是俺告诉他们，这个结也好，那个结也好，只要你把它打在耳朵下面，都是一样仁慈的。那个不幸的又是个亲戚吗？或者我该说，也许是（他看了看她的装束）你雇用的一个人？”

“不是。绞刑在什么时候执行？”

“和以前一样——十二点，或者说只等伦敦来的邮车一到就执行。我们总是等邮车到，准备等缓刑令。”

“噢——缓刑令——我希望没有！”她不觉说了出夹。

“好吧——嘻——嘻！——当作公事办，我也这么希望！可是不管怎样，如果说一个年轻小伙子应该得到从轻发落的话，这个小伙子就应该。才刚刚十八岁出头嘛，而且只是碰巧在草垛着火的时候在那儿。不管怎么说，那并没有多大的危险，其实他们是不得已拿他来杀一儆百，这些日子像那样破坏财产的事太多啦。”

“我的意思是，”她解释说，“我想摸摸他，作为治病的法术，治一种病痛。有一个人证明，这种疗法很灵，是他出的主意。”

“噢，是的，小姐！现在我懂了。前几年有这种人来找过我。可是我想不到，你会是需要调理血脉的那种人。是怎么不好？这种事搞错了，我可担着责任呢。”

“我的胳膊。”她很不情愿地露出那块干瘪的皮肤来。

“啊，这就是胳膊萎缩！”绞刑吏一边观察一边说。

“是。”她说。

“好吧，”他很感兴趣地接着说，“我不得不承认，这真是个很好的病例！我喜欢这种样子的伤，就我所见过的来比较，这肯定真正适合做这种治疗。告诉你来这儿的，不管他是谁，可真是一个明白人。”

“你能费心帮我把要办的都安排好吗？”她屏住呼吸问。

“你应该去找监狱长，和你的医生一起去，说出你的名字和住址——要是我记得不错，一向都是这么办的。不过，也许俺能帮你办，只要很少一点费用。”

“噢，谢谢你！我宁愿这么办，因为我愿意保密。”

“不让情人知道，嗯？”

“不是，是不让丈夫知道。”

“哈哈！好极了。俺会让你摸一下尸体。”

“它现在在哪儿？”她一边说一边颤抖。

“它？你的意思是说他吧，他现在还活着。在上面那个暗处，就在那个小矮窗后面。”他指着悬崖上面的那个监狱。

她想起她丈夫和她那些朋友。“是的，当然啰，”她说，“那么，我怎么进行呢？”

他把她领到门口。“看，你可以等在那堵墙上的小门旁边，你往上走，在那个小巷里就可以找到，不要迟过一点钟。我从里边把门打开，因为不把他放下来，我是不会回家吃饭的。晚安。要准时到；要是你不想让别人看见你，罩块面纱。嗯——俺有一阵子有过你这么个女儿！”

她走了，爬上上面的那条小路，想自己先去弄清楚，好在第二天能够找到那扇小门。小门的轮廓，她很快就看得见了——是在监狱外面围墙上的一个小缺口。这是那么高的一个陡坡，她爬到小门旁边，不得不停下喘一会儿气，她朝后面望了一下水边的那所小房子，看见绞刑吏又在爬他户外的楼梯。他进了楼梯顶上的那个阁楼，或者屋子，过了几分钟，他的烛光就灭了。

郡城的钟敲了十点，她像她刚到的时候那样，回到了白鹿客栈。

九 不期而遇

星期六中午一点钟。格楚德·洛吉像前面说过的那样，得到允许进入监狱，坐在第二道大门里面一个会客室里。这道门建在条石砌成的古典式拱廊下面，在当时看来，拱廊还是比较新式的，门上有几个字：“郡监狱；1793年”。这就是她前一天从荒原上看到的那面墙。旁边有一个通道，通向竖着绞刑架的房顶。

城里面人山人海，市场暂时停业了，但是格楚德几乎没有见到一个人影，她在屋子里一直待到约定的时刻，然后就动身去指定的地点。她走的那条路避开了悬崖下面那片开阔地带，观众那时都会集在那里，但是她甚至能听得见那里人声鼎沸。喧嚣声停顿的时候，一个沙哑的粗嗓子大叫了一声：“死前最后遗言，忏悔！”并没来缓刑令，绞刑已经执行了；但是大伙还在等着，想看看尸体怎样卸下来。

不久，这个苦苦等待的女人听到头顶上有脚步声，然后就有一只手招呼她，她随着指引的方向，走了出去，穿过门房外面铺平了的院子。她的双膝发抖，简直走不动了。她一只胳膊露在袖子外面，只用披肩盖着。

她现在来到的地方，有两个支架，她还没来得及想这两个支架是干什么用的，就听见沉重的脚步在她背后什么地方下楼。她没有转过头去，或者无法转过头去，就用这种姿势僵在那里：她模模糊糊感到有四个人抬着一个粗糙的棺材和她擦肩而过。棺材敞开着，里面躺着一个年轻小伙子的尸体，身上穿着一件农民干活儿穿的长罩衫和一条粗斜纹布过膝短裤。尸体是匆匆忙忙扔进棺材的，所以罩衫的下摆吊在上面。这副沉重的东西暂时搁在支架上。

这个年轻女人现在处于这样一种状态：好像有一阵灰色的雾在她眼前浮动，因为这个缘故，再加上她又戴着面纱，她简直分辨不出任何东西，她好像已经快要死了，只是由于某种电流刺激才缓着没有断气。

“来吧！”紧靠她身边有个声音，她刚刚能意识到，这句话是对她说的。

她拼命使出最后的一点气力，向前走去，就在这个时候，她听见背后有人向她走过来。她露出她那只被诅咒的可怜的胳膊，于是戴维斯揭开罩在尸体脸上的布，拉过格楚德的手举着，好让她的胳膊搭在死者的脖子周围，像还没熟透的黑莓果那种颜色的一道线上面。

格楚德尖叫了一声：法师预言的“调理血脉”实现了。但是就在这个当口，第二声尖叫响彻这个围墙里面的整个空间，它不是格楚德的喊叫。这一声尖叫使她大吃一惊，不禁往四处看。

紧靠她身后，站着若达·布茹克，她的脸歪扭着，两只眼睛因为哭泣而红肿起来了。若达身后站着格楚德自己的丈夫，他的脸上布满皱纹，两眼黯然无光，但是并没有眼泪。

“见鬼！你来这里干什么？”他声音沙哑地问道。

“臭婊子——现在到我们和我们孩子中间来了！”若达大叫，“这就是魔鬼在幻梦中显示给我的意思！到头来你还是像她！”她一把抓住这个年轻女人袒露出来的那只胳膊，把她死命地向后拉，一直把她顶到墙上。布茹克刚一松手，年轻虚弱的格楚德就滑溜下来，瘫靠在她丈夫的脚上，他把她抱起来的时候，她已经不省人事了。

一看见那一对，就足以提醒她，死去的年轻人是若达的儿子。在那个时代，罪犯处死之后，他的亲属只要愿意就有权要求领回尸体下葬，因此洛吉同若达一起在等待验尸。这个年轻人这次被拘留之后，若达就把他叫去了，以后又在不同的时候叫去过几次，而且审判期间，他还曾经在法庭出席。这就是他近来经常沉迷其中的“度假”。这一对可怜的父母原来希望避免事情暴露，因此他们亲自来收尸，运尸的马车和盖尸的单子都在外面等着呢。

格楚德的病情十分严重，所以大家认为最好还是让她在附近就医。她被抬出监狱送往市内，但是她再也没有活着回家。她脆弱的生命力，由于胳膊瘫痪也许一直在逐渐给榨干，而在这以前的二十四小时内，她的身体和精神方面都受到重压，于是一受到双重的震惊就彻底垮了。她的血脉的确得到了“调理”——但是太过头了。两天以后，她就在市内死去。

她的丈夫再也没有在卡斯特桥露过面，仅仅在他一向经常光顾的安格伯瑞老市场曾经露过一次面。而在任何公开场合，他都很少出现。他最初由于郁郁寡欢和悔恨交加，心情沉重，后来逐渐好转，看来像是一个历经磨炼和细心体贴的人了。他参加了他那年轻亡妻的葬礼之后，立即采取了放弃霍姆斯托克和邻近教区的农场的行动，并且卖掉了他的每一头牲口，然后离开，去到这个郡另一头的波特布瑞迪，住在那里孤零零的寓所中，直到两年以后因衰竭无疾而终。直到那个时候，大家才知道，他早已把他那笔不算菲薄的财产，全部遗赠给一家男童感化院，唯一的附带条件是，如果能找到若达·布茹克认领，就给她一小笔年金。

有一段时间，并没有找到她。但是她终于在她那个老教区重新出现了，不过她坚决拒绝与为她制定的规定有什么瓜葛。她又恢复了在牛奶场挤奶那种毫无变化的活儿，一直干了很多年，直到最后身体变得伛偻了，原来那一头浓密的头发变成了银丝，前额也脱光了——也许是因为挤奶时长期顶着奶牛的缘故。这里一些了解她身世的人，有时会站住看着她，并且寻思：随着那交错流下的条条奶流的节奏，在那个一动不动、满布皱纹的脑门儿后面，有些什么阴沉忧郁的思想在那儿悸动呢？

（张扬 张玲 译）

[1] 一码等于0.914米。（说明：书中脚注均为编者注。）

[2] 一英里等于1.609千米。

[3] 一英担约等于50.802千克。

[4] 一英寸等于0.025米。

[5] 英国历史家兼博古家凯姆敦（1551—1623），在他的《不列颠纪拾遗》里，曾提过威塞克斯的国王是伊那，哈代以此为据，引用到自己的书中。但除此以外，包括莎士比亚在内的其他大家作品中，所提到的威塞克斯国王均为李尔。

止不住打喷嚏的贼

很多很多年前，当现在已不茂盛的老橡树还只和老绅士的拐杖一样粗的时候，有位农民和儿子住在韦塞克斯。当时儿子休伯特十四岁上下，直率坦荡又英勇果敢，大家都很看好他。不过这个小伙子倒是有一点自负。

一个寒冷的圣诞节前夜，由于人手不足，父亲只能差遣他去离家数英里外的小镇办个重要差事。他是骑马去的，又被差事拖到很晚，时间已近深夜。所幸最后事情圆满解决了，他赶回小旅馆，给马配好鞍后，就上路了。回家要穿过肥沃但有些荒僻的布莱克摩山谷，那时的山谷土质黏重，小路蜿蜒，和如今一样被大片丛林所覆盖。

大约九点前后，休伯特骑着自己壮实的矮脚马杰瑞，走在遮天的林荫小道上，哼起了圣诞颂歌。仿佛是为了应和此情此景，他恍惚觉得自己听到林间有些微响动，不由得想起，他所经过的这个地方可是恶名在外，以前路过的人曾在此遭到伏击。休伯特看看杰瑞，真希望它不是这一身亮灰鬃毛，其他任何颜色都好；因为如此一来，即便在昏暗的荫蔽中，这匹温驯小马的身形也清晰可见。“我在担心什么呢？”他想了一下，大声说道，“杰瑞这么敏捷矫健，一定不会让强盗靠近我的。”

“哈哈！那倒是。”一个低沉的声音响起。转眼间一个身影从他右手边的密林里蹿出来，又有一个从左边的树丛中跳出，另一个则在前方好几码外的树干后现身。接着休伯特手中的缰绳便被夺走，自己也被从马上拽下。尽管奋力挣扎，像任何一个英勇的男孩都会做的那样，最终他还是被制服了，双臂捆在身后，两腿紧紧绑在一起。强盗把他扔进道沟后，驾马扬长而去。此时他才勉强看清：那两个人的脸都被故意涂黑了。

当休伯特意识清醒一点时，他发现，虽然自己可以奋力挣脱腿上的绳子，但不管怎么活动，两只胳膊还是捆得严严实实。所以他只能跳起来，双手背在身后前进，希望能够在某一个瞬间把绳结挣开。他知道今晚是走不到家了，而且还是在这种情况下，但他也没有放弃，依然坚持前进。谁知刚才受到的袭击让脑袋昏昏沉沉的，他很快就迷了路。如果不是很清楚大冬天毫无覆盖地睡在霜地上有多危险，休伯特真想就此躺下，休息一晚。他继续往前走，双臂被绳索绑着拧着，早已麻木，心中想到失去了可怜的杰瑞，便愈加伤痛：他的杰瑞不踹人也不咬人，从没有半点臭毛病。走着走着，休伯特惊喜地看到森林中依稀有微弱的灯光射出。于是他循着光亮向前，最终发现自己来到了一栋有宽阔侧翼、山墙和高塔的大宅前，碉堡之上有城垛和烟囱，映衬在星空下。

四周一片寂静，宅邸的门却赫然洞开，正是门内射出的光吸引他来到这里。进去之后，他发现这个巨大套间是一个餐厅，灯火通明，墙面均铺了深色的护壁板，配有缘饰镶板、各种雕刻、壁橱门柜，以及其他这类大房子里常见的装饰陈设。不过，最吸引休伯特的还是正中央的大桌子，因为上面摆满了珍馐佳肴，是无比丰盛的晚餐，但却未被动过。而桌子四周摆好了餐椅，看起来像是正要开始的晚宴被什么事突然打断了。

就算休伯特再想，他现在这个状况也吃不了，除非把嘴浸在盘子里，像猪牛一样拱着进食，所以当务之急是看看有没有人能帮忙解开绳子。正当他准备往房子里走时，突然听到门廊处传来匆忙的脚步声和说话声：“快点！”这声音低沉，和他从马背上被拖下来时听到的一模一样。他赶紧往桌下一钻，接着三个男人就进来了。休伯特从垂下的桌布边缘偷偷向外望，只见那几个人的脸也是涂黑的，这时他心中最后一点疑问打消了：真是同一伙贼。

“现在，”走在最前的那个人用低沉的嗓音说，“我们快藏起来。他们一会儿就又回来了。这方法不错吧？让他们都出去了。”

“嗯。别说，你模仿惊慌失措的叫声还真挺像。”第二个人说。

“惟妙惟肖。”另一个说。

“不过他们很快就会发现警报是假的，快，我们藏哪儿好呢？最好是能待两三个小时的地方，可以一直等到所有人都上床睡着。啊！知道了。这边！之前听人说过最远的橱柜一年都开不了一次，正合我意。”

说话人出了餐厅进入一条走廊。休伯特悄悄往前爬了些，依稀可以看见伫立在走廊另一头的橱柜，柜门朝着餐厅这边。这几个贼猫腰躲进去，关上了柜门。休伯特屏住呼吸，向前挪了挪，想要弄清楚他们的意图；凑近后，他听见强盗们在小声谈论哪些房间有金银珠宝，其他值钱的东西藏在哪里，很显然，他们准备行窃。

不一会儿，露台那边开始传来绅士、淑女们的闲谈欢笑声。休伯特意识到如果被人发现自己在房子里鬼鬼祟祟可不太好，除非他想要被当成劫匪给抓起来，于是他悄悄潜回厅外，藏在门廊黑暗的角落里。在这里他可以看见厅内的一切，却不会被人发现。很快，一群人走过来，和休伯特擦身而过，进了房子。其中有一对较为年长的绅士和淑女，还有年轻的小姐和男士各八九位，除此之外随行的男女仆从共有六人。显然，他们才是这栋大房子真正的主人、客人，之前有事出去了。

“孩子们、年轻人，现在，晚宴继续，”老绅士说，“我也不知道刚才的吵闹声是怎么回事，但敢肯定的是，一定有一个人在家门口被杀了。”

随后，女士们开始讨论方才的情形有多么骇人，她们又是怎样暗自期待一场冒险奇遇，结果到头来什么事也没发生。

“等着吧，女士们，”休伯特自言自语道，“不久后你们就会有一场货真价实的冒险了。”

看起来，年轻的男士、女士似乎是老夫妻已婚的儿女们，他们在这一天回家，与父母共度圣诞佳节。

接着大门就关上了，休伯特被留在了门廊外。他意识到这是自己寻求帮助的绝佳时机，由于双手被捆起来了没办法敲，他便开始用身体使劲地撞门。

“喂！在这儿闹什么呢？”开门的男仆质问道，一把抓住休伯特的肩膀，把他拽进餐厅里。“西蒙爵士，我发现这个男孩在门廊里制造噪声，非常可疑。”

所有人都看向休伯特。

“把他带过来。”西蒙男爵说，他正是之前提到的那位老绅士，“孩子，你在那里做什么呀？”

“为什么他的手臂被绑起来了？”其中一位女士说。

“可怜的孩子！”另一位说道。

休伯特立即解释了自己是在回家途中遭受伏击，被盗贼夺去马匹后残忍地抛下，才沦落至此的。

“想想都让人难过！”西蒙爵士大声说道。

“这很可能只是编造的故事。”一位绅士打扮的客人狐疑道。

“你不相信，嗯？”西蒙爵士问。

“也许他自己就是一个盗匪。”一位女士表示。

“我仔细看了他的相貌，长得就邪里邪气，不像好人。”老夫人说道。

休伯特脸唰的一下红了；他没有再说下去，想到强盗们还藏在房子里，他赶紧停住了嘴，一边开始思忖如何让这群人自己发现危险。

“给他松绑吧。”西蒙爵士说，“这样，既然今天是圣诞前夜，我们还是要好好招待一下。来，小伙子，坐在长桌那头的空座上吧，敞开了吃，尽情享用。等你吃饱喝足了，我们再细听你的故事。”

于是盛宴又继续进行着；休伯特现在没有了束缚，一点也不觉得不好意思。他们吃得越多喝得越多，休伯特也就愈加高兴。葡萄酒在人们的杯中芳香四溢，木材燃起熊熊炭火，直顶烟囱，女士们被绅士们讲的故事逗得捧腹大笑；简而言之，周遭一切都是喧闹欢愉的，和那个时候所有热闹的圣诞聚会一样。

人们的欢呼与嬉笑，在座主宾的热闹与狂喜，这场面使休伯特也情不自禁被感染了，虽然因为别人怀疑自己的诚实而有点受伤，但此时他的身心都备感温暖。他渐渐融入其中，到最后，他和老从男爵、西蒙男爵一样，也因为那些风趣故事和妙语如珠而痛快大笑。宴席快结束的时候，男爵的一个儿子，好像酒喝得多了点，和那个世纪的男人们一样，晃晃悠悠地靠过来跟休伯特说：“嘿，我的朋友，最近怎么样啊？要吸撮鼻烟吗？”说着他掏出一个鼻烟盒。这种小盒子当时风靡全国，老人、年轻人都很喜欢。

“谢谢。”休伯特说，吸了一口。

“告诉这些女士们，你是谁，你是做什么的，你能干什么。”年轻男人接着说道，重重拍着休伯特的肩膀。

“当然，”我们的男主人公说，提了提精神，想着最好还是勇敢面对，“我是一个旅行魔术师。”

“没错！”

“接下来要说什么呢？”

“你能从深渊招魂吗，小巫师？”

“我能在橱柜里掀起一场小风暴。”休伯特回答道。

“哈哈！”老从男爵听了兴奋地搓搓手，“那我们可得好好看看。女士们，别走远，好戏就要开始啦。”

“应该不危险吧？”老夫人问。

休伯特从桌旁起身，对刚才那个无礼的年轻人说：“请把鼻烟盒递给我一下。”“现在，”他继续说道，“请大家保持安静，随我来。任何人出声都会打破咒语。”

于是宾客们都乖乖听话，鸦雀无声。休伯特脱下皮靴，进入走廊，蹑手蹑脚地靠近那扇柜门，其他人默默跟在他后面，保持一小段距离。接着休伯特悄悄在门前放下一只凳子，自己站上去，刚好能够到柜顶。他悄无声息地从上面的柜门外把鼻烟倾倒进去，再呼出短短几口气，就把鼻烟恰好从门缝里吹进了橱柜。他挥手示意人群继续保持安静。

“我的天哪，什么声音？”过了一两分钟后，老夫人说。

只听得柜子里面一声压抑的喷嚏。

休伯特继续示意安静。

“真是奇了怪了，”西蒙爵士小声说，“太有意思了。”

休伯特趁此机会悄悄插紧橱柜的门闩，平静地说：“再来点鼻烟。”

“来点鼻烟。”西蒙爵士说。两三个绅士立即递来几个鼻烟盒，里面的东西继而也从柜门上方被吹了进去。接着又是一声喷嚏，已经不像第一声那样闷了；然后又一声，似乎在诉说自己无论如何都不想压抑了。最后，只听得一阵雷鸣般的喷嚏声此起彼伏。

“非常好，真是年少有为！”西蒙爵士说，“我对这种发声技巧很感兴趣，我猜，是叫腹语术吧。”

“还需要鼻烟。”休伯特说。

“还需要鼻烟。”西蒙爵士吩咐下去，于是仆从们拿来了一大罐香气浓郁的苏格兰鼻烟。

休伯特再次对准柜门上方的空隙，像之前一样把鼻烟吹进去。反复了好几次，直至把罐子全部清空。喷嚏声变得喧闹起来，毫不费力就能听见——并且一刻不停，就像是暴风雨中狂风、大雨和海水的激荡。

“我想这里面是有人的，根本就不是什么魔术！”西蒙爵士恍然大悟，大声说道。

“是的，”休伯特说，“他们是来打劫的，也是他们抢了我的马。”

此时喷嚏声已转为断断续续的嘟囔呻吟，其中一个贼听到了休伯特的声音，大喊道：“噢！行行好！饶了我吧！让我们出去！”

“我的马在哪儿？”休伯特问。

“系在了山谷间的一棵树上，就在绞刑架后面。行行好！行行好！放我们出去，不然就要被闷死了！”

此时，所有圣诞宾客都明白了，这不是什么消遣戏法，而是严肃的真事。枪和棍棒都已备好，所有男仆也都被叫进来，严阵以待。信号一发，休伯特抽开门闩，准备好防守姿势。然而这三个强盗哪还有力气攻击他们，早就在柜子角落蜷缩成一团，上气不接下气了。他们毫无抵抗便乖乖束手就擒，绑住双臂后就直接被扔到外屋去，等候明早处置。

休伯特现在才将整个故事向宾客众人娓娓道来，大家都对他的竭力帮助感激不尽。西蒙爵士表示一定要留他下来过夜，并且让他享用大宅子里最好的卧室。伊丽莎白女王和查尔斯王子到访当地时，就曾先后下榻在那间房。不过休伯特婉言谢绝了，因为他迫不及待地要找回自己的小马杰瑞，他要去验证强盗们的说辞是否真实。

几位客人陪着休伯特走到绞刑架后，根据盗贼暗指的意思，杰瑞就藏在这附近。他们走上小圆丘四处查看，瞧！小马就站在那里呢，毫发无伤，而且颇为惬意。一看到休伯特，它便兴奋地嘶叫起来；对于休伯特来说，也没有什么比找到杰瑞更开心了。他骑了上去，向身边朋友们道了声“晚安”，便策马朝着他们所指的方向飞驰，那是回家最近的路。清晨四点前后，他终于平安抵家。

（谢万容 译）

The Withered Arm

I A Lorn MILkMAId

It was an eighty- cow dairy, and the troop of milkers, regular and supernumerary, were all at work; for, though the time of year was as yet but early April, the feed lay entirely in water- meadows and the cows were ‘in full pail’. The hour was about six in the evening, and three- fourths of the large, red, rectangular animals having been finished off, there was opportunity for a little conversation.

‘He brings home his bride tomorrow, I hear. They’ve come as far as Anglebury today.’

The voice seemed to proceed from the belly of the cow called Cherry, but the speaker was a milking- woman, whose face was buried in the flank of that motionless beast.

‘Has anybody seen her?’ said another.

There was a negative response from the first. ‘Though they say she’s a rosy- cheeked, tisty- tosty little body enough,’ she added; and as the milkmaid spoke she turned her face so that she could glance past her cow’s tail to the other side of the barton, where a thin, faded woman of thirty milked somewhat apart from the rest.

‘Years younger than he, they say,’ continued the second, with also a glance of reflectiveness in the same direction.

‘How old do you call him, then?’

‘Thirty or so.’

‘More like forty,’ broke in an old milkman near, in a long white pinafore or ‘wropper’, and with the brim of his hat tied down, so that he looked like a woman. ‘ ’A was born before our Great Weir was builded, and I hadn’t man’s wages when I laved water there.’

The discussion waxed so warm that the purr of the milk- streams became jerky, till a voice from another cow’s belly cried with authority, ‘Now then, what the Turk do it matter to us about Farmer Lodge’s age, or Farmer Lodge’s new mis’ess? I shall have to pay him nine pound a year for the rent of every one of these milchers, whatever his age or hers. Get on with your work, or ’twill be dark before we have done. The evening is pinking in a’ready.’ This speaker was the dairyman himself, by whom the milkmaids and men were employed.

Nothing more was said publicly about Farmer Lodge’s wedding, but the first woman murmured under her cow to her next neighbour, ‘ ’Tis hard for she,’ signifying the thin worn milkmaid aforesaid.

‘Oh no,’ said the second. ‘He hasn’t spoken to Rhoda Brook for years.’

When the milking was done they washed their pails and hung them on a many- forked stand made of the peeled limb of an oak- tree, set upright in the earth, and resembling a colossal antlered horn. The majority then dispersed in various directions homeward. The thin woman who had not spoken was joined by a boy of twelve or thereabout, and the twain went away up the field also.

Their course lay apart from that of the others, to a lonely spot high above the water- meads, and not far from the border of Egdon Heath, whose dark countenance was visible in the distance as they drew nigh to their home.

‘They’ve just been saying down in barton that your father brings his young wife home from Anglebury tomorrow,’ the woman observed. ‘I shall want to send you for a few things to market, and you’ll be pretty sure to meet ’em.’

‘Yes, mother,’ said the boy. ‘Is father married, then?’

‘Yes . . . You can give her a look, and tell me what she’s like, if you do see her.’

‘Yes, mother.’

‘If she’s dark or fair, and if she’s tall – as tall as I. And if she seems like a woman who has ever worked for a living, or one that has been always well off, and has never done anything, and shows marks of the lady on her, as I expect she do.’

‘Yes.’

They crept up the hill in the twilight, and entered the cottage. It was thatched, and built of mud- walls, the surface of which had been washed by many rains into channels and depressions that left none of the original flat face visible; while here and there a rafter showed like a bone protruding through the skin.

She was kneeling down in the chimney- corner, before two pieces of turf laid together with the heather inwards, blowing at the red- hot ashes with her breath till the turves flamed. The radiance lit her pale cheek, and made her dark eyes, that had once been handsome, seem handsome anew. ‘Yes,’ she resumed, ‘see if she is dark or fair, and if you can, notice if her hands are white; if not, see if they look as though she had ever done housework, or are milker’s hands like mine.’

The boy again promised, inattentively this time, his mother not observing that he was cutting a notch with his pocket- knife in the beech- backed chair.

II The young wIfe

The road from Anglebury to Holmstoke is in general level; but there is one place where a sharp ascent breaks its monotony. Farmers homeward- bound from the former market- town, who trot all the rest of the way, walk their horses up this short incline.

The next evening, while the sun was yet bright, a handsome new gig, with a lemon- coloured body and red wheels, was spinning westward along the level highway at the heels of a powerful mare. The driver was a yeoman in the prime of life, cleanly shaven like an actor, his face being toned to that bluish- vermilion hue which so often graces a thriving farmer’s features when returning home after successful dealings in the town. Beside him sat a woman, many years his junior – almost, indeed, a girl. Her face too was fresh in colour, but it was of a totally different quality – soft and evanescent, like the light under a heap of rose- petals.

Few people travelled this way, for it was not a turnpike- road; and the long white riband of gravel that stretched before them was empty, save of one small scarce- moving speck, which presently resolved itself into the figure of a boy, who was creeping on at a snail’s pace, and continually looking behind him – the heavy bundle he carried being some excuse for, if not the reason of, his dilatoriness. When the bouncing gig- party slowed at the bottom of the incline above mentioned, the pedestrian was only a few yards in front. Supporting the large bundle by putting one hand on his hip, he turned and looked straight at the farmer’s wife as though he would read her through and through, pacing along abreast of the horse.

The low sun was full in her face, rendering every feature, shade, and contour distinct, from the curve of her little nostril to the colour of her eyes. The farmer, though he seemed annoyed at the boy’s persistent presence, did not order him to get out of the way; and thus the lad preceded them, his hard gaze never leaving her, till they reached the top of the ascent, when the farmer trotted on with relief in his lineaments – having taken no outward notice of the boy whatever.

‘How that poor lad stared at me!’ said the young wife.

‘Yes, dear; I saw that he did.’

‘He is one of the village, I suppose?’

‘One of the neighbourhood. I think he lives with his mother a mile or two off.’

‘He knows who we are, no doubt?’

‘Oh yes. You must expect to be stared at just at first, my pretty Gertrude.’

‘I do, – though I think the poor boy may have looked at us in the hope we might relieve him of his heavy load, rather than from curiosity.’

‘Oh no,’ said her husband off- handedly. ‘These country lads will carry a hundredweight once they get it on their backs; besides, his pack had more size than weight in it. Now, then, another mile and I shall be able to show you our house in the distance – if it is not too dark before we get there.’ The wheels spun round, and particles flew from their periphery as before, till a white house of ample dimensions revealed itself, with farm- buildings and ricks at the back.

Meanwhile the boy had quickened his pace, and turning up a by- lane some mile and half short of the white farmstead, ascended towards the leaner pastures, and so on to the cottage of his mother.

She had reached home after her day’s milking at the outlying dairy, and was washing cabbage at the doorway in the declining light. ‘Hold up the net a moment,’ she said, without preface, as the boy came up.

He flung down his bundle, held the edge of the cabbage- net, and as she filled its meshes with the dripping leaves she went on, ‘Well, did you see her?’

‘Yes; quite plain.’

‘Is she ladylike?’

‘Yes; and more. A lady complete.’

‘Is she young?’

‘Well, she’s growed up, and her ways are quite a woman’s.’

‘Of course. What colour is her hair and face?’

‘Her hair is lightish, and her face as comely as a live doll’s.’

‘Her eyes, then, are not dark like mine?’

‘No – of a bluish turn, and her mouth is very nice and red; and when she smiles, her teeth show white.’

‘Is she tall?’ said the woman sharply.

‘I couldn’t see. She was sitting down.’

‘Then do you go to Holmstoke church tomorrow morning: she’s sure to be there. Go early and notice her walking in, and come home and tell me if she’s taller than I.’

‘Very well, mother. But why don’t you go and see for yourself?’

‘I go to see her! I wouldn’t look up at her if she were to pass my window this instant. She was with Mr Lodge, of course. What did he say or do?’

‘Just the same as usual.’

‘Took no notice of you?’

‘None.’

Next day the mother put a clean shirt on the boy, and started him off for Holmstoke church. He reached the ancient little pile when the door was just being opened, and he was the first to enter. Taking his seat by the font, he watched all the parishioners file in. The well- to- do Farmer Lodge came nearly last; and his young wife, who accompanied him, walked up the aisle with the shyness natural to a modest woman who had appeared thus for the first time. As all other eyes were fixed upon her, the youth’s stare was not noticed now.

When he reached home his mother said ‘Well?’ before he had entered the room.

‘She is not tall. She is rather short,’ he replied.

‘Ah!’ said his mother, with satisfaction.

‘But she’s very pretty – very. In fact, she’s lovely.’ The youthful freshness of the yeoman’s wife had evidently made an impression even on the somewhat hard nature of the boy.

‘That’s all I want to hear,’ said his mother quickly.‘Now, spread the table- cloth. The hare you caught is very tender; but mind that nobody catches you. – You’ve never told me what sort of hands she had.’

‘I have never seen ’em. She never took off her gloves.’

‘What did she wear this morning?’

‘A white bonnet and a silver- coloured gownd. It whewed and whistled so loud when it rubbed against the pews that the lady coloured up more than ever for very shame at the noise, and pulled it in to keep it from touching; but when she pushed into her seat, it whewed more than ever. Mr Lodge, he seemed pleased, and his waistcoat stuck out, and his great golden seals hung like a lord’s; but she seemed to wish her noisy gownd anywhere but on her.’

‘Not she! However, that will do now.’

These descriptions of the newly- married couple were continued from time to time by the boy at his mother’s request, after any chance encounter he had had with them. But Rhoda Brook, though she might easily have seen young Mrs Lodge for herself by walking a couple of miles, would never attempt an excursion towards the quarter where the farmhouse lay. Neither did she, at the daily milking in the dairyman’s yard on Lodge’s outlying second farm, ever speak on the subject of the recent marriage. The dairyman, who rented the cows of Lodge, and knew perfectly the tall milkmaid’s history, with manly kindliness always kept the gossip in the cow- barton from annoying Rhoda. But the atmosphere thereabout was full of the subject during the first days of Mrs Lodge’s arrival; and from her boy’s description and the casual words of the other milkers, Rhoda Brook could raise a mental image of the unconscious Mrs Lodge that was realistic as a photograph.

III A vIsIon

One night, two or three weeks after the bridal return, when the boy was gone to bed, Rhoda sat a long time over the turf ashes that she had raked out in front of her to extinguish them. She contemplated so intently the new wife, as presented to her in her mind’s eye over the embers, that she forgot the lapse of time. At last, wearied with her day’s work, she too retired.

But the figure which had occupied her so much during this and the previous days was not to be banished at night. For the first time Gertrude Lodge visited the supplanted woman in her dreams. Rhoda Brook dreamed – since her assertion that she really saw, before falling asleep, was not to be believed – that the young wife, in the pale silk dress and white bonnet, but with features shockingly distorted, and wrinkled as by age, was sitting upon her chest as she lay. The pressure of Mrs Lodge’s person grew heavier; the blue eyes peered cruelly into her face; and then the figure thrust forward its left hand mockingly, so as to make the wedding- ring it wore glitter in Rhoda’s eyes. Maddened mentally, and nearly suffocated by pressure, the sleeper struggled; the incubus, still regarding her, withdrew to the foot of the bed, only, however, to come forward by degrees, resume her seat, and flash her left hand as before.

Gasping for breath, Rhoda, in a last desperate effort, swung out her right hand, seized the confronting spectre by its obtrusive left arm, and whirled it backward to the floor, starting up herself as she did so with a low cry.

‘Oh, merciful heaven!’ she cried, sitting on the edge of the bed in a cold sweat, ‘that was not a dream – she was here!’

She could feel her antagonist’s arm within her grasp even now – the very flesh and bone of it, as it seemed. She looked on the floor whither she had whirled the spectre, but there was nothing to be seen.

Rhoda Brook slept no more that night, and when she went milking at the next dawn they noticed how pale and haggard she looked. The milk that she drew quivered into the pail; her hand had not calmed even yet, and still retained the feel of the arm. She came home to breakfast as wearily as if it had been supper- time.

‘What was that noise in your chimmer, mother, last night?’ said her son. ‘You fell off the bed, surely?’

‘Did you hear anything fall? At what time?’

‘Just when the clock struck two.’

She could not explain, and when the meal was done went silently about her household work, the boy assisting her, for he hated going afield on the farms, and she indulged his reluctance. Between eleven and twelve the garden- gate clicked, and she lifted her eyes to the window. At the bottom of the garden, within the gate, stood the woman of her vision. Rhoda seemed transfixed.

‘Ah, she said she would come!’ exclaimed the boy, also observing her.

‘Said so – when? How does she know us?’

‘I have seen and spoken to her. I talked to her yesterday.’

‘I told you,’ said the mother, flushing indignantly, ‘never to speak to anybody in that house, or go near the place.’

‘I did not speak to her till she spoke to me. And I did not go near the place. I met her in the road.’

‘What did you tell her?’

‘Nothing. She said, “Are you the poor boy who had to bring the heavy load from market?” And she looked at my boots, and said they would not keep my feet dry if it came on wet, because they were so cracked. I told her I lived with my mother, and we had enough to do to keep ourselves, and that’s how it was; and she said then, “I’ll come and bring you some better boots, and see your mother.” She gives away things to other folks in the meads besides us.’

Mrs Lodge was by this time close to the door – not in her silk, as Rhoda had seen her in the bed- chamber, but in a morning hat, and gown of common light material, which became her better than silk. On her arm she carried a basket.

The impression remaining from the night’s experience was still strong. Brook had almost expected to see the wrinkles, the scorn, and the cruelty on her visitor’s face. She would have escaped an interview, had escape been possible. There was, however, no back- door to the cottage, and in an instant the boy had lifted the latch to Mrs Lodge’s gentle knock.

‘I see I have come to the right house,’ said she, glancing at the lad, and smiling. ‘But I was not sure till you opened the door.’

The figure and action were those of the phantom; but her voice was so indescribably sweet, her glance so winning, her smile so tender, so unlike that of Rhoda’s midnight visitant, that the latter could hardly believe the evidence of her senses. She was truly glad that she had not hidden away in sheer aversion, as she had been inclined to do. In her basket Mrs Lodge brought the pair of boots that she had promised to the boy, and other useful articles.

At these proofs of a kindly feeling towards her and hers, Rhoda’s heart reproached her bitterly. This innocent young thing should have her blessing and not her curse. When she left them a light seemed gone from the dwelling. Two days later she came again to know if the boots fitted; and less than a fortnight after that paid Rhoda another call. On this occasion the boy was absent.

‘I walk a good deal,’ said Mrs Lodge, ‘and your house is the nearest outside our own parish. I hope you are well. You don’t look quite well.’

Rhoda said she was well enough; and indeed, though the paler of the two, there was more of the strength that endures in her well- defined features and large frame, than in the soft- cheeked young woman before her. The conversation became quite confidential as regarded their powers and weaknesses; and when Mrs Lodge was leaving, Rhoda said, ‘I hope you will find this air agree with you, ma’am, and not suffer from the damp of the water- meads.’

The younger one replied that there was not much doubt of it, her general health being usually good. ‘Though, now you remind me,’ she added, ‘I have one little ailment which puzzles me. It is nothing serious, but I cannot make it out.’

She uncovered her left hand and arm; and their outline confronted Rhoda’s gaze as the exact original of the limb she had beheld and seized in her dream. Upon the pink round surface of the arm were faint marks of an unhealthy colour, as if produced by a rough grasp. Rhoda’s eyes became riveted on the discolorations; she fancied that she discerned in them the shape of her own four fingers.

‘How did it happen?’ she said mechanically.

‘I cannot tell,’ replied Mrs Lodge, shaking her head.‘One night when I was sound asleep, dreaming I was away in some strange place, a pain suddenly shot into my arm there, and was so keen as to awaken me. I must have struck it in the daytime, I suppose, though I don’t remember doing so.’ She added, laughing, ‘I tell my dear husband that it looks just as if he had flown into a rage and struck me there. Oh, I daresay it will soon disappear.’

‘Ha, ha! Yes . . . On what night did it come?’

Mrs Lodge considered, and said it would be a fortnight ago on the morrow. ‘When I awoke I could not remember where I was,’ she added, ‘till the clock striking two reminded me.’

She had named the night and the hour of Rhoda’s spectral encounter, and Brook felt like a guilty thing. The artless disclosure startled her; she did not reason on the freaks of coincidence; and all the scenery of that ghastly night returned with double vividness to her mind.

‘Oh, can it be,’ she said to herself, when her visitor had departed, ‘that I exercise a malignant power over people against my own will?’ She knew that she had been slily called a witch since her fall; but never having understood why that particular stigma had been attached to her, it had passed disregarded. Could this be the explanation, and had such things as this ever happened before?

Iv A suggesTIon

The summer drew on, and Rhoda Brook almost dreaded to meet Mrs Lodge again, notwithstanding that her feeling for the young wife amounted wellnigh to affection. Something in her own individuality seemed to convict Rhoda of crime. Yet a fatality sometimes would direct the steps of the latter to the outskirts of Holmstoke whenever she left her house for any other purpose than her daily work; and hence it happened that their next encounter was out of doors. Rhoda could not avoid the subject which had so mystified her, and after the first few words she stammered, ‘I hope your – arm is well again, ma’am?’She had perceived with consternation that Gertrude Lodge carried her left arm stiffly.

‘No; it is not quite well. Indeed it is no better at all; it is rather worse. It pains me dreadfully sometimes.’

‘Perhaps you had better go to a doctor, ma’am.’

She replied that she had already seen a doctor. Her husband had insisted upon her going to one. But the surgeon had not seemed to understand the afflicted limb at all; he had told her to bathe it in hot water, and she had bathed it, but the treatment had done no good.

‘Will you let me see it?’ said the milkwoman.

Mrs Lodge pushed up her sleeve and disclosed the place, which was a few inches above the wrist. As soon as Rhoda Brook saw it, she could hardly preserve her composure. There was nothing of the nature of a wound, but the arm at that point had a shrivelled look, and the outline of the four fingers appeared more distinct than at the former time. Moreover, she fancied that they were imprinted in precisely the relative position of her clutch upon the arm in the trance; the first finger towards Gertrude’s wrist, and the fourth towards her elbow.

What the impress resembled seemed to have struck Gertrude herself since their last meeting. ‘It looks almost like finger- marks,’ she said; adding with a faint laugh,‘my husband says it is as if some witch, or the devil himself, had taken hold of me there, and blasted the flesh.’

Rhoda shivered. ‘That’s fancy,’ she said hurriedly. ‘I wouldn’t mind it, if I were you.’

‘I shouldn’t so much mind it,’ said the younger, with hesitation, ‘if – if I hadn’t a notion that it makes my husband – dislike me – no, love me less. Men think so much of personal appearance.’

‘Some do – he for one.’

‘Yes; and he was very proud of mine, at first.’

‘Keep your arm covered from his sight.’

‘Ah – he knows the disfigurement is there!’ She tried to hide the tears that filled her eyes.

‘Well, ma’am, I earnestly hope it will go away soon.’

And so the milkwoman’s mind was chained anew to the subject by a horrid sort of spell as she returned home. The sense of having been guilty of an act of malignity increased, affect as she might to ridicule her superstition. In her secret heart Rhoda did not altogether object to a slight diminution of her successor’s beauty, by whatever means it had come about; but she did not wish to inflict upon her physical pain. For though this pretty young woman had rendered impossible any reparation which Lodge might have made Rhoda for his past conduct, everything like resentment at the unconscious usurpation had quite passed away from the elder’s mind.

If the sweet and kindly Gertrude Lodge only knew of the scene in the bed- chamber, what would she think? Not to inform her of it seemed treachery in the presence of her friendliness; but tell she could not of her own accord –neither could she devise a remedy.

She mused upon the matter the greater part of the night; and the next day, after the morning milking, set out to obtain another glimpse of Gertrude Lodge if she could, being held to her by a gruesome fascination. By watching the house from a distance the milkmaid was presently able to discern the farmer’s wife in a ride she was taking alone –probably to join her husband in some distant field. Mrs Lodge perceived her, and cantered in her direction.

‘Good morning, Rhoda!’ Gertrude said, when she had come up. ‘I was going to call.’

Rhoda noticed that Mrs Lodge held the reins with some difficulty.

‘I hope – the bad arm,’ said Rhoda.

‘They tell me there is possibly one way by which I might be able to find out the cause, and so perhaps the cure, of it,’ replied the other anxiously. ‘It is by going to some clever man over in Egdon Heath. They did not know if he was still alive – and I cannot remember his name at this moment; but they said that you knew more of his movements than anybody else hereabout, and could tell me if he were still to be consulted. Dear me –what was his name? But you know.’

‘Not Conjuror Trendle?’ said her thin companion, turning pale.

‘Trendle – yes. Is he alive?’

‘I believe so,’ said Rhoda, with reluctance.

‘Why do you call him conjuror?’

‘Well – they say – they used to say he was a – he had powers other folks have not.’

‘Oh, how could my people be so superstitious as to recommend a man of that sort! I thought they meant some medical man. I shall think no more of him.’

Rhoda looked relieved, and Mrs Lodge rode on. The milkwoman had inwardly seen, from the moment she heard of her having been mentioned as a reference for this man, that there must exist a sarcastic feeling among the work- folk that a sorceress would know the whereabouts of the exorcist. They suspected her, then. A short time ago this would have given no concern to a woman of her common- sense. But she had a haunting reason to be superstitious now; and she had been seized with sudden dread that this Conjuror Trendle might name her as the malignant influence which was blasting the fair person of Gertrude, and so lead her friend to hate her for ever, and to treat her as some fiend in human shape.

But all was not over. Two days after, a shadow intruded into the window- pattern thrown on Rhoda Brook’s floor by the afternoon sun. The woman opened the door at once, almost breathlessly.

‘Are you alone?’ said Gertrude. She seemed to be no less harassed and anxious than Brook herself.

‘Yes,’ said Rhoda.

‘The place on my arm seems worse, and troubles me!’the young farmer’s wife went on. ‘It is so mysterious! I do hope it will not be a permanent blemish. I have again been thinking of what they said about Conjuror Trendle. I don’t really believe in such men, but I should not mind just visiting him, from curiosity – though on no account must my husband know. Is it far to where he lives?’

‘Yes – five miles,’ said Rhoda backwardly. ‘In the heart of Egdon.’

‘Well, I should have to walk. Could not you go with me to show me the way – say tomorrow afternoon?’

‘Oh, not I – that is,’ the milkwoman murmured, with a start of dismay. Again the dread seized her that something to do with her fierce act in the dream might be revealed, and her character in the eyes of the most useful friend she had ever had be ruined irretrievably.

Mrs Lodge urged, and Rhoda finally assented, though with much misgiving. Sad as the journey would be to her, she could not conscientiously stand in the way of a possible remedy for her patron’s strange affliction. It was agreed that, to escape suspicion of their mystic intent, they should meet at the edge of the heath, at the corner of a plantation which was visible from the spot where they now stood.

v Conjuror TrendLe

By the next afternoon Rhoda would have done anything to escape this inquiry. But she had promised to go. Moreover, there was a horrid fascination at times in becoming instrumental in throwing such possible light on her own character as would reveal her to be something greater in the occult world than she had ever herself suspected.

She started just before the time of day mentioned between them, and half an hour’s brisk walking brought her to the south- eastern extension of the Egdon tract of country, where the fir plantation was. A slight figure, cloaked and veiled, was already there. Rhoda recognized, almost with a shudder, that Mrs Lodge bore her left arm in a sling.

They hardly spoke to each other, and immediately set out on their climb into the interior of this solemn country, which stood high above the rich alluvial soil they had left half an hour before. It was a long walk; thick clouds made the atmosphere dark, though it was as yet only early afternoon; and the wind howled dismally over the hills of the heath – not improbably the same heath which had witnessed the agony of the Wessex King Ina, presented to after- ages as Lear. Gertrude Lodge talked most, Rhoda replying with monosyllabic preoccupation. She had a strange dislike to walking on the side of her companion where hung the afflicted arm, moving round to the other when inadvertently near it. Much heather had been brushed by their feet when they descended upon a cart- track, beside which stood the house of the man they sought.

He did not profess his remedial practices openly, or care anything about their continuance, his direct interests being those of a dealer in furze, turf, ‘sharp sand’, and other local products. Indeed, he affected not to believe largely in his own powers, and when warts that had been shown him for cure miraculously disappeared – which it must be owned they infallibly did – he would say lightly,‘Oh, I only drink a glass of grog upon ’em – perhaps it’s all chance,’ and immediately turn the subject.

He was at home when they arrived, having in fact seen them descending into his valley. He was a grey- bearded man, with a reddish face, and he looked singularly at Rhoda the first moment he beheld her. Mrs Lodge told him her errand; and then with words of self- disparagement he examined her arm.

‘Medicine can’t cure it,’ he said promptly. ‘’Tis the work of an enemy.’

Rhoda shrank into herself, and drew back.

‘An enemy? What enemy?’ asked Mrs Lodge.

He shook his head. ‘That’s best known to yourself,’ he said. ‘If you like I can show the person to you, though I shall not myself know who it is. I can do no more; and don’t wish to do that.’

She pressed him; on which he told Rhoda to wait outside where she stood, and took Mrs Lodge into the room. It opened immediately from the door; and, as the latter remained ajar, Rhoda Brook could see the proceedings without taking part in them. He brought a tumbler from the dresser, nearly filled it with water, and fetching an egg, prepared it in some private way; after which he broke it on the edge of the glass, so that the white went in and the yolk remained. As it was getting gloomy, he took the glass and its contents to the window, and told Gertrude to watch them closely. They leant over the table together, and the milkwoman could see the opaline hue of the egg- fluid changing form as it sank in the water, but she was not near enough to define the shape that it assumed.

‘Do you catch the likeness of any face or figure as you look?’ demanded the conjuror of the young woman.

She murmured a reply, in tones so low as to be inaudible to Rhoda, and continued to gaze intently into the glass. Rhoda turned, and walked a few steps away.

When Mrs Lodge came out, and her face was met by the light, it appeared exceedingly pale – as pale as Rhoda’s – against the sad dun shades of the upland’s garniture. Trendle shut the door behind her, and they at once started homeward together. But Rhoda perceived that her companion had quite changed.

‘Did he charge much?’ she asked tentatively.

‘Oh no – nothing. He would not take a farthing,’ said Gertrude.

‘And what did you see?’ inquired Rhoda.

‘Nothing I – care to speak of.’ The constraint in her manner was remarkable; her face was so rigid as to wear an oldened aspect, faintly suggestive of the face in Rhoda’s bed- chamber.

‘Was it you who first proposed coming here?’ Mrs Lodge suddenly inquired, after a long pause. ‘How very odd, if you did!’

‘No. But I am not sorry we have come, all things considered,’ she replied. For the first time a sense of triumph possessed her, and she did not altogether deplore that the young thing at her side should learn that their lives had been antagonized by other influences than their own.

The subject was no more alluded to during the long and dreary walk home. But in some way or other a story was whispered about the many- dairied Swenn valley that winter that Mrs Lodge’s gradual loss of the use of her left arm was owing to her being ‘overlooked’ by Rhoda Brook. The latter kept her own counsel about the incubus, but her face grew sadder and thinner; and in the spring she and her boy disappeared from the neighbourhood of Holmstoke.

vI A seCond ATTeMpT

Half a dozen years passed away, and Mr and Mrs Lodge’s married experience sank into prosiness, and worse. The farmer was usually gloomy and silent: the woman whom he had wooed for her grace and beauty was contorted and disfigured in the left limb; moreover, she had brought him no child, which rendered it likely that he would be the last of a family who had occupied that valley for some two hundred years. He thought of Rhoda Brook and her son; and feared this might be a judgement from heaven upon him.

The once blithe- hearted and enlightened Gertrude was changing into an irritable, superstitious woman, whose whole time was given to experimenting upon her ailment with every quack remedy she came across. She was honestly attached to her husband, and was ever secretly hoping against hope to win back his heart again by regaining some at least of her personal beauty. Hence it arose that her closet was lined with bottles, packets, and ointment- pots of every description – nay, bunches of mystic herbs, charms, and books of necromancy, which in her schoolgirl time she would have ridiculed as folly.

‘Damned if you won’t poison yourself with these apothecary messes and witch mixtures some time or other,’said her husband, when his eye chanced to fall upon the multitudinous array.

She did not reply, but turned her sad, soft glance upon him in such heart- swollen reproach that he looked sorry for his words, and added, ‘I only meant it for your good, you know, Gertrude.’

‘I’ll clear out the whole lot, and destroy them,’ said she huskily, ‘and attempt such remedies no more!’

‘You want somebody to cheer you,’ he observed. ‘I once thought of adopting a boy; but he is too old now. And he is gone away I don’t know where.’

She guessed to whom he alluded; for Rhoda Brook’s story had in the course of years become known to her; though not a word had ever passed between her husband and herself on the subject. Neither had she ever spoken to him of her visit to Conjuror Trendle, and of what was revealed to her, or she thought was revealed to her, by that solitary heath- man.

She was now five- and- twenty; but she seemed older.‘Six years of marriage, and only a few months of love,’she sometimes whispered to herself. And then she thought of the apparent cause, and said, with a tragic glance at her withering limb, ‘If I could only again be as I was when he first saw me!’

She obediently destroyed her nostrums and charms; but there remained a hankering wish to try something else – some other sort of cure altogether. She had never revisited Trendle since she had been conducted to the house of the solitary by Rhoda against her will; but it now suddenly occurred to Gertrude that she would, in a last desperate effort at deliverance from this seeming curse, again seek out the man, if he yet lived. He was entitled to a certain credence, for the indistinct form he had raised in the glass had undoubtedly resembled the only woman in the world who – as she now knew, though not then – could have a reason for bearing her ill- will. The visit should be paid.

This time she went alone, though she nearly got lost on the heath, and roamed a considerable distance out of her way. Trendle’s house was reached at last, however: he was not indoors, and instead of waiting at the cottage she went to where his bent figure was pointed out to her at work a long way off. Trendle remembered her, and laying down the handful of furze- roots which he was gathering and throwing into a heap, he offered to accompany her in her homeward direction, as the distance was considerable and the days were short. So they walked together, his head bowed nearly to the earth, and his form of a colour with it.

‘You can send away warts and other excrescences, I know,’ she said; ‘why can’t you send away this?’ And the arm was uncovered.

‘You think too much of my powers!’ said Trendle; ‘and I am old and weak now, too. No, no; it is too much for me to attempt in my own person. What have ye tried?’

She named to him some of the hundred medicaments and counterspells which she had adopted from time to time. He shook his head.

‘Some were good enough,’ he said approvingly; ‘but not many of them for such as this. This is of the nature of a blight, not of the nature of a wound; and if you ever do throw it off, it will be all at once.’

‘If I only could!’

‘There is only one chance of doing it known to me. It has never failed in kindred afflictions, – that I can declare. But it is hard to carry out, and especially for a woman.’

‘Tell me!’ said she.

‘You must touch with the limb the neck of a man who’s been hanged.’

She started a little at the image he had raised.

‘Before he’s cold – just after he’s cut down,’ continued the conjuror impassively.

‘How can that do good?’

‘It will turn the blood and change the constitution. But, as I say, to do it is hard. You must get into jail, and wait for him when he’s brought off the gallows. Lots have done it, though perhaps not such pretty women as you. I used to send dozens for skin complaints. But that was in former times. The last I sent was in ’13 – near twenty years ago.’

He had no more to tell her; and, when he had put her into a straight track homeward, turned and left her, refusing all money as at first.

vII A rIde

The communication sank deep into Gertrude’s mind. Her nature was rather a timid one; and probably of all remedies that the white wizard could have suggested there was not one which would have filled her with so much aversion as this, not to speak of the immense obstacles in the way of its adoption.

Casterbridge, the county- town, was a dozen or fifteen miles off; and though in those days, when men were executed for horse- stealing, arson, and burglary, an assize seldom passed without a hanging, it was not likely that she could get access to the body of the criminal unaided. And the fear of her husband’s anger made her reluctant to breathe a word of Trendle’s suggestion to him or to anybody about him.

She did nothing for months, and patiently bore her disfigurement as before. But her woman’s nature, craving for renewed love, through the medium of renewed beauty(she was but twenty- five), was ever stimulating her to try what, at any rate, could hardly do her any harm. ‘What came by a spell will go by a spell surely,’ she would say. Whenever her imagination pictured the act she shrank in terror from the possibility of it: then the words of the conjuror, ‘It will turn your blood,’ were seen to be capable of a scientific no less than a ghastly interpretation; the mastering desire returned, and urged her on again.

There was at this time but one county paper, and that her husband only occasionally borrowed. But oldfashioned days had old- fashioned means, and news was extensively conveyed by word of mouth from market to market or from fair to fair; so that, whenever such an event as an execution was about to take place, few within a radius of twenty miles were ignorant of the coming sight; and, so far as Holmstoke was concerned, some enthusiasts had been known to walk all the way to Casterbridge and back in one day, solely to witness the spectacle. The next assizes were in March; and when Gertrude Lodge heard that they had been held, she inquired stealthily at the inn as to the result, as soon as she could find opportunity.

She was, however, too late. The time at which the sentences were to be carried out had arrived, and to make the journey and obtain admission at such short notice required at least her husband’s assistance. She dared not tell him, for she had found by delicate experiment that these smouldering village beliefs made him furious if mentioned, partly because he half entertained them himself. It was therefore necessary to wait for another opportunity.

Her determination received a fillip from learning that two epileptic children had attended from this very village of Holmstoke many years before with beneficial results, though the experiment had been strongly condemned by the neighbouring clergy. April, May, June passed; and it is no overstatement to say that by the end of the last- named month Gertrude wellnigh longed for the death of a fellow- creature. Instead of her formal prayers each night, her unconscious prayer was, ‘O Lord, hang some guilty or innocent person soon!’

This time she made earlier inquiries, and was altogether more systematic in her proceedings. Moreover, the season was summer, between the haymaking and the harvest, and in the leisure thus afforded her husband had been holiday- taking away from home.

The assizes were in July, and she went to the inn as before. There was to be one execution – only one – for arson.

Her greatest problem was not how to get to Casterbridge, but what means she should adopt for obtaining admission to the jail. Though access for such purposes had formerly never been denied, the custom had fallen into desuetude; and in contemplating her possible difficulties, she was again almost driven to fall back upon her husband. But, on sounding him about the assizes, he was so uncommunicative, so more than usually cold, that she did not proceed, and decided that whatever she did she would do alone.

Fortune, obdurate hitherto, showed her unexpected favour. On the Thursday before the Saturday fixed for the execution, Lodge remarked to her that he was going away from home for another day or two on business at a fair, and that he was sorry he could not take her with him.

She exhibited on this occasion so much readiness to stay at home that he looked at her in surprise. Time had been when she would have shown deep disappointment at the loss of such a jaunt. However, he lapsed into his usual taciturnity, and on the day named left Holmstoke.

It was now her turn. She at first had thought of driving, but on reflection held that driving would not do, since it would necessitate her keeping to the turnpike- road, and so increase by tenfold the risk of her ghastly errand being found out. She decided to ride, and avoid the beaten track, notwithstanding that in her husband’s stables there was no animal just at present which by any stretch of imagination could be considered a lady’s mount, in spite of his promise before marriage to always keep a mare for her. He had, however, many horses, fine ones of their kind; and among the rest was a serviceable creature, an equine Amazon, with a back as broad as a sofa, on which Gertrude had occasionally taken an airing when unwell. This horse she chose.

On Friday afternoon one of the men brought it round. She was dressed, and before going down looked at her shrivelled arm. ‘Ah!’ she said to it, ‘if it had not been for you this terrible ordeal would have been saved me!’

When strapping up the bundle in which she carried a few articles of clothing, she took occasion to say to the servant, ‘I take these in case I should not get back tonight from the person I am going to visit. Don’t be alarmed if I am not in by ten, and close up the house as usual. I shall be at home tomorrow for certain.’ She meant then to privately tell her husband: the deed accomplished was not like the deed projected. He would almost certainly forgive her.

And then the pretty palpitating Gertrude Lodge went from her husband’s homestead; but though her goal was Casterbridge she did not take the direct route thither through Stickleford. Her cunning course at first was in precisely the opposite direction. As soon as she was out of sight, however, she turned to the left, by a road which led into Egdon, and on entering the heath wheeled round, and set out in the true course, due westerly. A more private way down the county could not be imagined; and as to direction, she had merely to keep her horse’s head to a point a little to the right of the sun. She knew that she would light upon a furze- cutter or cottager of some sort from time to time, from whom she might correct her bearing.

Though the date was comparatively recent, Egdon was much less fragmentary in character than now. The attempts – successful and otherwise – at cultivation on the lower slopes, which intrude and break up the original heath into small detached heaths, had not been carried far: Enclosure Acts had not taken effect, and the banks and fences which now exclude the cattle of those villagers who formerly enjoyed rights of commonage thereon, and the carts of those who had turbary privileges which kept them in firing all the year round, were not erected. Gertrude therefore rode along with no other obstacles than the prickly furze- bushes, the mats of heather, the white water- courses, and the natural steeps and declivities of the ground.

Her horse was sure, if heavy- footed and slow, and though a draught animal, was easy- paced; had it been otherwise, she was not a woman who could have ventured to ride over such a bit of country with a half- dead arm. It was therefore nearly eight o’clock when she drew rein to breathe the mare on the last outlying high point of heath- land towards Casterbridge, previous to leaving Egdon for the cultivated valleys.

She halted before a pond, flanked by the ends of two hedges; a railing ran through the centre of the pond, dividing it in half. Over the railing she saw the low green country; over the green trees the roofs of the town; over the roofs a white flat facade, denoting the entrance to the county jail. On the roof of this front specks were moving about; they seemed to be workmen erecting something. Her flesh crept. She descended slowly, and was soon amid corn- fields and pastures. In another half- hour, when it was almost dusk, Gertrude reached the White Hart, the first inn of the town on that side.

Little surprise was excited by her arrival: farmers’ wives rode on horseback then more than they do now; though, for that matter, Mrs Lodge was not imagined to be a wife at all; the inn- keeper supposed her some harum- skarum young woman who had come to attend ‘ hang- fair’ next day. Neither her husband nor herself ever dealt in Casterbridge market, so that she was unknown. While dismounting she beheld a crowd of boys standing at the door of a harness- maker’s shop just above the inn, looking inside it with deep interest.

‘What is going on there?’ she asked of the ostler.

‘Making the rope for tomorrow.’

She throbbed responsively, and contracted her arm.

‘ ’Tis sold by the inch afterwards,’ the man continued.‘I could get you a bit, miss, for nothing, if you’d like?’

She hastily repudiated any such wish, all the more from a curious creeping feeling that the condemned wretch’s destiny was becoming interwoven with her own; and having engaged a room for the night sat down to think.

Up to this time she had formed but the vaguest notions about her means of obtaining access to the prison. The words of the cunning- man returned to her mind. He had implied that she should use her beauty, impaired though it was, as a pass- key. In her inexperience she knew little about jail functionaries; she had heard of a high- sheriff and an under- sheriff, but dimly only. She knew, however, that there must be a hangman, and to the hangman she determined to apply.

vIII A wATer- sIde herMIT

At this date, and for several years after, there was a hangman to almost every jail. Gertrude found, on inquiry, that the Casterbridge official dwelt in a lonely cottage by a deep slow river flowing under the cliff on which the prison buildings were situate – the stream being the self- same one, though she did not know it, which watered the Stickleford and Holmstoke meads lower down in its course.

Having changed her dress, and before she had eaten or drunk – for she could not take her ease till she had ascertained some particulars – Gertrude pursued her way by a path along the water- side to the cottage indicated. Passing thus the outskirts of the jail, she discerned on the level roof over the gateway three rectangular lines against the sky, where the specks had been moving in her distant view; she recognized what the erection was, and passed quickly on. Another hundred yards brought her to the executioner’s house, which a boy pointed out. It stood close to the same stream, and was hard by a weir, the waters of which emitted a steady roar.

While she stood hesitating the door opened, and an old man came forth shading a candle with one hand. Locking the door on the outside, he turned to a flight of wooden steps fixed against the end of the cottage, and began to ascend them, this being evidently the staircase to his bedroom. Gertrude hastened forward, but by the time she reached the foot of the ladder he was at the top. She called to him loudly enough to be heard above the roar of the weir; he looked down and said, ‘What d’ye want here?’

‘To speak to you a minute.’

The candle- light, such as it was, fell upon her imploring, pale, upturned face, and Davies (as the hangman was called) backed down the ladder. ‘I was just going to bed,’ he said; ‘ “Early to bed and early to rise,” but I don’t mind stopping a minute for such a one as you. Come into the house.’ He reopened the door, and preceded her to the room within.

The implements of his daily work, which was that of a jobbing gardener, stood in a corner, and seeing probably that she looked rural, he said, ‘If you want me to undertake country work I can’t come, for I never leave Casterbridge for gentle nor simple – not I. Though sometimes I make others leave,’ he added formally.

‘Yes, yes! That’s it! Tomorrow!’

‘Ah! I thought so. Well, what’s the matter about that?’Tis no use to come here about the knot – folks do come continually, but I tell ’em one knot is as merciful as another if ye keep it under the ear. Is the unfortunate man a relation; or, I should say, perhaps’ (looking at her dress) ‘a person who’s been in your employ?’

‘No. What time is the execution?’

‘The same as usual – twelve o’clock, or as soon after as the London mail- coach gets in. We always wait for that, in case of a reprieve.’

‘Oh – a reprieve – I hope not!’ she said involuntarily.

‘Well, – he, he! – as a matter of business, so do I! But still, if ever a young fellow deserved to be let off, this one does; only just turned eighteen, and only present by chance when the rick was fired. Howsomever, there’s not much risk of it, as they are obliged to make an example of him, there having been so much destruction of property that way lately.’

‘I mean,’ she explained, ‘that I want to touch him for a charm, a cure of an affliction, by the advice of a man who has proved the virtue of the remedy.’

‘Oh yes, miss! Now I understand. I’ve had such people come in past years. But it didn’t strike me that you looked of a sort to require blood- turning. What’s the complaint? The wrong kind for this, I’ll be bound.’

‘My arm.’ She reluctantly showed the withered skin.

‘Ah! – ’tis all a- scram!’ said the hangman, examining it.

‘Yes,’ said she.

‘Well,’ he continued with interest, ‘that is the class o’subject, I’m bound to admit! I like the look of the place; it is truly as suitable for the cure as any I ever saw. ’Twas a knowing- man that sent ’ee, whoever he was.’

‘You can contrive for me all that’s necessary?’ she said breathlessly.

‘You should really have gone to the governor of the jail, and your doctor with ’ee, and given your name and address – that’s how it used to be done, if I recollect. Still, perhaps, I can manage it for a trifling fee.’

‘Oh, thank you! I would rather do it this way, as I should like it kept private.’

‘Lover not to know, eh?’

‘No – husband.’

‘Aha! Very well. I’ll get ’ee a touch of the corpse.’

‘Where is it now?’ she said, shuddering.

‘It? – he, you mean; he’s living yet. Just inside that little small winder up there in the glum.’ He signified the jail on the cliff above.

She thought of her husband and her friends. ‘Yes, of course,’ she said; ‘and how am I to proceed?’

He took her to the door. ‘Now, do you be waiting at the little wicket in the wall, that you’ll find up there in the lane, not later than one o’clock. I will open it from the inside, as I shan’t come home to dinner till he’s cut down. Good night. Be punctual; and if you don’t want anybody to know ’ee, wear a veil. Ah – once I had such a daughter as you!’

She went away, and climbed the path above, to assure herself that she would be able to find the wicket next day. Its outline was soon visible to her – a narrow opening in the outer wall of the prison precincts. The steep was so great that, having reached the wicket, she stopped a moment to breathe; and, looking back upon the water- side cot, saw the hangman again ascending his outdoor staircase. He entered the loft or chamber to which it led, and in a few minutes extinguished his light.

The town clock struck ten, and she returned to the White Hart as she had come.

IX A renCounTer

It was one o’clock on Saturday. Gertrude Lodge, having been admitted to the jail as above described, was sitting in a waiting- room within the second gate, which stood under a classic archway of ashlar, then comparatively modern, and bearing the inscription, ‘CovnTy jAIL: 1793.’ This had been the facade she saw from the heath the day before. Near at hand was a passage to the roof on which the gallows stood.

The town was thronged, and the market suspended; but Gertrude had seen scarcely a soul. Having kept her room till the hour of the appointment, she had proceeded to the spot by a way which avoided the open space below the cliff where the spectators had gathered; but she could, even now, hear the multitudinous babble of their voices, out of which rose at intervals the hoarse croak of a single voice, uttering the words, ‘Last dying speech and confession!’ There had been no reprieve, and the execution was over; but the crowd still waited to see the body taken down.

Soon the persistent girl heard a trampling overhead, then a hand beckoned to her, and, following directions, she went out and crossed the inner paved court beyond the gatehouse, her knees trembling so that she could scarcely walk. One of her arms was out of its sleeve, and only covered by her shawl.

On the spot at which she had now arrived were two trestles, and before she could think of their purpose she heard heavy feet descending stairs somewhere at her back. Turn her head she would not, or could not, and, rigid in this position, she was conscious of a rough coffin passing her shoulder, borne by four men. It was open, and in it lay the body of a young man, wearing the smockfrock of a rustic, and fustian breeches. It had been thrown into the coffin so hastily that the skirt of the smockfrock was hanging over. The burden was temporarily deposited on the trestles.

By this time the young woman’s state was such that a grey mist seemed to float before her eyes, on account of which, and the veil she wore, she could scarcely discern anything: it was as though she had nearly died, but was held up by a sort of galvanism.

‘Now,’ said a voice close at hand, and she was just conscious that it had been addressed to her.

By a last strenuous effort she advanced, at the same time hearing persons approaching behind her. She bared her poor curst arm; and Davies, uncovering the face of the corpse, took Gertrude’s hand, and held it so that her arm lay across the dead man’s neck, upon a line the colour of an unripe blackberry, which surrounded it.

Gertrude shrieked: ‘the turn o’ the blood,’ predicted by the conjuror, had taken place. But at that moment a second shriek rent the air of the enclosure: it was not Gertrude’s, and its effect upon her was to make her start round.

Immediately behind her stood Rhoda Brook, her face drawn, and her eyes red with weeping. Behind Rhoda stood her own husband; his countenance lined, his eyes dim, but without a tear.

‘ D— n you! what are you doing here?’ he said hoarsely.

‘Hussy – to come between us and our child now!’ cried Rhoda. ‘This is the meaning of what Satan showed me in the vision! You are like her at last!’ And clutching the bare arm of the younger woman, she pulled her unresistingly back against the wall. Immediately Brook had loosened her hold the fragile young Gertrude slid down against the feet of her husband. When he lifted her up she was unconscious.

The mere sight of the twain had been enough to suggest to her that the dead young man was Rhoda’s son. At that time the relatives of an executed convict had the privilege of claiming the body for burial, if they chose to do so; and it was for this purpose that Lodge was awaiting the inquest with Rhoda. He had been summoned by her as soon as the young man was taken in the crime, and at different times since; and he had attended in court during the trial. This was the ‘holiday’ he had been indulging in of late. The two wretched parents had wished to avoid exposure; and hence had come themselves for the body, a waggon and sheet for its conveyance and covering being in waiting outside.

Gertrude’s case was so serious that it was deemed advisable to call to her the surgeon who was at hand. She was taken out of the jail into the town; but she never reached home alive. Her delicate vitality, sapped perhaps by the paralysed arm, collapsed under the double shock that followed the severe strain, physical and mental, to which she had subjected herself during the previous twenty- four hours. Her blood had been ‘turned’ indeed –too far. Her death took place in the town three days after.

Her husband was never seen in Casterbridge again; once only in the old market place at Anglebury, which he had so much frequented, and very seldom in public anywhere. Burdened at first with moodiness and remorse, he eventually changed for the better, and appeared as a chastened and thoughtful man. Soon after attending the funeral of his poor young wife he took steps towards giving up the farms in Holmstoke and the adjoining parish, and, having sold every head of his stock, he went away to Port- Bredy, at the other end of the county, living there in solitary lodgings till his death two years later of a painless decline. It was then found that he had bequeathed the whole of his not inconsiderable property to a reformatory for boys, subject to the payment of a small annuity to Rhoda Brook, if she could be found to claim it.

For some time she could not be found; but eventually she reappeared in her old parish, – absolutely refusing, however, to have anything to do with the provision made for her. Her monotonous milking at the dairy was resumed, and followed for many long years, till her form became bent, and her once abundant dark hair white and worn away at the forehead – perhaps by long pressure against the cows. Here, sometimes, those who knew her experiences would stand and observe her, and wonder what sombre thoughts were beating inside that impassive, wrinkled brow, to the rhythm of the alternating milkstreams.

The Thieves Who Couldn’t Help Sneezing

Many years ago, when oak- trees now past their prime were about as large as elderly gentlemen’s walking- sticks, there lived in Wessex a yeoman’s son, whose name was Hubert. He was about fourteen years of age, and was as remarkable for his candour and lightness of heart as for his physical courage, of which, indeed, he was a little vain.

One cold Christmas Eve his father, having no other help at hand, sent him on an important errand to a small town several miles from home. He travelled on horseback, and was detained by the business till a late hour of the evening. At last, however, it was completed; he returned to the inn, the horse was saddled, and he started on his way. His journey homeward lay through the Vale of Blackmore, a fertile but somewhat lonely district, with heavy clay roads and crooked lanes. In those days, too, a great part of it was thickly wooded.

It must have been about nine o’clock when, riding along amid the overhanging trees upon his stout- legged cob Jerry, and singing a Christmas carol, to be in harmony with the season, Hubert fancied that he heard a noise among the boughs. This recalled to his mind that the spot he was traversing bore an evil name. Men had been waylaid there. He looked at Jerry, and wished he had been of any other colour than light grey; for on this account the docile animal’s form was visible even here in the dense shade. ‘What do I care?’ he said aloud, after a few minutes of reflection. ‘Jerry’s legs are too nimble to allow any highwayman to come near me.’

‘Ha! ha! indeed,’ was said in a deep voice; and the next moment a man darted from the thicket on his right hand, another man from the thicket on his left hand, and another from a tree- trunk a few yards ahead. Hubert’s bridle was seized, he was pulled from his horse, and although he struck out with all his might, as a brave boy would naturally do, he was overpowered. His arms were tied behind him, his legs bound tightly together, and he was thrown into the ditch. The robbers, whose faces he could now dimly perceive to be artificially blackened, at once departed, leading off the horse.

As soon as Hubert had a little recovered himself, he found that by great exertion he was able to extricate his legs from the cord; but, in spite of every endeavour, his arms remained bound as fast as before. All, therefore, that he could do was to rise to his feet and proceed on his way with his arms behind him, and trust to chance for getting them unfastened. He knew that it would be impossible to reach home on foot that night, and in such a condition; but he walked on. Owing to the confusion which this attack caused in his brain, he lost his way, and would have been inclined to lie down and rest till morning among the dead leaves had he not known the danger of sleeping without wrappers in a frost so severe. So he wandered further onwards, his arms wrung and numbed by the cord which pinioned him and his heart aching for the loss of poor Jerry, who never had been known to kick, or bite, or show a single vicious habit. He was not a little glad when he discerned through the trees a distant light. Towards this he made his way, and presently found himself in front of a large mansion with flanking wings, gables, and towers, the battlements and chimneys showing their shapes against the stars.

All was silent; but the door stood wide open, it being from this door that the light shone which had attracted him. On entering he found himself in a vast apartment arranged as a dining- hall, and brilliantly illuminated. The walls were covered with a great deal of dark wainscoting, formed into moulded panels, carvings, closet- doors, and the usual fittings of a house of that kind. But what drew his attention most was the large table in the midst of the hall, upon which was spread a sumptuous supper, as yet untouched. Chairs were placed around, and it appeared as if something had occurred to interrupt the meal just at the time when all were ready to begin.

Even had Hubert been so inclined, he could not have eaten in his helpless state, unless by dipping his mouth in the dishes, like a pig or cow. He wished first to obtain assistance; and was about to penetrate further into the house for that purpose when he heard hasty footsteps in the porch and the words, ‘Be quick!’ uttered in the deep voice which had reached him when he was dragged from the horse. There was only just time for him to dart under the table before three men entered the dining- hall. Peeping from beneath the hanging edges of the tablecloth, he perceived that their faces, too, were blackened, which at once removed any remaining doubts he may have felt that these were the same thieves.

‘Now, then,’ said the first – the man with the deep voice – ‘let us hide ourselves. They will all be back again in a minute. That was a good trick to get them out of the house – eh?’

‘Yes. You well imitated the cries of a man in distress,’said the second.

‘Excellently,’ said the third.

‘But they will soon find out that it was a false alarm. Come, where shall we hide? It must be some place we can stay in for two or three hours, till all are in bed and asleep. Ah! I have it. Come this way! I have learnt that the further closet is not opened once in a twelvemonth; it will serve our purpose exactly.’

The speaker advanced into a corridor which led from the hall. Creeping a little farther forward, Hubert could discern that the closet stood at the end, facing the dining- hall. The thieves entered it, and closed the door. Hardly breathing, Hubert glided forward, to learn a little more of their intention, if possible; and, coming close, he could hear the robbers whispering about the different rooms where the jewels, plate, and other valuables of the house were kept, which they plainly meant to steal.

They had not been long in hiding when a gay chattering of ladies and gentlemen was audible on the terrace without. Hubert felt that it would not do to be caught prowling about the house, unless he wished to be taken for a robber himself; and he slipped softly back to the hall, out at the door, and stood in a dark corner of the porch, where he could see everything without being himself seen. In a moment or two a whole troop of personages came gliding past him into the house. There were an elderly gentleman and lady, eight or nine young ladies, as many young men, besides half- a- dozen men- servants and maids. The mansion had apparently been quite emptied of its occupants.

‘Now, children and young people, we will resume our meal,’ said the old gentleman. ‘What the noise could have been I cannot understand. I never felt so certain in my life that there was a person being murdered outside my door.’

Then the ladies began saying how frightened they had been, and how they had expected an adventure, and how it had ended in nothing after all.

‘Wait a while,’ said Hubert to himself. ‘You’ll have adventure enough by- and- by, ladies.’

It appeared that the young men and women were married sons and daughters of the old couple, who had come that day to spend Christmas with their parents.

The door was then closed, Hubert being left outside in the porch. He thought this a proper moment for asking their assistance; and, since he was unable to knock with his hands, began boldly to kick the door.

‘Hullo! What disturbance are you making here?’ said a footman who opened it; and seizing Hubert by the shoulder, he pulled him into the dining- hall. ‘Here’s a strange boy I have found making a noise in the porch, Sir Simon.’

Everybody turned.

‘Bring him forward,’ said Sir Simon, the old gentleman before mentioned. ‘What were you doing there, my boy?’

‘Why, his arms are tied!’ said one of the ladies.

‘Poor fellow!’ said another.

Hubert at once began to explain that he had been waylaid on his journey home, robbed of his horse, and mercilessly left in this condition by the thieves.

‘Only to think of it!’ exclaimed Sir Simon.

‘That’s a likely story,’ said one of the gentleman- guests, incredulously.

‘Doubtful, hey?’ asked Sir Simon.

‘Perhaps he’s a robber himself,’ suggested a lady.

‘There is a curiously wild wicked look about him, certainly, now that I examine him closely,’ said the old mother.

Hubert blushed with shame; and, instead of continuing his story, and relating that the robbers were concealed in the house, he doggedly held his tongue, and half resolved to let them find out their danger for themselves.

‘Well, untie him,’ said Sir Simon. ‘Come, since it is Christmas Eve, we’ll treat him well. Here, my lad; sit down in that empty seat at the bottom of the table, and make as good a meal as you can. When you have had your fill we will listen to more particulars of your story.’

The feast then proceeded; and Hubert, now at liberty, was not at all sorry to join in. The more they ate and drank the merrier did the company become; the wine flowed freely, the logs flared up the chimney, the ladies laughed at the gentlemen’s stories; in short, all went as noisily and as happily as a Christmas gathering in old times possibly could do.

Hubert, in spite of his hurt feelings at their doubts of his honesty, could not help being warmed both in mind and in body by the good cheer, the scene, and the example of hilarity set by his neighbours. At last he laughed as heartily at their stories and repartees as the old Baronet, Sir Simon, himself. When the meal was almost over one of the sons, who had drunk a little too much wine, after the manner of men in that century, said to Hubert, ‘Well, my boy, how are you? Can you take a pinch of snuff?’ He held out one of the snuff- boxes which were then becoming common among young and old throughout the country.

‘Thank you,’ said Hubert, accepting a pinch.

‘Tell the ladies who you are, what you are made of, and what you can do,’ the young man continued, slapping Hubert upon the shoulder.

‘Certainly,’ said our hero, drawing himself up, and thinking it best to put a bold face on the matter. ‘I am a travelling magician.’

‘Indeed!’

‘What shall we hear next?’

‘Can you call up spirits from the vasty deep, young wizard?’

‘I can conjure up a tempest in a cupboard,’ Hubert replied.

‘ Ha- ha!’ said the old Baronet, pleasantly rubbing his hands. ‘We must see this performance. Girls, don’t go away: here’s something to be seen.’

‘Not dangerous, I hope?’ said the old lady.

Hubert rose from the table. ‘Hand me your snuffbox, please,’ he said to the young man who had made free with him. ‘And now,’ he continued, ‘without the least noise, follow me. If any of you speak it will break the spell.’

They promised obedience. He entered the corridor, and, taking off his shoes, went on tiptoe to the closet door, the guests advancing in a silent group at a little distance behind him. Hubert next placed a stool in front of the door, and, by standing upon it, was tall enough to reach to the top. He then, just as noiselessly, poured all the snuff from the box along the upper edge of the door, and, with a few short puffs of breath, blew the snuff through the chink into the interior of the closet. He held up his finger to the assembly, that they might be silent.

‘Dear me, what’s that?’ said the old lady, after a minute or two had elapsed.

A suppressed sneeze had come from inside the closet.

Hubert held up his finger again.

‘How very singular,’ whispered Sir Simon. ‘This is most interesting.’

Hubert took advantage of the moment to gently slide the bolt of the closet door into its place. ‘More snuff,’ he said, calmly.

‘More snuff,’ said Sir Simon. Two or three gentlemen passed their boxes, and the contents were blown in at that top of the closet. Another sneeze, not quite so well suppressed as the first, was heard: then another, which seemed to say that it would not be suppressed under any circumstances whatever. At length there arose a perfect storm of sneezes.

‘Excellent, excellent for one so young!’ said Sir Simon.‘I am much interested in this trick of throwing the voice –called, I believe, ventriloquism.’

‘More snuff,’ said Hubert.

‘More snuff,’ said Sir Simon. Sir Simon’s man brought a large jar of the best scented Scotch.

Hubert once more charged the upper chink of the closet, and blew the snuff into the interior, as before. Again he charged, and again, emptying the whole contents of the jar. The tumults of sneezes became really extraordinary to listen to – there was no cessation. It was like wind, rain, and sea, battling in a hurricane.

‘I believe there are men inside, and that it is no trick at all!’ exclaimed Sir Simon, the truth flashing on him.

‘There are,’ said Hubert. ‘They are come to rob the house; and they are the same who stole my horse.’

The sneezes changed to spasmodic groans. One of the thieves, hearing Hubert’s voice, cried, ‘Oh! mercy! mercy! let us out of this!’

‘Where’s my horse?’ said Hubert.

‘Tied to the tree in the hollow behind Short’s Gib bet. Mercy! mercy! let us out, or we shall die of suffo cation!’

All the Christmas guests now perceived that this was no longer sport, but serious earnest. Guns and cudgels were procured; all the men- servants were called in, and arranged in position outside the closet. At a signal Hubert withdrew the bolt, and stood on the defensive. But the three robbers, far from attacking them, were found crouching in the corner, gasping for breath. They made no resistance; and, being pinioned, were placed in an out- house till the morning.

Hubert now gave the remainder of his story to the assembled company, and was profusely thanked for the services he had rendered. Sir Simon pressed him to stay over the night, and accept the use of the best bed- room the house afforded, which had been occupied by Queen Elizabeth and King Charles successively when on their visits to this part of the country. But Hubert declined, being anxious to find his horse Jerry, and to test the truth of the robbers’ statements concerning him.

Several of the guests accompanied Hubert to the spot behind the gibbet, alluded to by the thieves as where Jerry was hidden. When they reached the knoll and looked over, behold! there the horse stood, uninjured, and quite unconcerned. At sight of Hubert he neighed joyfully; and nothing could exceed Hubert’s gladness at finding him. He mounted, wished his friends ‘Good night!’ and cantered off in the direction they pointed out as his nearest way, reaching home safely about four o’clock in the morning.

樱花树下的清酒

序段

无聊之日，枯坐砚前，心中不由得杂想纷呈，乃随手写来；其间似有不近常理者，视为怪谈可也。

*

人生在世，最是贪图名位。

天皇固然尊贵至极，皇亲国戚也都是金枝玉叶，不是寻常人可以高攀；摄政关白[1]在一人之下、万人之上，当然不容奢望。

至于身在大内，号称“舍人”的诸贵人，也不能等闲视之。其子孙即便破落，也自有其清姿贵格。相比之下，有一点身份就小人得志、自命不凡的人，就不足道了。

世上怕没有多少人把法师瞧得上眼吧。清少纳言就说过：人视之“犹如木屑”。说得很客观。法师一辈子高座说法，俯临众生，似有无上的权威，但对他来说，究竟有什么意义呢？增贺上人似乎说过，一心求名，是有违佛陀教义的。

不过真心舍弃现世、皈依佛门的人，倒颇为令人钦羡。

人都想有秀美的姿容。不过谈吐招人喜爱而并不多话的人，也让人整天面对都不觉得乏味。姿采虽然炫目，德行并不相符的人，就着实令人惋惜了。德行与容貌都是天生的，姑且不论。思想境界，通过持续不断的修习，能够日复一日地精进。天生容貌气质不错的人，如果腹中并无才学，又常与品貌俱无的人在一起，甚至被其习性品味所浸染，比他们还不如，就实在是我所不愿看到的。

我对于世上男子的期许，在于有修身齐家的真才实学，长于诗赋文章，通晓和歌乐理，精通典章制度，而能够为人表率，这是最理想的。其次，工于书法，信笔挥洒皆成模样；善于歌咏，而能合乎音律节拍；对于席上别人的劝酒，如果推辞不了，也能略饮一点，以不伤应酬的和气，对于男人来说，这也是相当好的事。

事事能干却不解风情的男子，好比没有杯底的玉杯，中看不中用。

相比之下，彷徨无计、流离失所，整日里晨霜夜露、疲于奔命，既怕听父母的训诫，又担心世人的讥讽，时时刻刻心中慌乱不安，而常常孤枕难眠，这样的日子，倒是其味无穷。

只要不一味沉迷于女色，且让女子们知道自己不是随意苟且之人，就比较得体了。

*

倘若无常野的露水和鸟部山的云烟都永不消散，世上的人，既不会老，也不会死，则纵然有大千世界，又哪里有生的情趣可言呢？世上的万物，原本是变动不居、生死相续的，也唯有如此，才妙不可言。

天生万物，而以人之寿命最长。其他如蜉蝣，早上出生晚上即死；如夏蝉，只活一夏而不知有春与秋。然而抱着从容恬淡的心态过日子，一年都显得漫长无尽；抱着贪婪执着的心态过日子，纵有千年也短暂如一夜之梦。

以过客之身，暂居于世上，等待老丑之年的必然到来，到底所图为何呢？寿则多辱。所以至迟四十岁以前，就应该瞑目谢世，这是天大好事。过了这个年纪，还没有自惭形秽的觉悟，仍然热衷于在众人中抛头露脸，等到了晚年，又溺爱子孙，奢望在有生之年看到他们功成名就，把心思一味地放在世俗的名利上，对人情物趣一无所知，这样的人，想起来就觉得可悲可厌。

*

世上最能迷惑人心的，莫过于色欲。人心实在是愚昧啊！

明知薰香并不能常驻，虽暂时附着于衣物之上，闻着也不禁心旌荡漾，难以自持。

昔年有位久米仙人，能够御空而行。当他飞过家乡时，看见河边洗衣女用双脚踏踩衣物，裸露出雪白的小腿，心中起了色欲，顿时丧失神通之力，从天上掉了下来。不过女人手足的丰满美艳如凝脂，是其天然的本色，能够让人心迷惑，倒在情理之中。

女子美发的修饰，最引人注目。至于她的人品、气质之类，就算隔帘相语，不睹其面，也能从二三语中听出大概来。女人的作为，能让男人心旌荡漾、神魂颠倒。她自己也常为春思所催，不能安眠，以至于不惜自荐于枕席之间，行苟且之事。这都是心怀色欲的缘故。

人心的爱欲，根自本性，其源也远。能令人沾惹六尘的嗜欲虽然不少，舍而弃之，是可以办到的。唯有爱欲，不论老幼贤愚，莫不为其所惑，不能了断。

是以用女人的发丝搓为绳索，能够拴住象腿不令其动；以女人的木屐削而为笛，横吹之声能令秋日之牡鹿集于眼前。

想来这色欲之惑，是最需戒惧的。

*

住所要舒适自在，虽说浮生如逆旅，也不妨有盎然的意趣。

高人雅士幽居之所，月光流入时，自有一股沁人心脾的气象。今天的时尚，追逐的都是些恶俗的风格，一无可取。此间则是古木缭绕、园草杂生，一派天然野趣。篱围与墙垣的造设，要考虑到周边的景致宜人，日常器物的措置，也一定富有古朴之趣，没有一丝做作的痕迹，才可以让人到此则雅兴勃发。

唐土与日本之器物，有极精致的，都是工匠们费尽心思、百般雕琢而成，如果将它们错杂并陈，又将庭前的草木，一律违拗其天性，肆意摧残，看了真让人心生厌恶。这样的地方，又怎么能长住呢？我每见到这样的庭户，就想，搞得这么精致，谁知道它哪天不会顷刻间付诸一炬呢？

大体说来，从住所的布置情况，就能够推断主人的品位气质。

后德大寺大臣[2]在寝殿中拉了绳索，不让野鸢飞到庭院中来。前来造访的西行法师看见了，就问：“就算野鸢飞进来，又有什么关系？这位大人怎么会有这样的心胸呢？”据说他从此以后再不来这里了。绫小路宫居住的小坂殿的梁柱上，也曾经拉了绳，我因此才想起西行法师的事。小坂殿中的人说：“这是因为乌鸦飞进来啄食池中的青蛙，亲王心痛那些青蛙的缘故。”如果是这样的话，就是一件大好事了。后德大寺大臣那么做，或者也有他的原因吧，只是我不知道而已。

*

神无月时节[3]，我路过叫栗栖野的地方，到一个山村去。

沿着长满苔藓的小路走了很久，来到山村的深处，见到一个清寂的佛庵。被落叶所埋的引水筒中，水声泠泠可闻，此外便寂然无声。在于伽棚上，看到散放着摘下的菊花、红叶，才知道此处仍有人居住。

如此简陋的地方，也有人居住，不禁感慨系之。又见前方庭园里，有一株果实沉沉的橘树，只是四周严实地围着一圈篱栅，有些令人扫兴。如果没有这棵树，这里的天然之趣，或者就得以保全了吧？

*

与志趣相投的友人从容闲谈，不论所谈为饶有趣味之事，还是琐屑无聊之事，都能以性情相见，真是一大快乐。不过这样的人很难遇到。如果谈话的对象，意见与自己一味相同，则与自己独坐有何差异？

我辈倾谈之时，有完全倾向于对方意见的，也有意见略有分歧的，要争论起来，说“我的看法不是这样”“因此我的结论是”等等，在闲来无事时，都挺有意思的。有人对世道人心颇为不满，而我的想法则迥然不同，与之论辩一番，也可稍慰寂寥之心。然而毕竟心存隔阂，不能尽兴，和与知己晤对时的感觉不同。

*

在孤灯下独坐翻书，与古人相伴，真是乐何如哉！

书籍当中，《文选》的各卷都是富于情趣的作品，除此之外，如白居易的《白氏文集》、老子《道德经》及庄子《南华真经》等，都是佳作。本国历代诸博士的著述中，也常有高妙之作。

*

人如果立身简素，不慕豪奢，不敛财货，不贪图功名利禄，则可谓人中之上品也。自古以来，很少见到富贵贤人。

唐土有个许由，没有任何身外之物。有人见他用双手捧水喝，就送他一个水瓢。他将水瓢挂在树上，因为风吹得响动，听了心烦，就弃而不用，仍然用手捧水喝。此人心中，何其清澈啊！

还有个名叫孙晨的人，冬天没有被褥，只有蒿草一束，晚上睡在上面，早上便收起来。

唐土的人视之为高士，记入书中传之后世。此等之人若在我国，是无人记述的。

*

万物随四季的更替，各有其不同的情趣。

人都说，秋天的事物最有情趣。这话确乎不错。然而最使人心潮涌动的则莫过于春色。当此之际，啁啾鸟鸣中饱含春意，和煦的阳光下，幼草在墙根悄然萌动，而春意随之渐浓。此时霞光遍洒，众花含苞欲放，如不幸遇上连日风雨，则又仓皇殒落、飘散一地。此后则草木繁滋、天地转绿，其中触动人心、惹人愁思的，就多了。

橘之花，本就令人怀旧了；梅之香，也让人思虑往昔，牵惹旧情；何况还有棣棠之花的艳光明丽，藤花的娇弱无依、我见犹怜。凡此种种，都令人逡巡流连，不能忘怀。

浴佛日与祭祀日的时候，到处装饰着葵花，初发的新叶与嫩枝，透出欣欣的生意，让人有清凉之感。于是有人说，这是人世间的情趣与人的恋世之心最为浓郁的时候，此话不假。五月间，要在门上插菖蒲驱邪，稻田里开始插稻秧，水鸡的鸣叫笃笃如叩门之声，都让人为之心动。六月里，穷人家的墙根开满了白色的夕颜花，到处燃起驱赶蚊虫的烟火，很有味道。六月末的大祓[4]也很有意思。

七夕的祭仪很是优雅。夜晚逐渐转凉，大雁飞来，在天际鸣叫，芦荻之叶开始变黄，早稻收割、晾晒等事务接踵而来。秋日，乃是农事最多的时节。劲风吹拂的晚秋之晨，也有趣。这样的情景，在《源氏物语》《枕草子》等书中都有过描述，然而相同的事物，亲身经历后，不妨自己也来描述一番。心中有所感触而不把它表达出来，不免会腹胀气闷，郁积不堪，所以就信手写下来。不过也没有必要拿给别人看，随手扔掉就是了。

冬日草木枯萎的景色，不下于秋色。早上起来，水边的草地上，散落着红叶，泛着白色的霜气；庭院的流水之上，寒烟缭绕，颇饶意趣。就要到年终了，看着世人忙着备置货物，心中也不免有所感触。

过腊月二十日后，月亮就见不着了，静夜里面没有什么可观赏的，只有一天的澄澈清寒，令人有寂寞之感。佛名会、祭陵使诸事都很有意趣，也让人心怀崇敬。这个时候，朝中政事繁忙，又要为新春到来时的诸事务做好准备，还真不轻松。除夕夜宫中的追傩仪式与紧接着元日早上皇上的四方拜仪式，都非常有意思。

除夕，众人于午夜前手持松枝火把狂呼乱叫，四处叩门，奔跑起来好像双脚都没有着地，哪知道为了什么呢。天亮之后，到处寂静无声，只有旧年的余味在心头萦回，令人有怅然之感。除夕之夜原本是祭奠亡灵的时间，但现在京城已经没有这个风俗了，只在关东地区还有人这么做。这也是个让人产生兴趣的事。

元日的早晨，晴空万里，景色与昨日并无两样，但心情却大不相同，真是奇怪。京城里，通衢大道的两旁，家家户户都摆出了门松，一眼望去，绵延不绝，充满盎然的生机，令人心生喜爱，真是有味道啊。

*

有遁世者说：“我在世上已经了无牵挂，只对于时序节令的推移，还不能忘怀。”此话我深以为然。

*

人心是不待风吹而自落的花。以前的恋人，还记得她情深意切的话，但人已离我而去，形同路人。此种生离之痛，有甚于死别也。故见到染丝，有人会伤心；面对岔路，有人会悲泣。堀川院的百首和歌中有歌云：

旧垣今又来，

彼姝安在哉？

唯见萋萋处，

寂寞堇花开。

这种寂寞的景况，谁说没有呢。

*

死后的情景，是最令人伤心的。

死后中阴期间，遗体停在山寺里，亲戚朋友从各处云集而来，举行法事。一时间这里就显得拥挤嘈杂，让人心绪不宁。时间过得很快，不觉就是最后一天了，大家都意兴阑珊，彼此之间也没什么话说了，于是收拾行李，各自返回来处。回家之后，让人伤心的事恐怕会更多吧。

有人说：“这种事不要随便谈论，多考虑下活着的人吧。”这世道竟然有这样的言论，想起来真让人感到遗憾。

对亡人的追思，并不随岁月的流逝而消减，但古话说“去者日以疏”，其哀伤之情，已不如当初深切，乃至说起往事时，已是言笑如常。

遗骸葬于了无人迹的深山之中，只有在忌日才去洒扫一次。不久，坟上的碑碣便长出青苔，落叶也覆盖了墓地，来访的，只有日暮的风、夜半的月罢了。

怀念者在世时尚且如此，当其逝世之后，子孙只是听说其人，又如何会有由衷的缅怀呢？从此墓地就再无人凭吊，沦为无名荒坟，只有年年春草，令善感者望之动情。呜咽之苍松，不待千年就已伐而为薪，古墓也犁为田地，从此再无形迹可寻，可悲啊！

*

早晨起来，白雪飞舞，真是意趣盎然。又因有事要告诉某人，就去了一封信，信中只字没有提到早晨的飞雪。对方回信说：“对这场雪作何感想，尊驾真是吝于一言。如此俗物，岂能与我言事？君胸中甚少情趣也。”这话着实令人回味。

这位友人如今已经故去，但这件小事，却令我难忘。

*

九月二十日，应某人的邀约，一起去赏月夜游。中途此人一时兴起，要去拜访他的一位友人。于是派人传达入内，我则站在荒芜的庭院中等他。四下里露气繁重，飘浮着薰香的气味，这幽居的住所，景致还不错。

那人不久便从屋里出来，我还在欣赏美景。从暗处望去，见主人送完客后，又把旁边的窗户推开一点，抬头望月。此时如果只是关门进屋，就毫无韵味了。她却不知道外面有人看到她推户赏月，所以此举当出于她平素的修养，绝不是做给人看的。

听说此主人不久即去世了。

*

被名利驱使，一辈子紧张劳累，是何等不明智的事啊！

只顾积累钱财，忽略了修身养性，钱财就只是招累买烦的东西。而“身后堆金拄北斗”，又把烦恼都留给了后人。凡夫俗子们就喜欢看到家中堆金砌银，十分无聊。乘高车、坐大马，穿金戴玉，在明白人看来，不仅讨厌，而且愚不可及。最好还是“捐金于山，沉珠于渊”。一味沉迷于利欲的人，可谓愚蠢之至。

人都想有不朽的盛名能够传诸后世。达官贵人，不一定都是忠贞正直的人。名门之下，也有拙劣之辈，靠出身和运气跻身庙堂，甚至过着穷奢极欲的生活。相反，杰出的圣贤，一生地位卑下、怀才不遇的，也不乏其人。因此，一心渴慕高官显位的人，其愚蠢的程度，仅次于沉醉利欲的人。

还有想以出众的智慧与品行留名后世的人。然而这也是经不起推敲的：一般喜爱名誉的人，都喜欢听到世人的赞扬。只是不管是赞扬你的人，还是诋毁你的人，在世上都待不久，替你传名的人，也要不多久就消逝了。害怕愧对谁，希望得到谁的认可，又有什么意义呢？非议随声誉而起，身后之名毫无用处，执意去追求，实在也是愚蠢之举。

一心想变得智慧或者成为贤者的人，要知道虚伪出自智慧，一身才能让人一生烦恼。不管是经别人传授而掌握知识，还是经自己勤学而掌握知识，都不能说有了真智慧。什么是真智慧呢？即要明白可与不可都一样的道理。至人无智、无德、无功、无名，没有人知道他，也没有人替他传名于后世。这样的人，并不是有意要变得大智若愚，而是已经超越贤与愚、得与失的区分，达到了更高的境界。

追逐世间浮名与虚利的痴愚之人，大略就有以上几类。实质世上万事皆非，没必要在意，也不值得期盼。

*

因幡国有位入道的女儿容貌非凡，来求婚的人极多。但这女子平常只吃栗子，不进米面，其父就对求婚的众人说：“我这女儿，不是寻常之人，不可以与人婚配。”就这样把前来求婚的人都回绝了。

*

五月初五，驱车去贺茂神社观看赛马，到后，发现围观的人极多，车上无法观看，就下了车，想到马场的围栏边去近看。然而那里更为拥挤，根本无法靠近。

这时发现对面一棵楝树上，有个法师蹲踞在树杈中间，手扶着身旁的树枝打瞌睡。每当眼看就要掉下来时，就会惊醒过来，如此反复再三。观众中有人嘲讽说：“真是个大蠢物，在这么高的树枝上还能安心睡觉？”

我听了这话，心中忽然有所触动，便应声道：“我等又怎知死期不近在眼前呢？还不是整天在这儿观看赛马，比那法师，岂不更蠢？”

众人闻言，都回头看着我，点头说：“足下所言极是，此事确实愚蠢。”于是一边说“请进、请进”，一边为我让开一席之地，使我得以近前。

其实这道理人人都知道，只不过在这种场合下，犹如现场说法，让人听了更有当头一棒、恍然大悟之感。人非木石，触景生情是情理之中的事。

*

有志于出家参悟佛乘、圆满功德的人，心中纵有万千难以舍弃、不能心安之事，也要当即放下。有人或者会想：“这件事随手就可以办了”，“那件事也随手就能办妥”，“这些事，为了不给将来留下麻烦，也免得让人嘲笑，还是先处理妥当为好”，“这么多年都忙碌过来了，这点事也不太费时间，还是不急这一时片刻吧”。如果这样，则无可逃避的事反而会越来越多，无穷无尽，最终永无修行之日。

世间略有慧根而有心向佛的人不少，但都耽误在这样的想法中，枉度了一生。遇到火灾要逃命时，哪有说“再等一等”的道理？为了保住性命，总会顾不上羞耻，抛下家中财物就跑。生命的迫促，也像大火一样不会等人。无常相逼，比水火之灾还要紧迫，也更难逃脱。死期一到，家中的老人、幼子，身受的君恩、人情，一切难舍之人事，也都不得不舍弃了。

*

书写上人，即因长诵《法华经》而臻于六根清净之境的法师。

某日，上人在旅舍进房之际，听到用豆荚煮豆时发出的咕嘟咕嘟之声，似是豆子在对豆荚说：“君等是我近亲，为何如此无情地煮我，让我痛苦难当？”豆荚的毕剥爆裂之声，似又在回答说：“这不是我等的本意，我等被烧，也已不堪忍受其苦，实在无能为力啊！求你不要出语抱怨了。”

*

听到一个人的名字，心中就在想象其相貌，待见面之后，才发现与之前的想象完全不同。

听到过去的掌故，则容易联想到今日的某户人家，且也将今日之人物，与昔日之人物相比较。这些都是人之常情，不独我如此。

又有时候，眼前的所闻所见，让自己觉得过去某个时候也同样经历过，虽然记不起确切时间，但肯定确有其事。这种感觉，恐怕也不是我才有的吧？

*

没品位的事有：坐席四周常用之物多；砚上笔多；佛堂内佛像多；庭院草木山石多；家中子孙多；与人见面话多；祈愿文中自述的善行多。

虽多而百看不厌的什物有：文车上的书卷；尘冢上的积尘。

*

我不知道人为何要为无聊所苦。不要用心于外物，最好的办法，是一个人独处。

一旦把心放在世俗，就免不了被它迷惑，失去自主。比如和别人交谈，总想博得别人的好感，就做不到言为心声了。又不免有和人嬉闹的时候，有和人争执的时候，以至于喜怒不定，妄念丛生，得失之心就再难放下。

如此执迷于尘世，陶醉其中，且又好发痴心梦想，全不悟我佛真谛。就算无法彻悟佛理，只要能了断俗缘，让此身清净，澄清俗务，让此心安宁，也还可以暂得此生之乐。生活、人事、技艺、学问诸般，都得放下，《摩诃止观》如是说。

*

有世上盛传的事，非当事之人，却知之甚详，一边与人说，一边向人打听，好不奇怪。偏远地区的和尚们尤其有此嗜好，尽皆热衷于打听俗事，好像是自己的事一样，然后滔滔不绝地说与他人听，真不知其何以知道得如此详尽！

*

对俗世盛传的奇闻异事津津乐道，实在是无聊。也有种人，当事情已流传很久了，他还懵然不知，是为清雅之人也。彼此熟稔的人之间经常谈论的话题、物事，只消片言只语，便能相互会意。

初来乍到者，则不知其所云，遂有身在局外之窘。此种情况，未免于人情世故有所不合，而品流低下的人必犯此病。

*

有人说：“书籍墨宝用薄绢装裱，容易损坏，真是没有办法。”顿阿听了说：“薄绢装裱的东西，两端有所破损，或其螺钿卷轴上的贝壳有所脱落，都是可喜的事。”真是超人一等的见识。又有人说，一部草子中的各册装帧不统一，看着令人极不舒服。弘融僧都却说：“把什么都弄得整齐划一，是无聊人才会做的事。就要参差残缺才好。”这话也品之有味。

把什么都弄得规整如一，确实令人难以忍受。没有完成的东西，保持其没有完成的样子，不仅别具趣味，还有意犹未尽之妙。又有人说：“建造皇宫时必定会留下若干未曾完成的地方。”

先贤所著的内外典籍中，也有不少残章断文。

*

大纳言法印有一童仆，名叫乙鹤丸，常与某贵人相往来。

有天，乙鹤丸从那贵人处回来，法印问：“到哪里去了？”童仆答：“去某贵人家了。”“他是俗家人还是出家人？”

童仆两袖拢在胸前期期艾艾地说：“不……不太清楚，没见到他的头顶。”

不过，我倒想知道——为什么他不提议看看贵人身体的其他部分呢？[5]

*

关于赤舌日的诸种说法，阴阳道未曾提及。古人于此并不忌讳，近来有人说起，才讲究起来。民间的说法是：此日百事不顺。做事都不能圆满，到手之物也会放脱，有什么谋划都要落空。如此等等都是愚昧无知的迷信。在吉日里办的事，其顺利的和不顺利的，数量其实大致相当。

原因在于，世间本是变化无常的所在，各种可能都存在。人一旦开始做某事，就对结果满心期待。但人心是变幻不定的，事物的结果也因而不能确定，随时都在随人心而变化。这个道理，常人都不明白。古人云，吉日为恶必凶，凶日行善必吉，吉凶皆由人定，而非由日期定。

*

有人初学射箭，就一次拿上两支箭瞄准箭靶。

师父说：“初学者不要一次拿两支箭。想到后面还有一箭的机会，对第一箭，就不会用全心。射箭时心中不能患得患失，要专注于这一箭，而且要志在必得。”师父当前，就算只发两箭，也不能忽略其中之一。这中间的懈怠之心，自己可能并未意识到，但师父却能洞察。同样的道理，可以用在其他事情上。

学道之人，晚上惦记着明早的功课，早晨又惦记着当晚的功课，看起来是日催一日，勤奋精进，但其间有刹那的懈怠之心，自己恐怕是没有察觉的吧？为何只专注于当前的一念一世，就这么难呢？

*

有人在闲聊中说：“有个买牛的人，与卖牛的人说好明日付钱后就把牛牵走，不料当晚牛就死了。这样的事，对买者有利，对卖者则是损失。”

旁边有人听了说：“牛主人确实有损失，但未必没有大利。具体说来，生者是料想不到死期逼近的，牛如此，人也如此。牛的死，是意料之外的事；牛主人的生死，恐怕一样难料，但与牛相比，已多得一日之生。一日的生命，值过万金，一头牛的价钱与之相比，简直轻如鸿毛。所以损失一钱而得到万金，谈不上什么损失吧？”

众人听了都嘲笑他说：“这道理怕不仅适用于牛主人吧！”

那人又说：“怕死的话，就该爱惜生命，故理当日日享受生之愉悦。但愚驽之人忘了生命本身的愉悦，不辞劳苦地追逐身外之乐；忘了生命本身即财宝，而不顾生死地贪求身外之财，从不满足。既不知生的乐趣，又害怕死的到来，这两种情况是不会并存的。人活得不快乐，恰恰是因为不怕死；人不是不怕死，而是忘记了死就是眼前的事。只有超越了死生，才算得参透真谛。”

听了这段宏论，众人益发嘲笑他了。

*

有个女子，幽居在荒僻无人的地方，也不知是在逃避什么。某傍晚时分，月色朦胧之际，一名男子悄然来访，惹得犬儿汪汪地叫起来，侍女出门探视，问：“是何方的贵客呢？”乃把他引入院中。

见到一派凄凉景象，他不由得心中黯然，寻思道：此地岂宜佳人久居？随后在屋前粗陋的木板上立候了片刻，听得里面一个恬静稚细的声音传来：“请进吧！”才拉开已不灵便的门走进去。

室内的情形，却不似外面那么荒凉，别有一番幽雅景致。炉火摇曳，微光影绰，四壁之物皆因之熠熠生辉；暗盈的薰香，却不是为来客新燃起的，闻着倍觉亲切。

又听女主人说：“烦请将门关好，怕是要下雨了。车可停于门下，诸随从的住宿也请妥善安排。”随从皆嗡嗡窃语道：“到。”

于是相对絮语，把近况一一说与她听。不知不觉间，就听到了第一声鸡鸣，但意兴仍然浓厚，继续倾心交谈，于过去、未来莫不畅所欲言。不久，又听到雄鸡高唱，想必天亮了吧？不过此地是僻静之所，不必如别处需趁暗夜匆匆离去。所以等亮光已从门隙间透入时，才从容起身辞别。

出来时已是四月初夏的曙色，树梢与庭草都深翠欲滴，景色绝美。登车之后，一夜的深情相晤，还萦回于心，恋恋不舍中，回首门前之大桂树，一直到车儿渐行渐远，再看不到为止。

*

一位攀树的名手叫某人到树的高处去砍伐树枝，当攀树的人爬到很高的地方时，他在下面一言不发；当攀树的人下到如屋檐高的地方时，他才说：“小心点，别掉下来了。”

我好奇地问他：“已到此处，一跃而下都无妨，为何还提醒他呢？”

他回答说：“恰好要在此处提醒呢。人到了高处，会感觉头晕目眩，看着又高又细的树条，自己都会警惕起来，所以不需要提醒。但失误多出现在感觉轻松的地方，所以必须提醒他。”

虽然是身份卑微之人，说出的道理，却颇合乎圣人的训诫。

蹴鞠也是同样的道理，把高难度的动作对付了，如果掉以轻心，球则必然掉在地上。

*

不宜结交为友的人有：一、地位尊贵的人；二、年纪太轻的人；三、健壮无病的人；四、嗜酒的人；五、勇武暴躁的人；六、爱说谎的人；七、贪欲太盛的人。

可结为良友的人有：一、乐善好施的人；二、医师；三、有慧根灵性的人。

*

人常饲养的家畜是马与牛，套上枷辕后，终日奴役，实在可叹。然而马与牛又是日常不可或缺的东西，莫奈何也。狗能够守夜防盗，比人还能干，也是不可或缺的，故每家都养，但不必搜求更多来喂养。

其余各种鸟兽就没有什么实际用途了。把走兽带回家中，锁上铁链，把飞鸟剪掉羽毛，放进鸟笼，让它们那思恋云霄、怀想山野的愁苦永无尽头，如果换作人，恐怕也难忍受吧？所以有心之人，怎能以此为乐呢？残害生灵来娱乐自己的人，其心与桀纣何异？

王子猷爱鸟，称林中嬉戏的鸟儿为逍遥之友。他不会把鸟儿捉回家让它痛苦的。《尚书》云：“珍禽奇兽不育于国。”

*

雅房大纳言才学俱佳，品行高卓，皇上准备升任他为大将军，但身边的近臣却说：“最近看到些见不得人的事。”

皇上问：“什么事呢？”回答说：“我从墙壁的缝隙间，看见雅房卿割下活犬的脚来喂鹰。”

皇上听了心中大为厌恶，对雅房的印象顿时改变，升迁之事也就搁置了。

其实犬足饲鹰等等，全属乌有之事。遭人诽谤，固然不幸，但君王听说有这种事，心生憎恶之情，其仁爱之心也甚为感人。

总而言之，以杀戮、折磨动物为乐的人，就像以自相残杀为乐的牲畜。上自鸟兽，下至昆虫，如果细心观察它们的行为的话，就看得出它们也爱护幼子、关怀亲人，有夫有妻，会嫉妒、会发火，有七情六欲，也爱惜生命，甚至比人还执迷痴愚。折磨它们的身体、夺去它们的生命，实在令人痛心。对世间一切众生不怀慈悲之心者，不能视之为人。

*

颜回的志向是不将自己的意志强加于人。大体说来，残虐生灵之事不可为，贱民的意志，也不能剥夺。

有人喜欢用谎话来哄骗、恫吓和戏谑幼童，这些谎话，在成人看来，也许并不觉得有什么，但对幼童的心灵，则有深刻的影响。他们会感到恐惧、羞耻、悲痛，好像亲身经历了那样的事一样。用别人的痛苦来让自己开心的人，是没有慈悲之心的人。

成人的喜怒哀乐都是心中的虚妄，但人都当作实有之相来在意。

伤害心灵，比伤害身体更为严重。病痛多半来自心中，少有来自外界。服药发汗，有时会没有效果；而心中羞愧恐惧时，则必定要出汗。由此可见心的作用，书凌云之额而忽然白头的典故，即是先例。

*

盛开的樱花和明朗的月色，世人所能观赏的，难道仅此二者？不论对阴雨而怀明月，抑或垂帘幽居不问春归何处，都是极有情趣的事。而如含苞待放的树梢、落花遍地的庭院等等，可供观赏之处还多着呢。和歌之小序中有“本要看花而花已零落”或“无奈没能前去赏花”的话，其难道不比“赏着了花”之类更有味吗？花殒月沉，皆为之惋惜嗟叹，这是人之常情，但只有俗不可耐的人才说得出这样的话：“这儿的花没了，那儿的花也没了，没什么看头了！”

世上的事，最令人回味的，是始和终这两端。男女恋爱，也是如此。恋爱之真味，不只在于日日相会长相厮守。有时要因暂难相会而忧虑重重，有时要悲叹缘分之变幻莫测，有时独自辗转到天明，有时遥寄相思于远地，有时则远避他乡而追怀往日，凡此种种，都体验过了，才敢说明白了恋爱的真谛。

发皎洁之光而令人一望千里的满月，不如期盼了一夜，到天快亮时才姗姗而来的月有意味。此时的月，略带青苍之色，或在远山之杉树梢间隐现，或为天上之雨云遮断，都极其有味。一丛丛的椎木与白橡树，叶面如洗，辉映在月光下，望之沁人心脾。此情此景，岂能无会心者共赏？不禁怀想起京中的诸友来。

大体说来，可观赏者，岂只限于眼前所见之月与花？春日闭门家中，或月夜静处室内时，于心中想象其风致，也别有兴味。

品流高尚的人物虽好物而不溺于物，虽兴致颇高也能淡然处之。只有那些不解风雅的村夫俗子，才于游赏时力求尽兴。赏花时拥挤在花下，或凑近盯着花看，要饮酒，要作连歌，末了手持折下的花枝，欢欢喜喜地打道回府；路过泉水时，一定要把手足都泡进去；遇到下雪时，一定要在雪地上踩踏，留下自己的足印。总之凡有景致处，决不悠然旁观，一定要去耍弄一番才甘心。

此辈观看贺茂祭的情形，也是妙不可言。“祭神的行列要有一阵才过来呢，这会儿待在看台上有什么意思？”说罢就拥入看台后的人家里，饮酒、大嚼，下围棋、双六。待到外面放风之人喊道“行列过来了！”才又一拥而出，你推我搡地挤上看台，连看台上的布帘也似要被其挤落了。在观看时，此辈绝不错过任何细节，且都要评头论足一番。当一个行列过去后，就说：“咱回去等下一轮吧。”又钻回台后的屋子去戏耍了。此辈人眼中，只认实在之物。

比较起来，京都人士就要文雅得多。彼等做闭目养神状，似乎并不热衷于观看。职位较低的年轻侍从们紧随其主，立于身后，也没有谁探身引颈做粗俗状。总之这群人中，没有一个表现出一定要看个清楚才甘心的样子。

现场到处悬挂着葵叶，秀雅可人，而驾车前来者，已在天色未明之际悄然云集于此，车中人不时左右探望，看看有无旧识，打打招呼。众车错杂相陈，有的妙趣横生，有的光彩夺目，颇富观赏趣味，在等待时，细加观玩，倒颇能解闷。然而到了日暮时分，一排排牛车与拥挤不堪的人群便突然不知去向，变得稀疏零落，看台上的布帘与坐垫也纷纷被取走了，眼前呈现一片凄凉景象，让人联想到世道的盛衰，不禁感慨有加。把大路上的情景，这样看下来，才可以说观了贺茂祭。

聚集于看台之上的众人中，相识的人不少，可知世上的人，其实并不太多。假设我须等到众人死后才最后死去，实在也等不了太久。在一个大容器中盛满水，在它的底部凿开一个小孔，水于是要往下流。这孔虽然细小，但如果长流不止，也不需要太久，水就会流尽。京都的人虽多，但每日都有人死去，且不止一二人。鸟部野、舟冈及众多无名野山上，只见过送葬之人众多的时候，没见过无人前去送葬的时候。因此卖棺材者的棺材做好不久就能卖出，不论老幼强弱，皆死期难料，侥幸能活到今天，实在是不可思议的奇妙之事。所以人生在世，来日方长的想法，是片刻都不能有的。

可尝试将双六的棋子排作“继子立”的形状，当其首尾成列之后，起初不知从何处下手取子。等数下数来，则依数取出一子；其他诸子，似乎还安然无事；然而再数、再取，最终会一子不剩。人死也是如此：死是必然的，所不同者先后而已。战士在阵前，知道死亡就在眼前，所以能身家两忘，不顾一切。遁世之人长住茅庵，静享林泉之趣，如果自以为与战士阵前迥乎不同，那就太不明智了。深山里虽然静僻，难道“无常”这个敌人就不会挟常胜之势来攻打你？此时与死面对，与战士在战场上的情形，并无不同。

*

留下身后之财，是智者不为的事。积蓄不好的东西没有意义，而好东西再舍不得也终不能带走。一生积蓄太多，反而是件苦事。口称“我一定要得到它”，而争夺人死后遗物的行径，尤其丑恶。凡想于身后留给某人的东西，最好在世的时候就给他。

人除了日常必需品外，别的东西就不用再有了。

*

看起来毫无情趣的人，只言片语中，偶尔也有可取之处。

有个乡村武士，凶神恶煞的样子，有次问旁边的人：“你有子女吗？”那人回答说：“一个也没有。”

武士就说：“没有子女的人是不懂人间真情的。如此说来，你真是个冷酷无情的人，可怕呀！”

这可谓至理名言。不懂恩爱的人，心中就没有慈悲之心。不懂得孝养的人，有了子女后，才会明白父母之心。

舍世出家的人，孑然一身，与万事不相关联，常常鄙视羁绊尘世、谄人媚上、欲望深重的人，其实也不应当。若换了自己，为了至爱的亲人与妻儿，就算不顾廉耻地沦为盗贼，也必然会愿意的。缉拿盗贼，因他所犯的恶行而治他的罪，不如把国家治理好，让世人免于饥寒。人无恒产，则无恒心，人穷则为盗，如果国家治理不善，人民会受饥寒之苦，犯罪之人也难以绝迹。把人置于苦难之中，使其犯法，又绳之以法，真是可悲的做法。

然而如何才能普惠众生呢？上能摒弃奢靡，下能抚民劝农，则天下必得其利。倘有人在衣食能保的情况下，还要为非作恶，那就是真正的盗贼了。

*

御随身秦重躬在谈到北面武士下野入道信愿时，说：“这人是落马之相，当慎之又慎！”但信愿一向不以此为然，最后果然落马而亡。秦重躬真是精于此道的人，一句话，就让人视之为神人。

后来有人请教他：“什么叫作落马之相呢？”他回答说：“此人的臀部状似桃核，又好骑沛艾之马，故有落马之相。看来我这话，是说中了。”

*

没什么要紧的事，到别人家里去盘桓，是不好的。最好有事才去，事了之后就回来。在别人家中待得太久，也特别让人讨厌。

坐在一起后，话必定就多，令人身体疲惫，心中烦乱，既耽误做事，又浪费时间，于人于己都无益处。对客人感厌烦时，也不宜说话烦躁。如果不喜欢来客久坐，就明白地告诉他也无妨。

至于情趣相投，愿意畅谈的人，如果正好无事可忙，就可以说：“请不妨安坐，今日可以做一长谈。”阮籍的青眼、白眼，恐怕人人都有吧。

如果没什么事，过来坐坐，悠然闲谈一阵，然后回去，也不错。或者修书一封，说“久未奉教”云云，也颇为愉快。

*

少年时血气旺盛，心易动，多情欲，此时恰如落地而走的珍珠，容易触物而碎，常有性命之危。年少的时候，总会做一些耽误自己的事：或者贪好美艳之物而不惜钱财；或者心血来潮舍红尘而着僧衣；或者逞强斗狠，既耻于不如人，又羡慕别人比自己强，喜好多变，每日不同；或者沉溺女色，感情用事，讲究仗义而误了大事；或者竟然效仿他人而不惜一死，从不知爱惜生命以求长寿；又或者因好色之名而饱受物议。

老年人精神衰退，嗜欲清淡，对于外物，能够无动于衷，心中自然平静，不会做无益之事，要爱惜身体，既不自烦，也不扰人。年老后，智慧胜过年轻时，就好比年轻时容貌风采胜过老年。

*

世上有许多不可思议的事。

但凡有事，一定要喝酒，且喜欢强行劝酒，真不知道理何在。被劝酒的人，端着酒杯，皱着眉头，一脸为难之色，直想趁人不备扔下酒杯逃走。然而被发现后，则牵裳捉臂地被留在座上，强行灌饮。结果本来稳重端庄的人，变得疯疯癫癫，一味丢人现眼；本来正常的人，变成病重的人，醉得分不清前后左右，倒头便睡。这样的事如果发生在喜庆的场合，更是令人咂舌。大醉的次日醒来，头痛欲裂，粒米难进，躺在床上痛苦呻吟，昨日的事仿佛发生在前世，一点也记不得了。公私大事都被耽误，造成诸多不便。让人落到这地步的人，既不仁，也无礼；而遭此不幸的人，对强行灌酒的人，又岂能不心生怨恨？假如这样的陋习，只在外国有，而我国没有，我们听起来，一定会觉得匪夷所思吧。

酒席上的众生相，若只是旁观，也会觉得不堪入目：体面而有教养的人，在酒席上却放肆笑骂，说起话来喋喋不休，乌帽歪着，上衣敞着，下装高卷，双腿裸裎，全然不顾体统，与平时的举止大相径庭；女人则撩起头发，不知羞耻地媚笑撒娇，掰开那端着酒的粗人的嘴巴，往里面塞进菜肴，自己也大嚼不已，真是丑态难当；一众人尽力吼叫着，自歌自舞，甚至叫来年长的法师，光着污黑的臂膀，一副不堪入目的恶俗样，连兴致勃勃的旁观者都觉得再也看不下去。

有人喝醉了喜欢夸夸其谈，吹嘘自己，还强迫身边的人洗耳恭听；有人喝醉了就哭泣；贱人们则相互谩骂，大打出手，让人既惊又怕。接下来就开始为非作歹，强取别人之物，或摔倒在屋檐下，或自马及车上坠落受伤。无车可乘的人，就跌跌撞撞地走在大路上，到土墙下或别人门前去行那方便之事。还有身着袈裟的年长法师，扶着小童的肩，满口胡言、步履蹒跚，看着让人心生怜悯。

如此等等，倘有益于今生来世，倒也无话可说；但实际而言，酒之于今生，是令人犯错误、损财货、生疾病之物。虽然号称“百药之长”，但百病皆因酒而生；虽然号称可以解忧，但醉后反易让人伤心而泣。于来世而言，酒让人丧失心智，如被火烧去善根，恶胆顿生，破除诸戒，最终必堕入地狱。佛祖云：“若以己手持酒器与人饮者，五百世轮回中无手。”

然而酒虽有如上可厌处，也有其可爱而难舍时。月之夜、雪之朝、花之下，与人悠然闲谈，举杯小饮，可以助清兴，发雅趣；闲暇之日，友人意外来访，则端出酒食，小加款待，心情也甚为愉快。在高贵之人家里，酒食出于庖厨，经美人之手端来席上，感觉也颇不错。

隆冬之日，斗室之中，于火上小煮点什么，与亲密知己举杯豪饮，是极有味的事。在旅舍或山野间，口中说着“何不上酒肴”，而径直在草地上坐下饮用，也有意趣。不善饮者，为人所强劝，则少许饮下一点，是不错的事。此时座中有身份的人端起酒杯自言自语：“那么我就再来一杯如何？反正酒已不多了。”听着令人高兴。若自己酒量甚豪，席上又有极愿结识的人在，则与之杯盏相亲，也是十分可喜的事。

善饮的人，其实也天真可爱，颇为有趣。在别人家中醉卧不起，早上，主人家拉开纸窗时，他顿时手脚慌乱，睡眼惺忪，细髻曝露，都来不及穿衣，一把抱在手上就狼狈而逃。看着他穿着短衣短裤的背影和长满毛发的瘦腿，实在是有趣，还真像个醉汉的模样。

*

男子不应有妻。

我每听人说“我一向独居”，就觉得其人不俗；听说其为某人女婿或要带回某女同住，就极其反感。我猜想，那人其实没什么头脑，竟把平常女子认作美人，一定要迎娶回家。如果女子确实是美人，则那人必定全心全意地侍奉着，就像我侍奉佛祖一样。我这想法大体是没有错的。主持家政的女人尤其让人讨厌，生儿育女，百般宠爱，也是毫无意义的事。男人死后，女人削发为尼，其年老之丑状，就算男人死了，也很难让人接受。

不管是何种女人，与她相处久了，也会心生厌恶。从女方看来，不谈婚娶，就有悬空而无着落之感。但不同住而经常往来的男女，反而可能成为感情持久、至死不渝的伴侣。不期然而来，留宿一夜，可于双方都保有新鲜之感。

*

所谓入夜则无物可观的说法，是不足取的。

万物的光华、装饰与色彩，在夜晚看来更觉不同凡响。白天的装束可以简淡朴素一点，到了晚上，则以绚丽华美为佳。灯光之下，人的容颜神采看上去会美上加美。别人的谈话，在暗处听来，也更觉优雅而有味。各种香味与音乐，都在夜晚更加动人。

平时有夜深来访之人，觉得别有一番清新韵致，颇为有味。青年人无时不在打量着他人的装束容貌，特别在可以放任的场合，不分便装与盛装，都是用心打扮了的。美男子在日暮时分才开始梳头，女子也是在夜色渐深的时候才离开座位，拿出镜子来化妆。这些都很有味道。

*

德大寺右大臣大人任检非违使的时候，有一日在中门使厅讨论官厅公事，官人章兼牛车上的牛走脱了，来到使厅，径直走上大理所坐的滨床，卧床反刍。这是少有的怪事，众人都说应该把牛牵到阴阳师那里断一断吉凶。

大理之父相国说：“牛又不晓得人事，既然有脚，哪里不能去？因为这点意外就要没收小吏的牛，真是岂有此理！”于是将牛归还其主人，更换掉卧席，此后并无不吉利之事发生。

这正是“见怪不怪，其怪自败”。

*

世事无常，万物都不足以长久倚赖。执迷不悟的人深信此生有物可恃，必争为己有，于是心生怨怒之情。

实则权势不可倚赖，因为强者先亡；财富不可倚赖，因为可以轻易散尽；才学不可倚赖，因为孔子也有怀才不遇的时候；德行不可倚赖，因为颜回也是不幸之人；君王的宠幸不可倚赖，因为说不准何时会有杀身之祸；奴仆的恭顺不可倚赖，因为难免有叛逃的事发生；人的志向不可倚赖，因为志向总有变化的时候；说好的事，不可倚赖，因为守信的人太少。

既然自己与他人都不可靠，那么时运来时固然可喜，时运背时也不要抱怨。左右广大才无障碍，前后远阔方能通畅。若置身于逼仄处，则容易有冲突毁损；若用心于狭隘处，则不能舒坦通泰；拂逆他人而与之相争，则容易伤及身体。若能心宽而性柔，才可以毫发无损。

人为天地灵长，天地无限，人之心性也一样。人心如能广大无垠，则不为喜怒所羁绊，也不为外物所烦扰。

*

丹波有个地方叫出云，有个大神社迁移来此，建筑极为雄伟。此地是名为志太的人的任职之地，到了秋天，这个志太就邀请圣海上人等一众人，说：“敬请光临出云之神社，将以萩饼款待诸君。”于是带着众人来到了神社。众人于社中各处参拜，深为震服，无不肃然起敬。

神社前有一狮子和一狛犬之石像，二者相背而立。上人看了极为感动，含着眼泪说：“善哉善哉，这狮犬的立向，实为罕见，必有其深意在，诸君若不留意此稀有之景，实在可惜！”

众人也觉得奇怪，都说：“确实和别的地方不同，回去后一定要把这地方的胜景告诉都中人士。”

上人还想追究它的来由，就叫来一位看着体体面面、博学多闻的神官，问道：“贵社的狮子如此安放，是有什么来由的吧？愿闻其详。”

神官回答说：“这实在是顽童所为，真是岂有此理！”于是上前将狮子与狛犬的方向调回到正面相对的原状。

上人的感动之泪，算是白流了。

*

男女之于暗夜私会，既怕人见到，又怕人听到，但心中恋情之强烈，不见不行。此种情形于日后必然永难忘怀。如是那种经父母兄弟同意了的明媒正娶，就让人扫兴得很了。

有迫于生计的女子，因贪慕钱财，就托人对根本不相配的老法师或乡巴佬说：“愿奉君之箕帚。”媒人也两头说好话，尽力撮合，于是把这素不相识的女子迎娶回来。这真是难以接受的事。这样的夫妇之间，有什么话可说呢？夫妇之间，能够一起回忆当年恋爱如何辛苦，如何担惊受怕地只求一见的情形，那才叫情深意永呢。

凡是由他人撮合的夫妇，不免会厌恶对方，常常闹得不愉快。若本是品貌俱无的老朽，把年轻貌美的女子娶回来，想着这么个美女竟下嫁我这副德行的人，心中恐怕也会不太自在吧？品貌都不如人，相比之下，必定会自惭形秽，这样过着真没什么意思。

梅香暗吐、月色朦胧之夜，伫立在她身旁；或任由宅垣旁的草露沾湿了衣裳，和她一起踏着晓月回去——没有这些可供追忆的往事，还不如不要谈情说爱。

*

十五的满月瞬间即亏，不留心观察的人是看不到月在一夜中的变化的。

人在重病之时，病况也是时刻都在变化，不觉就濒于死亡。

当病情还不至于致命，就习惯性地想着存世之日还长久，还可以完成若干心愿，然后再潜心修佛；当病情加重，快迈进鬼门关时，自己还一事无成，才后悔一向的懈怠，想着这次若能痊愈，保住一命，一定要夜以继日、勇猛精进，完成这件事、那件事；虽然发了这些誓，但病情突然恶化，神志不清，行为失控，最终还是过世了。世上的人，以这样的人居多。所以最紧要而需要牢记的事是：

人都想完成了各种心愿后，再把余下的时间用以事佛，但人的心愿是无穷无尽的。在变幻莫测的一生中，能做成什么事呢？一切愿望都是妄想。愿望的产生，源于心的迷乱，所以一桩也不要去做了。要立即放下一切，一心向佛，心中才坦然无碍；只有一无所为，才能保全身心的宁静。

*

我八岁的时候曾问家父：“什么是佛？”

家父回答：“佛是人所化。”

我又问：“人怎么才能化为佛呢？”

家父又回答说：“遵从佛的教诲就可以成佛。”

我又问：“教人的佛，又是谁教的呢？”

家父又回答说：“是他之前的佛教的。”

我又问：“那么第一个教人成佛的佛是什么样的呢？”

家父大笑着说：“要不是从天上掉下来的，就是从地里冒出来的，谁知道呢！”

后来家父在与众人笑谈时说：“追问到这地步，就实在无法回答了。”

[1] 摄政是指在天皇年幼时，帮助处理国政的大臣官职，关白则是在天皇成年后，帮助处理国政的大臣官职。此处意指一人担任了两种职务，也可简称为“摄关”。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明的之外，均为编者注。）

[2] 此处指的应是后德大寺左大臣藤原实定。他的祖父因修建德大寺而被称为“德大寺左大臣”。

[3] 日本民间将一年划分为十二个月，相当于我们的农历节气，神无月对应的是农历十月。

[4] 大袚即大袚式，每年日本各大神社都会举行两次的祭祀仪式。一次在夏越晦日，另一次在大晦日（过年之袚）。夏越大袚旨在将上半年积累的晦气和过错清除，平安的迎来下半年，也顺利度过容易生病的夏季。

[5] 此处微妙暗示了男色关系。日本自古以来男色文化兴盛，尤以稚子受人欢迎。——译者注

A Cup of Sake Beneath the Cherry Trees

What strange folly, to beguile the tedious hours like this all day before my ink stone, jotting down at random the idle thoughts that cross my mind . . .

*

To be born into this world of ours, it seems, brings with it so much to long for.

The rank of emperor is, of course, unspeakably exalted; even his remotest descendants fill one with awe, having sprung from no mere human seed.

Needless to say, the great ruler, and even the lesser nobles who are granted attendant guards to serve them, are also thoroughly magnificent. Their children and grandchildren too are still impressive, even if they have come down in the world. As for those of lesser degree, although they may make good according to their rank, and put on airs and consider themselves special, they are really quite pathetic.

No one could be less enviable than a monk. Sei Shōnagon wrote that people treat them like unfeeling lumps of wood, and this is perfectly true. And there is nothing impressive about the way those with power will throw their weight around. As the holy man Sōga, I think, remarked, fame and fortune are an affliction for a monk, and violate the Buddha’s teachings.

There is much to admire, though, in a dedicated recluse.

It is most important to present well, in both appearance and bearing. One never tires of spending time with someone whose speech is attractive and pleasing to the ear, and who does not talk overmuch. There is nothing worse than when someone you thought impressive reveals himself as lacking in sensibility. Status and personal appearance are things one is born with, after all, but surely the inner man can always be improved with effort. It is a great shame to see a fine upstanding fellow fall in with low and ugly types who easily run rings round him, and all for want of cultivation and learning.

A man should learn the orthodox literature, write poetry in Chinese as well as Japanese, and study music, and should ideally also be a model to others in his familiarity with ceremonial court customs and precedents. He should write a smooth, fair hand, carry the rhythm well when songs are sung at banquets, and when offered sake, make a show of declining it but nevertheless be able to drink.

*

No matter how splendid in every way, there is something dreadfully lacking in a man who does not pursue the art of love. He is, to coin the old phrase, like a beautiful wine cup that lacks a base.

The elegant thing is for a lover to wander aimlessly hither and yon, drenched with the frosts or dews of night, tormented by fears of his parents’ reproaches and the censure of the world, the heart beset with uncertainties, yet for all that sleeping often alone, though always fitfully.

On the other hand, he shouldn’t lose himself to love too thoroughly, or gain the reputation of being putty in women’s hands.

*

If our life did not fade and vanish like the dews of Adashino’s graves or the drifting smoke from Toribe’s burning grounds, but lingered on for ever, how little the world would move us. It is the ephemeral nature of things that makes them wonderful.

Among all living creatures, it is man that lives longest. The brief dayfly dies before evening; summer’s cicada knows neither spring nor autumn. What a glorious luxury it is to taste life to the full for even a single year. If you constantly regret life’s passing, even a thousand long years will seem but the dream of a night.

Why cling to a life which cannot last for ever, only to arrive at ugly old age? The longer you live, the greater your share of shame. It is most seemly to die before forty at the latest. Once past this age, people develop an urge to mix with others without the least shame at their own unsightliness; they spend their dwindling years fussing adoringly over their children and grandchildren, hoping to live long enough to see them make good in the world. Their greed for the things of this world grows ever deeper, till they lose all ability to be moved by life’s pathos, and become really quite disgraceful.

*

Nothing so distracts the human heart as sexual desire. How foolish men’s hearts are!

Aroma, for instance, is a mere transient thing, yet a whiff of delightful incense from a woman’s robes will always excite a man, though he knows perfectly well that it is just a passing effect of robe- smoking.

The wizard priest of Kume is said to have lost his supernatural powers when he spied the white legs of a woman as she squatted washing clothes. I can quite believe it – after all, the beautiful, plump, glowing flesh of a woman’s arm or leg is quite a different matter from some artificial allurement.

*

Beautiful hair on a woman will draw a man’s gaze – but we can judge what manner of person she is and the nature of her sensibility even by simply hearing her speak from behind a screen. A mere unintended glimpse of a woman can distract a man’s heart; and if a woman sleeps fitfully, and is prepared to endure impossible difficulties heedless of her own well- being, it is all because her mind is on love.

Yes indeed, the ways of love lie deep in us. Many are the allurements of our senses, yet we can distance ourselves from them all. But among them this one alone seems without exception to plague us all, young and old, wise and foolish.

So it is that we have those tales of how a woman’s hair can snare and hold even an elephant, or how the rutting stag of autumn will always be drawn by the sound of a flute made from the wood of a woman’s shoe.

We must discipline ourselves to be constantly prudent and vigilant lest we fall into this trap.

*

Though a home is of course merely a transient habitation, a place that is set up in beautiful taste to suit its owner is a delightful thing.

Even the moonlight is so much the more moving when it shines into a house where a refined person dwells in tranquil elegance. There is nothing fashionable or showy about the place, it is true, yet the grove of trees is redolent of age, the plants in the carefully untended garden carry a hint of delicate feelings, while the veranda and openweave fence are tastefully done, and inside the house the casually disposed things have a tranquil, old- fashioned air. It is all most refined.

How ugly and depressing to see a house that has employed a bevy of craftsmen to work everything up to a fine finish, where all the household items set out for proud display are rare and precious foreign or Japanese objects, and where even the plants in the garden are clipped and contorted rather than left to grow as they will. How could anyone live for long in such a place? The merest glimpse will provoke the thought that all this could go up in smoke in an instant.

Yes, on the whole you can tell a great deal about the owner from his home.

The Later Tokudaiji Minister once had rope strung over the roof of the main house to stop the kites from roosting on it. ‘What could be wrong with having kites on your roof? This shows what manner of man he is!’ exclaimed the poet- monk Saigyō, and it is said he never called there again. I was reminded of this story when I noticed once that Prince Ayanokōji had laid rope over his Kosaka residence. Someone told me, however, that it was because he pitied the frogs in his pond when he observed how crows gathered on the roof to catch them. I was most impressed. Perhaps the Tokudaiji Minister too might have had some such reason for acting as he did?

*

One day in the tenth month, I went to call on someone in a remote mountain village beyond Kurusuno.

Making my way along the mossy path, I came at length to the lonely hut where he lived. There was not a sound except for the soft drip of water from a bamboo pipe buried deep in fallen leaves. The vase on the altar shelf with its haphazard assortment of chrysanthemums and sprigs of autumn leaves bespoke someone’s presence.

Moved, I said to myself, ‘One could live like this’ – but my mood was then somewhat spoiled by noticing at the far end of the garden a large mandarin tree, branches bowed with fruit, that was firmly protected by a stout fence. If only that tree weren’t there! I thought.

*

What happiness to sit in intimate conversation with someone of like mind, warmed by candid discussion of the amusing and fleeting ways of this world . . . but such a friend is hard to find, and instead you sit there doing your best to fit in with whatever the other is saying, feeling deeply alone.

There is some pleasure to be had from agreeing with the other in general talk that interests you both, but it’s better if he takes a slightly different position from yours.‘No, I can’t agree with that,’ you’ll say to each other combatively, and you’ll fall into arguing the matter out. This sort of lively discussion is a pleasant way to pass the idle hours, but in fact most people tend to grumble about things different from oneself, and though you can put up with the usual boring platitudes, such men are far indeed from the true friend after your own heart, and leave you feeling quite forlorn.

*

It is a most wonderful comfort to sit alone beneath a lamp, book spread before you, and commune with someone from the past whom you have never met.

As to books – those moving volumes of Wenxuan, the Wenji of Bai Juyi, the words of Laozi and Zhuangzi. There are many moving works from our own land, too, by scholars of former times.

*

It is an excellent thing to live modestly, shun luxury and wealth and not lust after fame and fortune. Rare has been the wise man who was rich.

In China once there was a man by the name of Xu You, who owned nothing and even drank directly from his cupped hands. Seeing this, someone gave him a ‘singing gourd’ to use as a cup; he hung it in a tree, but when he heard it singing in the wind one day he threw it away, annoyed by the noise it made, and went back to drinking his water from his hands. What a free, pure spirit!

Sun Chen had no bedclothes to sleep under in the winter months, only a bundle of straw which he slept in at night and put away again each morning.

The Chinese wrote these stories to hand down to later times because they found them so impressive. No one bothers to tell such tales in our country.

*

The changing seasons are moving in every way.

Everyone seems to feel that ‘it is above all autumn that moves the heart to tears’, and there is some truth in this, yet surely it is spring that stirs the heart more profoundly. Then, birdsong is full of the feel of spring, the plants beneath the hedges bud into leaf in the warm sunlight, the slowly deepening season brings soft mists, while the blossoms at last begin to open, only to meet with ceaseless winds and rain that send them flurrying restlessly to earth. Until the leaves appear on the boughs, the heart is endlessly perturbed.

The scented flowering orange is famously evocative, but it is above all plum blossom that has the power to carry you back to moments of cherished memory. The exquisite kerria, the hazy clusters of wisteria blossom – all these things linger in the heart.

Someone has said that at the time of the Buddha’s birthday and the Kamo festival in the fourth month, when the trees are cool with luxuriant new leaf, one is particularly moved by the pathos of things and by a longing for others, and indeed it is true. And who could not be touched to melancholy in the fifth month, when the sweet flag iris leaves are laid on roofs, and the rice seedlings are planted out, and the water rail’s knocking call is heard? The sixth month is also moving, with white evening- glory blooming over the walls of poor dwellings, and the smoke from smouldering smudge fires. The purifications of the sixth month are also delightful.

The festival of Tanabata is wonderfully elegant. Indeed so many things happen together in autumn – the nights grow slowly more chill, wild geese come crying over, and when the bush clover begins to yellow the early rice is harvested and hung to dry. The morning after a typhoon has blown through is also delightful.

Writing this, I realize that all this has already been spoken of long ago in The Tale of Genji and The Pillow Book – but that is no reason not to say it again. After all, things thought but left unsaid only fester inside you. So I let my brush run on like this for my own foolish solace; these pages deserve to be torn up and discarded, after all, and are not something others will ever see.

To continue – the sight of a bare wintry landscape is almost as lovely as autumn. It is delightful to see fallen autumn leaves scattered among the plants by the water’s edge, or vapour rising from the garden stream on a morning white with frost. It is also especially moving to observe everyone bustling about at year’s end, preparing for the new year. And then there is the forlornly touching sight of the waning moon around the twentieth day, hung in a clear, cold sky, although people consider it too dreary to look at. The Litany of Buddha Names and the Presentation of Tributes are thoroughly moving and magnificent, and in fact all the numerous court ceremonies and events at around this time, taking place as they do amidst the general end- of- year bustle, present an impressive sight. The way the Worship of the Four Directions follows so quickly upon the Great Demon Expulsion is wonderful too.

In the thick darkness of New Year’s Eve, people light pine torches and rush about, so fast that their feet virtually skim the ground, making an extraordinary racket for some reason, and knocking on everyone’s doors until late at night – but then at last around dawn all grows quiet, and you savour the touching moment of saying farewell to the old year. I was moved to find that in the East they still perform the ritual for dead souls on the night when the dead are said to return, although these days this has ceased to be done in the capital.

And so, watching the new year dawn in the sky, you are stirred by a sense of utter newness, although the sky looks no different from yesterday’s. It is also touching to see the happy sight of new year pines gaily decorating the houses all along the main streets.

*

A certain recluse monk once remarked, ‘I have relinquished all that ties me to the world, but the one thing that still haunts me is the beauty of the sky.’ I can quite see why he would feel this.

*

How mutable the flower of the human heart, a fluttering blossom gone before the breeze’s touch – so we recall the bygone years when the heart of another was our close companion, each dear word that stirred us then still unforgotten; and yet, it is the way of things that the beloved should move into worlds beyond our own, a parting far sadder than from the dead. Thus did Mozi grieve over a white thread that the dye would alter for ever, and at the crossroads Yang Zhu lamented the path’s parting ways.

In Retired Emperor Horikawa’s collection of one hundred poems, we read:

Where once I called on her　　　　　mukashi mishi

the garden fence is now in ruins–　imo ga kakine wa

flowering there I find　　　　　　　arenikeri

only wild violets, woven through　　tsubana majiri no

with rank spring grasses.　　　　　 sumire nomi shite

Such is the desolate scene that once must have met the poet’s eye.

*

Nothing is sadder than the aftermath of a death.

How trying it is to be jammed in together in some cramped and inconvenient mountain establishment for the forty- nine- day mourning period, performing the services for the dead. Never have the days passed faster. On the final day everyone is gruff and uncommunicative; each becomes engrossed in the importance of his own tidying and packing, then all go their separate ways. Once home again, the family will face all manner of fresh sorrows.

People go about warning each other of the various things that should be ritually avoided for the sake of the family. What a way to talk, at such a time! Really, what a wretched thing the human heart is!

Even with the passage of time the deceased is in no way forgotten, of course, but ‘the dead grow more distant with each day’, as the saying goes. And so, for all the memories, it seems our sorrow is no longer as acute as at death, for we begin to chatter idly and laugh again.

The corpse is buried on some deserted mountainside, we visit it only at the prescribed times, and soon moss has covered the grave marker, the grave is buried under fallen leaves, and only the howling evening winds and the moon at night come calling there.

It is all very well while there are those who remember and mourn the dead, but soon they too pass away; the descendants only know of him by hearsay, so they are hardly likely to grieve over his death. Finally, all ceremonies for him cease, no one any longer knows who he was or even his name, and only the grasses of each passing spring grow there to move the sensitive to pity; at length even the graveyard pine that sobbed in stormy winds is cut for firewood before its thousand years are up, the ancient mound is levelled by the plough, and the place becomes a field. The last trace of the grave itself has finally disappeared. It is sad to think of.

*

One morning after a beautiful fall of snow, I had reason to write a letter to an acquaintance, but I omitted to make any mention of the snow. I was delighted when she responded, ‘Do you expect me to pay any attention to the words of someone so perverse that he fails to enquire how I find this snowy landscape? What deplorable insensitivity!’

The lady is no longer alive, so I treasure even this trifling memory.

*

Around the twentieth day of the ninth month, someone invited me along to view the moon with him. We wandered and gazed until first light. Along the way, my companion came upon a house he remembered. He had his name announced, and in he went. In the unkempt and dew- drenched garden, a hint of casual incense lingered in the air. It was all movingly redolent of a secluded life.

In due course my companion emerged, but the elegance of the scene led me to stay a little longer and watch from the shadows. Soon the double doors opened a fraction wider; it seemed the lady was gazing at the moon. It would have been very disappointing had she immediately bolted the doors as soon as the visit was over. She could not know that someone would still be watching. Such sensibility could only be the fruit of a habitual attitude of mind.

I heard that this lady died not long after.

*

It is foolish to be in thrall to fame and fortune, engaged in painful striving all your life with never a moment of peace and tranquillity.

Great wealth will drive you to neglect your own well- being in pursuit of it. It is asking for harm and tempting trouble. Though you leave behind at your death a mountain of gold high enough to prop up the North Star itself, it will only cause problems for those who come after you. Nor is there any point in all those pleasures that delight the eyes of fools. Big carriages, fat horses, glittering gold and jewels – any man of sensibility would view such things as gross stupidity. Toss your gold away in the mountains; hurl your jewels into the deep. Only a complete fool is led astray by avarice.

Everyone would like to leave their name unburied for posterity – but the high- born and exalted are not necessarily fine people, surely. A dull, stupid person can be born into a good house, attain high status thanks to opportunity and live in the height of luxury, while many wonderfully wise and saintly men choose to remain in lowly positions, and end their days without ever having met with good fortune. A fierce craving for high status and position is next in folly to the lust for fortune.

We long to leave a name for our exceptional wisdom and sensibility – but when you really think about it, desire for a good reputation is merely revelling in the praise of others. Neither those who praise us nor those who denigrate will remain in the world for long, and others who hear their opinions will be gone in short order as well. Just who should we feel ashamed before, then? Whose is the recognition we should crave? Fame in fact attracts abuse and slander. No, there is nothing to be gained from leaving a lasting name. The lust for fame is the third folly.

Let me now say a few words, however, to those who dedicate themselves to the search for knowledge and the desire for understanding. Knowledge leads to deception; talent and ability only serve to increase earthly desires. Knowledge acquired by listening to others or through study is not true knowledge. So what then should we call knowledge? Right and wrong are simply part of a single continuum. What should we call good? One who is truly wise has no knowledge or virtue, nor honour nor fame. Who then will know of him, and speak of him to others? This is not because he hides his virtue and pretends foolishness – he is beyond all distinctions such as wise and foolish, gain and loss.

I have been speaking of what it is to cling to one’s delusions and seek after fame and fortune. All things of this phenomenal world are mere illusion. They are worth neither discussing nor desiring.

*

A certain novice monk in Inaba was rumoured to have a beautiful daughter, and many men came asking for her hand. But the girl ate nothing but chestnuts and never touched grains, so her father declared that she was too eccentric to be marriageable, and rejected them all.

*

When I went to see the horse racing at the Kamo Shrine on the fifth day of the fifth month, the view from our carriage was blocked by a throng of common folk. We all got down and moved towards the fence for a better view, but that area was particularly crowded and we couldn’t make our way through.

We then noticed a priest who had climbed a chinaberry tree across the way to sit in its fork and watch from there. He was so sleepy as he clung there that he kept nodding off, and only just managed to start awake in time to save himself from falling each time. Those who saw him couldn’t believe their eyes. ‘What an extraordinary fool!’ they all sneered.‘How can a man who’s perched up there so precariously among the branches relax so much that he falls asleep?’

A thought suddenly occurred to me. ‘Any of us may die from one instant to the next,’ I said, ‘and in fact we are far more foolish than this priest – here we are, contentedly watching the world go by, oblivious to death.’

‘That’s so true,’ said those in front of me. ‘It’s really very stupid, isn’t it,’ and they turned around and invited me in and made room for me.

Anyone can have this sort of insight, but at that particular moment it came as a shock, which is no doubt why people were so struck by it. Humans are not mere insensate beings like trees or rocks, after all, and on occasion things can really strike home.

*

Those who feel the impulse to pursue the path of enlightenment should immediately take the step, and not defer it while they attend to all the other things on their mind. If you say to yourself, ‘Let’s just wait until after this is over,’ or ‘While I’m at it I’ll just see to that,’ or ‘People will criticize me about such- and- such so I should make sure it’s all dealt with and causes no problem later,’ or‘There’s been time enough so far, after all, and it won’t take long just to a wait a little longer while I do this. Let’s not rush into things,’ one imperative thing after another will occur to detain you. There will be no end to it all, and the day of decision will never come.

In general, I find that reasonably sensitive and intelligent people will pass their whole life without taking the step they know they should. Would anyone with a fire close behind him choose to pause before fleeing? In a matter of life and death, one casts aside shame, abandons riches and runs. Does mortality wait on our choosing? Death comes upon us more swiftly than fire or flood. There is no escaping it. Who at that moment can refuse to part with all they love – aged parents, beloved children, lord and master, or the love of others?

*

The holy man of Shosha had accumulated such merit through recitations of The Lotus Sutra that he had attained purity of the Six Senses.

Once, on a journey, he entered the lodging where he was to stay the night and heard the bubbling of a pot of beans being boiled over a fire made from their husks.‘We’re so closely related and yet you boil us so brutally!’they were crying, and the bean husks crackling in the flames seemed to him to reply, ‘Do you imagine we’re boiling you on purpose? It’s excruciating for us to be burning like this, heaven knows, but we’re powerless to stop. Enough of these recriminations!’

*

As soon as I hear someone’s name, I feel I can picture their face, but when I actually meet them no one ever looks as I had been imagining all that time.

Also, I wonder if everyone, on hearing some old tale, imagines it as taking place in a certain part of some house he knows, and identifies the characters with people he sees in life, as I do.

And is it just I who sometimes feels a conviction that what someone is saying, or what you’re seeing or thinking just then, has already happened before, though you cannot remember when?

*

Unpleasant things – a great many things cluttering up the area where someone is sitting. A lot of brushes lying on an ink stone. A crowd of Buddhist images in a private worship hall. A large collection of stones and plants in a garden. Too many children and grandchildren in a house. Too much talk when meeting others. A long list of one’s virtuous acts in a supplicatory prayer.

Things that are not unpleasant in large amounts are books on a book cart, and rubbish on a rubbish heap.

*

What kind of man will feel depressed at being idle? There is nothing finer than to be alone with nothing to distract you.

If you follow the ways of the world, your heart will be drawn to its sensual defilements and easily led astray; if you go among people, your words will be guided by others’ responses rather than come from the heart. There is nothing firm or stable in a life spent between larking about together and quarrelling, exuberant one moment, aggrieved and resentful the next. You are forever pondering pros and cons, endlessly absorbed in questions of gain and loss. And on top of delusion comes drunkenness, and in that drunkenness you dream.

Scurrying and bustling, heedless and forgetful – such are all men. Even if you do not yet understand the True Way, you can achieve what could be termed temporary happiness at least by removing yourself from outside influences, taking no part in the affairs of the world, calming yourself and stilling the mind. As The Great Cessation and Insight says, we must ‘break all ties with everyday life, human affairs, the arts and scholarship’.

*

I cannot bear the way people will make it their business to know all the details of some current rumour, even though it has nothing to do with them, and then proceed to pass the story on and do their best to learn more. Wandering monks up from some provincial backwater seem particularly adept at prying into tales about others as if it was their own concern, and spreading the word in such detail that you wonder how on earth they came to know so much.

*

Nor can I bear the way people will spread excited rumours about the latest marvels. A refined person will not learn of things until the rumours are old and stale.

If someone new comes visiting, the boorish and insensitive will always manage to make the visitor feel ignorant by exchanging cryptic remarks about something they all know among themselves, some story or name, chuckling and exchanging knowing glances.

*

When someone complained that it was a great shame the way fine silk covers are so soon damaged, Ton’a replied,‘It is only after the top and bottom edges of the silk have frayed, or when the mother- of- pearl has peeled off the roller, that a scroll is truly impressive’ – an astonishingly fine remark, I felt. Similarly, an unmatched set of bound books can be considered unattractive, but Bishop Kōyūimpressed me deeply by saying that only a boring man will always want things to match; real quality lies in irregularity – another excellent remark.

In all things, perfect regularity is tasteless. Something left not quite finished is very appealing, a gesture towards the future. Someone told me that even in the construction of the imperial palace, some part is always left uncompleted.

In the Buddhist scriptures and other works written by the great men of old there are also a number of missing sections.

*

The Dainagon Abbot employed a young acolyte by the name of Otozuru- maru, who came to be on intimate terms with one Yasura- dono and was constantly coming and going to visit him.

One day, seeing the lad return, the abbot asked where he had been. ‘I’ve been to see Yasura- dono,’ he replied.

‘Is this Yasura- dono a layman, or a monk?’ enquired the abbot.

Bringing his sleeves together in a polite bow, the acolyte replied, ‘I really don’t know, sir. I’ve never seen his head.’

I wonder why not – after all, he would have seen the rest of him.

*

The Yin- Yang masters do not concern themselves with those days of the calendar marked ‘Red Tongue Days’. Nor did people of old treat the day as unpropitious. It seems someone more recently has declared it unlucky, and now everyone has begun to avoid it, believing that things undertaken on this day will miscarry. This idea – that whatever is said or done on this day will fail, that objects gained on the day will be lost and plans made will go awry – is ridiculous. If you count the number of failures that happen on an auspicious day, you will find there are just as many.

This is because, in this transient phenomenal world with its constant change, what appears to exist in fact does not. What is begun has no end. Aims go unfulfilled, yet desire is endless. The human heart changes ceaselessly. All things are passing illusion. What is there that remains unchanging? The folly of such beliefs springs from people’s inability to understand this.

It is said that evil performed on an auspicious day is always ill- fated, while good performed on an inauspicious one will be blessed by good fortune. It is people who create good fortune and misfortune, not the calendar.

*

A man who was studying archery took two arrows in his hand and stood before the target.

‘A beginner should not hold two arrows,’ his teacher told him. ‘You will be careless with the first, knowing you have a second. You must always be determined to hit the target with the single arrow you shoot, and have no thought beyond this.’ With only two arrows, and standing before his master, would he really be inclined to be slapdash with one of them? Yet although he may not have been aware of his own carelessness, his teacher was. The same injunction surely applies in all matters.

A man engaged in Buddhist practice will tell himself at night that there is always the morning, or in the morning will anticipate the night, always intending to make more effort later. And if such are your days, how much less aware must you be of the passing moment’s indolence. Why should it be so difficult to carry something out right now when you think of it, to seize the instant?

*

Someone told the following tale. A man sells an ox. The buyer says he will come in the morning to pay and take the beast. But during the night, the ox dies. ‘The buyer thus gained, while the seller lost,’ he concluded.

But a bystander remarked, ‘The owner did indeed lose on the transaction, but he profited greatly in another way. Let me tell you why. Living creatures have no knowledge of the nearness of death. Such was the ox, and such too are we humans. As it happened, the ox died that night; as it happened, the owner lived on. One day’s life is more precious than a fortune’s worth of money, while an ox’s worth weighs no more than a goose feather. One cannot say that a man who gains a fortune while losing a coin or two has made a loss.’

Everyone laughed at this. ‘That reasoning doesn’t only apply to the owner of the ox,’ they scoffed.

The man went on. ‘Well then, if people hate death they should love life. Should we not relish each day the joy of survival? Fools forget this – they go striving after other enjoyments, cease to appreciate the fortune they have and risk all to lay their hands on fresh wealth. Their desires are never sated. There is a deep contradiction in failing to enjoy life and yet fearing death when faced with it. It is because they have no fear of death that people fail to enjoy life – no, not that they don’t fear it, but rather they forget its nearness. Of course, it must be said that the ultimate gain lies in transcending the relative world with its distinction between life and death.’

At this, everyone jeered more than ever.

*

A lady who had reason to withdraw from the world for a time had retired to a lonely tumbledown house, where she was idling away the long days of her seclusion, when one dimly moonlit evening a certain man decided to call; but as he was creeping stealthily to her door, a dog set up a fierce barking. This brought one of the maidservants.‘Where do you hail from?’ she enquired. The man promptly announced himself, and was shown in.

His heart was heavy as he took in his forlorn surroundings. How must she spend her time here? He stood hesitating on the veranda’s rough wooden boards. ‘This way,’ came a wonderfully serene and youthful voice, so he slid open the door with some difficulty and entered.

The place was not so shabby after all, but was modest and refined. At the far end a lamp shone softly, revealing the beauty of the furnishings, and the scent of incense lit some time earlier imbued the place with an evocative and beguiling air.

He heard orders being given among the servants – ‘Take care to lock the gate. It may rain. Put the carriage under the shelter of the gate roof’ – and talk of where his retainers should spend the night. Then one added, in a soft murmur that nevertheless reached his ears because he was quite close, ‘Tonight at least we can sleep easy.’

The two spoke together of all that had happened since they last met, until the first cock crowed while it was yet night. On they talked earnestly, of matters past and to come, and now the cock’s crow was loud and persistent. The day must by now have dawned, he thought, but this was not a place he must hasten to leave before light, so he lingered on a little, until sunlight whitened the cracks in the door. At last, with promises not to forget her, he departed.

Recalling the enchanting scene, he remembers how beautifully green the trees and garden plants glowed in that early summer daybreak, and even now, whenever he passes the house, he turns to gaze until the great camphor tree in the garden is lost to sight.

*

A man famed for his tree- climbing skills once directed another to climb a tall tree and cut branches. While the fellow was precariously balanced aloft, the tree- climber watched without a word, but when he was descending and had reached the height of the eaves the expert called to him, ‘Careful how you go! Take care coming down!’

‘Why do you say that? He’s so far down now that he could leap to the ground from there,’ I said.

‘Just so,’ replied the tree- climber. ‘While he’s up there among the treacherous branches I need not say a word –his fear is enough to guide him. It’s in the easy places that mistakes will always occur.’

Lowly commoner though he was, his words echoed the warnings of the sages.

Apparently one of the laws of kickball also states that if you relax after achieving a difficult kick, this is the moment when the ball will always fall to the ground.

*

There are seven types of people one should not have as a friend.

The first is an exalted and high- ranking person. The second, somebody young. The third, anyone strong and in perfect health. The fourth, a man who loves drink. The fifth, a brave and daring warrior. The sixth, a liar. The seventh, an avaricious man.

The three to choose as friends are – one who gives gifts, a doctor and a wise man.

*

The domestic animals are the horse and the ox. It is a shame to tether the poor things and make them suffer, but it can’t be helped, since they are indispensable to us. One should most certainly have a dog, as they are better than men at guarding the house. However, since all the houses around you will have dogs, you probably don’t need to go out of your way to get one yourself.

All other creatures, be it bird or beast, are useless. When you lock an animal that runs free into a cage or chain it up, when you snip the wings of a flying bird and confine it, the beast will ceaselessly pine for the wild and the bird for the clouds. Surely no one with a heart to imagine how unbearable he himself would find it could take pleasure in these creatures’ torment. It would take the stony heart of a Jie or a Zhou to enjoy witnessing the suffering of a living creature.

Wang Huizhi loved birds. He watched them frolicking happily in the forest, and made them his companions in his rambles. He did not catch them and make them suffer. We should follow the words of the classic: ‘Do not cultivate rare birds or strange beasts in your own land.’

*

Grand Counsellor Masafusa was a fine, scholarly man, and the retired emperor was planning to promote him to Commander of the Guards, when someone in close service informed His Majesty that he had just witnessed something dreadful.

‘What was it?’ His Majesty enquired.

‘I watched through a gap in the fence as Count Masafusa cut off the leg of a live dog to feed to his hawk,’ the man replied.

His Majesty was appalled. The thought of Masafusa revolted him, and he was not promoted after all.

It is extraordinary that such a man would own a hawk, and the story of the dog’s leg is absolutely unfounded. The lie was most unfortunate, but how splendid of His Majesty to have reacted with such disgust when he heard the tale.

Overall, it must be said that those who kill or harm living creatures, or set them up to fight each other for their own pleasure, are no better than wild beasts themselves. If you pause and look carefully at the birds and animals, and even the little insects, you will see that they love their children, feel affection for their parents, live in couples, are jealous, angry, full of desire, self- protecting and fearful for their lives, and far more so than men, since they lack all intelligence. Surely one should pity them when they are killed or made to suffer? If you can look on any sentient being without compassion, you are less than human.

*

Yan Hui’s firm belief was that he must avoid burdening others. One should not cause suffering and pain to others, nor undermine the will of the humble man.

Some will take pleasure in deceiving, frightening or mocking little children. Adults treat such tales lightly, knowing that they are quite unfounded, but those words will strike deep into the heart of a poor little child, and humiliate, terrify or appal it. It is heartless to enjoy tormenting children in this way.

The joys, angers, sorrows and pleasures of adults too are all based on illusion, but who among us is not attached to the seeming reality of this life?

It harms a man more to wound his heart than to hurt his body. Illness, too, often originates in the mind. Few illnesses come from without. There are times when medicine cannot produce the intended sweat, but shame or fear will always bring one on, which should prove to us that such things come from the mind. We find examples in the classics, after all – think of the man who was hoisted up the Ling Yun Tower to write its signboard, whose hair turned white from fear at the height.

*

Should we look at the spring blossoms only in full flower, or the moon only when cloudless and clear? To long for the moon with the rain before you, or to lie curtained in your room while the spring passes unseen, is yet more poignant and deeply moving. A branch of blossoms on the verge of opening, a garden strewn with fading petals, have more to please the eye. Could poems on the themes of ‘Going to view the blossoms to find them already fallen’or ‘Written when I was prevented from going to see the flowers’ be deemed inferior to ‘On seeing the blossoms’? It is natural human feeling to yearn over the falling blossoms and the setting moon – yet some, it seems, are so insensitive that they will declare that since this branch and that have already shed their flowers, there is nothing worth seeing any longer.

In all things, the beginning and end are the most engaging. Does the love of man and woman suggest only their embraces? No, the sorrow of lovers parted before they met, laments over promises betrayed, long lonely nights spent sleepless until dawn, pining thoughts for one in some far place, a woman left sighing over past love in her tumbledown abode – it is these, surely, that embody the romance of love.

Rather than gazing on a clear full moon that shines over a thousand leagues, it is infinitely more moving to see the moon near dawn and after long anticipation, tinged with most beautiful palest blue, a moon glimpsed among cedar branches deep in the mountains, its light now hidden again by the gathering clouds of an autumn shower. The moist glint of moonlight on the glossy leaves of the forest shii oak or the white oak pierces the heart, and makes you yearn for the distant capital and a friend of true sensibility to share the moment with you.

Are blossoms and the moon merely things to be gazed at with the eye? No, it brings more contentment and delight to stay inside the house in spring and, there in your bedroom, let your heart go out to the unseen moonlit night.

The man of quality never appears entranced by anything; he savours things with a casual air. Country bumpkins, however, take flamboyant pleasure in everything. They will wriggle their way in through the crowd and stand there endlessly gaping up at the blossoms, sit about under the trees drinking sake and indulging in linked verse- making together and, finally, oafishly break off great branches of blossom to carry away. They will dip their hands and feet into clear spring water, get down to stand in unsullied snow and leave their footprints everywhere, and in short throw themselves into everything with uninhibited glee.

I have observed such people behaving quite astonishingly when they came to see the Kamo festival. Declaring that the procession was horribly late so there was no point in hanging around on the viewing stand, a group retired to a house behind the stands and settled down to eat, drink and play go and sugoroku, leaving one of their number back on the stand to keep watch. ‘It’s coming by!’ he shouted, whereupon they all leaped frantically to their feet and dashed back, elbowing each other out of the way as they scrambled up, nearly tumbling off in their eagerness to thrust aside the blinds for a better look, jostling for position and craning to miss nothing, and commenting volubly on everything they saw. Then, when that section of the procession had passed, off they went again, declaring they’d be back for the next one. They were clearly only there to see the spectacle.

The upper echelons from the capital, on the other hand, will sit there dozing without so much as a glance at the scene. Young gentlemen of lesser rank are constantly rising to wait on their superiors, while those seated in the back rows never rudely lean forward, and no one goes out of his way to watch as the procession passes.

On the day of the festival everything is elegantly strewn with the emblematic aoi leaves, and even before dawn the carriages quietly begin to arrive to secure a good viewing position, everyone intrigued about which carriage is whose, sometimes identifying them by an accompanying servant or ox- boy they recognize. It is endlessly fascinating to watch the carriages come and go, some charming, others more showy. By the time evening draws in, all those rows of carriages and the people who were crammed into the stands have disappeared, and hardly a soul is left. Once the chaos of departing carriages is over, the blinds and matting are taken down from the stands as you watch, and the place is left bare and forlorn, moving you to a poignant sense of the brevity of worldly things. It is this that is the real point of seeing the festival.

Among the people coming and going in front of the stands there are many you recognize, making you realize there are not really so many people in this world. Even if you were destined to die after all these others, clearly your own death cannot be far away. When a large vessel filled with water is pierced with a tiny hole, though each drop is small it will go on relentlessly leaking until soon the vessel is empty. The city is filled with people, but not a day would go by without someone dying. And is it only one or two a day? There are times when the corpses on the pyres of Toribe, Funaoka and elsewhere further afield are piled high, but no day passes without a funeral. And so the coffin sellers no sooner make one than it is sold. Be they young, be they strong, the time of death comes upon all unawares. It is an extraordinary miracle that we have escaped it until now. Can we ever, even briefly, have peace of mind in this world?

It is like the game of mamakodate, played with sugoroku pieces, in which no one knows which in the line of pieces will be removed next – when the count is made and a piece is taken, the rest seem to have escaped, but the count goes on and more are picked off in turn, so that no piece is finally spared. Soldiers going into battle, aware of the closeness of death, forget their home and their own safety. And it is sheer folly for a man who lives secluded from the world in his lowly hut, spending his days in idle delight in his garden, to pass off such matters as irrelevant to himself. Do you imagine that the enemy Impermanence will not come forcing its way into your peaceful mountain retreat? The recluse faces death as surely as the soldier setting forth to battle.

*

A sensible man will not die leaving valuables behind. A collection of vulgar objects looks bad, while good ones will suggest a futile attachment to worldly things. And it is even more unfortunate to leave behind a vast accumulation. There will be ugly fights over it after your death, with everyone determined to get things for himself. If you plan to leave something to a particular person, you should pass it on while you are still alive.

Some things are necessary for day- to- day living, but one should have nothing else.

*

Even people who seem to lack any finer feelings will sometimes say something impressive.

An alarming- looking ruffian from the eastern provinces once turned to the man beside him and asked if he had any children. ‘Not one,’ the man replied.

‘Well then,’ said the Easterner, ‘you’ll not know what true depth of feeling is. It frightens me to think of a man unacquainted with tenderness. It’s having your own children that brings home to you the poignant beauty of life.’

This is indeed true. Without familial love, would such a man as this be able to feel compassion? Even a man who lacks all filial piety will discover how a parent feels when he himself has children.

It is wrong for a man who has taken the tonsure and cast all away to despise those he sees around him encumbered with worldly ties, who go crawling abjectly after this person and that and are full of craving. If you imagined yourself in his place, you would see how he might abase himself so far as to steal for the sake of his beloved parents or wife and children. Rather than seizing thieves and punishing their crimes, it would be better to make the world a place where people did not go hungry or cold. A man without stable means is a man whose heart is unstable. People steal from extremity. There will be no end to crime while the world is not governed well, and men suffer from cold and starvation. It is cruel to make people suffer and drive them to break the law, then treat the poor creatures as criminals.

As for how to improve people’s lives, there can be no doubt that it would benefit those below if people in high positions were to cease their luxurious and wasteful ways and instead were kind and tender to the people, and encouraged agriculture. The true criminal must be defined as a man who commits a crime though he is as decently fed and clothed as others.

*

The imperial bodyguard Hada no Shigemi once said of one of the retired emperor’s guard, the Shimotsuke Novice Shingan, ‘He has the mark of one prone to falling from horses. He should take great care.’ Shingan thought this very unlikely, but he did indeed fall from his horse and die. Everyone then decided that the words issuing from such an expert in his field were divinely prophetic.

So just what was this mark? people asked him. ‘He showed all the signs by having a very poor riding seat, and favouring horses that tend to buck,’ replied the guard. ‘Have I ever been wrong?’

*

It is not good to call on someone if you have no particular reason. Even if you go with some purpose, you should leave promptly once your business is accomplished. It is very annoying if a visit drags on.

There is so much talking when people get together. It is exhausting, disturbs the peace of mind and wastes time better spent on other things. There is nothing to be gained for either party. It is bad, too, to feel irritable as you talk. When you don’t care for something, you should come right out and say so.

The exception to all this is when someone after your own heart, whom you feel inclined to talk with, is at a loose end and encourages you to stay a while longer for a peaceful chat. No doubt we all have Ruan Ji’s ‘welcoming green eyes’ from time to time.

It is very nice when a friend simply drops in, has a quiet talk with you, and then leaves. It is also wonderfully pleasing to receive a letter that simply begins, ‘I write because it’s been some time since I sent news,’ or some such.

*

A young man overflows with vigour, things stir his heart, and he is prone to passions. Like a flung ball, such a youth courts danger and physical harm. Riches are wasted in pursuit of magnificence, then all this is suddenly abandoned for the wretched robes of the monk; he is full of fervour and fight, suffers agonies of shame or bitterness, and his fancies are constantly shifting from day to day. He will devote himself to women and pursue infatuations, or take his example from those who have died with no thought to their own safety or longevity, behaving with such reckless daring that ‘a long life lies ruined’, or let himself be drawn wherever his heart urges, becoming the cause of talk for many years to come. It is indeed in youth that we make our mistakes.

In age, on the other hand, the spirit weakens, we become indifferent and apathetic, and nothing rouses us. The heart grows naturally calm, so that we no longer act in futile ways but instead tend to our bodies, live free of discontent and try to avoid troubling others. Age has more wisdom than youth, just as youth has more beauty than does age.

*

There are many incomprehensible things in this world.

I cannot understand why people will seize any occasion to immediately bring out the sake, delighting in forcing someone else to drink. The other will frown and grimace in painful protest, attempt to throw it away when no one’s looking or do his best to escape, but this man will seize him, pin him down and make him swallow cup after cup. A genteel man will quickly be transformed into a madman and start acting the fool; a vigorous, healthy fellow will before your very eyes become shockingly afflicted and fall senseless to the floor. What a thing to do, on a day of celebration! Right into the next day his head hurts, he can’t eat, and he lies there groaning with all memory of the previous day gone as if it were a former life. He neglects essential duties both public and private, with disastrous effects. It is both boorish and cruel to subject someone to this sort of misery. Surely a man who has had this bitter experience will be filled with regret and loathing. Anyone from a land that lacked this custom would be amazed and appalled to hear of its existence in another country.

It is depressing enough just to witness this happening to another. A man who had always seemed thoughtful and refined will burst into mindless laughter, prattle on and on, his lacquered court cap askew, the ties of his robes loosened and the skirts hauled up above his shins, and generally behave so obliviously that he seems a changed man. A woman will blatantly push her hair up away from her face, throw back her head and laugh quite shamelessly, and seize the hand of the person with the sake, while the more uncouth might grab one of the snacks and hold it to someone else’s mouth or eat it herself – a quite disgraceful sight. People bellow at the top of their lungs, everyone sings and prances about, and an old monk is called in, who proceeds to bare his filthy black shoulder and writhe about so that you can hardly stand to watch, and you loathe just as much the others who sit there enjoying the spectacle.

Some will make you cringe by the way they sing their own praises, others will cry into their drink, while the lower orders abuse each other and get into quite shocking and appalling fights. Finally, after all manner of disgraceful and pitiful behaviour, the drunkard will seize things without permission, then end up hurting himself by rolling off the veranda or tumbling from his horse or carriage. If he’s of a class that goes on foot he’ll stagger away down the high road, doing unspeakable things against people’s walls or gates as he goes. It is quite disgusting to see the old monk in his black robe stumbling off, steadying himself with his hand on the shoulder of the lad beside him and rambling on incomprehensibly.

If drinking like this profited us in this world or the next, what could one say? But in this world it leads to all manner of error, and causes both illness and loss of wealth. Wine has been called ‘the greatest of medicines’, but in fact all sickness springs from it. It is claimed that you forget your sorrows in drink, but from what I can see, men in their cups will in fact weep to recall their past unhappiness. As for the next world – having lost the wisdom you were born with, reduced all your good karma to ashes, built up a store of wickedness and broken all the Buddhist precepts, you are destined for hell. Remember, the Buddha teaches that those who lift the wine glass either to their own lips or to others’ will spend five hundred lifetimes without hands.

Yet, loathsome though one finds it, there are situations when a cup of sake is hard to resist. On a moonlit night, a snowy morning, or beneath the flowering cherry trees, it increases all the pleasures of the moment to bring out the sake cups and settle down to talk serenely together over a drink. It is also a great comfort to have a drink together if an unexpected friend calls round when time is hanging heavy on your hands. And it is quite wonderful when sake and snacks are elegantly served from behind her curtains by some remote and exalted lady.

It is also quite delightful to sit across from a close friend in some cosy little nook in winter, roasting food over the coals and drinking lots of sake together. And delightful too on a journey to sit about on the grass together in some wayside hut or out in the wild, drinking and lamenting the lack of a suitable snack. And it’s a fine thing when someone who really hates having sake pressed on them is forced to have just a little. You are thrilled when some grand person singles you out and offers to refill your cup, urging, ‘Do have more. You’ve barely drunk.’ And it is also very pleasing when someone you would like to get to know better is a drinker and becomes very pally with you in his cups.

All things considered, a drunkard is so entertaining he can be forgiven his sins. Think of the charming scene when a master throws open the door on his servant, who is sound asleep next morning after an exhausting night on the drink. The poor befuddled fellow rushes off, rubbing his bleary eyes, topknot exposed on his hatless head, only half dressed and clutching the rest of his trailing clothes, his hairy shins sticking out below his lifted skirts as he scampers into the distance – a typical drunk.

*

The one thing a man should not have is a wife.

One is impressed to hear that a certain man always lives alone, while someone who is reported to have married into this or that family, or to have taken a wife and be living together, will find himself quite looked down on.‘He must have married that nondescript girl because he thought she was something special,’ people will say scornfully, or if she is a good woman they will think, ‘He’ll be so besotted that he treats her like his own personal buddha.’ The impression is even more dreary when she runs the house well. It is depressing to watch her bear children and fuss over them, and things don’t end with his death, for then you have the shameful sight of her growing old and decrepit as a nun.

No matter who the woman may be, you would grow to hate her if you lived with her and saw her day in day out, and the woman must become dissatisfied too. But if you lived separately and sometimes visited her, your feelings for each other would surely remain unchanged through the years. It keeps the relationship fresh to just drop in from time to time on impulse and spend the night.

*

What a shame it is to hear someone declare that things lose their beauty at night! All lustre, ornamentation and brilliance come into their own at night.

In daylight, one can keep things simple and dress sedately. But the best clothing for night is showy and dazzling formal wear. The same goes for people – a good- looking person will look still finer by lamplight, and it’s charming to hear a careful voice speaking in darkness. Scents and music too are still lovelier at night.

It is a fine thing to see a man who calls on some great household looking his best late on an uneventful evening. Young people who pay attention to such things will always notice one’s appearance no matter what the hour, so it is wise to dress well whatever the situation, whether formal or informal, and most especially at times when one is inclined to relax and unwind. Particularly delightful is when a fine gentleman has bothered to plaster down his hair though it is after dark, or when a lady slips from the room late at night to take up a mirror and see to her face before rejoining the company.

*

When the now- deceased Tokudaiji Minister of the Right was Superintendent of Police, he was one day holding court at his central gate when the ox of one of the officers, Akikane, broke loose, got into the court room, scrambled up on to the Superintendent’s seating platform and there settled down to chew its cud. This was deemed a disturbingly untoward event, and everyone present declared that the beast should be taken off for Yin- Yang divination to determine the meaning.

However, when the Superintendent’s father the Minister heard of this, he declared, ‘An ox has no understanding. It has its four legs which can take it anywhere. There is no reason to impound a skinny beast that happens to have brought some lowly official here.’ He had the ox returned to its master, and changed the matting where the ox had lain. There were no ill consequences from the event.

It is sometimes said that if you see something sinister and choose to treat it as normal, you will thereby avert whatever it portended.

*

Nothing in this world can be trusted. Fools put all their faith in things, and so become angry and bitter.

The powerful should place no faith in their powerful position. The strong are the first to go. The rich should never depend on their wealth. A fortune can easily disappear from one moment to the next. A scholar should never be complacent about his skills. Even Confucius did not meet with the reception he deserved. The virtuous should not rely on their virtue. Even the exemplary Yan Hui met with misfortune. Nor should those favoured by the emperor be smug. You may at any time find yourself instead faced with execution for some crime. Never rely on your servants to be loyal. They can rebel and flee. Never put your faith in others’ goodwill. They will inevitably change their minds. Never depend on a promise made. People seldom keep their word.

If you rely neither on yourself nor on others, you will rejoice when things go well, and not be aggrieved when they don’t. Maintain a clear space on either side, and nothing will obstruct you; keep open before and behind you, and you will be unimpeded. If you let yourself be hemmed in, you can be squeezed to breaking point. Without care and flexibility in your dealings with the world, you will find yourself in conflict and be damaged, while if you live calmly and serenely, not a hair on your head will come to harm.

Humans are the most miraculous and exalted of all things in heaven and earth. And heaven and earth are boundless. How, then, could we differ in essence? If our spirit is open and boundless, neither fear nor joy will obstruct it, and we will remain untroubled by the world.

*

There is a place in Tamba called Izumo, where the deity of the great Izumo Shrine has been installed in a magnificent shrine building. The area is ruled by a certain Shida, who one autumn invited a great many people, including the holy man Shōkai. ‘Come and pray to Izumo,’ he said, ‘and let us feast on rice cakes.’ He led them to the shrine, and every one of them prayed and was filled with faith.

The holy man was immensely moved by the sight of the guardian Chinese lion and Korean dog, which were placed back to back and facing backwards. ‘How marvellous!’he exclaimed, close to tears. ‘Such an unusual position to stand them in! There must be some deep reason behind it.’ Then he turned to the others. ‘How can you not have noticed this wonder?’ he cried. ‘I’m amazed at you.’

They were very struck. ‘Yes indeed,’ they all declared,‘they are different from elsewhere. We’ll tell this to everyone back in the capital.’

The holy man now wished to learn more, so he called over an elderly and wise- looking shrine priest. ‘There must be some interesting tale explaining the placement of these images,’ he said. ‘Do be so kind as to tell us.’

‘Indeed there is,’ replied the priest. ‘Some naughty children did it. A disgraceful business,’ and so saying he went over to the statues, set them to rights and walked off.

The holy man’s tears of delight had been for nothing.

*

He whose deep love spurs him to dare all and go to his beloved, though ‘watchful eyes surround the stealthy lover’ and ‘guards are set to snare him in the dark’, will leave them both replete with powerful memories of all the moments when they tasted life’s poignancy to the full. It must feel very awkward and unromantic for the woman, however, if a man simply takes her as his wife with the full consent of the family and without further ado.

How dreary it is when a woman hard up in the world announces that she will ‘answer the call of any current’ so long as he is well- off, be it some unsuitable old priest or an uncouth Easterner, and a go- between sets about singing the praises of each to the other, with the result that she comes to someone’s house as a bride without either knowing the other at all. What on earth would they say to each other when they first come face to face? On the other hand, a couple can find endless conversation in the memories of long hardships overcome, ‘forging their way through the dense autumn woods’ to be together at last.

It can generally be said that a great deal of dissatisfaction results from a marriage set up by a third party. If the wife is excellent and the man a lowly and ugly old fellow, he will despise her for allowing herself to be thrown away on the likes of himself, and feel ashamed in her presence –a deplorable situation.

If you can never linger beneath the clouded moon on a plum- scented evening, nor find yourself recalling the dawns when you made your way home through the dew- soaked grasses by her gate after a night of love, you had best not aspire to be a lover at all.

*

The full moon’s perfect roundness lasts barely a moment, and in no time is lost. Those with no eye for such things, it seems, fail to see how it changes in the course of a night.

An illness will grow graver as each moment passes, and death is already close at hand, yet while the sickness is still mild and you are not yet confronting death, you are lulled by your accustomed assumptions of a normal life in an unchanging world, and choose to wait until you have accomplished all you want in life before calmly turning your thoughts to salvation and a Buddhist practice, with the result that when you fall ill and confront death, none of your dreams has been fulfilled. Now, too late, you repent of your long years of negligence, and swear that if only you were to recover you would dedicate yourself unstintingly day and night to this thing and that – but for all your prayers your illness grows graver, until you lose your senses and die a raving death. It happens to so many of us. We must fully grasp this, here and now.

If you plan to turn your thoughts to the Buddhist Way after you have fulfilled all your desires, you will find that those desires are endless. What could be achieved, in this illusory life of ours? All desire is delusion. If desires arise within you, realize that they spring from your lost and deluded mind, and ignore them all. Relinquish all today and turn to the Buddhist path, and you will be freed of all obstruction, released from the need for action, and lasting peace will be yours body and soul.

*

The year I turned eight, I asked my father, ‘What sort of thing is a buddha?’

‘A buddha is what a human becomes,’ he replied.

‘How does a human become a buddha?’ I asked.

‘You become a buddha by following the Buddha’s teaching,’ he answered.

‘So who taught the Buddha?’ I asked.

‘He became a buddha by following the teaching of previous buddhas,’ he said.

‘So what sort of buddha was the first one who began the teaching?’ I asked.

My father laughed and replied, ‘I suppose he just fell from the sky like rain or rose out of the earth like water.’

He used to enjoy recounting this story to others, adding, ‘He had me cornered. I couldn’t think what to reply.’

‘ “I die I die” the Mother said’

‘I die I die’ the Mother said,

‘My Children will die for lack of bread!

What more has the merciless tyrant said?’

The Monk sat down on her stony bed.

His Eye was dry, no tear could flow.

A hollow groan first spoke his woe.

He trembled & shudderd upon the bed.

At length with a feeble cry he said

‘When God commanded this hand to write

In the studious hours of deep midnight

He told me that All I wrote should prove

The bane of all that on Earth I love.

‘My brother starvd between two walls,

His children’s cry my soul appalls.

I mockd at the wrack & griding chain,

My bent body mocks at their torturing pain.

‘Thy father drew his sword in the north,

With his thousands strong he is marched forth.

Thy brother has armed himself in steel

To revenge the wrongs thy Children feel.

‘But vain the sword & vain the bow,

They never can work war’s overthrow!

The Hermit’s prayer & the widow’s tear

Alone can free the world from fear.’

The hand of vengeance sought the bed

To which the purple tyrant fled.

The iron hand crushd the tyrant’s head

And became a tyrant in his stead.

THE CHIMNEY SWEEPER

When my mother died I was very young,

And my father sold me while yet my tongue

Could scarcely cry ‘weep weep weep weep,’

So your chimneys I sweep & in soot I sleep.

There’s little Tom Dacre, who cried when his head

That curl’d like a lamb’s back was shav’d, so I said:

‘Hush Tom, never mind it, for when your head’s bare,

You know that the soot cannot spoil your white hair.’

And so he was quiet, & that very night,

As Tom was asleeping he had such a sight,

That thousands of sweepers, Dick, Joe, Ned & Jack

Were all of them lock’d up in coffins of black,

And by came an Angel who had a bright key,

And he open’d the coffins & set them all free.

Then down a green plain leaping laughing they run

And wash in a river and shine in the Sun.

Then naked & white, all their bags left behind,

They rise upon clouds, and sport in the wind.

And the Angel told Tom if he’d be a good boy,

He’d have God for his father & never want joy.

And so Tom awoke and we rose in the dark

And got with our bags & our brushes to work.

Tho’ the morning was cold, Tom was happy & warm.

So if all do their duty, they need not fear harm.

NIGHT

The sun descending in the west,

The evening star does shine.

The birds are silent in their nest,

And I must seek for mine,

The moon like a flower

In heaven’s high bower;

With silent delight

Sits and smiles on the night.

Farewell green fields and happy groves,

Where flocks have took delight;

Where lambs have nibbled, silent moves

The feet of angels bright;

Unseen they pour blessing,

And joy without ceasing,

On each bud and blossom,

And each sleeping bosom.

They look in every thoughtless nest,

Where birds are coverd warm;

They visit caves of every beast

To keep them all from harm:

If they see any weeping

That should have been sleeping

They pour sleep on their head

And sit down by their bed.

When wolves and tygers howl for prey

They pitying stand and weep;

Seeking to drive their thirst away,

And keep them from the sheep.

But if they rush dreadful,

The angels most heedful

Recieve each mild spirit

New worlds to inherit.

And there the lion’s ruddy eyes

Shall flow with tears of gold:

And pitying the tender cries,

And walking round the fold:

Saying: ‘Wrath by his meekness

And by his health sickness,

Is driven away

From our immortal day.

‘And now beside thee, bleating lamb,

I can lie down and sleep;

Or think on him who bore thy name,

Graze after thee and weep.

For wash’d in life’s river,

My bright mane for ever

Shall shine like the gold,

As I guard o’er the fold.’

THE SCHOOL BOY

I love to rise in a summer morn,

When the birds sing on every tree;

The distant huntsman winds his horn,

And the sky- lark sings with me.

O! what sweet company.

But to go to school in a summer morn,

O! it drives all joy away:

Under a cruel eye outworn,

The little ones spend the day

In sighing and dismay.

Ah! then at times I drooping sit,

And spend many an anxious hour,

Nor in my book can I take delight,

Nor sit in learning’s bower,

Worn thro’ with the dreary shower.

How can the bird that is born for joy

Sit in a cage and sing?

How can a child when fears annoy

But droop his tender wing

And forget his youthful spring?

O! father & mother, if buds are nip’d,

And blossoms blown away,

And if the tender plants are strip’d

Of their joy in the springing day,

By sorrow and cares dismay,

How shall the summer arise in joy,

Or the summer fruits appear?

Or how shall we gather what griefs destroy

Or bless the mellowing year,

When the blasts of winter appear?

THE TYGER

Tyger, Tyger, burning bright,

In the forests of the night:

What immortal hand or eye

Could frame thy fearful symmetry?

In what distant deeps or skies

Burnt the fire of thine eyes?

On what wings dare he aspire?

What the hand dare seize the fire?

And what shoulder, & what art,

Could twist the sinews of thy heart?

And when thy heart began to beat,

What dread hand? & what dread feet?

What the hammer? what the chain,

In what furnace was thy brain?

What the anvil? what dread grasp

Dare its deadly terrors clasp!

When the stars threw down their spears

And waterd heaven with their tears:

Did he smile his work to see?

Did he who made the Lamb make thee?

Tyger, Tyger burning bright,

In the forests of the night:

What immortal hand or eye

Dare frame thy fearful symmetry?

THE BALLADS (OR PICKERING) MANUSCRIPT

([?after 1807])

The Mental Traveller

I traveld thro’ a Land of Men,

A Land of Men & Women too

And heard & saw such dreadful things

As cold Earth wanderers never knew

For there the Babe is born in joy

That was begotten in dire woe

Just as we Reap in joy the fruit

Which we in bitter tears did Sow

And if the Babe is born a Boy

He’s given to a Woman Old

Who nails him down upon a rock,

Catches his Shrieks in Cups of gold.

She binds iron thorns around his head,

She pierces both his hands & feet,

She cuts his heart out at his side

To make it feel both cold & heat.

Her fingers number every Nerve

Just as a Miser counts his gold;

She lives upon his shrieks & cries

And She grows young as he grows old

Till he becomes a bleeding youth

And she becomes a Virgin bright;

Then he rends up his Manacles

And binds her down for his delight.

He plants himself in all her Nerves

Just as a Husbandman his mould

And She becomes his dwelling place

And Garden fruitful Seventy fold.

An aged Shadow soon he fades

Wandring round an Earthly Cot

Full filled all with gems & gold

Which he by industry had got

And these are the gems of the Human Soul,

The rubies & pearls of a lovesick eye,

The countless gold of the akeing heart,

The martyr’s groan & the lover’s sigh.

They are his meat, they are his drink;

He feeds the Beggar & the Poor

And the way faring Traveller;

For ever open is his door.

His grief is their eternal joy;

They make the roofs & walls to ring

Till from the fire on the hearth

A little Female Babe does spring

And she is all of solid fire

And gems & gold that none his hand

Dares stretch to touch her Baby form

Or wrap her in his swaddling- band

But She comes to the Man she loves

If young or old or rich or poor;

They soon drive out the aged Host

A Beggar at another’s door.

He wanders weeping far away

Untill some other take him in

Oft blind & age- bent, sore distrest

Until he can a Maiden win

And to allay his freezing Age

The Poor Man takes her in his arms;

The Cottage fades before his Sight,

The garden & its lovely Charms.

The Guests are scatterd thro’ the land

For the Eye altering alters all;

The Senses roll themselves in fear

And the flat Earth becomes a Ball;

The Stars, Sun, Moon all shrink away

A desart vast without a bound

And nothing left to eat or drink

And a dark desart all around.

The honey of her Infant lips,

The bread & wine of her sweet smile,

The wild game of her roving Eye

Does him to Infancy beguile

For as he eats & drinks he grows

Younger & younger every day

And on the desart wild they both

Wander in terror & dismay.

Like the wild Stag she flees away,

Her fear plants many a thicket wild

While he pursues her night & day

By various arts of Love beguild,

By various arts of Love & Hate

Till the wide desart planted oer

With Labyrinths of wayward Love

Where roams the Lion, Wolf & Boar

Till he becomes a wayward Babe

And she a weeping Woman Old.

Then many a Lover wanders here;

The Sun & Stars are nearer rolld.

The tree brings forth sweet Extacy

To all who in the desart roam

Till many a City there is Built

And many a pleasant Shepherd’s home

But when they find the frowning Babe

Terror strikes thro the region wide;

They cry ‘the Babe, the Babe is Born’

And flee away on Every side

For who dare touch the frowning form

His arm is witherd to its root;

Lions, Boars, Wolves all howling flee

And every Tree does shed its fruit

And none can touch the frowning form

Except it be a Woman Old;

She nails him down upon the Rock

And all is done as I have told.

译者序

这十封信是赖内·马利亚·里尔克（Rainer Maria Rilke，1875—1926）在他三十岁左右时写给一个青年诗人的。里尔克除却他诗人的天职外，还是一个永不疲倦的书简家；他一生写过无数比这十封更亲切、更美的信。但是这十封信却浑然天成，无形中自有首尾；向着青年说得最多。里边他论到诗和艺术，论到两性的爱，严肃和冷嘲，悲哀和怀疑，论到生活和职业的艰难——这都是青年人心里时常起伏的问题。

人们爱把青年比作春，这比喻是正确的。可是彼此的相似点与其说是青年人的晴朗有如春阳的明丽，倒不如从另一方面看，青年人的愁苦、青年人的生长，更像那在阴云暗淡的风里、雨里、寒里演变着的春。因为后者比前者更漫长、沉重而更有意义。我时常在任何一个青年的面前，便联想起荷兰画家梵·高的一幅题作《春》的画：那幅画背景是几所矮小、狭窄的房屋，中央立着一棵桃树或杏树，杈丫的枝干上寂寞地开着几朵粉红色的花。我想，这棵树是经过了长期的风雨，如今还在忍受着春寒，四围是一个穷乏的世界，在枝干内却流动着生命的汁浆。这是一个真实的、没有夸耀的春天！青年人又何尝不是这样呢，生命无时不需要生长，而外边却不永远是日光和温暖的风。他们要担当许多的寒冷和无情、淡漠和误解。他们一切都充满了新鲜的生气，而社会的习俗却是腐旧的，腐旧得像是洗染了许多遍的衣衫。他们觉得内心和外界无法协调，处处受着限制，同时又不能像植物似的那样沉默，他们要向人告诉——他们寻找能够听取他们的话的人，他们寻找能从他们表现力不很充足的话里体会出他们的本意而给以解答的过来人。在这样的寻找中几乎是一百个青年有一百个失望了。但是有一人，本来是一时的兴会，写出一封抒发自己内心状况的信，寄给一个不相识的诗人，那诗人读完了信有所会心，想起自己的青少年时代，仿佛在抚摸他过去身上的伤痕，随即来一封，回答一封，对于每个问题都给一个精辟的回答和分析——同时他却一再声明，人人都要自己料理，旁人是很难给以一些帮助的。

可是他告诉我们，人到世上来，是艰难而孤单。一个个的人在世上好似园里的那些并排着的树。枝枝叶叶也许有些呼应吧，但是它们的根，它们盘结在地下摄取营养的根却各不相干，又沉静，又孤单。人每每为了无谓的喧嚣，忘却生命的根蒂，不能在寂寞中、在对草木鸟兽（它们和我们一样都是生物）的观察中体验一些生的意义，只在人生的表面上永远往下滑过去。这样，自然无所谓艰难，也无所谓孤单，只是隐瞒和欺骗。欺骗和隐瞒的工具，里尔克告诉我们说，是社会的习俗。人在遇见了艰难，遇见了恐怖，遇见了严重的事物而无法应付时，便会躲在习俗的下边去求它的庇护。它成了人们的避难所，却不是安身立命的地方——谁若是要真实地生活，就必须脱离开现成的习俗，自己独立成为一个生存者，担当生活上种种的问题，和我们的始祖所担当过的一样，不能容有一些儿代替。

在这几封信里，处处流露着这种意义，使读者最受感动。当我于1931年的春天，第一次读到这一小册书信时，觉得字字都好似从自己心里流出来，又流回到自己心里，感到一种满足，一种兴奋，禁不住读完一封，便翻译一封，为的是寄给不能读德文的远方的朋友。如今已经过了六年，原书不知又重版多少次，而我的译稿则在行箧内睡了几年觉，始终没有印成书。现在我把它取出来，略加修改付印，仍然是献给不能读德文原文的朋友。

关于里尔克的一生和他的著作，不能在这短短的序中有所叙述。去年他去世十周年纪念时，上海的《新诗》月刊第一卷第三期，曾为他出了一个特辑，读者可以参看。他的作品有一部分已由卞之琳、梁宗岱、冯至译成中文，散见《沉钟》半月刊、《华胥社论文集》、《新诗》月刊、大公报的《文艺》和《艺术周刊》中。

至于收信人的身世，我知道得很少，大半正如他的《引言》上所说的一样，后来生活把他“赶入了正是这位诗人温暖、和蔼而多情的关怀”所为他“防护的境地”了。

1937年5月1日

收信人引言

1902年的深秋——我在维也纳·新城陆军学校的校园里，坐在古老的栗树下读着一本书。我读时是这样专心，几乎没有注意到，那位在我们学校中唯一不是军官的教授、博学而慈祥的校内牧师荷拉捷克（Horaček）是怎样走近我的身边。他从我的手里取去那本书，看看封面，摇摇头。“赖内·马利亚·里尔克的诗？”他深思着问。随后他翻了几页，读了几行，望着远方出神，最后才点头说道：“勒内·里尔克[1]从陆军学生变成一个诗人了。”

于是我知道一些关于这个瘦弱苍白的儿童的事，十五年前他的父母希望他将来做军官，把他送到圣坡尔腾（Sankt-Pölten）的陆军初级学校读书。那时荷拉捷克在那里当牧师，他还能清清楚楚想得起这个陆军学生。他说他是一个平静、严肃、天资很高的少年，喜欢寂寞，忍受着宿舍生活的压抑，四年后跟别的学生一齐升入梅里史·外司克尔心（Mäbrisch-Weisskirchen）地方的陆军高级中学。可是他的体格担受不起，于是他的父母把他从学校里召回，教他在故乡布拉格继续读书。此后他的生活怎样发展，荷拉捷克就不知道了。

按照这一切很容易了解，这时我立即决定把我的诗的试作寄给赖内·马利亚·里尔克，请他批评。我还没有满二十岁，就逼近一种职业的门槛，我正觉得这职业与我的意趣相违，我希望，如果向旁人去寻求理解，就不如向这位《自庆》[2]的作者去寻求了。我无意中在寄诗时还附加一封信，信上自述是这样坦白，我在这以前和以后从不曾向第二个人做过。

几个星期过去，回信来了。信上印着巴黎的戳记，握在手里很沉重；从头至尾写着与信封上同样清晰美丽而固定的字体。于是我同赖内·马利亚·里尔克开始了不断的通信，继续到1908年才渐渐稀疏，因为生活把我赶入了正是诗人的温暖、和蔼而多情的关怀所为我防护的境地。

这些事并不重要。所重要的是下边的这十封信，为了理解里尔克所生活所创造的世界是重要的，为了今日和明天许多生长者和完成者也是重要的。一个伟大的人、旷百世而一遇的人说话的地方，小人物必须沉默。

弗兰斯·克萨危尔·卡卜斯

（Franz Xaver Kappus）

1929年6月，柏林

[1] 里尔克少年时名勒内·里尔克（René Rilke）。（说明：书中脚注均为译者注。）

[2] 《自庆》（Mir zur Feier），里尔克早年的诗集，1899年出版。

第二封信

请你原谅我，亲爱的、尊敬的先生，我直到今天才感谢地想到你2月24日的来信：这段时间我很苦恼，不是病，但是一种流行性感冒类的衰弱困扰我做什么事都没有力气。最后，这种现象一点也没变，我才来到这曾经疗养过我一次的南方的海滨。但是我还未康复，写作还困难，你只得接受这封短信代替我更多的心意。

你自然必须知道，你的每封信都永远使我欢喜，可是你要宽恕我的回答，它也许对你没有什么帮助；因为在根本处，也正是在那最深奥、最重要的事物上我们是无名地孤单；要是一个人能够对别人劝告，甚至帮助时，彼此间必须有许多事情实现了，完成了，一切事物必须有一个完整的安排，才会有一次的效验。

今天我只要向你谈两件事：第一是“暗嘲”（Ironie）[1]：

你不要让你被它支配，尤其是在创造力贫乏的时刻。在创造力丰富的时候你可以试行运用它，当作一种方法去理解人生。纯洁地用，它就是纯洁的，不必因为它而感到羞愧；如果你觉得你同它过于亲密，又怕同它的亲密日见增长，那么你就转向伟大、严肃的事物吧，在它们面前它会变得又渺小又可怜。寻求事物的深处：在深处暗嘲是走不下去的——若是你把它引近伟大的边缘，你应该立即考量这个理解的方式（暗嘲）是不是发自你本性的一种需要。因为在严肃事物的影响下（如果它是偶然发生的），它会脱离了你（如果它真是天生就属于你），它就会强固成为一个严正的工具，而列入你创作艺术的一些方法的行列中。

第二件我今天要向你说的是：

在我所有的书中只有少数的几本是不能离身的，有两部书甚至无论我走到哪里都在我的行囊里。此刻它们也在我的身边：一部是《圣经》，一部是丹麦伟大诗人茵斯·彼得·雅阔布生[2]的书。我忽然想起，不知你读过他的著作没有。这很容易买到，因为有一部分很好的翻译在雷克拉木（Reclam）万有文库中出版。你去买他的《六篇短篇小说》和他的长篇《尼尔·律内》（Niels Lyhne）。你先读前一本的第一篇《摩根斯》（Mogens）。一个世界将要展现在你的面前，一个世界的幸福、丰富、不可捉摸的伟大。请你在这两本书里体验一些时，学你以为值得学的事物，但最重要的是你要爱它们。这种爱将为你得到千千万万的回报，并且，无论你的生活取怎样的途径——我确信它将穿过你的成长的丝纶，在你一切经验、失望与欢悦的线索中成为最重要的一条。

如果我应该说，从谁那里我体验到一些关于创作的本质以及它的深奥与它的永恒的意义，那么我只能说出两个名字：一个是雅阔布生，伟大的诗人；一个是奥古斯特·罗丹[3]，那在现存的艺术家中无人能与比拟的雕刻家。

愿你前途一切成功！

你的：赖内·马利亚·里尔克

1903年4月5日，意大利

比萨（Pisa），维亚雷焦（Viareggio）

[1] Ironie，一译“反讽”。

[2] 茵斯·彼得·雅阔布生（Jens Peter Jacobsen，1847—1885），丹麦小说家、诗人，著有长、短篇小说及诗、随笔等。

[3] 奥古斯特·罗丹（Auguste Rodin，1840—1917），法国雕刻家，里尔克于1902年赴巴黎，拜访罗丹，于1906年曾短期任罗丹秘书。

第三封信

亲爱的、尊敬的先生，你复活节的来信给我许多欢喜；因为它告诉我许多关于你的好消息，并且像你对雅阔布生伟大而可爱的艺术所抒发的意见也可以证明，我把你的生活和生活上的许多问题引到这丰富的世界里来，我并没有做错。

现在你该读《尼尔·律内》了，那是一部壮丽而深刻的书；越读越好像一切都在书中，从生命最轻妙的芬芳到它沉重的果实的厚味。这里没有一件事不能被我们去理解、领会、经验，以及在回忆的余韵中亲切地认识；没有一种体验是过于渺小的，就是很小的事件的开展都像是一个大的命运，并且这命运本身像是一块奇异的广大的织物，每条线都被一只无限温柔的手引来，排在另一条线的旁边，千百条互相持衡。你将要得到首次读这本书时的大幸福，通过无数意料不到的惊奇仿佛在一个新的梦里。可是我能够向你说，往后我们读这些书时永远是个惊讶者，它们永不能失去它们的魅力，连它们首次给予读者的童话的境界也不会失掉。

我们只在那些书中享受日深，感激日笃，观察更为明确而单纯，对于生的信仰更为深沉，在生活里也更幸福博大——

往后你要读那部叙述马丽·葛鲁伯夫人的命运与渴望的奇书[1]，还有雅阔布生的信札、日记、片断，最后还有他的诗（纵使是平庸的德文翻译），也自有不能磨灭的声韵（这时我要劝告你，遇机会时可以去买一部雅阔布生的全集，一切都在里边。共三册，译文很好，莱比锡外根·笛得利许（Eugen Diederichs）书店出版，每册据我所知只卖五六个马克）。

关于那篇非常细腻而精练的短篇小说《这里该有蔷薇……》，你对于作序者不同的意见实在很对。顺便我劝你尽可能少读审美批评的文字——它们多半是一偏之见，已经枯僵在没有生命的硬化中，毫无意义；不然就是乖巧地卖弄笔墨，今天这派得势，明天又是相反的那派。艺术品都是源于无穷的寂寞，没有比批评更难望其边际的了。只有爱能够理解它们，把住它们，认识它们的价值——面对每个这样的说明、评论或导言，你要相信你自己和你的感觉；万一你错误了，你内在的生命自然的成长会慢慢地随时使你认识你的错误，把你引到另外的一条路上。让你的判断力静静地发展，发展跟每个进步一样，是深深地从内心出来，既不能强迫，也不能催促。一切都是时至才能产生。让每个印象与一种情感的萌芽在自身里、在暗中、在不能言说，不知不觉、个人理解所不能达到的地方完成。以深深的谦虚与忍耐去期待一个新的豁然贯通的时刻：这才是艺术地生活，无论是理解或是创造，都一样。

不能计算时间，年月都无效，就是十年有时也等于虚无。艺术家是：不算，不数；像树木似的成熟，不勉强挤它的汁液，满怀信心地立在春日的暴风雨中，也不担心后边没有夏天来到。夏天终归是会来的。但它只向着忍耐的人们走来；他们在这里，好像永恒总在他们面前，无忧无虑地寂静而广大。我天天学习，在我所感谢的痛苦中学习：“忍耐”是一切！

谈到理洽特·德美尔[2]：他的书（同时也可以说他这个人，我泛泛地认识他），我觉得是这样，每逢我读到他的一页好诗时，我常常怕读到第二页，又把前边的一切破坏，将可爱之处变得索然无味。你把他的性格刻画得很对：“情欲地生活，情欲地创作。”——其实艺术家的体验是这样不可思议地接近于性的体验，接近于它的痛苦与它的快乐，这两种现象本来只是同一渴望与幸福的不同的形式。若是可以不说是“情欲”——而说是“性”，是博大的、纯洁的、没有被教会的谬误所诋毁的意义中的“性”，那么他的艺术或者会很博大而永久地重要。他诗人的力是博大的，坚强似一种原始的冲动，在他自身内有勇往直前的韵律爆发出来，像是从雄浑的山中。

但我觉得，这个力并不永远是完全直率的，不无装腔作态（这对于创造者实在是一个严峻的考验，他必须永远不曾意识到、不曾预感到他最好的美德，如果他要保持住那美德的自然而混元的境地）。现在这个鼓动着他的本性的力向性的方面进发，但是它却没有找到它所需要的那个纯洁的人。那里没有一个成熟而纯洁的性的世界，只有一个缺乏广泛的“人性”，而只限于“男性”的世界，充满了情欲、迷醉与不安，为男人旧日的成见与傲慢的心所累，使爱失却了本来的面目。因为他只是作为男人去爱，不是作为人去爱，所以在他的性的感觉中有一些狭窄、粗糙、仇恨、无常，没有永久性的成分存在，减低艺术的价值，使艺术支离晦涩。这样的艺术不会没有污点，它被时代与情欲所渲染，很少能持续存在（多数的艺术却都是这样）。虽然，我们也可以享受其中一些卓绝的地方，可是不要沉溺迷失，变成德美尔世界中的信徒；他的世界是这样无穷地烦恼，充满了奸情、迷乱，同真实的命运距离太远了；真实的命运比起这些暂时的忧郁使人更多地担受痛苦，但也给人以更多的机会走向伟大，更多的勇气向着永恒。

最后关于我的书，我很愿意送你一整份你所喜欢的。但我很穷，并且我的书一出版就不属于我了。我自己不能买，虽然我常常想赠给能够对于我的书表示爱好的人们。

所以我在另纸上写给你我最近出版的书名和出版的书局（只限于最近的；若是算上从前的共有十二三种），亲爱的先生，我把这书单给你，遇机会时你任意订购好了。

我愿意我的书在你的身边。

珍重！

你的：赖内·马利亚·里尔克

1903年4月23日，意大利

比萨，维亚雷焦

[1] 指雅阔布生的长篇小说《马丽·葛鲁伯夫人》（Frau Marie Crubbe）。

[2] 理洽特·德美尔（Richard Dehmel，1863—1920），德国诗人，当时享有盛名。

第四封信

十天前我又苦恼又疲倦地离开了巴黎，到了一处广大的北方的平原，它的旷远、寂静与天空本应使我恢复健康。可是我却走入一个雨的季节，直到今天在风势不定的田野上才闪透出光来；于是我就用这第一瞬间的光明来问候你，亲爱的先生。

亲爱的卡卜斯先生：我很久没有答复你的信，我并没有忘记它——反而它是常常使我从许多信中检出来再读一遍的，并且在你的信里我认识你非常亲切。那是你5月2日的信，你一定记得起这封信。我现在在这远方无边寂静中重读你的信，你那对于生活的美好的忧虑感动我，比我在巴黎时已经感到的还深；在巴黎因为过分的喧嚣，一切都发出异样的声音，使万物战栗。这里周围是伟大的田野，从海上吹来阵阵的风，这里我觉得，那些问题与情感在它们的深处自有它们本来的生命，没有人能够给你解答；因为就是最好的字句也要失去真意，如果它们要解释那最轻妙、几乎不可言说的事物。虽然，我却相信你不会永远得不到解决，若是你委身于那同现在使我的眼目为之一新的相类似的事物。若是你依托自然，依托自然中的单纯，依托于那几乎没人注意到的渺小，这渺小会不知不觉地变得庞大而不能测度；若是你对于微小都怀有这样的爱，作为一个侍奉者质朴地去赢得一些好像贫穷的事物的信赖，那么，一切对于你就较为轻易、较为一致、较为容易和解了，也许不是在那惊讶着退却的理智中，而是在你最深的意识、觉醒与悟解中得到和解。你是这样年轻，一切都在开始，亲爱的先生，我要尽我的所能请求你，对于你心里一切的疑难要多多忍耐，要去爱这些“问题的本身”，像是爱一间锁闭了的房屋，或是一本用别种文字写成的书。现在你不要去追求那些你还不能得到的答案，因为你还不能在生活里体验到它们。一切都要亲身生活。现在你就在这些问题里“生活”吧。或者，不大注意，渐渐会有那遥远的一天，你生活到了能解答这些问题的境地。也许你自身内就负有可能性：去组织、去形成一种特别幸福与纯洁的生活方式；你要向那方面修养——但是，无论什么来到，你都要以广大的信任领受；如果它是从你的意志里、从任何一种内身的窘困里产生的，那么你要好好地负担着它，什么也不要憎恶——“性”，是很难的。可是我们分内的事都很难；其实一切严肃的事都是艰难的，而一切又是严肃的。如果你认识了这一层，并且肯这样从你自身，从你的禀性，从你的经验、你的童年、你的生命力出发，得到一种完全自己的（不是被因袭和习俗所影响的）对于“性”的关系，那么你就不要怕你有所迷惑，或是玷污了你最好的所有。

身体的快感是一种感官的体验，与净洁的观赏或是一个甜美的果实放在我们舌上的净洁的感觉没有什么不同；它是我们所应得的丰富而无穷的经验，是一种对于世界的领悟，是一切领悟的丰富与光华。我们感受身体的快感并不是坏事。所不好的是：几乎一切人都错用了、浪费了这种经验，把它放在生命疲倦的地方当作刺激，当作疏散，而不当作向着顶点的聚精会神。就是饮食，也有许多人使之失去了本意：一方面是“不足”，另一方面是“过度”，都搅混了这个需要的明朗；同样搅混的，是那些生命借以自新的一切深的、单纯的需要。但是一个“个人”能够把它认清，很清晰地生活（如果因为“个人”是要有条件的，那么我们就说是“寂寞的人”），他能够想起，动物和植物中一切的美就是一种爱与渴望的、静静延续着的形式；他能够同看植物一样去看动物，它们忍耐而驯顺地结合、增殖、生长，不是由于生理的享乐也不是由于生理的痛苦，只是顺从需要，这个需要是要比享乐与痛苦伟大，比意志与抵抗还有力。啊，人们要更谦虚地去接受、更严肃地负担这充满大地一直到极小的物体的神秘，并且去承受和感觉，它是怎样重大的艰难，不要把它看得过于容易！对于那只有“一个”的果实，不管它是身体的或是精神的，要有敬畏的心；因为精神的创造也是源于生理的创造，同属于一个本质，并且只像是一种身体快感的更轻妙、更兴奋、更有永久性的再现。至于你所说的“那个思想，去当创造者，去生产、去制作”，绝不能缺少他在世界中得到不断的伟大的证明和实现，也不能缺少从物与动物那里得来的千应万诺——他的享受也只是因此才这样难以形容地美丽而丰富，因为他具有从数百万制作与生产中遗传下来的回忆。在一个创造者思想里会有千百个被人忘记的爱情的良宵又重新苏醒，它们以崇高的情绪填实这个思想。并且那夜间幽会、结合在狂欢中的爱人们，是在做一种严肃的工作，聚集起无数的温存，为任何一个将来后起的诗人的诗歌预备下深厚的力量，去说那难于言说的欢乐。他们把“将来”唤来；纵使他们迷惑，盲目地拥抱，“将来”终于是要到的，一个新人在生长，这里完成一个偶然，在偶然的根处有永恒的规律醒来，一颗富于抵抗的种子就以这个规律闯入那对面迎来的卵球。你不要为表面所误；在深处一切都成为规律。那些把这种神秘虚伪而错误地去生活的人（这样的人本来很多），只是自己失掉了它，而把它往下传递，像是密封的信件，并不知它的内容。你也不要被名称的繁多和事物的复杂所迷惑。超越一切的也许是一个伟大的“母性”作为共同的渴望。那少女的、一种“还无所作为”（你这样说的很好）的本性的美是，它预感着、准备着，悚惧着、渴望着的母性。母亲的美是正在尽职的母性；一个丰富的回忆则存在于老妇的身内。但我以为在男人身内也有母性，无论是身体的或是精神的；他的创造也是一种生产，只要是从最内在的丰满中创造出来的便是生产。大半两性间的关系比人们平素所想的更密切，也许这世界伟大的革新就在于这一点：男人同女人从一切错误的感觉与嫌忌里解放出来，不作为对立面互相寻找，而彼此是兄妹或邻居一般，共同以“人”的立场去工作，以便简捷地、严肃而忍耐地负担那放在他们肩上的艰难的“性”。

凡是将来有一天许多人或能实现的事，现在寂寞的人已经可以起始准备了，用他比较确切的双手来建造。亲爱的先生，所以你要爱你的寂寞，负担那它以悠扬的怨诉给你引来的痛苦。你说，你身边的都同你疏远了，其实这就是你周围扩大的开始。如果你的亲近都离远了，那么你的旷远已经在星空下开展得很广大；你要为你的成长欢喜，可是向那里你不能带进来一个人，要好好对待那些落在后边的人，在他们面前你要稳定自若，不要用你的怀疑苦恼他们，也不要用你的信心或欢悦惊吓他们，这是他们所不能了解的。同他们寻找出一种简单而诚挚的谐和，这种谐和，任凭你自己将来怎么转变，都无须更改；要爱惜他们那种生疏方式的生活，要谅解那些进入老境的人；他们对于你所信任的孤独是畏惧的。要避免去给那在父母与子女间常演出的戏剧增加材料；这要费去许多子女的力，消蚀许多父母的爱，纵使他们的爱不了解我们；究竟是在爱着、温暖着我们。不要向他们问计，也不要计较了解；但要相信那种为你保存下来像是一份遗产似的爱，你要信任在这爱中自有力量存在，自有一种幸福，无须脱离这个幸福才能扩大你的世界。

那很好，你先进入一个职业[1]，它使你成为独立的人，事事完全由你自己料理。你耐心地等着吧，看你内心的生活是不是由于这职业的形式而受到限制。我认为这职业是很艰难很不容易对付的，因为它被广大的习俗所累，并且不容人对于它的问题有个人的意见存在。但是你的寂寞将在这些很生疏的关系中间是你的立足点和家乡，从这里出来你将寻得你一切的道路。

我一切的祝愿都在陪伴着你，我信任你。

你的：赖内·马利亚·里尔克

1903年7月16日，不来梅（Bremen）

沃普斯韦德（Worpswede）

[1] 卡卜斯被任命为奥地利军官。

第五封信

亲爱的、尊敬的先生：

我在佛罗伦萨收到你8月29日的信，现在——两个月了——我才写回信告诉你。请你原谅我的迟延——我在路上不喜欢写信，因为我写信除去必需的纸笔外还要用：一些幽静、寂寞和一个不太生疏的时刻。

我们在六个星期前到了罗马，那时还是个空虚、炎热、时疫流行的罗马，这种环境又添上许多现实生活上安排的困难，更助长围绕我们的不安，简直没有终结，使我们尝尽了异乡漂泊的痛苦。更加之以：罗马（如果我们还不认识它）在我们到达的头几天真令人窒闷悲哀——由于它放射出来的死气沉沉忧郁的博物馆的空气；由于它精华已尽，而又勉强保持着的过去时代的储存（从中滋养着一个可怜的现在）；由于这些，无名的、被学者和语言学家们所维护、经常不断的意大利旅游者所效仿的、对于一切改头换面或是毁败了的物品的过分的估价，根本这些物品也不过是另一个时代另一种生活的偶然的残余，这生活已经不是我们的了，而也不应该是我们的。在日日担心防范的几个星期后，虽还有些纷乱，却终于回到自己的世界，我们才说：这里并不比别的地方有更多的美，这些被世世代代所叹赏的对象，都经过俗手的修补，没有意义，无所包含，没有精神，没有价值——但这里也自有许多美，因为无论什么地方都有它的美。永远生动的流水从古老的沟渠流入这座大城，它们在许多广场的白石盘上欢舞，散入宽阔的贮水池中，昼间泠泠有声，夜晚的声音更为清澈，这里的夜色广大而星光灿烂，拂着习习轻风。并且有许多名园，使人难忘的林荫路与石阶——米霞盎基罗[1]所设计的石阶，那是按着向下流水的姿势建筑的石阶：宽宽地向下一层生出一层，像是后浪接着前浪。由于这样的印象，我们凝聚精神，从那些傲慢的、谈谈讲讲的“多数”（那是多么爱饶舌呀！）回到自身内，慢慢地学习认识“少数”，在少数的事物里延绵着我们所爱的永恒和我们轻轻地分担着的寂寞。

现在我还住在城内卡皮托丘上[2]，离那最美的从罗马艺术中保存下来的马克·奥雷尔[3]骑马式的石像不远；但是在几个星期后我将迁入一个寂静而简单的地方，是一座老的望楼，它深深地消失在一片大园林里，足以躲避城市的喧嚣与纷扰。我将要在那里住一冬，享受那无边的寂静，从这寂静中我期待着良好而丰盛的时间的赠品……

到那时我将常常在家，再给你写较长的信，还要谈到关于你信中的事。今天我必须告诉你的是（这已经是不对了，我没有早一点告诉你），你信中提到的那本书（其中想必有你的作品）没有寄到。是不是从沃普斯韦德给你退回去了（因为包裹不能转到外国）？退回是最好的，我愿意得到证实。希望不要遗失——这在意大利的邮务并不是例外的事——可惜。

我很愿意接到这本书（像是我愿意接到你所写的一切一样）；还有你最近的诗（如果你寄给我），我要永远尽我的所能诚心地一读再读，好好体验。

以多多的愿望和祝福:

你的赖内·马利亚·里尔克

1903年10月29日，罗马

[1] 米霞盎基罗（Michelangelo，1475—1564），意大利文艺复兴时期的雕刻家、画家兼诗人。

[2] 卡皮托（Kapitoe），罗马七座山丘中的一座。

[3] 马克·奥雷尔（Marc Aurel，118—180），罗马皇帝，著有《随感录》流传后世。

第七封信

我的亲爱的卡卜斯先生：

自从我接到你上次的来信，已经过了许久。请你不要见怪。先是工作，随后是事务的干扰，最后是小病，总阻挡着我给你写回信，因为我给你写信是要在良好平静的时刻。现在我觉得好些了（初春的恶劣多变的过渡时期在这里也使人觉得很不舒适），亲爱的卡卜斯先生，我问候你，并且（这是我衷心愿做的事）就我所知道的来回答你。

你看，我把你的十四行诗抄下来了，因为我觉得它美丽简练，是在很适当的形式里产生的。在我所读到的你的诗中，这是最好的一首。现在我又把它誊抄给你，因为我以为这很有意义，并且充满新鲜的体验，在别人的笔下又看到自己的作品。你读这首诗，像是别人作的，可是你将要在最深处感到它怎样更是你的。

这是我的一种快乐，常常读这首十四行诗和你的来信；为了这两件事我感谢你。

在寂寞中你不要徬徨迷惑，由于你自身内有一些愿望要从这寂寞里脱身——也正是这个愿望，如果你平静地、卓越地，像一件工具似的去运用它，它就会帮助你把你的寂寞扩展到广远的地方。一般人（用因袭的帮助）把一切都轻易地去解决，而且按着轻易中最轻易的方面；但这是很显然的，我们必须认定艰难；凡是生存者都认定，自然界中一切都是按照自己的方式生长，防御，表现出来自己，无论如何都要生存，抵抗一切反对的力量。我们知道的很少；但我们必须委身于艰难却是一件永不会丢开我们的信念。寂寞地生存是好的，因为寂寞是艰难的；只要是艰难的事，就有使我们更有理由为它工作。

爱，很好，因为爱是艰难的。以人去爱人：这也许是给与我们的最艰难、最重大的事，是最后的实验与考试，是最高的工作，别的工作都不过是为此而做的准备。所以一切正在开始的青年们还不能爱；他们必须学习。他们必须用他们整个的生命、用一切的力量，集聚他们寂寞、痛苦和向上激动的心去学习爱。可是学习的时期永远是一个长久的专心致志的时期，爱就长期地深深地侵入生命——寂寞，增强而深入的孤独生活，是为了爱着的人。爱的要义并不是什么倾心、献身、与第二者结合（那该是怎样的一个结合呢，如果是一种不明了，无所成就、不关重要的结合？），它对于个人是一种崇高的动力，去成熟，在自身内有所完成，去完成一个世界，是为了另一个人完成一个自己的世界，这对于他是一个巨大的、不让步的要求，把他选择出来，向广远召唤。青年们只应在把这当作课业去工作的意义中（“昼夜不停地探索，去锤炼”）去使用那给予他们的爱。至于倾心、献身，以及一切的结合，还不是他们的事（他们还须长时间地节省、聚集），那是最后的终点，也许是人的生活现在还几乎不能达到的境地。

但是青年们在这方面常常错误得这样深（因为在他们本性中没有忍耐），如果爱到了他们身上，他们便把生命任意抛掷，甚至陷入窒闷、颠倒、紊乱的状态——但随后又该怎样呢？这支离破碎的聚合（他们自己叫作结合，还愿意称为幸福），还能使生活有什么成就吗？能过得去吗？他们的将来呢？这其间每个人都为了别人失掉自己，同时也失掉别人，并且失掉许多还要来到的别人，失掉许多广远与可能性；把那些轻微的充满预感的物体的接近与疏远，改换成一个日暮穷途的景况，什么也不能产生：无非是一些厌恶、失望与贫乏，不得已时便在因袭中寻求补救，有大宗因袭的条例早已准备好了，像是避祸亭一般在这危验的路旁。在各种人类的生活中没有比爱被因袭的习俗附饰得更多的了，是无所不用其极地发明许多救生圈、游泳袋、救护船；社会上的理解用各种样式设备下避难所，因为它倾向于把爱的生活也看作一种娱乐，所以必须轻率地把它形成一种简易、平稳、毫无险阻的生活，跟一切公开的娱乐一样。

诚然也有许多青年错误地去爱，即随随便便地赠予，不能寂寞（一般总是止于这种境地——），他们感到一种失误的压迫，要按照他们自己个人的方式使他们已经陷入的境域变得富有生力和成果——因为他们的天性告诉他们，爱的众多问题还比不上其他的重要的事体，它们可以公开地按照这样或那样的约定来解决；都不过是人与人之间切身问题，它们需要一个在各种情况下都新鲜而特殊、“只是”个人的回答——但，他们已经互相抛掷在一起，再也不能辨别、区分，再也不据有自己的所有，他们怎么能够从他们自身内从这已经埋没的寂寞的深处寻得一条出路呢？

他们的行为都是在通常无可告援的情势下产生的，如果他们以最好的意愿要躲避那落在他们身上的习俗（譬如说结婚），也还是陷入一种不寻常，但仍同样是死气沉沉限于习俗的解决的网中。因为他们周围的一切都是——习俗：从一种很早就聚在一起的、暗淡的结合中表演出来的只是种种限于习俗的行动；这样的紊乱昏迷之所趋的每个关系，都有它的习俗，即使是那最不常见的（普通的意义叫作不道德的）也在内；是的，甚至于“分离”也几乎是一种习俗的步骤，是一种非个性的偶然的决断，没有力量，没有成果。

谁严肃地看，谁就感到，同对于艰难的“死”一样，对于这艰难的“爱”还没有启蒙，还没有解决，还没有什么指示与道路被认识；并且为了我们蒙蔽着、负担着、传递下去，还没有显现的这两个任务，也没有共同的、协议可靠的规律供我们探讨。但是在我们只作为单独的个人起始练习生活的程度内，这些伟大的事物将同单独的个人们在更接近的亲切中相遇。艰难的爱的工作对于我们发展过程的要求是无限的广大，我们作为信从者对于那些要求还不能胜任。但是，如果我们坚持忍耐，把爱作为重担和学业担在肩上，而不在任何浅易和轻浮的游戏中失掉自己（许多人都是一到他们生存中最严肃的严肃面前，便隐藏在游戏的身后）——那么将来继我们而来的人们或许会感到一点小小的进步与减轻；这就够好了。

可是我们现在正应该对于一个单独的人和另一个单独的人的关系，没有成见、如实地观察；我们试验着在这种关系里生活，面前并没有前例。可是在时代的变更中已经有些事，对于我们小心翼翼的开端能有所帮助了。

少女和妇女，在她们新近自己的发展中，只暂时成为男人恶习与特性的模仿者，男人职业的重演者。经过这样不稳定的过程后，事实会告诉我们，妇女只是从那（常常很可笑的）乔装的成功与变化中走过，以便把她们自己的天性从男性歪曲的影响中洗净。至于真的生命是更直接、更丰富、更亲切地在妇女的身内，根本上她们早应该变成比男人更纯净、更人性的人；男人没有身体的果实，只生活于生活的表面之下，傲慢而急躁，看轻他们要去爱的事物。如果妇女将来把这“只是女性”的习俗在她们外生活的转变中脱去，随后那从痛苦与压迫里产生出的妇女的“人性”就要见诸天日了，这是男人们现在还没有感到的，到那时他们将从中受到惊奇和打击。有一天（现在北欧的国家里已经有确切的证明）新的少女来到，并且所谓妇女这个名词，她不只是当作男人的对立体来讲，却含有一些独立的意义，使我们不再想到“补充”与“界限”，只想到生命与生存——女性的人。

这个进步将要把现在谬误的爱的生活转变（违背着落伍的男人们的意志），从根本更改，形成一种人对于人，不是男人对于女人的关系。并且这更人性的爱（它无限地谨慎而精细，良好而明晰地在结合与解脱中完成），它将要同我们辛辛苦苦地预备着的爱相似，它存在于这样的情况里：两个寂寞相爱护，相区分，相敬重。

还有：你不要以为，那在你童年曾经有过一次的伟大的爱已经失却了；你能说吗，那时并没有伟大的良好的愿望在你的生命里成熟，而且现在你还从中吸取养分？我相信那个爱是强有力地永在你的回忆中，因为它是你第一次的深的寂寞，也是你为你生命所做的第一次的内心的工作——祝你一切安好，亲爱的卡卜斯先生！

你的：赖内·马利亚·里尔克

1904年5月14日，罗马

十四行诗

我生命里有一缕阴深的苦恼

颤动，它不叹息，也不抱怨。

我梦里边雪一般的花片

是我寂静的长日的祭祷。

但是大问题梗住我的小道。

我变得渺小而凄凉

像是走过一座湖旁，

我不敢量一量湖水的波涛。

一种悲哀侵袭我，这般愁惨

好似暗淡的夏夜的苍茫

时时闪露出一点星光；

于是我的双手向着爱试探，

因为我想祈求那样的声调，

我热烈的口边还不能找到……

（弗兰斯·卡卜斯）

第八封信

亲爱的卡卜斯先生，我想再和你谈一谈，虽然我几乎不能说对你有所帮助以及对你有一些用处的话。你有过很多大的悲哀，这些悲哀都已过去了。你说，这悲哀的过去也使你非常苦恼。但是，请你想一想，是不是这些大的悲哀并不曾由你生命的中心走过？当你悲哀的时候，是不是在你生命里并没有许多变化，在你本性的任何地方也无所改变？危险而恶劣的是那些悲哀，我们把它们运送到人群中，以遮盖它们的声音；像是敷敷衍衍治疗的病症，只是暂时退却，过些时又更可怕地发作；它们聚集在体内，成为一种没有生活过、被摈斥、被遗弃的生命，能使我们死去。如果我们能比我们平素的知识所能达到的地方看得更远一点，稍微越过我们预感的前哨，那么也许我们将会以比担当我们的欢悦更大的信赖去担当我们的悲哀。因为它们（悲哀）都是那些时刻，正当一些新的、陌生的事物侵入我们的生命；我们的情感蜷伏于怯懦的局促的状态里，一切都退却，形成一种寂静，于是这无人认识的“新”就立在中间，沉默无语。

我相信几乎我们一切的悲哀都是紧张的瞬间，这时我们感到麻木，因为我们不再听到诧异的情感生存。因为我们要同这生疏的闯入者独自周旋；因为我们平素所信任的与习惯的都暂时离开了我们；因为我们正处在一个不能容我们立足的过程中。可是一旦这不期而至的新事物迈进我们的生命，走进我们的心房，在心的最深处化为无有，溶解在我们的血液中，悲哀也就因此过去了。我们再也经验不到当时的情形。这很容易使我们相信前此并没有什么发生；其实我们却是改变了，正如一所房子，走进一位新客，它改变了。我们不能说，是谁来了，我们往后也许不知道，可是有许多迹象告诉我们，在“未来”还没有发生之前，它就以这样的方式潜入我们的生命，以便在我们身内变化。所以我们在悲哀的时刻要安于寂寞，多注意，这是很重要的，因为当我们的“未来”潜入我们的生命的瞬间，好像是空虚而枯僵，但与那从外边来的、为我们发生的喧嚣而意外的时刻相比，是同生命接近得多。我们悲哀时越沉静，越忍耐，越坦白，这新的事物也越深、越清晰地走进我们的生命，我们也就更好地保护它，它也就更多地成为我们自己的命运；将来有一天它“发生”了（就是说：它从我们的生命里出来向着别人走进），我们将在最内心的地方感到我们同它亲切而接近。并且这是必要的。是必要的——我们将渐渐地向那方面发展——凡是迎面而来的事，是没有生疏的，都早已属于我们了。人们已经变换过这么多运转的定义，将来会渐渐认清，我们所谓的命运是从我们“人”里出来，并不是从外边向着我们“人”走进。只因为有许多人，当命运在他们身内生存时，他们不曾把它吸收，化为己有，所以他们也认不清，有什么从他们身内出现；甚至如此生疏，他们在仓皇恐惧之际，以为命运一定是正在这时走进他们的生命，因为他们确信自己从来没有见过这样类似的事物。正如对于太阳的运转曾经有过长期的蒙惑那样，现在人们对于未来的运转，也还在同样地自欺自蔽。其实“未来”站得很稳，亲爱的卡卜斯先生，但是我们动转在这无穷无尽的空间。

我们怎么能不感觉困难呢？

如果我们再谈到寂寞，那就会更明显，它根本不是我们所能选择或弃舍的事物。我们都是寂寞的。人能够自欺，好像并不寂寞。只不过如此而已。但是，那有多么好呢，如果我们一旦看出，我们都正在脱开这欺骗的局面。在其间我们自然要发生眩昏；因为平素我们的眼睛看惯了的一切这时都忽然失去，再也没有亲近的事物，一切的远方都是无穷的旷远。谁从他的屋内没有准备，没有过程，忽然被移置在一脉高山的顶上，他必会有类似的感觉；一种无与伦比的不安被交付给无名的事物，几乎要把他毁灭。他或许想象会跌落，或者相信会被抛掷在天空，或者粉身碎骨，他的头脑必须发现多么大的谎话，去补救、去说明他官感迷失的状态。一切的距离与尺度对于那寂寞的人就有了变化；从这些变化中忽然会有许多变化发生。跟在山顶上的那个人一样，生出许多非常的想象与稀奇的感觉，它们好像超越了一切能够担当的事体。但那是必要的，我们也体验这种情况。我们必须尽量广阔地承受我们的生存；一切，甚至闻所未闻的事物，都可能在里边存在。根本那是我们被要求的唯一的勇气：勇敢地面向我们所能遇到的最稀奇、最吃惊、最不可解的事物。就因为许多人在这意义中是怯懦的，所以使生活受了无限的损伤；人们称作“奇象”的那些体验、所谓“幽灵世界”、死，以及一切同我们相关联的事物，它们都被我们日常的防御挤出生活之外，甚至我们能够接受它们的感官都枯萎了。关于“神”，简直就不能谈论了。但是对于不可解的事物的恐惧，不仅使个人的生存更为贫乏，并且人与人的关系也因之受到限制，正如从有无限可能性的河床里捞出来，放在一块荒芜不毛的岸上。因为这不仅是一种惰性，使人间的关系极为单调而陈腐地把旧事一再重演，而且是对于任何一种不能预测、不堪胜任的新的生活的畏缩。但是如果有人对于一切有了准备，无论什么，甚至最大的哑谜，也不置之度外，那么他就会把同别人的关系，当作生动着的事物去体验，甚至充分理解自己的存在。正如我们把各个人的存在看成一块较大或较小的空间，那么大部分人却只认识了他们空间的一角、一块窗前的空地，或是他们走来走去的一条窄道。这样他们就有一定的安定。可是那危险的不安定是更人性的，它能促使爱伦·坡[1]的故事里的囚犯摸索他们可怕的牢狱的形状，而熟悉他们住处内不可言喻的恐怖。但我们不是囚犯，没有人在我们周围布置了陷阱，没有什么来恐吓我们，苦恼我们。我们在生活中像是在最适合于我们的原素里，况且我们经过几千年之久的适应和生活这样地相似了，如果我们静止不动，凭借一种成功的模拟，便很难同我们周围的一切有所区分。我们没有理由不信任我们的世界，因为它并不敌对我们。如果它有恐惧，就是我们的恐惧；它有难测的深渊，这深渊是属于我们的；有危险，我们就必须试行去爱这些危险。若是我们把我们的生活，按照那叫我们必须永远把握艰难的原则来处理，那么现在还最生疏的事物就会变得最亲切、最忠实的了。我们怎么能忘却那各民族原始时都有过的神话呢；恶龙在最紧急的瞬间变成公主的那段神话；也许我们生活中一切的恶龙都是公主们，她们只是等候着，美丽而勇敢地看一看我们。也许一切恐怖的事物在最深处是无助的，向我们要求救助。

亲爱的卡卜斯先生，如果有一种悲哀在你面前出现，它是从未见过的那样广大，如果有一种不安，像光与云影似的掠过你的行为与一切工作，你不要恐惧。你必须想，那是有些事在你身边发生了；那是生活没有忘记你，它把你握在手中，它永不会让你失落。为什么你要把一种不安、一种痛苦、一种忧郁置于你的生活之外呢，可是你还不知道，这些情况在为你做什么工作。为什么你要这样追问，这一切是从哪里来，要向哪里去呢？可是你要知道，你是在过渡中，要愿望自己有所变化。如果你的过程里有一些是病态的，你要想一想，病就是一种方法，有机体用以从生疏的事物中解放出来；所以我们只需让它生病，使它有整个的病发作，因为这才是进步。亲爱的卡卜斯先生，现在你自身内有这么多的事发生，你要像一个病人似的忍耐，又像一个康复者似的自信；你也许同时是这两个人。并且你还须是看护自己的医生。但是在病中常常有许多天，医生除了等候以外，什么事也不能做。这就是（尽你是你的医生的时候），现在首先必须做的事。

对于自己不要过甚地观察。不要从对你发生的事物中求得很快的结论，让它们单纯地自生自长吧。不然你就很容易用种种（所谓道德的）谴责回顾你的过去，这些过去自然和你现在遇到的一切很有关系。凡是从你童年的迷途、愿望、渴望中在你身内继续影响着的事，它们并不让你回忆，供你评判。一个寂寞而孤单的童年非常的情况是这样艰难，这样复杂，受到这么多外来的影响，同时又这样脱开了一切现实生活的关联，纵使在童年有罪恶，我们也不该简捷了当地称作罪恶。对于许多名称，必须多多注意；常常只是犯罪的名称使生命为之破碎，而不是那无名的、个人的行为本身，至于这个行为也许是生活中规定的必要，能被生活轻易接受的。因为你把胜利估量得过高，所以你觉得力的消耗如此巨大；胜利并不是你认为已经完成的“伟大”，纵使你觉得正确；“伟大”是你能以一些真的、实在的事物代替欺骗。不然你的胜利也不过是一种道德上的反应，没有广大的意义，但是它却成为你生活的一个段落。亲爱的卡卜斯先生，关于你的生活，我有很多的愿望。你还记得吗，这个生活是怎样从童年里出来，向着“伟大”渴望？我看着，它现在又从这些伟大前进，渴望更伟大的事物。所以艰难的生活永无止境，但因此生长也无止境。

如果我还应该向你说一件事，那么就是：你不要相信，那试行劝慰你的人是无忧无虑地生活在那些有时对你有益的简单而平静的几句话里。他的生活有许多的辛苦与悲哀，他远远地专诚帮助你。不然，他就绝不能找到那几句话。

你的：赖内·马利亚·里尔克

1904年8月12日，瑞典

弗拉底（Flädie），波格比庄园（Borgeby Cà rb）

[1] 爱伦·坡（Allan Poe，1809—1849），美国小说家、诗人，以描写神秘恐怖故事知名。这里指的是他的一篇小说《深坑和钟摆》（The Pit and the Pendulum），描述一个被判处死刑的人在黑暗的牢狱里摸索墙壁、猜度牢狱形状的恐怖情况。

第九封信

我亲爱的卡卜斯先生：

在这没有通信的时期内，我一半是在旅途上，一半是事务匆忙，使我不能写信。今天我写信也是困难的，因为我已经写了许多封，手都疲倦了。若是我能以口述给旁人写，我还能向你说许多，可是现在你只好接受这寥寥几行来报答你的长信。

亲爱的卡卜斯先生，我常常思念你，并且以这样专诚的愿望思念你，总要对你有所帮助。但是我的信到底能不能帮助你，我却常常怀疑。你不要说：它们能够帮助你。你只安心接受这些信吧，不必说感谢的话，让我们等着，看将要有什么事情来到。

现在我对于你信里个别的字句加以探讨，大半是没有用的；因为我关于你疑惑的倾向，关于体内外生活和谐的不可能，关于另外苦恼着你的一切——我所能说的，还依然是我已经说过的话：还是愿你自己有充分的忍耐去担当，有充分单纯的心去信仰；你将会越来越信任艰难的事物和你在众人中间感到的寂寞。以外就是让生活自然进展。请你相信：无论如何，生活是合理的。

谈到情感：凡是使你集中向上的情感都是纯洁的；但那只捉住你本性的一方面，对你有所伤害的情感是不纯洁的。凡是在你童年能想到的事都是好的。凡能够使你比你从前最美好的时刻还更丰富的，都是对的。各种提高都是好的，如果它是在你“全”血液中，如果它不是迷醉，不是忧郁，而是透明到底的欢悦。你了解我的意思吗？

就是你的怀疑也可以成为一种好的特性，若是你好好“培养”它。它必须成为明智的，它必须成为批判——当它要伤害你一些事物时，你要问它，这些事物“为什么”丑恶，向它要求证据，考问它，你也许见它仓皇失措，也许见它表示异议。但你不要让步，你同它辩论，每一回都要多多注意，立定脚步，终于有一天它会从一个破坏者变成你的一个最好的工作者——或许在一切从事于建设你的生活的工作者中它是最聪明的一个。

亲爱的卡卜斯先生，这是我今天所能向你说的一切。我附寄给你我一篇短的作品的抽印本[1]，这是在布拉格出版的《德意志工作》中发表的。在那里我继续着同你谈生和死，以及它们的伟大与美丽。

你的：赖内·马利亚·里尔克

1904年11月4日，瑞典

永瑟勒德（Jonsered），弗卢堡（Fruburg）

[1] 系里尔克的散文诗《旗手克里斯多夫·里尔克的爱与死之歌》（Die Weise Von Liebe und Tod des Cornets Christoph Rilke）。

第十封信

亲爱的卡卜斯先生，你该知道，我得你这封美好的信，我是多么欢喜。你给我的消息是真实、诚挚，又像你从前那样，我觉得很好，我越想越感到那实在是好的消息。我本来想在圣诞节的晚间给你写信，但是这一冬我多方从事没有间断的工作，这古老的节日是这样快地走来了，使我没有时间去做我必须处理的事，更少写信。

但是在节日里我常常思念你，我设想你是怎样寂静地在你寂寞的军垒中生活，两旁是空旷的高山，大风从南方袭来，好像要把这些山整块地吞了下去。

这种寂静必须是广大无边，好容许这样的风声风势得以驰骋，如果我想到，更加上那辽远的海也在你面前同时共奏，像是太古的谐音中最深处的旋律，那么我就希望你能忠实地、忍耐地让这大规模的寂寞在你身上工作，它不再能从你的生命中消灭；在一切你要去生活要去从事的事物中，它永远赓续着像是一种无名的势力，并且将确切地影响你，有如祖先的血在我们身内不断地流动，和我们自己的血混为唯一的、绝无仅有的一体，在我们生命的无论哪一个转折。

是的：我很欢喜，你据有这个固定的、可以言传的存在，有职称，有制服，有任务，有一切把得定、范围得住的事物，它们在这同样孤立而人数不多的军队环境中，接受严肃与必要的工作，它们超越军队职业的游戏与消遣意味着一种警醒的运用，它们不仅容许，而且正好培养自主的注意力。我们要在那些为我们工作、时时置我们于伟大而自然的事物面前的情况中生活，这是必要的一切。

艺术也是一种生活方式，无论我们怎样生活，都能不知不觉地为它准备；每个真实的生活都比那些虚假的、以艺术为号召的职业跟艺术更为接近，它们炫耀一种近似的艺术，实际上却否定了、损伤了艺术的存在，如整个的报章文字、几乎一切的批评界、四分之三号称文学和要号称文学的作品，都是这样。我很高兴，简捷地说，是因为你经受了易于陷入的危险，寂寞而勇敢地生活在任何一处无情的现实中。即将来到的一年会使你在这样的生活里更为坚定。

你的：赖内·马利亚·里尔克

1908年，圣诞节第二日，巴黎

Preface

In late autumn 1902 it was – I was sitting under ancient chestnut trees in the gardens of the Military Academy in Wiener Neustadt with a book. I was so absorbed by my reading that I hardly noticed it when the only one of our teachers who was not an army officer, Horaček, the learned and good- natured chaplain of the Academy, came and joined me. He took the volume from my hand, looked at the cover and shook his head. ‘Poems by Rainer Maria Rilke?’he asked thoughtfully. He leafed through its pages, ran his eyes over a few verses, looked reflectively into the distance and finally nodded. ‘So, our pupil René Rilke has become a poet.’

And I was told about the slight, pale boy sent by his parents more than fifteen years before to the Military Lower School in Sankt Pölten so that he might later become an officer. In those days Horaček had worked there as the chaplain and he still remembered his former pupil well. He described him as a quiet, serious, highly gifted child, who liked to keep himself to himself, put up with the discipline of boarding- school life patiently and after the fourth year moved on with the others to the Military Upper School in Mährisch- Weisskirchen. There his constitution proved not to be resilient enough, and so his parents took him out of the establishment and had him continue his studies at home in Prague. What path his career had taken after that Horaček was unable to say.

Given all this it is probably not difficult to understand that I decided that very hour to send my poetic efforts to Rainer Maria Rilke and ask him for his verdict. Not yet twenty years old and on the verge of going into a profession which I felt was directly opposed to my true inclinations, I thought that if anyone was going to understand my situation it was the author of the book To Celebrate Myself. And without its being my express intention, my verses were accompanied by a letter in which I revealed myself more unreservedly than to anyone ever before, or to anyone since.

Many weeks went by before an answer came. The letter with its blue seal bore a Paris postmark, weighed heavy in the hand and displayed on the envelope the same clarity, beauty and assurance of hand with which the content itself was written from the first line to the last. And so my regular correspondence with Rainer Maria Rilke began, lasting until 1908 and then gradually petering out because life forced me into domains which the poet’s warm, tender and moving concern had precisely wanted to protect me from.

But that is unimportant. The only important thing is the ten letters that follow, important for the insight they give into the world in which Rainer Maria Rilke lived and worked, and important too for many people engaged in growth and change, today and in the future. And where a great and unique person speaks, the rest of us should be silent.

Franz Xaver Kappus

Berlin, June 1929

Paris, 17 February 1903

Dear Sir,

Your letter only reached me a few days ago. Let me thank you for the great and endearing trust it shows. There is little more I can do. I cannot go into the nature of your verses, for any critical intention is too remote from me. There is nothing less apt to touch a work of art than critical words: all we end up with there is more or less felicitous misunderstandings. Things are not all as graspable and sayable as on the whole we are led to believe; most events are unsayable, occur in a space that no word has ever penetrated, and most unsayable of all are works of art, mysterious existences whose life endures alongside ours, which passes away.

Having begun with this preliminary remark, all I will go on to say is that your verses have no identity of their own, though they do have tacit and concealed hints of something personal. I feel that most clearly in the last poem, ‘My Soul’. There something individual is trying to come into words, to find its manner. And in the lovely poem ‘To Leopardi’ perhaps a kind of affinity with this great and solitary man develops. Still, the poems are not yet anything in themselves, nothing self sufficient, not even the last one and the one to Leopardi. The kind letter you wrote accompanying them does not fail to make many of the shortcomings I sensed in reading your verses explicable, without for all that being able to give them a name.

You ask whether your verses are good. You ask me that. You have asked others, before. You send them to magazines. You compare them with other poems, and you worry when certain editors turn your efforts down. Now(since you have allowed me to offer you advice) let me ask you to give up all that. You are looking to the outside, and that above all you should not be doing now. Nobody can advise you and help you, nobody. There is only one way. Go into yourself. Examine the reason that bids you to write; check whether it reaches its roots into the deepest region of your heart, admit to yourself whether you would die if it should be denied you to write. This above all: ask yourself in your night’s quietest hour: must I write? Dig down into yourself for a deep answer. And if it should be affirmative, if it is given to you to respond to this serious question with a loud and simple ‘I must ’, then construct your life according to this necessity; your life right into its most inconsequential and slightest hour must become a sign and witness of this urge. Then approach nature. Then try, like the first human being, to say what you see and experience and love and lose. Don’t write love poems; avoid at first those forms which are too familiar and habitual: they are the hardest, for you need great maturity and strength to produce something of your own in a domain where good and sometimes brilliant examples have been handed down to us in abundance. For this reason, flee general subjects and take refuge in those offered by your own day to day life; depict your sadnesses and desires, passing thoughts and faith in some kind of beauty – depict all this with intense, quiet, humble sincerity and make use of whatever you find about you to express yourself, the images from your dreams and the things in your memory. If your everyday life seems to lack material, do not blame it; blame yourself, tell yourself that you are not poet enough to summon up its riches, for there is no lack for him who creates and no poor, trivial place. And even if you were in a prison whose walls did not let any of the sounds of the world outside reach your senses – would you not have your childhood still, this marvellous, lavish source, this treasure house of memories? Turn your attention towards that. Attempt to raise the sunken sensations of this distant past; your self will become the stronger for it, your loneliness will open up and become a twilit dwelling in which the noise other people make is only heard far off. And if from this turn inwards, from this submersion in your own world, there come verses, then it will not occur to you to ask anyone whether they are good verses. Nor will you attempt to interest magazines in these bits of work: for in them you will see your beloved natural possessions, a piece, and a voice, of your life. A work of art is good if it has arisen out of necessity. The verdict on it lies in this nature of its origin: there is no other. For this reason, my dear Sir, the only advice I have is this: to go into yourself and to examine the depths from which your life springs; at its source you will find the answer to the question of whether you have to write. Accept this answer as it is, without seeking to interpret it. Perhaps it will turn out that you are called to be an artist. Then assume this fate and bear it, its burden and its greatness, without ever asking after the rewards that may come from outside. For he who creates must be a world of his own and find everything within himself and in the natural world that he has elected to follow.

But perhaps even after this descent into yourself and into your solitariness you will have to give up the idea of becoming a poet (the feeling that one could live without writing is enough, as I said, to make it something one should never do). But even then, to have taken pause in the way I am asking you to will not have been in vain. Whatever happens, your life will find its own paths from that point on, and that they may be good, productive and far reaching is something I wish for you more than I can say.

What else should I say to you? I think everything has been emphasized as it should be; and all I wanted to do in the end was advise you to go through your development quietly and seriously; you cannot disrupt it more than by looking outwards and expecting answers from without to questions that only your innermost instinct in your quietest moments will perhaps be able to answer.

I was delighted to find Professor Horaček’s name in your letter; I retain a great admiration for this kindhearted scholar, a gratitude that has endured over the years. Could you please pass on these sentiments to him; it is very kind of him still to remember me, and I much appreciate it.

The verses you were so good as to entrust me with I am sending back to you along with this letter. Thank you again for the extent and the warmth of your trust – as well as I can, I have attempted with this sincere reply to make myself a little worthier of it than, as a stranger, I really am.

With all devotion and sympathy,

Rainer Maria Rilke

Viareggio near Pisa (Italy), 5 April 1903

You must forgive me, my dear Sir, for only attending to your letter of 24 February today: the whole time I have been under the weather, not ill exactly but oppressed by an influenza like feebleness which has made me incapable of anything. And in the end, when all else had failed, I travelled down to this southern coast, whose beneficial effects have helped me in the past. But I’m still not well again, writing is difficult, and so you must take these few lines as if there were more of them.

First of all you should know that every letter from you will always be a pleasure, and you only need to be understanding with regard to the replies, which often, maybe, will leave you with empty hands; for at bottom, and particularly in the deepest and most important things, we are unutterably alone, and for one person to be able to advise, let alone help, another, a great deal must come about, a great deal must come right, a whole constellation of things must concur for it to be possible at all.

There are just two things I wanted to say to you today:

Irony: don’t let yourself be ruled by it, especially not in uncreative moments. In creative ones try to make use of it as one means among many to get a grasp on life. Used purely, it too is pure, and there is no need to be ashamed of it; and if you feel too familiar with it, if you fear your intimacy is growing too much, then turn towards great and serious subjects, next to which irony becomes small and helpless. Seek out the depths of things: irony will never reach down there – and if in so doing you come up against something truly great, inquire whether this way of relating to things originates in a necessary part of your being. For under the influence of serious things irony will either fall away (if it is something incidental) or on the contrary (if it really belongs to you in a native way) it will gain strength and so become a serious tool and take its place among the means with which you will be bound to create your art.

And the second thing I wanted to tell you today is this:

Of all my books there are only a few I cannot do without, and two are always among my effects, wherever I am. I have them with me here: the Bible, and the books of the great Danish writer Jens Peter Jacobsen. I wonder whether you know his works. They are easy to get hold of, because a number of them are available in good translations in Reclam’s Universal Bibliothek. Get hold of the little volume Six Novellas by J. P. Jacobsen, and his novel Niels Lyhne, and begin with the first story in the first of these volumes which is called ‘Mogens’. A world will come over you, the joy, the richness, the incomprehensible greatness of a new world. Live in these books for a while, learn from them what seems to be worth learning, but above all love them. This love will be repaid you thousands and thousands of times, and however your life may turn out – this love, I am sure of it, will run through the weave of your becoming as one of the most important threads of all among the other threads of your experiences, disappointments and joys.

If I had to say from whom I have learnt anything about the nature of artistic creation, about its profundity and eternity, there are only two names I can give: Jacobsen’s, the great, great poet, and Auguste Rodin’s, the sculptor who has no equal among all artists now alive. –

All success on your paths! Yours,

Rainer Maria Rilke

Viareggio near Pisa (Italy), 23 April 1903

Your Easter letter, my dear Sir, gave me a great deal of pleasure, for it had many good things to report, and the way you spoke about Jacobsen’s great and generous art showed me that I was not mistaken in conducting your life and its many questions to this source of plenty.

Now Niels Lyhne will reveal itself to you, a book full of splendours and depths; the more often one reads it, it seems to contain everything, from life’s faintest scent to the full, grand savour of its heaviest fruits. There is nothing in it that has not been understood, grasped, lived, and known in memory’s trembling, lingering resonance; no experience is too slight, and the merest occurrence unfolds like a fate, and fate itself is like a wonderful, vast fabric in which every thread is drawn by an infinitely tender hand and laid next to another, held in place and supported by a hundred others. You will experience the immense pleasure of reading this book for the first time, and will pass through its innumerable surprises as if in a new dream. But I can tell you that later too one always traverses these books with the same astonishment and that they lose nothing of the wondrous power, relinquish none of the magical qualities, which they lavish on the reader the first time round.

One just takes more and more enjoyment in them, one grows ever more grateful and somehow better and simpler in seeing the world, deeper in one’s faith in life and happier and larger in living. –

And later you must read the wonderful book of the fate and longings of Marie Grubbe and Jacobsen’s letters and diaries and fragments and finally his verse which (even if the translations are only moderate) has an infinite resonance. (To do so, I’d suggest you buy the lovely collected edition of Jacobsen’s works – which has all this in it – if you get the opportunity. It came out in three volumes and in good translations with Eugen Diederichs in Leipzig and costs, I believe, only 5 or 6 marks a volume.)

In your opinion on ‘Here roses should stand . . .’ (a work of such incomparable subtlety and form) you are of course absolutely in the right, and inviolably so, whatever the author of the preface may have to say. And let me at once make this request: read as little as possible in the way of aesthetics and criticism – it will either be partisan views, fossilized and made meaningless in its lifeless rigidity, or it will be neat wordplay, where one opinion will triumph one day and the opposite the next. Works of art are infinitely solitary and nothing is less likely to reach them than criticism. Only love can grasp them and hold them and do them justice. – With regard to any such disquisition, review or introduction, trust yourself and your instincts; even if you go wrong in your judgement, the natural growth of your inner life will gradually, over time, lead you to other insights. Allow your verdicts their own quiet untroubled development which like all progress must come from deep within and cannot be forced or accelerated. Everything must be carried to term before it is born. To let every impression and the germ of every feeling come to completion inside, in the dark, in the unsayable, the unconscious, in what is unattainable to one’s own intellect, and to wait with deep humility and patience for the hour when a new clarity is delivered: that alone is to live as an artist, in the understanding and in one’s creative work.

These things cannot be measured by time, a year has no meaning, and ten years are nothing. To be an artist means: not to calculate and count; to grow and ripen like a tree which does not hurry the flow of its sap and stands at ease in the spring gales without fearing that no summer may follow. It will come. But it comes only to those who are patient, who are simply there in their vast, quiet tranquillity, as if eternity lay before them. It is a lesson I learn every day amid hardships I am thankful for: patience is all!

richard dehmel: With his books (as also, by the way, with the man himself whom I know slightly) I always find myself, when I’ve come upon one of his best pages, fearful of the next, which can always undo it all again and turn what was so lovely into something base. You sum him up very well with your phrase about ‘living and writing in rut’. – And indeed artistic experience lies so incredibly close to sexual experience, to its pains and pleasures, that both phenomena are really just different forms of one and the same desire and felicity. And if instead of speaking of ‘rut’ we could say ‘sex’, sex in the large, capacious, pure sense, not rendered suspect by any misapprehensions stemming from the Church, his art would be very great and infinitely important. His poetic power is immense, as vigorous as instinct; it has its own reckless rhythms running through it and bursts out of him as if from a mountain.

But this power seems not always to be quite genuine and free of affectation. (But then that is one of the severest tests of an artist: he must always remain innocent and unconscious of his greatest virtues if he is to avoid depriving them of their uninhibitedness and purity.) And when this power, coursing through his being, reaches his sexuality, it doesn’t find quite the pure human being it needs. The world of sexuality it finds is not entirely mature and pure, it is not human enough, only virile, rut, intoxication, restlessness, and weighed down by the old prejudices and arrogance with which men have disfigured and overburdened love. Because he loves only as a man, not as a human being, there is in his sense of sexuality something narrow, seemingly savage, hateful, time bound, uneternal that diminishes his art and makes it ambivalent and doubtful. It is not without blemish, it is marked by the times and by passion, and little of it will prevail and endure. (But that’s the case with most art!) In spite of all this one can still take deep pleasure in what is great about his work and must just make sure not to lose oneself to it and become an acolyte of this Dehmel world which is so full of anxiety, of adultery and confusion, and remote from the real destinies, which create more suffering than these passing afflictions but also give more opportunity for greatness and more courage to make something that will last.

To come to my own books, really I’d like to send you all those that might give pleasure. But I am very poor, and as soon as my books have appeared they cease to belong to me. I cannot buy them myself and, as I’d so often like to, give them to those who would value and look after them.

For that reason I have written down for you on a slip of paper the titles (and publishing houses) of my recent books (that is the very newest, altogether I must have published 12 or 13) and must leave it to you, dear Sir, to order one or two of them if they take your fancy.

I shall be glad to know that my books are with you.

All good wishes,

Yours,

Rainer Maria Rilke

at present in Worpswede near Bremen, 16 July 1903

About ten days ago I left Paris, ailing and very weary, and travelled to these great northern plains whose vastness and quiet and sky are supposed to return my health to me. But I drove into unceasing rain which only today is beginning to clear a bit over the restless, windswept land; and I’m using this first moment of brightness to send you a greeting, my dear Sir.

My dear Mr Kappus: I have left your letter unanswered for a long time – not that I had forgotten it; on the contrary, it was the kind of letter one reads again, coming across it among one’s papers, and I recognized you in it as if I were in your presence. It was your letter of the second of May – I’m sure you remember it. When, as I do now, I read it in the great calm of these expanses, I am touched by your fine concern for life, even more than I was in Paris where everything has a different tone and gets lost in the immense din which sets things trembling. Here, surrounded as I am by a mighty stretch of land over which the winds blow in from seas, here I feel that no human being anywhere can respond to those questions and feelings that have a profound life of their own; for even the best of us get the words wrong when we want them to express such intangible and almost unsayable things. But all the same I believe that you need not remain without solution if you hold to things like those now refreshing my eyes. If you hold close to nature, to what is simple in it, to the small things people hardly see and which all of a sudden can become great and immeasurable; if you have this love for what is slight, and quite unassumingly, as a servant, seek to win the confidence of what seems poor – then everything will grow easier, more unified and somehow more conciliatory, not perhaps in the intellect, which, amazed, remains a step behind, but in your deepest consciousness, watchfulness and knowledge. You are so young, all still lies ahead of you, and I should like to ask you, as best I can, dear Sir, to be patient towards all that is unresolved in your heart and to try to love the questions themselves like locked rooms, like books written in a foreign tongue. Do not now strive to uncover answers: they cannot be given you because you have not been able to live them. And what matters is to live everything. Live the questions for now. Perhaps then you will gradually, without noticing it, live your way into the answer, one distant day in the future. Perhaps you do carry within yourself the possibility of forming and creating, as a particularly happy and pure way of living. School yourself for it, but take what comes in complete trust, and as long as it is a product of your will, of some kind of inner necessity, accept it and do not despise it. Sex is difficult, true. But difficult things are what we were set to do, almost everything serious is difficult, and everything is serious. If you only acknowledge this and manage from your own resources, from your own disposition and nature, from your own experience and childhood and strength, to win your way towards a relationship to sex that is wholly your own (not influenced by convention and custom), then you have no need to fear losing yourself and becoming unworthy of your best possession.

Physical desire is a sensual experience, no different from pure contemplation or the pure sensation with which a fine fruit sates the tongue; it is a great and endless feeling which is granted to us, a way of knowing the world, the fullness and the splendour of all knowledge. And that we receive this pleasure cannot be a bad thing; what is bad is the way almost all of us misuse the experience and waste it and apply it as a stimulus to the tired parts of our lives, as a distraction instead of as a concentration of ourselves into climactic points. Eating, too, has been turned away from its true nature: want on the one hand and superfluity on the other have troubled the clarity of this need, and all the profound, simple necessities in which life renews itself have similarly been obscured. But the individual can clarify them for himself and live in this clearness (and if not the individual, who is too dependent, then at least the solitary). He can remind himself that all beauty in plants and animals is a quiet and durable form of love and longing, and he can see the animal, as also the plant, patiently and willingly joining and multiplying and growing, not from physical pleasure, not from physical suffering, but bowing to necessities which are greater than pleasure and pain and more powerful than desire and resistance. Oh if only mankind could embrace this mystery, which penetrates the earth right into its smallest elements, with more humility, and bear and sustain it with more gravity and know how terribly heavy it is, instead of taking it lightly. If only mankind could hold its own fertility in awe, which is one and the same whether it manifests itself in the spirit or in the flesh. For creativity of the spirit has its origin in the physical kind, is of one nature with it and only a more delicate, more rapt and less fleeting version of the carnal sort of sex. ‘The desire to be a creator, to engender, to give form’ is nothing without its continuing, palpable confirmation and realization in the world, nothing without the myriad expressions of assent coming from animals and things. And the pleasure it gives is only as unutterably fine and abundant as it is because it is full of inherited memories of the engendering and bearing of millions. In one creative thought a thousand forgotten nights of love revive and lend it grandeur and height. And those who come together in the night time and are entwined in a cradle of desire are carrying out a serious work in collecting sweetness, profundity and strength for the song of some poet yet to come, who will rise up to speak unutterable pleasures. And they summon up the future; and even if they err and embrace one another blindly, the future will come all the same, a new creature will appear, and based on the chance act that seems to be accomplished here the law comes into being according to which a resistant and vigorous seed forces its way through to the egg moving forward to receive it. Do not be distracted by surfaces; it is in the depths that all laws obtain. And those who live the mystery falsely and badly(and there are many of them) forfeit it only for themselves and still hand it on like a sealed letter, unwittingly. And don’t be put off by the multiplicity of names and the complexity of the various cases. Perhaps a great maternity lies over everything, as a shared longing. The beauty of the virgin, of a being, who, as you put it so well, ‘has not yet achieved anything’, is maternity divining and preparing itself, anxious and full of longing. And the beauty of a mother is maternity at work, and that of the old woman a great memory. And in the man too there is maternity, as it seems to me, physical and spiritual; his engendering is also a kind of giving birth, and it is an act of birth when he creates out of his inmost resources. And perhaps the sexes are more closely related than we think, and the great renewal of the world will perhaps consist in man and woman, freed of all sense of error and disappointment, seeking one another out not as opposites but as brothers and sisters and neighbours, and they will join together as human beings, to share the heavy weight of sexuality that is laid upon them with simplicity, gravity and patience.

But everything which one day will perhaps be possible for many, the solitary individual can prepare for and build now with his hands which are more unerring. For this reason, dear Mr Kappus, love your solitude and bear the pain it causes you with melody wrought with lament. For the people who are close to you, you tell me, are far away, and that shows that you are beginning to create a wider space around you. And if what is close is far, then the space around you is wide indeed and already among the stars; take pleasure in your growth, in which no one can accompany you, and be kind hearted towards those you leave behind, and be assured and gentle with them and do not plague them with your doubts or frighten them with your confidence or your joyfulness, which they cannot understand. Look for some kind of simple and loyal way of being together with them which does not necessarily have to alter however much you may change; love in them a form of life different from your own and show understanding for the older ones who fear precisely the solitude in which you trust. Avoid providing material for the drama which always spans between parents and their children; it saps much of the children’s strength and consumes that parental love which works and warms even when it does not comprehend. Ask no advice of them and reckon with no understanding; but believe in a love which is stored up for you like an inheritance, and trust that in this love there is a strength and a benediction out of whose sphere you do not need to issue even if your journey is a long one.

It is good that for the moment you are going into a profession which will make you independent and mean you only have yourself to rely on, in every sense. Have the patience to wait and see whether your inmost life feels confined by the form of this occupation. I consider it a very difficult and a very demanding one, as it is burdened by powerful conventions and leaves almost no room to interpret its duties according to your own lights. But your solitude, even in the midst of quite foreign circumstances, will be a hold and a home for you, and leading from it you will find all the paths you need. All my good wishes are ready to accompany you, and you have all my confidence and trust.

Yours,

Rainer Maria Rilke

Rome, 29 October 1903

My dear Sir,

Your letter of 29 August reached me in Florence, and only now – two months on – do I give you news of it. Forgive me this delay, but I prefer not to write letters when I’m travelling because letter writing requires more of me than just the basic wherewithal: some quiet and time on my own and a moment when I feel relatively at home.

We arrived in Rome about six weeks ago, at a time when it was still the empty, hot city, the Rome supposedly ridden with fevers, and this circumstance, together with other practical difficulties to do with settling in, meant that the unrest surrounding us went on and on and the foreignness of the place lay on us with the weight of homelessness. On top of that you have to remember that Rome (if one is not yet acquainted with it) seems oppressively sad when one first arrives: the lifeless and drear museum atmosphere it breathes, the abundance of fragments of the past (on which a tiny present nourishes itself) that have been fetched out of the ground and laboriously maintained, the unspeakable excess of esteem, nourished by academics and philologists with the help of run of the mill tourists, given to all these disfigured and spoilt objects which after all are basically nothing more than accidental vestiges of another age and of a life that is not our own and is not meant to be. At last, after weeks of daily fending off, you get your bearings back, and somewhat dazed you tell yourself: No, there is not more beauty here than elsewhere, and all these objects which generation after generation have continued to admire, which inexpert hands have mended and restored, they mean nothing, are nothing and have no heart and no value; but there is a great deal of beauty here, because there is beauty everywhere. Infinitely lively waters go over the old aqueducts into the city and on the many squares dance over bowls of white stone and fill broad capacious basins and murmur all day and raise their murmur into the night, which is vast and starry and soft with winds. And there are gardens here, unforgettable avenues and flights of steps, steps conceived by Michelangelo, steps built to resemble cascades of flowing water – giving birth to step after broad step like wave after wave as they descend the incline. With the help of such impressions you regain your composure, win your way back out of the demands of the talking and chattering multitude(how voluble it is!), and you slowly learn to recognize the very few things in which something everlasting can be felt, something you can love, something solitary in which you can take part in silence.

I’m still living in the city, on the Capitol, not far from the finest equestrian statue that has come down to us from Roman art – that of Marcus Aurelius. But in a few weeks I shall be moving into a quiet, simple room, an old summer house lost in the depths of a great park, hidden away from the city with its noise and its inconsequentiality. I’ll live there for the whole winter and take pleasure in the great stillness from which I expect the gift of good and productive hours . . .

From there, where I shall feel more at home, I’ll write you a longer letter in which I’ll also have something to say about your writing. Today I must just mention (and it was perhaps wrong of me not to have done so before) that the book you announced in your letter (which you said contained pieces by you) has not arrived here. Has it been sent back to you, perhaps from Worpswede? (For: packets cannot be forwarded abroad.) This is the best explanation, which it would be nice to have confirmed. I hope it has not gone astray, which given the Italian postal service cannot be ruled out – alas.

I should have been glad to receive the book (as with everything that gives some sign of you); and any verse you have written since I shall always (if you entrust me with it) read and reread and take in as well and as completely as I can. With good wishes and greetings,

Yours,

Rainer Maria Rilke

Rome, 23 December 1903

My dear Mr Kappus,

You shall not go without greetings from me at Christmas time, when you are perhaps finding your solitude harder than usual to bear among all the festivities. But if you notice that it is great, then be glad of it; for what (you must ask yourself) would a solitude be that was not great? There is only one solitude, and it is vast and not easy to bear and almost everyone has moments when they would happily exchange it for some form of company, be it ever so banal or trivial, for the illusion of some slight correspondence with whoever one happens to come across, however unworthy . . . But perhaps those are precisely the hours when solitude grows, for its growth is painful like the growth of boys and sad like the beginning of spring. But that must not put you off. What is needed is this, and this alone: solitude, great inner loneliness. Going into oneself and not meeting anyone for hours –that is what one must arrive at. Loneliness of the kind one knew as a child, when the grown ups went back and forth bound up in things which seemed grave and weighty because they looked so busy, and because one had no idea what they were up to.

And when one day you realize that their preoccupations are meagre, their professions barren and no longer connected to life, why not continue to look on them like a child, as if on something alien, drawing on the depths of your own world, on the expanse of your own solitude, which itself is work and achievement and a vocation? Why wish to exchange a child’s wise incomprehension for rejection and contempt, when incomprehension is solitude, whereas rejection and contempt are ways of participating in what, by precisely these means, you want to sever yourself from?

Think, dear Mr Kappus, of the world that you carry within you, and call this thinking whatever you like. Whether it is memory of your own childhood or longing for your own future – just be attentive towards what rises up inside you, and place it above everything that you notice round about. What goes on in your innermost being is worth all your love, this is what you must work on however you can and not waste too much time and too much energy on clarifying your attitude to other people. Who says you have such an attitude at all? – I know, your profession is hard and goes against you, and I had foreseen your complaints and knew they would come. Now that they have come I cannot assuage them; I can only advise you to consider whether all professions are not like that, full of demands, full of hostility for the individual, steeped as it were in the hatred of those who with sullen resentment have settled for a life of sober duty. The station you are now obliged to occupy is no more heavily burdened with conventions, prejudices and misapprehensions than any other, and if there are some domains that make a show of greater freedom there are none that are vast and spacious and in contact with the great things of which real life consists. Only the solitary individual is subject, like a thing, to the fundamental laws, and if someone goes out into the morning as it is breaking, or looks out into the evening full of occurrence, and if he feels what is happening there, every hint of station slips from him as if from a dead man, although he is standing in the midst of life itself. Dear Mr Kappus, something similar to what you now have to undergo as an officer would have affected you in any of the existing professions, and even if, outside of any position, you had sought only fleeting and non committal contact with society, you would not have been spared this feeling of constraint. – It is the same everywhere; but that is no reason for anxiety or sadness; if there is no communal feeling between you and other people, try to be near to things – they will not abandon you. The nights are still there and the winds that go through the trees and over the many lands; among things and among animals all is still full of happenings in which you can take part; and the children are still as you were when you were a child, just as sad and happy, and whenever you think of your childhood you live among them again, among the lonely children, and adults are nothing and their dignity has no worth.

And if it frightens and pains you to think of your childhood and of the simplicity and stillness that go together with it, because you can no longer believe in God, who is everywhere present in it, then ask yourself, dear Mr Kappus, whether you have really lost God after all? Is it not rather the case that you have never yet possessed him? For when was it supposed to have been? Do you think a child can hold him, him whom grown men only bear with difficulty and whose weight bows down the old? Do you believe that anyone who really has him could lose him like a little pebble, or don’t you think that whoever had him could only be lost by him alone? – But if you acknowledge that he was not present in your childhood, and not before that, if you suspect that Christ was deceived by his longing and Mohammed betrayed by his pride, and if you feel with horror that even now he is not present, at the moment when we are talking about him, what then gives you the right to miss him who never was, as if he had disappeared, and to search for him as if he were lost?

Why don’t you think of him as a coming god, who since eternity has lain ahead of us, the future one, the eventual fruit of a tree of which we are the leaves? What prevents you from casting his birth out into the times of becoming and from living your life like a painful and beautiful day in the history of a great pregnancy? Don’t you see how everything that happens is always a beginning again, and could it not be His beginning, given that beginnings are in themselves always so beautiful? If he is the complete being, must not slighter things come before him, so that he can pick himself out of fullness and abundance? – Must he not be the last in order to encompass all things in himself, and what significance would we have if the one whom we hanker for had already been?

As the bees collect honey together, so we fetch the sweetness out of everything and build Him. We begin with the very slightest things, with what is barely noticeable (as long as it comes about through love), with our work and the repose that comes after, with a moment of silence or with a small solitary joy, with everything that we do on our own without helpers and accomplices, we begin him whom we shall never know, just as our ancestors could not live to know us. And yet they are in us, these people long since passed away, as a disposition, as a load weighing on our destinies, as a murmur in the blood and as a gesture that rises up out of the depths of time.

Is there anything that can strip you of the hope of dwelling one day in him, the most remote, the most extreme?

Dear Mr Kappus, celebrate Christmas in the piety of the feeling that He perhaps requires of you precisely this existential anxiety in order to begin. Precisely these days of transition are perhaps the period when everything in you is working on him, just as before, as a child, you worked on him with bated breath. Be patient and even tempered and remember that the least we can do is not make his becoming more difficult than the earth makes it for spring when it decides to come.

And I wish you happiness and confidence.

Yours,

Rainer Maria Rilke

Rome, 14 May 1904

My dear Mr Kappus,

Much time has gone past since I received your last letter. Don’t hold that against me; first it was work, then disruptions and finally ill health that kept me from replying, whereas I wanted to write to you out of good, peaceful days. Now I feel a little better again (even here the beginning of spring with its bad and fickle transitions was hard to bear) and can manage to send you greetings, dear Mr Kappus, and (as I am very glad to do) say this and that about your letter, as best I can.

You will see: I have copied out your sonnet because I found that it had beauty and simplicity and a native form in which it unfolds with such quiet propriety. It is the best of the verses of yours I have been permitted to read. And I’m giving you this copy now because I know that it is important and a whole new experience to come across a work of one’s own in a foreign hand. Read the lines as if they were unknown to you, and you will feel in your inmost self how very much they are yours. –

It has been a pleasure for me to read this sonnet and your letter, which I did often. I thank you for both.

And you must not let yourself be diverted out of your solitude by the fact that something in you wants to escape from it. Precisely this desire, if you use it calmly and judiciously, as a kind of tool, will help you to extend your solitude over a greater expanse of ground. People have tended (with the help of conventions) to resolve everything in the direction of easiness, of the light, and on the lightest side of the light; but it is clear that we must hold to the heavy, the difficult. All living things do this, everything in nature grows and defends itself according to its kind and is a distinct creature from out of its own resources, strives to be so at any cost and in the face of all resistance. We know little, but that we must hold fast to what is difficult is a certainty that will never forsake us. It is good to be alone, for solitude is difficult; that something is difficult should be one more reason to do it.

To love is also good, for love is hard. Love between one person and another: that is perhaps the hardest thing it is laid on us to do, the utmost, the ultimate trial and test, the work for which all other work is just preparation. For this reason young people, who are beginners in everything, do not yet know how to love: they must learn. With their whole being, with all their strength, concerted on their solitary, fearful, upward beating hearts, they have to learn to love. An apprenticeship though is always a long, secluded period, and love too is for a great long time and far into life: solitariness, heightened and deepened loneliness for the one in love. Love at first has nothing to do with unfolding, abandon and uniting with another person (for what would be the sense in a union of what is unrefined and unfinished, still second order?); for the individual it is a grand opportunity to mature, to become something in himself, to become a world, to become a world in himself for another’s sake; it is a great immoderate demand made upon the self, something that singles him out and summons him to vast designs. Only in this sense, as a duty to work on themselves (‘to hearken and to hammer day and night’), should young people use the love that is given them. The unfolding, the abandon and any kind of togetherness is not for them (who for a long time yet will have to scrimp and save). They are the culmination, and perhaps that for which a human life now is hardly sufficient.

But there young people so often and so badly go wrong: in that they (who by nature have no patience) fling themselves at one another when love comes over them, scatter themselves just as they are in all their troubledness, disorder, confusion . . . But what can come of that? What is life supposed to do with this heap of half broken things that they call their togetherness and would like to call their happiness, were it possible, their future? Each person loses himself then for the other’s sake and loses the other and many more who were yet to come. And loses the expanses and possibilities, exchanges the nearing and fleeing of delicate, mysterious things for a sterile helplessness of which nothing more can come; nothing but a bit of disgust, disappointment and deprivation and the escape into one of the many conventions which like public shelters are set up in great numbers along this most dangerous of paths. No area of human experience is so well furnished with conventions as this: there are lifebelts of the most various invention, dinghies and buoyancy devices; society in its wisdom has found ways of constructing refuges of all kinds, for since it has been disposed to make the love life a pastime, it has also felt obliged to trivialize it, to make it cheap, risk free and secure, as public pleasures usually are.

It is true that many young people who love wrongly, that is, simply with abandon and not in solitude (and your average person will never move beyond this), feel the oppression of having failed at something and do want to make the state into which they have got liveable and productive in their own, personal way; for their nature tells them that questions of love, even less than all other important matters, cannot be solved publicly and by following this or that consensus; that they are questions that touch the quick of what it is to be human and which in every case require a new, particular and purely private response: but how can people who have already flung together and no longer set themselves any limits or tell one another apart, and who therefore possess nothing of their own any more, how on earth can they find a way out of themselves, out of the depths of a solitude that has already been spilt and squandered?

They act out of a shared helplessness, and if they do their best to escape the convention they happen to have noticed (as marriage for example), they fall into the clutches of a less obvious but just as deadly conventional solution; for all around them there is nothing but –convention; when an action derives from a precipitately arrived at and unwitting union, it is always conventional; every relationship which is the product of such confusion has its conventions, however unusual (that is, immoral in the generally accepted sense) it may be; yes, even separation would in such a case be a conventional step, an impersonal, fortuitous decision without force and without point.

Whoever looks at the matter seriously finds that, as for death, which is difficult, no explanation, no solution, has yet been discovered for love, which is difficult too: there are no directions, no path. And for these two problems that we carry round with us in a sealed packet and hand on without opening, it will always be impossible to locate a common rule, resting on consensus. But to the same extent that we begin as individuals to venture onto life, these great things will encounter us, on our own, at ever closer quarters. The demands that the hard work of love makes on our development are larger than life, and as beginners we are not a match for them. But if we can hold out and take this love upon us as a burden and an apprenticeship, instead of losing ourselves in all the trivial and frivolous games behind which people have hidden from the utter seriousness of their existence, then perhaps a small advance and some relief will be sensible to those who come long after us. That would mean a great deal.

We are only now just coming to the point where we can consider the relationship of one human individual to another objectively and without prejudice, and our attempts to live such a relation have no model to go on. And yet in the shifting of the times there are already a few things that can help our tentative beginnings.

Girls and women, in their new, particular unfolding, will only in passing imitate men’s behaviour and misbehaviour and follow in male professions. Once the uncertainty of such transitions is over it will emerge that women have only passed through the spectrum and the variety of those (often laughable) disguises in order to purify their truest natures from the distorting influences of the other sex. Women, in whom life abides and dwells more immediately, more fruitfully and more trustingly, are bound to have ripened more thoroughly, become more human human beings, than a man, who is all too light and has not been pulled down beneath the surface of life by the weight of a bodily fruit and who, in his arrogance and impatience, undervalues what he thinks he loves. This humanity which inhabits woman, brought to term in pain and humiliation, will, once she has shrugged off the conventions of mere femininity through the transformations of her outward status, come clearly to light, and men, who today do not yet feel it approaching, will be taken by surprise and struck down by it. One day (there are already reliable signs which speak for it and which begin to spread their light, especially in the northern countries), one day there will be girls and women whose name will no longer just signify the opposite of the male but something in their own right, something which does not make one think of any supplement or limit but only of life and existence: the female human being.

This step forward (at first right against the will of the men who are left behind) will transform the experience of love, which is now full of error, alter it root and branch, reshape it into a relation between two human beings and no longer between man and woman. And this more human form of love (which will be performed in infinitely gentle and considerate fashion, true and clear in its creating of bonds and dissolving of them) will resemble the one we are struggling and toiling to prepare the way for, the love that consists in two solitudes protecting, defining and welcoming one another.

And one more thing: do not believe that that abundance of love which was once, as a boy, bestowed on you is now lost. Can you tell whether back then great and good desires did not ripen within you, and resolutions which you still live by today? I believe that love remains so strong and powerful in your memory because it was your first deep experience of solitariness and the first inner work that you undertook on your life. – All good wishes to you, dear Mr Kappus!

Yours,

Rainer Maria Rilke

Sonnet

Through my life there trembles unlamenting

suffering dark and deep, without a sigh.

Pure as snow the blossoming of my dreams

consecrates the stillest of my days.

Often though a question’s gravity

cuts across my path. I seem to shrink,

pass coldly on as if beside a lake

whose waters are too vast for me to measure.

And then a sadness settles, dim, opaque,

like the grey of pallid summer nights,

shimmered through with stars – now and then – :

love then is what my hands attempt to grasp

because I want to say a prayer whose sounds

my burning mouth, my lips, cannot bring forth . . .

}blr}(Franz Kappus)

Borgeby gård, Flãdie, Sweden, 12 August 1904

I want to talk to you again for a while, dear Mr Kappus, although I can say almost nothing that is of any help, hardly anything useful. You have had many great sadnesses which have now passed by. And you say that their passing was also hard and upsetting for you. But I ask you to consider whether these great unhappinesses did not rather pass through you. Whether much within you has not changed, whether somewhere, in some part of your being, you were not transformed while you were unhappy? The only sorrows which are harmful and bad are those one takes among people in order to drown them out. Like diseases which are treated superficially and inexpertly, they only abate, and after a short pause break out again with more terrible force, and accumulate inside and are life, unlived, rejected, lost life – from which we can die. If it were possible for us to see further than our knowledge reaches, and a little beyond the outworks of our intuitions, perhaps we should then bear our sadnesses with greater assurance than our joys. For they are the moments when something new enters into us, something unknown to us; our feelings, shy and inhibited, fall silent, everything in us withdraws, a stillness settles on us, and at the centre of it is the new presence that nobody yet knows, making no sound.

I believe that almost all our sadnesses are periods of tautening that we experience as numbness because we can no longer hear the stirring of our feelings, which have become foreign to us. Because we are alone with the strange thing that has entered into us; because everything familiar and accustomed is taken away from us for a moment; because we are in the middle of a transition where we cannot stand still. And that is why sadness passes: what is new in us, the thing that has supervened, has entered into our heart, penetrated to its innermost chamber and not lingered even there – it is already in our blood. And we never quite know what it was. One might easily suppose that nothing had happened, but we have altered the way a house alters when a guest enters it. We cannot say who has come, perhaps we shall never know, but there are many indications that it is the future that enters into us like this, in order to be transformed within us, long before it actually occurs. And that is why it is so important to be solitary and attentive when one is sad: because the apparently uneventful and static moment when our future comes upon us is so much closer to life than that other noisy and accidental point when it happens to us as if from the outside. The quieter, the more patient and open we are in our sadness, the deeper and more unerringly the new will penetrate into us, the better we shall acquire it, the more it will be our fate, and when one day in the future it ‘takes place’ (that is, steps out of us towards others) we shall feel related and close to it in our inmost hearts. And that is necessary. It is necessary –and little by little our development will tend in this direction – that nothing alien should happen to us, but only what has long been part of us. We have already had to adjust our understanding of so many theories of planetary motion, and so too we shall gradually learn to recognize that what we call fate originates in ourselves, in humankind, and does not work on us from the outside. Only because so many people did not absorb their fates while they were inhabited by them, and did not make them a part of themselves, only because of this did they fail to recognize what emerged from them. It was so foreign to them that in their confused panic they assumed it must just have entered into them, for they swore never to have found anything of the sort in themselves before. Just as for a long time people were deceived about the movement of the sun, so we are still deceived about the movement of what is to come. The future is fixed, dear Mr Kappus, but we move around in infinite space.

How could things not be difficult for us?

And if we come back to solitude, it grows ever clearer that fundamentally it is not something that one can take or leave. We are solitary. It is possible to deceive yourself and act as if it were not the case. That is all. How much better though, to see and accept that that is what we are, and even to take it as our starting point. If we do, the effect is admittedly one of giddiness; for all the points on which we are accustomed to rest our eyes are taken away from us, there is no longer anything close by, and everything remote is infinitely so. Someone transported from his room, almost without warning and interval, onto the top of a high mountain would feel something like it: he would be virtually destroyed by an unparalleled sense of insecurity, by an exposure to something nameless. He would think he was falling or believe himself to be hurtling out into space or shattered into a thousand pieces: what a monstrous lie his brain would have to invent to rein in and clarify the state of his senses. In the same way all distances, all measurements, alter for the one who becomes solitary; many such changes suddenly take place at once and, as with the man on the mountaintop, unusual imaginings and curious sensations occur which seem to take on dimensions greater than can be tolerated. But it is necessary for us to experience this too. We must accept our existence in as wide a sense as can be; everything, even the unheard of, must be possible within it. That, when you come down to it, is the only kind of courage that is demanded of us: the courage for the oddest, the most unexpected, the most inexplicable things that we may encounter. That human beings have been cowardly in this regard has done life endless harm; the experiences we describe as ‘apparitions’, the entire so called ‘spirit world’, death, all those things so closely akin to us have by our daily rejection of them been forced so far out of our lives that the senses with which we might apprehend them have atrophied. To say nothing of God. But the fear of the inexplicable has not just rendered the individual existence poorer; relations between people, too, have been restricted, as it were lifted out of the river bed of endless possibilities and placed on a deserted bank where nothing happens. For it is not lethargy alone which causes human relationships to repeat themselves in the same old way with such unspeakable monotony in instance after instance; it is the fearful shying away from any kind of new, unforeseeable experience which we think we may not be equal to. But only someone who is ready for anything and rules nothing out, not even the most enigmatic things, will experience the relationship with another as a living thing and will himself live his own existence to the full. For imagining an individual’s existence as a larger or smaller room reveals to us that most people are only acquainted with one corner of their particular room, a place by the window, a little area to pace up and down. That way, they have a certain security. And yet the perilous uncertainty that drives the prisoners in Poe’s tales to grope out the outlines of their terrible dungeons and so to know the unspeakable horrors of their surroundings, is so much more human. But we are not prisoners. There are no traps or snares set up around us, and there is nothing that should frighten or torment us. We are placed into life as into the element with which we have the most affinity, and moreover we have after thousands of years of adaptation come to resemble this life so closely that if we keep still we can, thanks to our facility for mimicry, hardly be distinguished from all that surrounds us. We have no reason to be mistrustful of our world, for it is not against us. If it holds terrors they are our terrors, if it has its abysses these abysses belong to us, if there are dangers then we must try to love them. And if we only organize our life according to the principle which teaches us always to hold to what is difficult, then what now still appears most foreign will become our most intimate and most reliable experience. How can we forget those ancient myths found at the beginnings of all peoples? The myths about the dragons who at the last moment turn into princesses? Perhaps all the dragons in our lives are princesses, only waiting for the day when they will see us handsome and brave? Perhaps everything terrifying is deep down a helpless thing that needs our help.

So, dear Mr Kappus, you shouldn’t be dismayed if a sadness rises up in front of you, greater than any you have ever seen before; or if a disquiet plays over your hands and over all your doings like light and cloud shadow. You must think that something is happening with you, that life has not forgotten you, that it holds you in its hand; it will not let you fall. Why should you want to exclude from your life all unsettling, all pain, all depression of spirit, when you don’t know what work it is these states are performing within you? Why do you want to persecute yourself with the question of where it all comes from and where it is leading? You well know you are in a period of transition and want nothing more than to be transformed. If there is something ailing in the way you go about things, then remember that sickness is the means by which an organism rids itself of something foreign to it. All one has to do is help it to be ill, to have its whole illness and let it break out, for that is how it mends itself. There is so much, my dear Mr Kappus, going on in you now. You must be patient as an invalid and trusting as a convalescent, for you are perhaps both. And more than that: you are also the doctor responsible for looking after himself. But with all illnesses there are many days when the doctor can do nothing but wait. And inasfar as you are your own doctor, this above all is what you must do now.

Do not watch yourself too closely. Do not draw overrapid conclusions from what is happening to you. Simply let it happen. Otherwise you will too readily find yourself looking on your past, which is of course not uninvolved with everything that is going on in you now, reproachfully (that is, moralistically). But what now affects you from among the divagations, desires and longings of your boyhood is not what you will recall and condemn. The extraordinary circumstances of a solitary and helpless childhood are so difficult, so complicated, exposed to so many influences and at the same time removed from any real life context, that if a vice enters into it we must not be too quick to call it a vice. We should in general be very careful with names; it is so often the name of a crime which destroys a life, not the nameless and personal act itself, which was perhaps completely necessary to that life and could have been absorbed by it without difficulty. And the expenditure of energy only seems so great because you put too much importance on the victory. It is not victory that is the ‘great thing’ you think you have achieved, though the feeling itself is not in error. What is great is that there was already something there that you were able to set in place of that deception, something true and real. Without it, your victory would only have been a moral reaction with no further significance, but as it is it has become a segment of your life. Of your life, dear Mr Kappus, which I am thinking of with so many hopes and wishes. Do you remember how this life of yours longed in childhood to belong to the ‘ grown ups’? I can see that it now longs to move on from them and is drawn to those who are greater yet. That is why it does not cease to be difficult, but also why it will not cease to grow.

And if I have anything else to say to you it is this: do not think that the person who is trying to console you lives effortlessly among the simple, quiet words that sometimes make you feel better. His life is full of troubles and sadness and falls far short of them. But if it were any different he could never have found the words that he did.

Yours,

Rainer Maria Rilke

Furuborg, Jonsered, Sweden, 4 November 1904

My dear Mr Kappus,

During this time that has passed without a letter I was partly travelling and partly too busy to be able to write. And even today writing is not going to be easy because I have had to write a good number of letters already and my hand is tired. If I had someone to dictate to I’d have plenty to say, but as it is you’ll have to make do with just a few words in return for your long letter.

I think of you often, dear Mr Kappus, and with such a concentration of good wishes that really in some way it ought to help. Whether my letters can really be a help to you, well, I have my doubts. Do not say: Yes, they are. Just let them sink in quietly and without any particular sense of gratitude, and let’s wait and see what will come of it.

There’s not perhaps much purpose in my dealing with the detail of what you wrote, for what I might be able to say about your tendency towards self doubt or your inability to reconcile your inner and outer life, or about anything else that assails you – it all comes down to what I have said before: the same desire that you might find enough patience in you to endure, and simplicity enough to have faith; that you might gain more and more trust in what is hard and in your own loneliness among other people. And otherwise let life take its course. Believe me: life is right, whatever happens.

And as to feelings: all feelings are pure that focus you and raise you up. An impure feeling is one that only comprises one side of your nature and so distorts you. Any thoughts that match up to your childhood are good. Everything that makes more of you than you have hitherto been in your best moments is right. Every heightening is good if it occurs in the quick of your bloodstream, if it is not an intoxication, not a troubling but a joy one can see right to the bottom of. Do you understand what I mean?

And your doubts can become a good quality if you school them. They must grow to be knowledgeable, they must learn to be critical. As soon as they begin to spoil something for you ask them why a thing is ugly, demand hard evidence, test them, and you will perhaps find them at a loss and short of an answer, or perhaps mutinous. But do not give in, request arguments, and act with this kind of attentiveness and consistency every single time, and the day will come when instead of being demolishers they will be among your best workers – perhaps the canniest of all those at work on the building of your life.

That is all, dear Mr Kappus, that I can say to you for today. But I’m also sending you the off print of a little work that has just appeared in the Prague journal Deutsche Arbeit. There I continue to speak to you of life and of death and of the greatness and splendour of both.

Yours,

Rainer Maria Rilke

Paris, on the second day of Christmas 1908

You ought to know, dear Mr Kappus, how happy I was to get this lovely letter from you. The news you give me, actual and articulate as it now is, seems good to me, and the more I thought about it the more it struck me as incontrovertibly good. I really wanted to write you this in time for Christmas Eve; but what with the work that has been occupying me variously and without interruption this winter the old festival came up so quickly that I hardly had time enough to make the most necessary purchases, much less to write a letter.

But during these Christmas days I have often thought of you and imagined how quiet you must be in your solitary fort up among the empty mountains over which those great south winds rush as if they wanted to devour them in mighty chunks.

The silence must be immense to be able to receive such sounds and movements, and when one thinks that they are joined by the noise of the sea, present in the distance, perhaps the most inward note in this prehistoric harmony, one can only hope that you have the trust and patience to let this marvellous solitude work on you, a solitude which will never be deleted from your life. In all that lies before you to experience and do, it will continue as an anonymous influence and have a subtly decisive effect, perhaps like the way the blood of our ancestors moves unceasingly within us and mingles with our own to make us the unique, not to be repeated being that we are at every turn of our lives.

Yes: I am glad that you have this firm, utterable form of existence, the rank, the uniform, the duty, all these tangible and well defined things that in such surroundings, with an equally isolated and not numerous company of men, take on a seriousness and necessity; and which, over and above the aspects of play and pastime that are also part of the military profession, make for a certain vigilance and not only permit an individual attentiveness but actually teach it. And to be in circumstances that work on us, that set us before great natural phenomena from time to time, is all we need.

Art too is only a way of living, and it is possible, however one lives, to prepare oneself for it without knowing; in every real situation we are nearer to it, better neighbours, than in the unreal half artistic professions which by pretending to be close to art in fact deny and hurt its very existence, as for example is the case with the whole of journalism and almost all criticism and three quarters of what passes for literature. I am glad, in a word, that you have withstood the dangers of slipping into all this, and that somewhere you are living alone and courageous in a rough reality. May the year to come maintain and strengthen you in it.

Ever yours,

R. M. Rilke

只有乏味的人会在早餐时才华横溢

对他们的伟人一无所知，是英国教育的必要元素之一。

我们人人都花时间寻找生活的秘诀。其实，生活的秘诀在艺术之中。

生活的至高目标是生活。很少人在生活。实现自己的完美状态，把自己的梦想逐一变为现实，那才叫生活。

商人早早起床吃了第一餐，赶火车进城，在昏暗无光、灰灰蒙蒙的商业世界混上一天，夜晚回到家里，吃完晚餐就睡觉，这种生活以我看来比奴工都不如——捆绑他的不是铁链，是金枷。

劣等艺术比没有艺术还要差远了。

……没有什么是值得做的，除了世人都说无法成功的事。

做一份美味沙拉相当于做一个优秀的外交家——两者涉及的问题完全相同：得知道应该往醋里掺多少油。

生活是太重要的事，不能认真地谈论它。

贵族政治里的金钱永远多于头脑。

好国王是唯一对现代民主政治构成威胁的敌人。

我一向认为，只有缺乏想象力的人会死守“始终如一”的立场……

……典型的英国厨子是个蠢女人，她的罪过是从来没学会如何放盐，为此她应该变成一根盐柱。[1]

关于莎士比亚，可以说他是第一个明白男式紧身上衣的戏剧价值，也知道如何运用一件裙撑托起一个高潮。

……舞台不单是各种艺术形式交会的地方，而且是艺术向生活回归的地方。

真正的戏剧家……向我们展现艺术条件下的生活，而不是生活形式的艺术。

……我们普通的英国小说家……没有做到……风格凝练。他们的人物过于能说会道，谈得自己也精疲力尽。我们想要的是多一点的现实，少一点的修辞……我们情愿他们谈得少些、想得多些。

它们领着我们穿越一片废话连连的荒漠，去到一座据说是人生的海市蜃楼：我们漫无目的地游走于词语的不毛之地，追寻一点点自然。不过，也别对英国小说太苛刻了；它们是智力空虚者的唯一消遣。

没有什么能打垮一个诗人，除了一处印刷错误。

……不神经质的诗人是稀有的。

美国没有蠢材。许多美国人招人厌烦、趣味庸俗、举止唐突、鲁莽无礼，这也同样是许多英国人爱犯的毛病；但愚蠢并不在美国人的缺点之列。真的，美国没有蠢材生存的土壤。美国人期许擦鞋的也有头脑，事实也不负所望。

至于婚姻，那是他们最流行的制度之一。美国男人早早结婚，美国女人常常结婚；这两种人是天作之合。

美洲始终不能原谅欧洲，因为在历史上它比自己被发现的时间早了一些。

……假如人要专门学习如何说话，那真会是一件功德。语言是我们拥有的最高贵的工具，既能揭示思想又能掩饰思想；讲话本身是一种精神化的行动，交谈则是最可爱的一门艺术。

唯一不会让真实人物显得突兀的杜撰之作是历史。

她在人生早年发现了一条重要的道理：一切都没有放浪那么看似天真；于是，借着一系列大胆的越轨行为（其中一半是无甚损害的），她获取了一个名人能有的各种特权。她不止一次换过丈夫；狄布列特说她有三场婚姻呢；但因为她从来没有换过情人，社会上早已不再流传她的丑闻了。

除非有钱，否则迷人的气质毫无用处。风流韵事是富人的特权，不是无业者的职业。穷人应当实际而本分。有一份持久收入比气质诱人更好。

哪怕在外郡[2]，也绝对不该容许在宴席上向人抛出一个纯属数学的智力问题。提这种问题，跟忽然询问人家灵魂的状况一样糟糕。

如果人不能畅所欲言，所谓良好的友谊又何在？人人都可以说动听的话去取悦和奉承，但是真朋友说的永远是逆耳的话，而且不担心令对方痛苦。的确，真朋友宁愿如此，因为这样一来他就会知道自己有益处。

觉得别人全都远远不如自己，这种意识是唯一叫人活得下去的东西，而我向来悉心培育这样的感觉。

我如此聪明，以至于有时我正在说的话，我自己一个词儿都听不懂。

我一向认为，操劳不过是无所事事者的救命稻草。

以“世纪末”这个词为人所知的一切，我都特别佩服和喜爱。这是我们的文明绽放的一朵娇花：唯有它才令世界不至于沦入平庸、粗俗、野蛮。

福楼拜没有写法语文章，他写的是一位艺术大师的文章，作者刚巧是法国人。

今天早晨我在床上想着，法国远远胜过英国的地方在于法国的资产阶级个个想当艺术家，而英国的艺术家个个想当资产阶级。

祈祷永远不能得到应答：否则哪还是祈祷，岂不成了通信。

我有一个重大发现……充分饮酒，足以产生沉醉的全部效果。

传教士呀，乖乖！难道你们不懂，传教士对又穷又饿的食人族来说是神赐的美食？每当他们快到饥馑边缘的时候，大慈大悲的老天就给他们送去一个白白胖胖的传教士。

哲学教我们心平气和地应对他人的不幸。

我个人的经验是我们越多研究艺术，就越少在乎自然……艺术是我们精神饱满的抗议，是我们要自然安守本分的英勇尝试。

思考是世界上最不健康的事，它像别的疾病一样可以夺人性命。谢天谢地，思考不会传染——至少在英国如此。

在文学中我们需要优异、魅力、美感和想象的魄力。我们不希望作品把下等阶级的所作所为描述一番，令人难受和恶心。

我完全承认现代小说有许多优点。我只不过坚持，作为一类书，它们没法读。

艺术本身就是一种夸张；艺术的精神在于甄选，它正是过度强调的一种强化模式。

事实不仅在历史中找到立足之地，而且逐渐在篡夺幻想的领域，并已经占领了传奇的王国。它们令人寒心地触碰着一切。它们让人类愈加庸俗。

社会迟早必须重投入它失去的领袖——那高雅迷人的说谎者的怀抱。

生活模仿艺术，远多于艺术模仿生活……生活向艺术举起镜子，要么复制画家或雕塑家想象的某种奇异事物，要么实现小说中的幻梦。

……模仿可以成为最恳切的一种侮辱。

昨晚阿伦德尔太太坚持要我走去窗前，看看她所谓的“天上荣光”。我当然不得不看。她是那种漂亮得不可理喻的俗人，你没法不答应她的任何要求。结果呢？那不过是一幅非常二流的透纳油画，属于透纳较差的时期，此画家最糟糕的缺点全都遭到夸张和过分的强调。

一种艺术越是抽象，越是理想化，就越可以向我们揭示它所属时代的气质。如果我们想通过艺术来了解一个国家，不妨看它的建筑，听它的音乐。

其实，我们完全仰赖了艺术的中介来回望历史，幸好，艺术从来就没有一次把真相告诉过我们。

成为一件艺术品是生活的宗旨。

英国人总把真实降级为事实。当真实变作事实的时候，就失去了它全部的智力价值。

小说从尾读起的好处一言难尽。最后一页通常最有兴味，当读者从灾难或结局开始，就会感到和作者平起平坐的愉悦，好比去剧场后台探班一样。人不再沉迷于故事，男主角绝处逢生，女主角呼天抢地，都完全令人无动于衷。读者知道了精心埋藏的秘密，那么，面对小说中傀儡们义不容辞地表现出的不必要的焦灼，就大可一笑而过。

一切风采翩翩的人，我猜，都是被惯坏了的。这是他们有魅力的秘诀。

给人建议总是一桩愚行，给人以好的建议则绝对是致命的。我希望你永远不犯这种错。否则，你将会追悔莫及。

你忘了，一件事并不由于有人为它丧命便是真实的。

艺术，哪怕是视野最完整、景象最开阔的艺术，也从未真的向我们呈现外在世界。它向我们呈现的只是我们自己的灵魂，那个我们唯一具有真切认识的世界……只有艺术能让我们发现自己。

评论家应当学会在评论一件艺术品的时候不谈及作者的个性。这其实是评论的开始。

如今每一个大人物都有门徒，而给他写传记的永远是犹大。

旁征博引的谈话要么是无知者的做作，要么是精神空虚者的专业。

教育是一件可敬的事。但最好不要忘了，值得了解的事情都不是能教的。

谁都能写一部三卷本的小说。这只需要对生活和文学全然无知。

谁都能创造历史。只有伟人能把它写出来。

有时听人说，艺术家生涯的悲剧在于他不能实现理想。但是大多数艺术家一路走来，妨碍他们的真正悲剧却在于他们把理想实现得太彻底。因为当理想实现时，它就失去了它的奇妙和神秘，仅仅变成了另一个理想的新起点。音乐是完美的艺术，这是原因所在。

交谈的话题，应该无所不触及，又无所偏重。

……生活极度缺乏形式。它的灾祸以错误方式发生在错误的人身上。它的喜剧有一种怪诞的恐怖，它的悲剧似乎以胡闹为高潮。人走近它的时候永远是受伤的。各种过程要么漫长，要么匆促。

……一切艺术都无关道德，除了较低层次的感官艺术或说教艺术，只有它们才会企图激起或邪恶或正义的行动。因为任何行动都属于道德领域。艺术的目标仅止于造成一种情绪。

世界上没有哪个国家像我们国家这样需要不切实际的人。在我们这儿，思想由于一直跟实践相联系而遭受贬低……我们活在一个工作过度，而又教养不足的时代；这时代的人勤勤恳恳，以至于变得愚不可及。

通向对生活无知的不二法门，是努力让自己有用。

人多么容易同情困苦，多么难同情思想。

一个不危险的观念根本不配称作观念。

人以自己的身份说话时最是言不由衷。给他一副面具，他就会道出真情。

因为何谓真实？在宗教方面，它不过是胜出的观点。在科学方面，它是最终的感觉。在艺术方面，它是人上一次的情绪。

不爱艺术有两种方式……一种是不爱它。另一种是理智地爱它。

一点点真诚会带来危险，大量的真诚绝对要致命。

看出美丽的事物蕴含着丑恶的意义，这样的人既堕落又不讨人喜欢。这是一种缺点。

看出美丽的事物蕴含着美丽的意义，这样的人有教养。他们身上有希望。

所谓道德的书和不道德的书都是无稽之谈。书要么写得好，要么写得糟。仅此而已。

恶习和美德对艺术家来说是艺术的素材。

一切艺术都兼具表面和象征。

揭开表面的人，风险自负。

解读象征的人，风险自负。

艺术之镜真正映出的是观者，不是生活。

评论家莫衷一是的时候，艺术家与自己达成了一致。

我们能原谅别人制作一件有用之物，只要他不欣赏它。制作一件无用之物的唯一理由是对它欣赏备至。

经验并没有伦理价值。大家只是用它来称呼自己犯过的错罢了。

一个人不再爱另一个人以后，对方表现出的感情总显得荒唐可笑。

自责含有一种奢侈。我们责备自己的时候，觉得别人都无权责备我们。给我们赦罪的是忏悔，不是神父。

不真诚有那么可怕？我不觉得。它只不过是一种令我们个性倍增的手段。

随着私有财产的废除，我们将会迎来真正、美好而健康的个人主义。将来不再有人会把生命浪费于积累物品和物品的符号上。人将会生活。生活是世界上最稀有的。多数人只是在生存，仅此而已。

社会之中只有一个阶级想钱比富人想得还多，那就是穷人。穷人没有别的可想。这是贫穷的痛苦。

民主一度被寄以厚望，但民主不过是代表人民者对人民的压迫。[3]

其实，文明需要奴隶。古希腊人的做法不无道理。除非有奴隶去做丑陋、可怕、无聊的工作，否则文化和沉思都遥不可及。人类奴隶制是错误、不安全且令人颓丧的。世界的未来有赖于机械奴隶制，有赖于奴役机器。

一件艺术品是一种独特心性的独到成果……艺术家一旦留意别人想要什么，并尝试有求必应的时候，他就不再是艺术家，而成了一个沉闷或逗笑的工匠，一个诚实或不诚实的买卖人。

艺术永远不应当努力做到通俗。公众应当努力学会鉴赏。

在英国，幸免于难的艺术，以那些不令公众感兴趣的艺术为最。诗歌这个例子可以佐证我的话。英国之所以继续有好诗，是因为公众不读诗，对它没有影响。

昔年人民受刑具之苦。如今他们被报章所误。

在英国，除了几个众所周知没有发展到粗暴无度的事例，报业依然是一个重要因素、一股可观的力量。它有意施于民众私生活的专横统治，以我看来非同寻常。其实，公众的好奇心是没有餍足的，他们什么都想知道，唯独对有价值的东西不感兴趣。报业深明此理，而且长于商人之道，对他们有求必应。在我们之前的很多个世纪，公众把记者的耳朵钉在水泵上。这骇人听闻。本世纪，记者把耳朵牢牢贴近钥匙孔。这样更加不堪。

谁都能够同情一个受苦的朋友，但同情一个成功的朋友，这就得有一种极好的性格——实际上，得有一个真正的个人主义者的性格。

工作是本国饮酒阶级的诅咒。

唯独没有想法的地方才有民意。

本身美丽的题材不能给艺术家以启发。它少了缺憾。

艺术是世界上唯一认真的事。艺术家是唯一从来不认真的人。

可以安慰穷人的只有挥霍。可以安慰富人的只有省俭。

人永远不该聆听。聆听意味着对你的听众漠不关心。

生活的头一件义务在于尽可能地做到人工化。第二件义务何在，迄今无人发现。

“坏”是好人杜撰的一种迷思，以此解释别人为何有奇异的魅力。

认为灵魂和肉体有区别的人这两样都没有。

一朵别在扣眼上的工艺精致的花，是艺术和自然的唯一联系。

宗教死于它们得到证实的时候。科学是已死宗教的记录。

上等人反驳别人。智者反驳自己。

真实发生的事，没有一桩是无足轻重的。

沉闷是严肃的成年阶段。

在所有不重要的事情上，风格而非诚意是基本要素；在所有重要的事情上，风格而非诚意是基本要素。

如果人说了真话，肯定是迟早要被识穿的。

人只该为了享受活着。幸福是最快变味的。

没有罪恶是粗俗的，但一切粗俗都是罪恶。粗俗是他人的行为举止。

唯独浅薄的人有自知之明。

时间是浪费金钱。

人永远应该有点不合常规。

一切良好的决心都有一个致命伤。那就是决心全都下得太快。

偶尔盛装过度只有一种补救，那就是，永远要绝对地表现出过度的学问。

执着于行为的对错观念，显示出智力发育的不完全。

“有野心”是失败的最后一种遁词。

人应该要么当一件艺术品，要么穿戴一件艺术品。

只有肤浅的性格才持久。人类较深沉的本性总被迅速识破。

产业是一切丑陋的根源。

各个时代以时空错杂的途径活在历史之中。

老年人无所不信，中年人无所不疑，青年人无所不晓。

完美性的条件是悠闲，完美性的目标是青春。

只有文体大师曾经成功地做到晦涩。

爱自己是终生浪漫之始。

啊，男人有一套律法，女人另有一套律法，这真是遗憾之至。我觉得，谁都应该无法无天才是。

第一杯之后，你看见的东西如你所愿。第二杯之后，你看见的东西似是而非。最后你看见了各种东西的本相，这是世界上最可怕的事。（谈苦艾酒）

我的存在是一桩丑闻。

生活中真实的悲剧，往往以一种难以言喻的方式发生，其伤人之处在于它们粗鲁的暴力、绝对的不连贯、荒谬的缺乏意义、彻底的没有风格。

一切同伴关系，不管婚姻还是友谊，纽带终究是谈话……

肉体的罪孽何足挂齿。它们只是让医生治疗的疾病，如果该治的话。只有灵魂的罪孽才可耻。

爱的目标就是去爱：不多，也不少。

对体验感到后悔是故步自封。否定自己的体验，是在个人生活的唇齿间放进一个谎言。那样无异于灵魂上的否定。

艺术家始终追寻的是灵肉合一而不相分割的存在模式：外在可以表现内在；形式即揭示。

依我如今看来，某个类型的爱恋，是人世间苦难深重的唯一合理解释。

大多数人是别人。他们的想法是别人的见解，他们的生活是一种模仿，他们的热情是一种照搬。

每件艺术品都是一个预言的实现：因为每件艺术品都是观念向形象转化而成的。

……一切伟大的观念都是危险的。

模仿结束的地方才是艺术开始之处……

一切糟糕的艺术都源于良好的意图。

出于天性和选择，我极其懒惰。

我从不推迟到明天——既然是可以后天做的事。

我天生属于例外，不属于规律。

赞美使我谦卑，但是谩骂纷起之际，我知道我摘到了星辰。

这一切何去何从呢？半个世界不相信上帝，另外半个世界不相信我。

假设我孤身一人滞留荒岛，而物品齐全的话，我每天晚餐时都会盛装打扮。

我有最单纯的品味。我向来只满意最好的。

由于爱国而身陷牢狱的爱国者爱他的国家，由于爱男孩子而坐牢的诗人爱男孩子。如果要改变我的人生，等于要我承认同性爱是不高贵的。我坚持认为它高贵，比其他形式的爱更高贵。

我进监狱时心如铁石，只考虑自己的享受，但现在我的心已被击碎，怜悯进入了我的心；我现在知道怜悯是世间最伟大也最美好的事物。所以，我无法怨恨那些控告我的人，也并不怨恨任何人，因为从前的我不会懂得这一切。

我不是一个为自己曾经坐牢感到羞愧的败类。令我羞愧难当的是那种把我送进牢狱的物质至上的生活。它跟一个艺术家大不相称。

我喜欢表演。它比生活真实太多。

人一旦上了年纪，活到看透的份儿上，就什么也看不透了。

老年的悲剧并不是人老迈，而是人稚嫩。

我会不惜一切来重获青春，除了锻炼身体、早起和循规蹈矩。

友善地对待自己毫不关心的人总是不难。

法律应该明文禁止自我牺牲。为别人牺牲自己，会极大地损害别人的志气。

英国人对美国的粗野兴致勃勃，对美国的文明兴味索然。

一件称身的衣物，对于两性都同样称身，根本没有什么分明属于女性的衣装。

实在是唯独有闲阶级才衣着不堪。任何需要体力劳动的时候，用到的服装通常都无比称身，因为劳动得有自由，而没有自由，就谈不上衣着之美。

穿上一身晚礼服，任何人，哪怕是证券经纪，也可以博得文雅之名。

只有浅薄的人才会不凭借外表作判断。

天然无饰只不过是一种姿态，据我所知是最讨厌的故作姿态。

也许人最自在的状态，莫过于他得要扮演某个角色的时候。

我觉得人应该虚构关于自己的神话。

一切艺术都毫无用处。

伟大的艺术家从来不会如实地观看事物。若然，他就不再是艺术家。

对美的欲望，不外乎生命欲望的一种高级形态。

挥霍是穷人的奢侈，吝啬是富人的奢侈。

世人常说，穷人对慈善感恩。当然有些人是感恩的，但是最优秀的穷人从来不会感恩。他们不感恩，愤愤不平，抗命，反叛。他们很有理由如此。

向穷人提倡节俭是既怪诞又无礼的。这好比建议挨饿的人减食。

他们（穷人）干吗要对从富人桌上洒落的面包屑感恩戴德？他们有平起平坐的权利，也渐渐知道了这一点。

穷人真正的悲剧在于，他们除了克己忘我就什么都没有条件做。美丽的罪孽，犹如美好的事物一样，是富人的特权。

狂恋是无所事事者的特权。一个国家的有闲阶级的用途莫不如此。

民族里代代相传的愚蠢——英国人健全的常识。

谁都能有常识，只要缺乏想象力。

我热衷于迷信。它们是思维和想象力的彩色元素。它们是常识的对手。

现在大多数人不知不觉地被一种常识拘禁终生，太晚才意识到人只对自己做错的事无悔。

自私不是过自己想过的生活，而是要求别人过自己想过的生活。

谈话属于最可爱的艺术之列。

谈话的目标在于消遣，不在于赐教。

“如果同伴乏味，那是你的错”这句格言，叫我们觉得未免乐观了些。

晚宴上遇见一位天才、一位公爵，这种时候，善谈者会试着把自己提升到天才的高度，而把公爵拉低到他自己的高度。要在社交场上高自己一等的人中间成功，你必须毫不犹豫地反驳他们。

一个人能在伦敦的晚宴上抢尽风头，就能在全世界抢尽风头。

我迷恋它们（伦敦的晚宴）。聪明人从不听别人说，蠢材从不开口。

向来只有智力上迷失的人要争辩。

相信是很无趣的。怀疑是引人入胜的。保持警醒是活着，沉陷于安全感是死去。

现在我从不赞成或反对什么。那样的人生态度是荒唐的。我们降生到世界上，并不是为了炫耀我们的道德偏见。

使人笃信不疑的事物从来都不真实。那是信仰的致命伤，和传奇的教训。

没有人殉身他了解的真实。人殉身他们期望的真实，殉身他们内心深处恐怖地知道并不真实的东西。

谋杀总是错的。人不该做任何一件不能在晚宴后谈起的事。

现代罪案的元祖是贫困，不是罪孽。

习惯性地用惩罚来治理会造成社区野蛮化，其恶果远远大于偶尔发生的罪案。

牢狱生涯叫人如实地看见人和事物。所以监狱使人变得冷酷。监狱外的人被幻象所迷惑，才以为生活在不断变动。

对身在狱中的人，眼泪属于日常的体验。在监狱里不曾哭泣的一天是心灵冷酷的一天，并不是心灵快乐的一天。

（牢狱生涯）最可怕的事不是它令人心碎——心天生是易碎的——而是它令人心如铁石。

正因为一个人没有能力做某件事，他才适合做这件事的裁判。

玩火唯一的好处……是玩火者永远不会被灼伤。不懂玩火的才是会被烧伤的人。

何谓犬儒主义者[4]？他们知道所有东西的价格，却不知道任何东西的价值。

感伤主义者内心永远是个犬儒主义者。没错，感伤主义不过是犬儒主义者休假的表现。

感伤主义者不过是个想要情感的奢侈又不愿为之付出的人。

他是个典型的英国人，永远乏味，时常粗暴。

像所有要把一个话题说尽的人那样，他说到听众全都筋疲力尽。

她举止像是个美人儿。美国女性大多如此。这是她们的魅力之源。

她努力打扮得像幅画，结果却显得景象凌乱。

（她）滔滔不绝而言语空洞，比我见识过的任何人更甚。她是个天生的演说家。

一个土气、乏味的姑娘，长着某一种典型的英国面孔，叫人一见之下再也回忆不起来。

不满是驱使一个人或一个民族前进的第一步。

在任何一个熟知历史的人看来，抗命是人类的原德[5]。进步是通过抗命——抗命和反叛——取得的。

如同在政治的领域一样，艺术领域的革命全都出自一个来源，那就是人追求一种更高贵的生活形态、更自由的表达方式和机会的愿望。

一个绅士的首要责任是梦想。

梦想家是只能借着月光认路的人，他受到的惩罚在于他比全世界更早看见曙光。

社会往往宽恕罪犯；它从不宽恕梦想家。

唯一比梦想家有更多幻觉的人是行动家。

我对自己的责任是让自己乐趣无穷。

世人从不考虑培育少女的想象力。这是现代教育的重大缺点。

我们教人记诵，我们从不教他们成长。

牛津在夏季学期开课传授闲逸这一门精妙的艺术，这是任何大学能传授的最重要的东西之一。

生活的秘诀是永远不要怀着不得体的情感。

只有浅薄的人，才需要用很多年来摆脱一份情感。能放能收的人了断一种哀愁，跟他生发一种快乐同样轻易。

啤酒、《圣经》和七宗致命的美德[6]，造就了我们今天的英格兰。

英国公众在听一个庸才讲话的时候永远感到无比舒服。

家庭真是一种可怕的妨碍，尤其是当人未婚的时候。

时装不过是一种难以承受的丑陋，我们忍无可忍，只好每半年改换它一次。

始于一句夸奖的相识必然会深化为真正的友谊。以这种方式开始是对的。

一场友谊从笑声开始一点也不赖，而且它绝对是友谊最好的收尾。

我对新朋友总想无所不知，对老朋友总想一无所知。

礼俗客套会让亲密友谊变得紧张。

儿女最初爱恋父母。过些年，他们评判父母。他们绝少（哪怕真有）会原谅父母。

我们这个灰蒙蒙的、又大又丑的伦敦呀，容纳着它难以计数的居民、它龌龊的罪人，和它辉煌的罪恶。

我不喜欢瑞士：它只出产过神学家和侍者。

对于专制者可以说一句好话：他是一个人，因此可能有教养，而乌合之众是一头怪物，绝无教养。

历史从不自我重复。历史学家们互相重复。

我们对历史的唯一义务是重写它。

我们全都喜欢把别人设想得很好，原因是我们全都替自己担忧。乐观主义的基础在于纯然的恐惧。

笑是对待生命的原初态度——这种模式只在艺术家和罪犯身上依然存在。

什么都不做是世界上最困难的事——最困难且最智性的。

生活的目标是自我完善。去完美地实现个人的天性——我们人人都为此而生。

有时候人会多年来浑浑噩噩地活着，然后在一个钟点之内经历生命的密集冲撞。

我们在生活中顶多只会有一种伟大的体验，而生活的秘诀就在于尽可能频繁地重复那体验。

别跟我说你榨干了生活的可能性。一个男人这么说，旁人便知道是生活榨干了他。

变成自己生活的旁观者，就是逃逸出生活的苦难。

生活用影子来玩弄我们。我们向它求取享受。它给我们享受，继之以苦恼和失望。

文学总是预言了生活。它不抄袭生活，而是照它的目标来塑造生活。我们所知的19世纪，一大半是巴尔扎克发明的。

我讨厌文学中的庸俗写实主义。实话照说的人应该被逼着拿起铁锹[7]。

难道没有一些书让我们在一小时内获得生命的丰收，盖过我们二十年乏善可陈的人生？

把真人放进小说或戏剧，意味着想象力贫乏的头脑、粗糙而不老练的观察、文体的完全缺失。

世人称为伤风败俗的书，是一些把世界的可耻面目展示出来的书。

没有人能经受高估，要毁掉一个作者的声望，最有力的手段莫过于一味地赞美他、过分地颂扬他。

所有爱情都是一场悲剧。

误会……是爱情的基础。

忠贞者只知道爱情琐碎的一面；不忠者才知道爱情的悲剧。

在感情生活方面忠贞，正如在智力生活方面见解始终不变——不外乎承认失败。

色欲……使人爱恋自己憎恶的一切。

人很难不对所爱的不公平。

人应该永远恋爱。因此之故，人应该永远不结婚。

婚姻的适当基础是互相误会。

婚姻生活只是一个习惯，一个坏习惯。

婚姻多么能毁掉男人！它跟香烟一样令人丧志，而价格贵得多。

已婚男人的幸福……取决于他没有娶的那些人。

婚姻只有一个魅力，那就是它让双方完全必要地过上哄骗的生活。

任何看似幸福婚姻的东西，现在都会引来世界的深深怀疑。

一个丈夫如今在公共场合对妻子注目是最危险的。旁人看了，总会认为这丈夫在夫妇独处的时候殴打妻子。

这年头所有人妒忌所有人，当然，无人妒忌夫妻。

谈二十年恋爱，女人看上去会像一座废墟；结二十年婚，她会变成公共建筑一类的东西。

姑娘从来不跟调情的对象结婚。姑娘觉得这样不对。

男人结婚是因为疲倦；女人是因为好奇。两者都感到失望。

男人太早懂得生活……女人太晚懂得生活。这是男女的区别。

女人只有一个改造男人的办法：令他彻底厌倦，以至他对生活完全失去兴趣。

男人一旦爱过一个女人，就会为她做任何事，但继续爱她除外。

男人跟任何女人在一起都能够快乐，只要是他不爱的女人。

男人总想做女人的初恋。那是他们笨拙的虚荣……女人对事物有较为精细的本能。（她们）喜欢的是做男人的最后一段罗曼史。

女人的生活中只有一个真正的悲剧：过去永远是她的爱人，而她的将来一成不变的是她的丈夫。

男女之间没有友谊。有激情、敌意、崇拜、爱，但没有友谊。

女人对事物有一种奇妙的本能。她们能发现一切，偏偏看不到最明显的。

人永远不该信任说出自己真实年龄的女人。连这个都说的女人，是无所不言的。

藏起面孔的女人总是要么奇丑，要么极美。

如果女人想控制一个男人，只需勾起他最坏的本性。

我旅行必带日记。坐火车，手上永远应该有一本耸动视听的读物。

假如我们不怕有人捡，我们会丢掉的东西有很多。

人何以落得身败名裂？毁灭何以有这样的魅力？

人需要不幸才能幸福地生活。

要活得幸福，你必须知道人生的某些不幸福。

世界上幸福的人有他们的价值，但仅仅是反衬作用的负值。他们令不幸福者的美感和魅力格外突出。

火烧而不毁的，益加坚固。

苦难和苦难的共同体使人们善良。

虽然打算成为更好的人是种没有科学根据的空谈，但曾经受苦的人确实独具优势，可以变成更有深度的人。

哀愁是无与伦比的真实。有些时候，我觉得哀愁是唯一的真实。

一切放纵，与一切克制相同，都会自食其果。

过度会带来无与伦比的成功。

形式上纯粹的现代性总是带有庸俗的倾向。

没什么比做得太现代更危险：它容易一下子就过时。

电话的价值，在于两人要说的话的价值。

只有一样东西始终叫我迷恋不已：情绪的奥秘。做这些情绪的主人是美妙的，凭它们做主又更加妙不可言。

你们这些标榜自己始终如一的人，跟别人会有一样多的情绪。仅有的差别在于你们的情绪没什么意义。

没有一种情绪是人不能感同身受的，没有一种暮气沉沉的生活是不能重焕朝气的。

道德只是我们对自己反感的人作出的姿态。

道德属于无稽之谈，因为心灵的健康没有通用法则；它是全然个人的，因人而异。

现代道德无非是接受生当其时的标准。我认为，任何有教养的人接受生当其时的标准，都是一种最重大的不道德行径。

举止风度比道德准则重要。

道德教训再明显不过。

我遇到的满腔道德感的人，没有一个不是硬心肠、冷酷、报复心重、愚蠢不堪、缺乏丝毫人情味的。所谓道德人士，是些简单的禽兽。

音乐这门艺术……最完全地实现了艺术的观念，它处于其他一切艺术时时在追求的境界。

音乐……给人开创了一个先前自己不知晓的过去，使人内心充满流泪时未曾体会的各种哀愁。

如果你弹奏出优美的音乐，人们会充耳不闻，如果你弹奏出糟糕的音乐，人们会一言不发。

我偏爱瓦格纳的音乐胜过别人的。它大吵大闹，由始至终你都可以谈话，又不会被人听见说了什么。

音乐界的人蛮不讲理。他们总是偏偏在你渴望完全耳聋的时候，希望你哑口无声。

天地万物并不属于我们；我们怎样领受的，就该怎样留给子孙。

至少在我而言，自然之中有治愈的力量。

我们全都对自然审视太多，与她共生太少。

假如自然令人舒适，人类就永远不会发明建筑。

自然令一切不会常驻，它永远在自我循环，好让造化的一切都不消失。

自然总是落后于时代。

每当我们回归于生活和自然，我们的作品总会变得粗俗、平庸、无趣。

只有两种人真正有魅力——无所不知的，和一无所知的。

我当然剽窃。这是赏识者的特权。

缺乏想象力的人方才杜撰。真艺术家的标志，就在于他把东西据为己有的手法，而他把一切都据为己有。

一出戏里的每一个词都既有智力上的也有音韵上的价值，它得传达出某种情感。

我从不给任何人写戏。我写戏是自娱自乐。过后，如果有人想演它，我有时会予以准许。

你可以用两种方式不欣赏我的话剧：要么统统不欣赏，要么欣赏《不可儿戏》[8]。

愉悦是大自然的测验，是她表达赞许的信号。人觉得开心，就是他跟自己和环境都和谐共处的时候。

没有文明人会去懊悔一次享受，粗鄙者从来不知享受为何物。

我钟爱简单的享受。它们是复杂之人最后的避难所。

一支烟就是一次完美享受的完美体现。它精致，又叫人意犹未尽，还奢求什么呢？

我没有一刻后悔过自己为了享受而活。我这样生活做到了极致，因为每个人都应该把自己做的事做到极致。我体验过的享受无所不有。

我喜欢人多于原则，我喜欢没有原则的人多于世上的一切。

我不喜欢原则……我宁可要偏见。

驱动时代的是人物，不是原则。

我纳闷是谁把人定义为理性动物。这是古往今来最不成熟的定义了。人是什么，一言难尽，但人并不理性。

我很想把人定义为理性动物——这种理性动物一到需要依照理性的指令行事时就发脾气。

期望别人和自己一样出色是不公平的。

只有乏味的人会在早餐时才华横溢。

[1] 《圣经•创世记》中，罗得的妻子未遵从天使的告诫，回望了自己所逃出的罪恶之城，化作盐柱。（说明：书中脚注均为译者注。）

[2] 外郡原文是provinces，指伦敦地区以外的各郡，一般认为外郡的人不如首都的人那么练达。

[3] 原文“democracy means simply the bludgeoning of the people by the people for the people”套用美国总统林肯葛底斯堡演说的名言“民有，民治，民享”（of the people, by the people, for the people）而去掉了其中的逗号铸成新意，有特殊的幽默感。

[4] 犬儒主义（Cynicism）是古希腊的一个哲学流派，英文中大写的Cynic译为“犬儒”。在近现代，小写的cynicism则泛称这样一种人生态度：不相信世间有超越自私自利之心的高贵品质。它近乎“理想主义”的反义词。

[5] 与基督教的概念“原罪”相对。

[6] 天主教中有七美德，是相对于七宗罪而提出的。“致命的”（deadly）原是七宗罪，挪用来形容“七美德”有揶揄之意。

[7] “实话照说”的原文“call a spade a spade”是一句古老的俗语，字面意义即“把铁锹叫成铁锹”。

[8] 原文剧名用简称Earnest，全称为The Importance of Being Earnest。

Only Dull People are Brilliant at Breakfast

To know nothing about their great men is one of the necessary elements of English education.

We spend our days, each one of us, in looking for the secret of life. Well, the secret of life is in art.

The supreme object of life is to live. Few people live. It is true life only to realize one’s own perfection, to make one’s every dream a reality.

To me the life of the businessman who eats his breakfast early in the morning, catches a train for the city, stays there in the dingy, dusty atmosphere of the commercial world, and goes back to his house in the evening, and after supper to sleep, is worse than the life of the galley slave – his chains are golden instead of iron.

Bad art is a great deal worse than no art at all.

. . . nothing is worth doing except what the world says is impossible.

To make a good salad is to be a brilliant diplomatist –the problem is entirely the same in both cases. To know exactly how much oil one must put with one’s vinegar.

Life is much too important a thing ever to talk seriously about it.

There is always more brass than brains in an aristocracy.

Good kings are the only dangerous enemies that modern democracy has.

I have always been of the opinion that consistency is the last refuge of the unimaginative . . .

. . . the British cook is a foolish woman, who should be turned, for her iniquities, into a pillar of that salt which she never knows how to use.

Of Shakespeare it may be said he was the first to see the dramatic value of doublets, and that a climax may depend on a crinoline.

. . . the stage is not merely the meeting- place of all the arts, but is also the return of art to life.

The true dramatist . . . shows us life under the conditions of art, not art in the form of life.

. . . our ordinary English novelists . . . fail . . . in concentration of style. Their characters are far too eloquent and talk themselves to tatters. What we want is a little more reality and a little less rhetoric . . . we wish that they would talk less and think more.

They lead us through a barren desert of verbiage to a mirage that they call life: we wander aimlessly through a very wilderness of words in search of one touch of nature. However, one should not be too severe on English novels; they are the only relaxation of the intellectually unemployed.

A poet can survive everything but a misprint.

. . . a poet without hysterics is rare.

There is no such thing as a stupid American. Many Americans are horrid, vulgar, intrusive and impertinent, just as many English people are also; but stupidity is not one of the national vices. Indeed, in America there is no opening for a fool. They expect brains even from a boot- black, and get them.

As for marriage, it is one of their most popular institutions. The American man marries early, and the American woman marries often; and they get on extremely well together.

America has never quite forgiven Europe for having been discovered somewhat earlier in history than itself.

. . . it would be a very good thing if people were taught how to speak. Language is the noblest instrument we have, either for the revealing or the concealing of thought; talk itself is a sort of spiritualized action; and conversation is one of the loveliest of the arts.

The only form of fiction in which real characters do not seem out of place is history.

Early in life she had discovered the important truth that nothing looks so like innocence as an indiscretion; and by a series of reckless escapades, half of them quite harmless, she had acquired all the privileges of a personality. She had more than once changed her husband; indeed, Debrett credits her with three marriages; but as she had never changed her lover, the world had long ago ceased to talk scandal about her.

Unless one is wealthy there is no use in being a charming fellow. Romance is the privilege of the rich, not the profession of the unemployed. The poor should be practical and prosaic. It is better to have a permanent income than to be fascinating.

Nobody, even in the provinces, should ever be allowed to ask an intelligent question about pure mathematics across a dinner table. A question of this kind is quite as bad as inquiring suddenly about the state of a man’s soul . . .

But what is the good of friendship if one cannot say exactly what one means? Anybody can say charming things and try to please and to flatter, but a true friend always says unpleasant things, and does not mind giving pain. Indeed, if he is a really true friend he prefers it, for he knows that then he is doing good.

The only thing that sustains one through life is the consciousness of the immense inferiority of everybody else, and this is a feeling that I have always cultivated.

I am so clever that sometimes I don’t understand a single word of what I am saying.

I have always been of opinion that hard work is simply the refuge of people who have nothing whatever to do. All that is known by that term [fin de siècle ] I particularly admire and love. It is the fine flower of our civilization: the only thing that keeps the world from the commonplace, the coarse, the barbarous.

Flaubert did not write French prose, but the prose of a great artist who happened to be French.

I was thinking in bed this morning that the great superiority of France over England is that in France every bourgeois wants to be an artist, whereas in England every artist wants to be a bourgeois.

Prayer must never be answered: if it is, it ceases to be prayer and becomes correspondence.

I have made an important discovery . . . that alcohol, taken in sufficient quantities, produces all the effects of intoxication.

Missionaries, my dear! Don’t you realize that missionaries are the divinely provided food for destitute and underfed cannibals? Whenever they are on the brink of starvation, Heaven in its infinite mercy sends them a nice plump missionary.

Philosophy teaches us to bear with equanimity the misfortunes of others.

My own experience is that the more we study Art, the less we care for Nature . . . Art is our spirited protest, our gallant attempt to teach Nature her proper place.

Thinking is the most unhealthy thing in the world, and people die of it just as they die of any other disease. Fortunately, in England at any rate, thought is not catching.

In literature we require distinction, charm, beauty and imaginative power. We don’t want to be harrowed and disgusted with an account of the doings of the lower orders.

I quite admit that modern novels have many good points. All I insist on is that, as a class, they are quite unreadable.

Art itself is really a form of exaggeration; and selection, which is the very spirit of art, is nothing more than an intensified mode of over- emphasis.

Facts are not merely finding a footing- place in history, but they are usurping the domain of Fancy, and have invaded the kingdom of Romance. Their chilling touch is over everything. They are vulgarizing mankind.

Society sooner or later must return to its lost leader, the cultured and fascinating liar.

Life imitates Art far more than Art imitates Life . . . Life holds the mirror up to Art, and either reproduces some strange type imagined by painter or sculptor, or realizes in fact what has been dreamed in fiction.

. . . imitation can be made the sincerest form of insult.

Yesterday evening Mrs Arundel insisted on my going to the window, and looking at the glorious sky, as she called it. Of course I had to look at it. She is one of those absurdly pretty Philistines to whom one can deny nothing. And what was it? It was simply a very second- rate Turner, a Turner of a bad period, with all the painter’s worst faults exaggerated and over- emphasized.

The more abstract, the more ideal an art is, the more it reveals to us the temper of its age. If we wish to understand a nation by means of its art, let us look at its architecture or its music.

The fact is that we look back on the ages entirely through the medium of art, and art, very fortunately, has never once told us the truth.

To become a work of art is the object of living.

The English are always degrading truths into facts. When a truth becomes a fact it loses all its intellectual value.

There is a great deal to be said in favour of reading a novel backwards. The last page is as a rule the most interesting, and when one begins with the catastrophe or the dénouement one feels on pleasant terms of equality with the author. It is like going behind the scenes of a theatre. One is no longer taken in, and the hair- breadth escapes of the hero and the wild agonies of the heroine leave one absolutely unmoved. One knows the jealously guarded secret, and one can afford to smile at the quite unnecessary anxiety that the puppets of fiction always consider it their duty to display.

All charming people, I fancy, are spoiled. It is the secret of their attraction.

It is always a silly thing to give advice, but to give good advice is absolutely fatal. I hope you will never fall into that error. If you do, you will be sorry for it.

You forget that a thing is not necessarily true because a man dies for it.

Art, even the art of fullest scope and widest vision, can never really show us the external world. All that it shows us is our own soul, the one world of which we have any real cognizance . . . It is Art, and Art only, that reveals us to ourselves.

A critic should be taught to criticize a work of art without making any reference to the personality of the author. This, in fact, is the beginning of criticism.

Every great man nowadays has his disciples, and it is always Judas who writes the biography.

Learned conversation is either the affectation of the ignorant or the profession of the mentally unemployed.

Education is an admirable thing. But it is well to remember from time to time that nothing that is worth knowing can be taught.

Anybody can write a three- volume novel. It merely requires a complete ignorance of both life and literature.

Anybody can make history. Only a great man can write it.

It is sometimes said that the tragedy of an artist’s life is that he cannot realize his ideal. But the true tragedy that dogs the steps of most artists is that they realize their ideal too absolutely. For, when the ideal is realized, it is robbed of its wonder and its mystery, and becomes simply a new starting- point for an ideal that is other than itself. This is the reason why music is the perfect type of art.

Conversation should touch everything, but should concentrate itself on nothing.

. . . life is terribly deficient in form. Its catastrophes happen in the wrong way and to the wrong people. There is a grotesque horror about its comedies, and its tragedies seem to culminate in farce. One is always wounded when one approaches it. Things last either too long or not long enough.

. . . all the arts are immoral, except those baser forms of sensual or didactic art that seek to excite to action of evil or of good. For action of every kind belongs to the sphere of ethics. The aim of art is simply to create a mood.

There is no country in the world so much in need of unpractical people as this country of ours. With us, Thought is degraded by its constant association with practice . . . We live in the age of the overworked, and the under- educated; the age in which people are so industrious that they become absolutely stupid.

The sure way of knowing nothing about life is to try to make oneself useful.

It is so easy for people to have sympathy with suffering. It is so difficult for them to have sympathy with thought.

An idea that is not dangerous is unworthy of being called an idea at all.

Man is least himself when he talks in his own person. Give him a mask, and he will tell you the truth.

For what is Truth? In matters of religion, it is simply the opinion that has survived. In matters of science, it is the ultimate sensation. In matters of art, it is one’s last mood.

There are two ways of disliking art . . . One is to dislike it. The other, to like it rationally.

A little sincerity is a dangerous thing, and a great deal of it is absolutely fatal.

Those who find ugly meanings in beautiful things are corrupt without being charming. This is a fault.

Those who find beautiful meanings in beautiful things are the cultivated. For these there is hope.

There is no such thing as a moral or an immoral book. Books are well written, or badly written. That is all.

Vice and virtue are to the artist materials for an art.

All art is at once surface and symbol.

Those who go beneath the surface do so at their peril.

Those who read the symbol do so at their peril.

It is the spectator, and not life, that art really mirrors.

When critics disagree the artist is in accord with himself.

We can forgive a man for making a useful thing as long as he does not admire it. The only excuse for making a useless thing is that one admires it intensely.

Experience was of no ethical value. It was merely the name men gave to their mistakes.

There is always something ridiculous about the emotions of people whom one has ceased to love.

There is a luxury in self- reproach. When we blame ourselves we feel that no one else has a right to blame us. It is the confession, not the priest, that gives us absolution.

Is insincerity such a terrible thing? I think not. It is merely a method by which we can multiply our personalities.

With the abolition of private property, then, we shall have true, beautiful, healthy Individualism. Nobody will waste his life in accumulating things, and the symbols for things. One will live. To live is the rarest thing in the world. Most people exist, that is all.

There is only one class in the community that thinks more about money than the rich, and that is the poor. The poor can think of nothing else. That is the misery of being poor.

High hopes were once formed of democracy; but democracy means simply the bludgeoning of the people by the people for the people.

The fact is, that civilization requires slaves. The Greeks were quite right there. Unless there are slaves to do the ugly, horrible, uninteresting work, culture and contemplation become almost impossible. Human slavery is wrong, insecure and demoralizing. On mechanical slavery, on the slavery of the machine, the future of the world depends.

A work of art is the unique result of a unique temperament . . . the moment that an artist takes notice of what other people want, and tries to supply the demand, he ceases to be an artist, and becomes a dull or an amusing craftsman, an honest or a dishonest tradesman.

Now Art should never try to be popular. The public should try to make itself artistic.

In England, the arts that have escaped best are the arts in which the public take no interest. Poetry is an instance of what I mean. We have been able to have fine poetry in England because the public do not read it, and consequently do not influence it.

In the old days men had the rack. Now they have the Press.

In England, Journalism, except in a few wellknown instances, not having been carried to such excesses of brutality, is still a great factor, a really remarkable power. The tyranny that it proposes to exercise over people’s private lives seems to me to be quite extraordinary. The fact is that the public have an insatiable curiosity to know everything, except what is worth knowing. Journalism, conscious of this, and having tradesman- like habits, supplies their demands. In centuries before ours the public nailed the ears of journalists to the pump. That was quite hideous. In this century journalists have nailed their own ears to the keyhole. That is much worse.

Anybody can sympathize with the sufferings of a friend, but it requires a very fine nature – it requires, in fact, that nature of a true Individualist – to sympathize with a friend’s success.

Work is the curse of the drinking classes of this country.

Public opinion exists only where there are no ideas.

A subject that is beautiful in itself gives no suggestion to the artist. It lacks imperfection.

Art is the only serious thing in the world. And the artist is the only person who is never serious.

The only thing that can console one for being poor is extravagance. The only thing that can console one for being rich is economy.

One should never listen. To listen is a sign of indifference to one’s hearers.

The first duty in life is to be as artificial as possible. What the second duty is no one has as yet discovered.

Wickedness is a myth invented by good people to account for the curious attractiveness of others.

Those who see any difference between soul and body have neither.

A really well- made buttonhole is the only link between Art and Nature.

Religions die when they are proved to be true. Science is the record of dead religions.

The well- bred contradict other people. The wise contradict themselves.

Nothing that actually occurs is of the smallest importance.

Dullness is the coming of age of seriousness.

In all unimportant matters, style, not sincerity, is the essential. In all important matters, style, not sincerity, is the essential.

If one tells the truth, one is sure, sooner or later, to be found out.

Pleasure is the only thing one should live for. Nothing ages like happiness.

No crime is vulgar, but all vulgarity is crime. Vulgarity is the conduct of others.

Only the shallow know themselves.

Time is waste of money.

One should always be a little improbable.

There is a fatality about all good resolutions. They are invariably made too soon.

The only way to atone for being occasionally a little over- dressed is by being always absolutely overeducated.

Any preoccupation with ideas of what is right or wrong in conduct shows an arrested intellectual development.

Ambition is the last refuge of the failure.

One should either be a work of art, or wear a work of art.

It is only the superficial qualities that last. Man’s deeper nature is soon found out.

Industry is the root of all ugliness.

The ages live in history through their anachronisms.

The old believe everything: the middle- aged suspect everything: the young know everything.

The condition of perfection is idleness: the aim of perfection is youth.

Only the great masters of style ever succeed in being obscure.

To love oneself is the beginning of a life- long romance.

Oh, it is indeed a burning shame that there would be one law for men and another law for women. I think that there should be no law for anybody.

After the first glass, you see things as you wish they were. After the second, you see things as they are not. Finally you see things as they really are, and that is the most horrible thing in the world. (On absinthe)

My existence is a scandal.

It often happens that the real tragedies of life occur in such an inarticulate manner that they hurt one by their crude violence, their absolute incoherence, their absurd want of meaning, their entire lack of style.

Ultimately the bond of all companionship, whether in marriage or in friendship, is conversation . . .

Sins of the flesh are nothing. They are maladies for physicians to cure, if they should be cured. Sins of the soul alone are shameful.

The aim of love is to love: no more, and no less.

To regret one’s own experiences is to arrest one’s own development. To deny one’s own experiences is to put a lie into the lips of one’s own life. It is no less than a denial of the soul.

What the artist is always looking for is the mode of existence in which soul and body are one and indivisible: in which the outward is expressive of the inward: in which form reveals.

Now it seems to me that love of some kind is the only possible explanation of the extraordinary amount of suffering that there is in the world.

Most people are other people. Their thoughts are someone else’s opinions, their lives a mimicry, their passions a quotation.

Every single work of art is the fulfilment of a prophecy: for every work of art is the conversion of an idea into an image.

. . . all great ideas are dangerous.

Art only begins where Imitation ends . . .

All bad art is the result of good intentions.

By nature and by choice, I am extremely indolent.

I never put off till tomorrow what I can possibly do – the day after.

I am one of those who are made for exceptions, not for laws.

Praise makes me humble, but when I am abused I know I have touched the stars.

Where will it all end? Half the world does not believe in God, and the other half does not believe in me.

If I were all alone, marooned on some desert island and had my things with me, I should dress for dinner every evening.

I have the simplest tastes. I am always satisfied with the best.

A patriot put in prison for loving his country loves his country, and a poet in prison for loving boys loves boys. To have altered my life would have been to have admitted that Uranian love is ignoble. I hold it to be noble, more noble than other forms.

I entered prison with a heart of stone, thinking only of my pleasure, but now my heart has been broken; pity has entered my heart; I now understand that pity is the greatest and the most beautiful thing that there is in the world. And that’s why I can’t be angry with those who condemned me, nor with anyone, because then I would not have known all that.

I am not a scrap ashamed of having been in prison. I am horribly ashamed of the materialism of the life that brought me there. It was quite unworthy of an artist.

I love acting. It is so much more real than life.

As soon as people are old enough to know better, they don’t know anything at all.

The tragedy of old age is not that one is old, but that one is young.

To get back my youth I would do anything in the world, except take exercise, get up early, or be respectable.

One can always be kind to people about whom one cares nothing.

Self- sacrifice is a thing that should be put down by law. It is so demoralizing to the people for whom one sacrifices oneself.

English people are far more interested in American barbarism than they are in American civilization.

Every right article of apparel belongs equally to both sexes, and there is absolutely no such thing as a definitely feminine garment.

It is really only the idle classes who dress badly. Wherever physical labour of any kind is required, the costume used is, as a rule, absolutely right, for labour necessitates freedom, and without freedom there is no such thing as beauty in dress at all.

With an evening coat and a white tie, anybody, even a stock- broker, can gain a reputation for being civilized.

It is only shallow people who do not judge by appearances.

Being natural is simply a pose, and the most irritating pose I know.

Perhaps one never seems so much at one’s ease as when one has to play a part.

I think a man should invent his own myth.

All art is quite useless.

No great artist ever sees things as they really are. If he did, he would cease to be an artist.

The desire for beauty is merely a heightened form of the desire for life.

Extravagance is the luxury of the poor, penury the luxury of the rich.

We are often told that the poor are grateful for charity. Some of them are, no doubt, but the best amongst the poor are never grateful. They are ungrateful, discontented, disobedient, and rebellious. They are quite right to be so.

To recommend thrift to the poor is both grotesque and insulting. It is like advising a man who is starving to eat less.

Why should they [the poor] be grateful for the crumbs that fall from the rich man’s table? They should be seated at the board, and are beginning to know it.

The real tragedy of the poor is that they can afford nothing but self- denial. Beautiful sins, like beautiful things, are the privilege of the rich.

A grande passion is the privilege of people who have nothing to do. That is the one use of the idle classes of a country.

The inherited stupidity of the race – sound English common sense.

Anybody can have common sense, provided that they have no imagination.

I love superstitions. They are the colour element of thought and imagination. They are the opponents of common sense.

Nowadays most people die of a sort of creeping common sense, and discover, when it is too late, that the only thing one never regrets are one’s mistakes.

Selfishness is not living as one wishes to live, it is asking others to live as one wishes to live.

Conversation is one of the loveliest of the arts.

Recreation, not instruction, is the aim of conversation.

The maxim ‘If you find the company dull, blame yourself’ seems to us somewhat optimistic.

In the case of meeting a genius and a duke at dinner, the good talker will try to raise himself to the level of the former and to bring the latter down to his own level. To succeed among one’s social superiors one must have no hesitation in contradicting them.

A man who can dominate a London dinner table can dominate the world.

I adore them [London dinner parties]. The clever people never listen, and the stupid people never talk.

It is only the intellectually lost who ever argue.

To believe is very dull. To doubt is intensely engrossing. To be on the alert is to live, to be lulled into security is to die.

I never approve, or disapprove, of anything now. It is an absurd attitude to take towards life. We are not sent into the world to air our moral prejudices.

The things one feels absolutely certain about are never true. That is the fatality of Faith, and the lesson of Romance.

No man dies for what he knows to be true. Men die for what they want to be true, for what some terror in their hearts tells them is not true.

Murder is always a mistake. One should never do anything that one cannot talk about after dinner.

Starvation, and not sin, is the parent of modern crime.

A community is infinitely more brutalized by the habitual employment of punishment, than it is by the occasional occurrence of crime.

Prison life makes one see people and things as they really are. That is why it turns one to stone. It is the people outside who are deceived by the illusion of a life in constant motion.

To those who are in prison, tears are a part of every day’s experience. A day in prison on which one does not weep is a day on which one’s heart is hard, not a day on which one’s heart is happy.

The most terrible thing about it [imprisonment] is not that it breaks one’s heart – hearts are made to be broken – but that it turns one’s heart to stone.

It is exactly because a man cannot do a thing that he is the proper judge of it.

The one advantage of playing with fire . . . is that one never even gets singed. It is the people who don’t know how to play with it who get burned up.

What is a cynic? A man who knows the price of everything and the value of nothing.

The sentimentalist is always a cynic at heart. Indeed sentimentality is merely the bank holiday of cynicism.

A sentimentalist is simply a man who desires to have the luxury of an emotion without paying for it.

He is a typical Englishman, always dull and usually violent.

Like all people who try to exhaust a subject, he exhausted his listeners.

She behaves as if she was beautiful. Most American women do. It is the secret of their charm.

She tried to look picturesque, but only succeeded in being untidy.

[She] talks more and says less than anybody I ever met. She is made to be a public speaker.

A dowdy dull girl, with one of those characteristic British faces, that, once seen, are never remembered.

Discontent is the first step in the progress of a man or a nation.

Disobedience, in the eyes of anyone who has read history, is man’s original virtue. It is through disobedience that progress has been made, through disobedience and through rebellion.

In art, as in politics, there is but one origin for all revolutions, a desire on the part of man for a nobler form of life, for a freer method and opportunity of expression.

It is the first duty of a gentleman to dream.

A dreamer is one who can only find his way by moonlight, and his punishment is that he sees the dawn before the rest of the world.

Society often forgives the criminal; it never forgives the dreamer.

The one person who has more illusions than the dreamer is the man of action.

My duty to myself is to amuse myself terrifically.

People never think of cultivating a young girl’s imagination. It is the great defect of modern education.

We teach people how to remember, we never teach them how to grow.

In the summer term Oxford teaches the exquisite art of idleness, one of the most important things that any University can teach.

The secret of life is never to have an emotion that is unbecoming.

It is only shallow people who require years to get rid of an emotion. A man who is master of himself can end a sorrow as easily as he can invent a pleasure.

Beer, the Bible, and the seven deadly virtues have made our England what she is.

The English public always feels perfectly at its ease when a mediocrity is talking to it.

A family is a terrible encumbrance, especially when one is not married.

Fashion is merely a form of ugliness so unbearable that we are compelled to alter it every six months.

An acquaintance that begins with a compliment is sure to develop into a real friendship. It starts in the right manner.

Laughter is not at all a bad beginning for a friendship, and it is far the best ending for one.

I always like to know everything about my new friends, and nothing about my old ones.

Formal courtesies will strain a close friendship.

Children begin by loving their parents. After a time they judge them. Rarely, if ever, do they forgive them.

This grey, monstrous London of ours, with its myriads of people, its sordid sinners, and its splendid sins.

I don’t like Switzerland: it has produced nothing but theologians and waiters.

There is this to be said in favour of the despot, that he, being an individual, may have culture, while the mob, being a monster, has none.

History never repeats itself. The historians repeat each other.

The one duty we owe to history is to re- write it.

The reason we all like to think so well of others is that we are all afraid for ourselves. The basis of optimism is sheer terror.

Laughter is the primeval attitude towards life – a mode of approach that survives only in artists and criminals.

To do nothing at all is the most difficult thing in the world, the most difficult and the most intellectual.

The aim of life is self- development. To realize one’s nature perfectly – that is what each of us is here for.

One can live for years sometimes without living at all, and then all life comes crowding into one single hour.

We can have in life but one great experience at best, and the secret of life is to reproduce that experience as often as possible.

Don’t tell me that you have exhausted life. When a man says that one knows that life has exhausted him.

To become the spectator of one’s own life is to escape the suffering of life.

Life cheats us with shadows. We ask it for pleasure. It gives it to us, with bitterness and disappointment in its train.

Literature always anticipates life. It does not copy it, but moulds it to its purpose. The nineteenth century, as we know it, is largely an invention of Balzac.

I hate vulgar realism in literature. The man who could call a spade a spade should be compelled to use one.

Are there not books that can make us live more in one single hour than life can make us live in a score of shameful years?

To introduce real people into a novel or a play is a sign of an unimaginative mind, a coarse, untutored observation, and an entire absence of style.

The books that the world calls immoral books are books that show the world its own shame.

No one survives being over- estimated, nor is there any surer way of destroying an author’s reputation than to glorify him without judgement and to praise him without tact.

All love is a tragedy.

Misunderstanding . . . is the basis of love.

Those who are faithful know only the trivial side of love: it is the faithless who know love’s tragedies.

Faithfulness is to the emotional life what consistency is to the life of the intellect – simply a confession of failure.

Lust . . . makes one love all that one loathes.

It is difficult not to be unjust to what one loves.

One should always be in love. That is the reason one should never marry.

The proper basis for marriage is a mutual misunderstanding.

Married life is merely a habit, a bad habit.

How marriage ruins a man! It’s as demoralizing as cigarettes, and far more expensive.

The happiness of a married man . . . depends on the people he has not married.

The one charm of marriage is that it makes a life of deception absolutely necessary for both parties.

The world has grown so suspicious of anything that looks like a happy married life.

It’s most dangerous nowadays for a husband to pay attention to his wife in public. It always makes people think he beats her when they are alone.

Nowadays everybody is jealous of everyone else, except, of course, husband and wife.

Twenty years of romance make a woman look like a ruin; but twenty years of marriage make her something like a public building.

Girls never marry the men they flirt with. Girls don’t think it right.

Men marry because they are tired; women because they are curious. Both are disappointed.

Men know life too early . . . Women know life too late. That is the difference between men and women.

The only way a woman can ever reform a man is by boring him so completely that he loses all possible interest in life.

When a man has once loved a woman, he will do anything for her, except continue to love her.

A man can be happy with any woman, as long as he does not love her.

Men always want to be a woman’s first love. That is their clumsy vanity . . . Women have a more subtle instinct about things. What [they] like is to be a man’s last romance.

There is only one real tragedy in a woman’s life. The fact that the past is always her lover, and her future invariably her husband.

Between men and women there is no friendship possible. There is passion, enmity, worship, love, but no friendship.

Women have a wonderful instinct about things. They can discover everything except the obvious.

One should never trust a woman who tells one her real age. A woman who would tell one that, would tell one anything.

It is only very ugly or very beautiful women who ever hide their faces.

If a woman wants to hold a man she has merely to appeal to what is worst in him.

I never travel without my diary. One should always have something sensational to read in the train.

There are many things that we would throw away if we were not afraid that others might pick them up.

Why is it that one runs to one’s ruin? Why has destruction such a fascination?

One needs misfortunes to live happily.

To live in happiness, you must know some unhappiness in life.

The happy people of the world have their value, but only the negative value of foils. They throw up and emphasize the beauty and the fascination of the unhappy.

What fire does not destroy, it hardens.

Suffering and the community of suffering makes people kind.

While to propose to be a better man is a piece of unscientific cant, to have become a deeper man is the privilege of those who have suffered.

There is no truth comparable to Sorrow. There are times when Sorrow seems to me to be the only truth.

All excess, as well as all renunciation, brings its own punishment.

Nothing succeeds like excess.

Pure modernity of form is always somewhat vulgarizing.

Nothing is so dangerous as being too modern; one is apt to grow old- fashioned quite suddenly.

The value of the telephone is the value of what two people have to say.

Only one thing remains infinitely fascinating to me, the mystery of moods. To be master of these moods is exquisite, to be mastered by them more exquisite still.

You people who go in for being consistent have just as many moods as others have. The only difference is that your moods are rather meaningless.

There must be no mood with which one cannot sympathize, no dead mode of life that one cannot make alive.

Morality is simply the attitude we adopt towards people whom we personally dislike.

There is no such thing as morality, for there is no general rule of spiritual health; it is all personal, individual.

Modern morality consists in accepting the standard of one’s age. I consider that for any man of culture to accept the standard of his age is a form of the grossest immorality.

Manners are of more importance than morals.

The moral is too obvious.

I never came across anyone in whom the moral sense was dominant who was not heartless, cruel, vindictive, log- stupid, and entirely lacking in the smallest sense of humanity. Moral people, as they are termed, are simple beasts.

Music is the art . . . which most completely realizes the artistic idea, and is the condition to which all the other arts are constantly aspiring.

Music . . . creates for one a past of which one has been ignorant, and fills one with a sense of sorrows that have been hidden from one’s tears.

If one plays good music, people don’t listen, and if one plays bad music, people don’t talk.

I like Wagner’s music better than anybody’s. It is so loud that one can talk the whole time without people hearing what one says.

Musical people are so absurdly unreasonable. They always want one to be perfectly dumb at the very moment when one is longing to be absolutely deaf.

The things of nature do not really belong to us; we should leave them to our children as we have received them.

In nature there is, for me at any rate, healing power.

We all look at Nature too much, and live with her too little.

If Nature had been comfortable, mankind would never have invented architecture.

Nature, which makes nothing durable, always repeats itself so that nothing which it makes may be lost.

Nature is always behind the age.

Whenever we have returned to Life and Nature, our work has always become vulgar, common, and uninteresting.

There are only two kinds of people who are really fascinating – people who know absolutely everything, and people who know absolutely nothing.

Of course I plagiarize. It is the privilege of the appreciative man.

It is only the unimaginative who ever invent. The true artist is known by the use he makes of what he annexes, and he annexes everything.

Every word in a play has a musical as well as an intellectual value, and must be made expressive of a certain emotion.

I never write plays for anyone. I write plays to amuse myself. After, if people want to act in them, I sometimes allow them to do so.

There are two ways of disliking my plays. One is to dislike them, the other is to like Earnest.

Pleasure is Nature’s test, her sign of approval. When man is happy he is in harmony with himself and his environment.

No civilized man ever regrets a pleasure, and no uncivilized man ever knows what a pleasure is.

I adore simple pleasures. They are the last refuge of the complex.

A cigarette is the perfect type of a perfect pleasure. It is exquisite, and it leaves one unsatisfied. What more can one want?

I don’t regret for a single moment having lived for pleasure. I did it to the full, as one should do everything that one does to the full. There was no pleasure I did not experience.

I like persons better than principles, and I like persons with no principles better than anything else in the world.

I don’t like principles . . . I prefer prejudices.

It is personalities, not principles, that move the age.

I wonder who it was defined man as a rational animal. It was the most premature definition ever given. Man is many things, but he is not rational.

One is tempted to define man as a rational animal who always loses his temper when he is called upon to act in accordance with the dictates of reason.

It would be unfair to expect other people to be as remarkable as oneself.

雄鸡报晓

献给勒内·比约特

此前，贝尔特·德·阿旺塞勒夫人始终拒绝狂追她的约瑟夫·德·克罗瓦萨尔男爵的苦苦恳求。整个冬季在巴黎，男爵就紧追不舍，现在回到他在诺曼底的卡维尔城堡，又频频为她举办宴请聚会和出游打猎活动。

她丈夫德·阿旺塞勒先生还一如既往，对此一无所见，也一无所知。据说，他因身体衰弱，已同妻子分居。这在他夫人看来，是不可饶恕的。这个男人是个矮胖子，秃了顶，胳膊腿短，脖颈鼻子也短，全身无不奇短。

德·阿旺塞勒夫人则相反，是位高挑身材、棕发的少妇，她行事果断，冲她的先生咯咯大笑，声音洪亮，还当众称他“管家婆”。而她投向公开的追求者——约瑟夫·德·克罗瓦萨尔的目光，却含情脉脉，欣赏他那宽阔的肩膀、硕壮的颈项和长长金黄的胡须。

不过，她还什么都没有应承。男爵不惜为她倾家荡产，接二连三，不断组织晚会、打猎、各种新式娱乐活动，邀请周围一带城堡的贵族。

整个白天，大群猎犬在树林中飞奔，狂吠着追逐狐狸和野猪。而每天夜晚，烟火令人眼花缭乱，腾空的羽饰花焰，与星光交相辉映。客厅窗户灯火通明，一条条光带投向宽阔的草坪，只见人影幢幢。

入秋时节，万物一片橙黄色。落叶宛如一群群鸟雀，在草地上飞旋。空气中弥漫着卸下衣装的土地潮湿的气味，就像舞会散场之后，一位女子脱掉长裙，露出肌肤的气味。

就在今年春天，一次晚会上，德·阿旺塞勒夫人耐不住纠缠的恳求，这样答复德·克罗瓦萨尔先生：“如果我难免失足，我的朋友，在落叶之前绝不会发生。今年夏天我没有时间，要做的事情太多了。”这种大胆的笑谈，男爵念念不忘，因而他越发坚持，日甚一日，步步进逼，认为他在这位敢作敢为的美人心中已经立足，她那推却的态度，不过是装装样子而已了。

一场大型狩猎活动举办在即。前一天晚上，贝尔特夫人笑吟吟地对男爵说道：“男爵，如果您能猎杀野兽，我给您准备了点儿东西。”

天刚拂晓，他就起身，前去侦察那头独行的野猪藏身的巢穴。他让饲养猎犬的仆人们跟随，一路亲自组织部署，确保一举成功。当出发的号角一齐吹响时，他已身穿红色带金饰的紧身猎装出现了，只见他腰身束紧，虎背宽肩，目光炯炯有神，斗志昂扬，那劲头就好像刚刚起床。

猎手们出发了。那头野猪被驱逐出来，惊慌逃窜，随后紧追着吼叫的猎犬，穿过一片片荆丛；马匹也都奔跑起来，驮着男女骑手，冲进林间小径，而随行车辆驶在松软的土路上，不声不响，远远跟着打猎的队伍。

德·阿旺塞勒夫人很狡黠，留住男爵陪伴身边，在大路上缓缓前行。笔直的大道长不见尽头，排成四列橡树，枝叶树冠交织成长长的穹顶。男爵的内心，也交织着爱恋和不安，浑身不免发颤，他一只耳朵聆听少妇嘲弄般的饶舌，另一只则追踪渐行渐远的号角之声，以及猎犬的吠鸣。

“怎么，您不爱我了吗？”少妇问道。

“何出此言，怎么会呢？”男爵回应。

“然而，您的心思，似乎更顾虑打猎，而不是放在我身上。”少妇接着说道。

“还不是您命令我，亲手猎杀那只野兽吗？”男爵哀叹道。

“不错，这事我很看重，您必须当着我的面，将其猎杀。”她又正色补充了一句。

闻听此言，男爵坐在鞍上，不由得浑身一抖，他双脚一磕。他的坐骑被马刺刺痛，蹿跳起来，他也失去了耐性：

“真见鬼！夫人，我们就待在这里，这事怎么办得到！”

少妇咯咯笑起来，抛给他一句：

“真的，这可必须办到……否则的话……倒霉的是您。”

随后，她对男爵说话就柔声细语了，手搭到他的胳膊上，或者，仿佛心不在焉似的，抚弄他那匹马的鬃毛。

继而，他们就拐进右侧一条杂草丛生的小路。忽然，为了躲避一根拦路的树枝，她身子朝他一斜，靠得极近，他的脖颈都感到了她那秀发的拂痒。于是，他猛地抱住她，大胡子贴到她额角，狂热地亲吻她。

在这种冲动的爱抚下，她起初一动也不动，随后，她晃了晃，头扭了一下，似偶然又似有意，她这娇小的嘴唇，遇到他那瀑布般金黄胡须下的嘴唇。这时，或因羞愧，或因后悔，她一鞭抽向马腹，马奔跑起来。他们就这样跑了许久，彼此甚至没有交换一下目光。

越跑越靠近狩猎的嘈杂声，短树林仿佛也随之颤动，突然，一头野猪闯开枝条，浑身是血冲出来，挣脱咬住不放的猎犬。男爵一见，登时发出胜利的欢声，嚷道：“爱我者，随我上！”说罢，他就冲进矮树林不见了，仿佛被树林吞没了。贝尔特夫人几分钟之后，赶到林间一片空地，这时男爵已经站起来，满身是泥，上装也撕破了，双手沾满了鲜血，而那头野猪则躺倒在地，肩头深深插进一把猎刀，只露出刀柄。

点起火把，享用猎物，夜色温和而又忧伤。月光映黄了火把的红焰，而燃烧树脂的烟雾又笼罩了夜空。猎犬吼叫，相互撕咬，争食野猪发臭的内脏。饲养猎犬的仆人和打猎的贵绅们，则围在野味四周，用足气力吹着号角。阵阵号角声传至树林清朗的夜空，在远处山谷中回荡，惊醒了惴惴不安的鹿群，惊得狐狸吱吱尖叫，也惊扰了在林间空地边缘嬉戏的一群小灰兔。惊飞的一群夜鸟，在狂欢的人群上空惶惶乱飞。这种种场面，又甜美又凶残，女士们不由得动情，微微靠着男人的手臂，已经离群踏上小径，不待猎犬用完美餐。

这一整天，又疲倦又多情，德·阿旺塞勒夫人无精打采，对男爵说道：

“我的朋友，您愿意在院子里走一走吗？”

男爵却不应声，他浑身颤抖，双腿发软，拉走了夫人。

二人一避开人群，便拥抱在一起。他们缓步走在叶子几乎落光的树木下面，月光透着枝丫照射下来。此情此景，他们的爱恋，他们的欲望，他们对彼此的渴望，已经变得极其强烈，几乎支撑不住，就地倒在一棵树脚下了。

号角声断了，猎犬都疲惫不堪，回窝睡觉去了。

“咱们回去吧。”少妇说道。于是他们往回走。

他们走到城堡主楼前时，她的声音微弱，喃喃说道：“我累极了，要去睡觉了，我的朋友。”男爵张开双臂，正要抱住她最后吻一下子，她却跑开了，仿佛告别似的丢给他一句：“不，我去睡了……爱我者，跟我来！”

一小时过后，整个城堡一片死寂，男爵蹑手蹑脚，走出卧室，走到他女友的卧室，轻轻叩门，由于她没有应声，他就实施推门：没有插上门闩。

她正俯在窗台上遐想。男爵跪倒她脚下，隔着睡袍，狂热地亲吻她的双膝，她一句话不讲，只是将她纤细的手指，爱抚一般插进男爵的头发里。她仿佛做出了重大决定，猛然脱身，一副果敢的神情，低声喃喃说了一句：“我这就回来，您等着我。”说着，她指向黑暗中，卧室里端床铺隐约白色的影子。

男爵心醉神迷，摸索着走过去，双手颤抖着脱掉衣服，钻进了新铺的床单被罩中。他躺在床上舒服极了，几乎忘记了女友，整个身子乏得不想动弹，沉浸在无比舒坦的被窝的惬意中。少妇根本就没有回来，无疑是乐得让他热切地等待。男爵闭上眼睛安享着美妙的舒适，温柔地畅想，甜美地等待梦寐以求的事情。不过，他的肢体逐渐懈怠，头脑逐渐昏沉，神思飘忽不定。他最终被强大的疲倦击垮了，沉沉睡过去了。

精疲力竭的猎手的困倦无法抵制，他睡得死死的，一直睡到拂晓。突然，栖息在附近树上的一只公鸡报晓，从半开的窗户传入响亮的鸡鸣，男爵猛地惊醒，睁开了眼睛。他感到挨着一个女人的身体，发现自己睡在他认不出来的床上，不免十分惊诧，什么也想不起来了，他刚醒就慌了神儿，讷讷问道：“怎么？我在哪儿？怎么回事儿？”

且说她通宵未眠，此刻看着这个头发蓬乱、眼睛发红、厚嘴唇的男人，她拿出对丈夫说话的那种高傲的声调，回答说：“没事儿。是一只公鸡打鸣。您接着睡吧，先生，没您的事儿。”

蛇蝎美人

蟋蟀饭店是游艇手的法伦斯泰尔[1]，顾客慢慢散去，而门前却闹哄哄的，叫嚷和呼唤声响成一片。身穿白色运动衫的高大的小伙子，肩上扛着桨，在那里指手画脚。女人则身着浅颜色的春装，她们小心翼翼地跨上游艇，坐到船尾，整理一下衣裙。游艇场老板，一个有名的大力士、蓄留棕红胡子的壮小伙子，一边用手搀扶那些漂亮的小娘们儿，一边稳住轻飘飘的小船。

桨手们也各就各位，他们光着胳臂，挺起胸脯，给长廊里围观的人摆出架势。围观的人有节日打扮的市民、工人和士兵，他们俯在桥栏杆上，聚精会神地观赏这种场景。游艇一只接着一只离开浮桥。那些划船手身子前伏，再往后仰，动作十分均匀。在打了弯的长桨的推动下，小船在河面上迅速滑行，越驶越远，越来越小，在一座铁路桥下消失不见，顺流而下驶向青蛙滩。

只有一对伴侣留了下来。男青年还未长出胡须，身材瘦溜，脸色苍白，他搂着女伴的腰肢。女孩娇小细弱，一头棕发，走路蹦蹦跳跳。二人不时相对凝注。

老板喊道：“来呀，保罗先生，你们快点儿。”

二人应声走过去。这船场的所有顾客中，保罗先生最受喜爱，最受尊敬。他出手大方，又按期结账，而其他顾客要让人揪着耳朵催好久，还可能付不出钱就再不露面了。再说，他成了这个船场的活广告，因为他父亲是参议员。如果有个外地人问道：“那个小家伙是谁呀？他把那个小浪货搂得那么紧！”就会有一位常客，郑重而神秘的样子，悄声答道：“他就是保罗·巴隆，您不知道？参议员的儿子呀。”可是，对方总要情不自禁地感叹：“可怜的家伙，他神魂颠倒了。”蟋蟀大妈为人诚实，会做生意，管这个青年及其女伴叫作“我的一对小斑鸠”，似乎非常喜爱对她饭店有利的这一对情侣。

这对情侣缓步走过去。“玛德琳号”游艇已经准备好，可是上了船，他们又搂抱在一起，惹得聚在桥上的人都笑起来。于是，保罗先生操起桨，也朝青蛙滩划去。

划到那里，将近三点钟了，水上大咖啡厅已经坐满了顾客。水上咖啡厅是一座大木排，由木柱撑着涂了柏油的棚盖，有两座小桥通往美丽的克鲁瓦西岛，其中一座直插这个水上建筑物的正中，而另一座则连着仅长一棵树而得了“花盆”绰号的小岛，从那里上岸便是浴场管理处。

保罗顺着木排把船拴住，攀过咖啡厅的栏杆，再把他情妇拉上来，二人在餐桌一端面对面坐下。

河对岸的纤道上车水马龙，普通出租车同豪华马车相混杂。前一种十分笨重，便便大腹压低了车弓，套的是一匹脖颈下垂、膝头弯曲的劣马；而另一种车轮轻巧，车身挺秀飘逸，套的马四肢修长挺拔，高扬起脖子，嚼口泛着雪似的白沫，车夫则一本正经，穿着号服，高领支着发僵的脑袋，腰板挺得直直的，鞭子放在一个膝头上。

堤岸上游人熙熙攘攘，有全家人或成帮结伙来的，也有成双成对或者孤身前来的。他们揪草茎，下到水里，再登上岸，回到路上，大家都来到同一地点，停下来等候摆渡的船工。小渡船满载游客，送到岛上，在两岸之间不停地来往。

水上咖啡厅所靠的一道河汊，水流极缓，仿佛在沉睡，人称死河汊。各式各样的船只——游船、赛艇、单人艇、快艇、舢板等，在静止的水面上往来如梭，交错混杂，相互碰撞，有时猛一用力让船急停，然后再突然奋臂，让船又冲出去，飞快滑行，活像一条条红色和黄色的大鱼。

从上游夏图和从下游布吉谷，还源源不断地有船划来。河面上笑声此起彼伏，呼叫、谩骂、召唤或争吵声不绝于耳。划船的人将棕色的皮肤、隆起的二头肌曝露在烈日下，坐在船尾的女士则撑开丝阳伞，红绿蓝黄，五彩缤纷，宛如盛开的异域鲜花，在水上漂流。

七月的太阳在中天燃烧，空气中似乎弥漫着灼人的欢乐。没有一丝风，杨柳的枝叶都纹丝不动。对面远远一道屏障，那便是瓦莱里昂山，它陡峭的山坡展现在强烈的阳光下。右侧秀丽的卢浮西安丘峦，则随同河流弯转，形成半圆，在那大片大片园子的苍莽黛绿中，点缀着乡下人家的白墙。

青蛙滩头有不少参天大树，使这岛上一隅成为世上最惬意的公园。大群游人在滩头的树下散步。那些黄头发的妓女，挺着过度丰满的乳房，撅着过分肥大的屁股，脸上搽的脂粉就像抹了一层白灰，嘴唇涂得血红，身上紧紧箍着系了带子的奇特怪异的衣裙，她们从绿油油的草坪上走过，便留下那种庸俗打扮的强烈味道。陪伴她们的年轻男子，一个个也都装腔作势，身穿时髦版画上的那种奇装异服，手戴浅色手套，足蹬油亮的皮鞋，拄着细绳一般的手杖，还戴着单片眼镜，愈加突出他们微笑时的愚昧。

小岛恰巧在青蛙滩这里变得狭窄，另一边也有一只渡船，将从克鲁瓦西来的游人送过来。这条河汊水流湍急，到处是漩涡、回流和浪花泡沫，大有滚滚激流的气势。一支身穿炮兵服的架桥部队驻扎在对岸，一些士兵并排坐在一根长梁上观看流水。

水上餐厅里人声嘈杂，混乱不堪。木桌上摆满了半空的酒瓶，围着半醉的顾客，桌面上洒的饮料，形成一条条黏糊糊的细流。这里的人都在大嚷大叫，扯着嗓门儿唱歌。男的将帽子推到后脑勺儿，一个个红头涨脸，眼睛闪着醉态，他们这样肆无忌惮，咋呼鼓噪，完全是出于粗鲁的人天生的需要。那些女的，都在捕捉过夜的对象，眼下先让人请喝酒。在餐桌之间的空地上，主要站着这里的常客、好起哄的划船手们以及穿着法兰绒短裙的女伴。

他们当中有一位正在奋力弹钢琴，仿佛手脚并用。有四对人在跳四对方舞。一些漂亮端庄的年轻人在观看，如果不露出无法掩饰的破绽的话，他们还真像文雅之士。

然而破绽太明显了，一到这儿就能嗅出这全是世界渣滓，全是臭名昭著的荒淫之徒、巴黎社会一切霉烂的东西。这个大杂烩里有时新商店的伙计、蹩脚演员、下流记者、财产代管人、小额股票投机商、无耻的酒色之徒、老牌腐朽的浪荡鬼、各色各样形迹可疑的人。五分可知，五分未知，五分受人尊敬，五分声名狼藉，是些扒手、骗子、拉皮条的、冒险家。一个个却是正人君子的模样，虚张声势，那神气似乎在说：“哪个胆敢把我当成坏蛋，我就要他的命。”这里充斥着愚蠢荒唐的东西，散发着风月场的假意殷勤和无耻欺诈。在这里，男的女的都半斤八两。这里飘浮着廉价爱情的气味，为了一声“对”还是“不对”，就打架斗殴，动剑动枪，要维护坏透了的名声，结果名声会更臭。

附近有些居民好奇，每逢星期天来瞧瞧。每年，也有几个青年，非常年轻，来这里学习生活。还有一些人散步，路过到这里，有几个天真的人就迷不知返了。

这里叫青蛙滩也有道理。就在喝酒的水上餐厅旁边，紧挨着“花盆”的水域，有人在游泳。那些肌肤丰腴足以示人的女人，便来这里展露肉体以招徕顾客。其他女人却不屑一顾，她们身上虽然这里塞了棉花，那里撑起弹簧，这里垫高一点儿，那里改变一下，但是却以鄙夷的神气望着她们嬉水的姊妹。

游泳的人挤在一个小平台上，要头朝下扎猛子。他们的体形，有的长得像竹竿，有的圆得像柠檬，有的扭曲得像橄榄树，有的弓着腰，有的腆着肚子朝后仰，但无一例外，都丑陋不堪，他们跳水时，溅起的水花会洒到旁边喝咖啡的顾客身上。

水上咖啡厅尽管有繁茂的大树遮阴，又挨着水面，可是仍然溽暑熏蒸。洒掉饮料的气味、人体散发的气味，同爱情女贩的浓烈香水味混杂在一起，须知香水已经渗进爱情女贩的皮肤中，待在这个火炉里便蒸发出来。不过，在这形形色色的气味掩盖下，还飘浮着一种搽面香粉的清香，时隐时现，但总能再次闻到，就好像有一只隐蔽的手在空中摇晃着一个无形的粉扑。

美妙的景观还在河上，往来如梭的游船引人注目。船上的女客半躺在圆椅里，面对着臂膀强健的男伴，带着几分蔑视的神态，望着岛上那些游荡觅食的女人。有时，一只快船飞速划过去，岸上的朋友们便高喊加油。咖啡馆里的全体观众也都突然疯狂起来，开始大吼大叫。在夏图方向的河湾上，不断出现新的游船。船划近了，越来越大，人们也渐渐认出船上人的面孔，于是又发出一阵阵吼叫。

一只篷船载着四个女人，顺水慢慢划过来。划船的女人瘦小枯干，穿着见习水手服，头发绾上去，戴着一顶漆布帽。她对面是个金发胖女人，一副男装打扮，穿着白色法兰绒上衣。她仰卧在船舱里，双腿举起搭在桨手两侧的坐凳上，嘴里叼着香烟，每当双桨用力划一下，她的胸脯和腹部就颤动、摇晃起来。后面船篷下有两个细高挑儿的漂亮姑娘，一位棕发，一位金发，两人相互搂着腰，一直看着她们的同伴。

有人从青蛙滩喊了一声：“来宝斯来啦！”于是，突然爆发一阵狂呼乱叫，大家拼命拥挤。酒杯倒了，有人登上餐桌，所有人都歇斯底里，大吼大叫：“来宝斯！来宝斯！来宝斯！”喧声滚荡，变得混杂不清，汇成一种骇人的喧嚣，继而，仿佛猛然拔地而起，冲上半空，笼罩平野，充塞大树的茂盛枝叶，扩展到远处的丘峦，并直趋高悬的太阳。

在欢呼声中，那位划船的女人从容地停住双桨，而躺在船舱里的那个金发胖姑娘，则用两肘支起身子，漫不经心地转过头去。坐在船尾的那两位美丽姑娘一边向人群致意，一边咯咯笑起来。于是，喧叫之声变本加厉，震动了水上咖啡厅。男人举起帽子，女人挥动手帕，所有人，不管尖嗓门儿还是粗嗓门儿，都齐声高呼：“来宝斯！”这场面，真像一帮堕落的人在向头头儿致敬，如同一位海军司令检阅时，船队鸣礼炮一样。成群结队的游船也向那几位女子欢呼。她们的小艇又慢悠悠地划开，到稍远一点儿的地方靠岸。

保罗先生则不然，他从兜里掏出一个薄片钥匙，用全力吹响。他那神经质的情妇脸色更加苍白，拉他胳臂叫他停下，这回，她瞪着保罗，眼睛冒火了。然而，保罗似乎恼羞成怒，表现出一种男人的嫉妒，一种深沉的、本能的而又混乱的愤怒，他气得嘴唇颤抖，结结巴巴地说：“真不要脸！就该像溺死母狗那样，在她们脖子上吊上石头沉到河里！”

这时，玛德琳突然发火了，她那小尖嗓门儿变得刺耳了，说了一大套，仿佛是为自己辩解：“你来什么劲，这关你什么事儿？她们不欠任何人的，难道连想干什么就干什么的权利都没有吗？收起你这套吧，别烦别人，管好你自己的事儿吧……”

但是，保罗打断她的话：“这与警察局有关系，哼，我要把她们投进圣拉扎尔监狱！”

玛德琳浑身一抖。

“就你！”

“对，就我！而且，这会儿我也不准你同她们说话，听见了吧，我就是不准。”

于是，她耸了耸肩，立刻平静下来：“我的小宝贝，我高兴干什么就干什么，你要是不满意，那就走开，马上走。我不是你老婆，对不对？你还是闭嘴吧。”

保罗没有回嘴，二人对视，嘴角抽搐，呼吸急促。

四个女人从木质结构的大咖啡厅另一侧进来，两个男装打扮的走在前面，一个干瘦，酷似老气横秋的小男孩，鬓颊蜡黄色；另一个肥胖，塞满白色法兰绒外衣，肥臀也撑起肥大的裤子，走路像肥鹅一般摇摆，那两条大腿胖得要命，连膝盖都显得凹进去了。她们的两个女友跟在后面。划船手都纷纷上前同她们握手。

她们四人在岸边租了一间小木屋，像两家人在一起生活。她们的淫荡是人所共知的，也是明目张胆的。大家提起来，就像谈论一件自然而然的事情，抱着几分同情的态度，私下里还讲些有关她们的离奇故事、妒火中烧的女人编造的艳事，说是知名的妇女、女演员都秘密造访河边这间小屋。一位邻居听了这些丑闻十分生气，告诉宪警。一名队长带着一名属员来调查。这任务很棘手，总的说来，这些女人根本不卖淫，并没有什么可指责的。那位队长大惑不解，甚至没怎么弄明白所怀疑的罪过是什么性质，随便询问了一些人，写了一份冗长的报告，得出无罪的结论。这个笑话都传到了圣日耳曼。

她们摆出王后的架势，缓步穿过青蛙滩的咖啡厅，那神气显然为她们的名气感到自豪，为能引人注目而感到高兴。她们傲视这群人，这帮无名鼠辈、乌合之众。玛德琳和她的情人注视她们走过来，而姑娘的眼神燃得明亮。

走在前面的两位到了长桌这一端时，玛德琳喊了一声：“波莉娜！”那个胖子回过头来，站住了，但是仍然挽着那个穿着见习水手服的女伴的胳膊，应声说道：“咦！玛德琳……我的心肝儿，过来跟我说说话。”

保罗扣在他情妇腕子上的手指又用了用力，可是她却说：“要知道，我的宝贝，你可以离开。”那语气十分坚持，保罗便不讲话了，独自留下。

她们三人站在那里，低声交谈，话讲得很快，她们的嘴唇上不时掠过快意的神情。波莉娜有时偷偷看保罗一眼，那微笑则含有讥讽与刻薄。保罗终于忍不住了，他忽地站起来，冲到玛德琳面前，四肢都在颤抖，一把抓住她的肩膀，说道：“过来，我叫你过来呢，说过不准你同这些娼妇交谈！”

可是，波莉娜却提高嗓门儿，使出市井泼妇的全套本领同他吵架。周围的人开始哄笑，都凑到近前，踮起脚，想看个究竟。脏话雨点一般地浇到他头上，保罗呆住了，觉得从那张嘴里吐出的话，就像往他身上泼屎泼尿，因此这闹剧一开场，他就退却了，掉头回去，靠到临河的栏杆上，背向那三个旗开得胜的女人。保罗俯在那里，凝望水面，有时他迅速抹一下，用神经质的手指抹掉在眼角聚成的泪珠，就好像是一把抓走似的。

这是因为他坠入情网，也不知为什么，既违背他敏锐的直觉，也违背他的良知和意愿。他坠入情网，如同人掉进泥坑里。他天生多情敏感，曾梦想过那种美妙的、理想而炽热的恋情，岂料这个瘦小的女人，跟所有妓女一样愚蠢，愚蠢得不可救药，甚至谈不上漂亮，又瘦又爱生气。就是这样一个女人将他抓住，将他俘获，从头到脚，从肉体到灵魂占有了他。他中了女性这种神秘的、威慑无比的魔力，不知道这种陌生的力量、这种神奇的牵制从何而来，是肉体之魔授予的，能让一个最明智的男人，匍匐在一个寻常女郎的脚下，根本无法解释她身上有什么天生的主宰大权。

他感到就在他身后，正策划一种可耻的举动。一阵阵笑声直刺他的心。怎么办？他完全明白，但又办不到。他定睛看着对岸一个垂钓者，守着纹丝不动的鱼线。

突然，那人猛地抬起鱼竿，只见线梢儿从水中拉出一尾摆动的银色小鱼来。接着，他要把鱼钩摘下来，拧来扭去都不成，便不耐烦了，干脆用劲一拉，将小鱼带血的喉头连同一段肠子拉出来了。保罗浑身一抖，心都撕裂了，他觉得那鱼钩就是他的爱情，要想夺走，那么铁钩尖就会把他内心深处的东西，全部从胸膛里拉出来，而拉着钓线的正是玛德琳。

一只手搭到他肩膀上，他吓了一跳，扭头看看，原来是他情妇回到了身边。二人谁也不讲话，玛德琳也像他一样，趴到栏杆上，定睛望着河水。保罗想找话说，却一句也没有想出来。他甚至弄不清内心里有什么活动，只感到她回到身边、有她陪伴的快慰，也感到一种蒙耻的懦弱、一种宽恕一切的愿望，只要她不离开，就什么都答应。

沉默了几分钟之后，他终于口气十分温和地问道：“咱们走吧，好吗？到船上更舒服些。”

玛德琳答道：“好吧，我的小猫。”

于是，保罗搀她登上游艇，紧紧抓着双手扶住她，温情脉脉，眼角还挂着泪花。玛德琳也含笑看着他，于是，二人又拥抱亲吻了。他们沿着岸边，缓缓地溯流而上。岸上绿茵覆盖，柳树成行，静悄悄的，沐浴在午后温暖的阳光里。他们回到蟋蟀饭店的时候，刚敲六点钟。他们舍船登上小岛，沿着岸边高大的杨树，穿过牧场，朝贝松走去。

高高的牧草快要开割了，遍地野花盛开，西斜的太阳在上面铺了一层橙黄色晖光。傍晚暑热稍减，青草飘香，加上河流的潮气，给空气增添一种缠绵的情调、一种淡淡的幸福感，好似令人舒坦的氤氲之气。

心扉透进一股缱绻的柔情，似乎应和黄昏这种宁静的霞光、生命勃发的这种幽微而神秘的震颤，应和这种沁人心脾的忧伤的诗意。仿佛从草木万物生发而蔓延的诗意，在这温馨而沉思的时刻，充盈着他的感官。这一切，他都感受到了，而她却毫不体悟。他们并排走着，她不耐沉默了，忽然唱起歌来。她那假嗓音有点儿刺耳，唱的是街头流行曲，残留在记忆中的一个小调，却蓦地撕破了黄昏幽深静谧的和谐。

于是，他看了她一眼，感到他们之间隔着一道不可逾越的鸿沟。她用阳伞抽打着青草，略微低头瞧着自己的脚，边走边唱，拖长音节，尝试华彩过门，敢于模仿颤音。

她那小小的、狭窄的额头，他爱得多深，居然如此空虚，如此空虚！那里面只装着这种八音盒式的音乐，即使偶尔形成一点儿思想，也类似这种音乐。她根本不理解他，他们之间的距离比不在一起还要大。难道他的吻从来没有超越嘴唇吗？

这时，她抬起眼睛看他，又微微一笑。于是，一股冲动深入骨髓，他张开手臂，以双倍的爱热烈地拥抱她。她见衣裙弄皱了，便挣脱拥抱，用呢喃的一句话给点儿补偿：“好了，我非常爱你，我的小猫。”不过，他又搂住了她的腰，发狂一般拖着她跑起来，一边欢蹦乱跳，一边吻她的脸蛋、鬓角和脖子。他们气喘吁吁，倒在被夕阳照成一片火的灌木丛脚下，二人交欢了，而她却没有领会他那份激情。

他们手拉手走回来，从树木中间，突然望见河上那四个女人的游船。胖波莉娜也瞧见他们俩，她站起来，朝玛德琳送来飞吻，接着喊道：“今晚见！”

玛德琳答道：“今晚见！”

保罗觉得自己的心一下子浸入冰水里。他们回去用晚餐，二人坐在临水的凉棚下，开始闷头吃饭。天色黑下来，伙计送来一支点燃的蜡烛，玻璃球罩里的微弱烛光摇曳不定。二楼大餐厅里不时传来划船手的阵阵喧哗。快要上甜食的时候，保罗温存地拉起玛德琳的手，对她说道：“我非常疲乏，我的小乖乖，你要是愿意的话，咱们就早点儿睡觉。”

然而，玛德琳明白这种花招，十分暧昧地瞥了他一眼，女人眼睛的深处，往往闪现这种负情的神色。她想了一下，才回答说：“你要睡就去睡吧，我呢，已经答应人家去参加青蛙滩舞会。”

保罗凄然一笑，这是人们用以掩饰极痛深悲的一种微笑，不过，他还是用既温柔又伤感的声调答道：“你要是体贴一点儿，那么咱们俩就会待在一起了。”她摇了摇头，但没有讲出“不”字。保罗仍不死心：“求求你了，我的小鹿。”

可是，她却打断他的话：“你知道我对你说过什么。你要是不满意，门是敞开的，没人强留你。至于我，答应了，就得去。”

保罗双肘撑在桌子上，用手捂住额头，木然不动，沉浸在冥思苦想中。游船客下楼来，仍然大嚷大叫，他们要划船去参加青蛙滩舞会。玛德琳对保罗说：“快点儿决定，你要是不去，还有这些先生，我求一位送我去。”

保罗站起来，咕哝道：“走吧。”于是，他们去了。夜色弥漫，星斗满天，到处流动着灼人的气息、滞重的气浪，负载着溽暑，无形中透着一丝活力。微风受其拖累也缓慢了，似乎变得稠浓而厚重，拂面给人一种热乎乎爱抚的感觉，令人呼吸加快，乃至喘息了。一只只游船启程了，船头都挂一盏花灯。根本看不清船身，只见一盏盏小彩灯疾驰跳动，宛如狂舞的流萤。黑暗中，四面八方都流动着人声笑语。两个年轻人的游艇缓缓滑行。有时，一只快艇从旁边超过去，他们就突然瞧见划船手被灯光照亮的白色背影。他们驶过河湾，就远远望见青蛙滩了。

水上咖啡厅一派节日气氛，挂起了大花灯、小彩灯花束和葡萄灯串。几只平底大船在塞纳河上缓缓游动，五彩斑斓的灯光在空中绘成圆顶、金字塔以及复杂建筑物，形状各异。点亮的花彩一直拖到水面。有时，一盏红灯或蓝灯，高高挑在一根看不见的长竿上，好似一颗摇曳的巨星。

所有这些彩灯，照亮咖啡厅的四周，从上到下照亮岸边的大树，只见浅灰色的树干和淡绿色的叶丛，被黑洞洞的田野和天空衬得尤为突出。乐队由五名郊区艺人组成，演奏着支离破碎的酒吧粗劣音乐，传得很远，玛德琳和着音乐歌唱。玛德琳要立刻进舞厅。保罗本来想在岛上转一圈，最后不得不让步。参加舞会的人几乎清一色是游船客，还有零星几个市民、几个携妓的青年。这场康康舞的指挥兼组织者，身穿黑色旧礼服，神气活现，满场展示他那颗兜售廉价娱乐的老商人秃头。胖波莉娜及其女伴不在那儿，保罗舒了一口气。

一对对跳舞的人面对面，发狂似的又蹦又吵，腿踢得很高，一直举到舞伴的鼻子上。那些女的大腿都要脱臼了，蹿跳时裙子飘起来，露出了内裤。她们的脚不费劲就举过头顶，令人惊叹。她们还摇晃肚子，摆动屁股，抖动乳房，向周围散发出汗馊的强烈气味。那些男的则蹲下来，学蛤蟆的样子，做出猥亵的姿势，身子弯来扭去，挤眉弄眼，丑态百出，还用手撑地倒翻跟头，或者忸怩作态，竭力装扮怪相。一名胖女招待和两名男招待送着饮料食物。

这个水上咖啡厅仅有棚盖，四面并无墙板同外面相隔，他们就在安谧的黑夜，在繁星满天的苍穹下疯狂地舞蹈。忽然间，对面瓦莱里昂山那边亮起来，仿佛山后发生了火灾。那片亮光越扩越大，越来越明亮，逐渐侵凌上空，勾画出一个光圈，先呈淡白色，继而又出现红晕，扩大开来，呈现火红色，如同铁砧上烧红的铁，再缓缓延展成圆，似乎从大地里出来。就这样，月亮很快离开地平线，冉冉升空，越升越高，绛红色随之渐淡，化为黄色，是亮晶晶的淡黄。而那星体离地面越远，也似乎越小了。

保罗久久凝望月亮，心驰神往，忘了他的情妇。等他再扭头看时，她已经不见了。

他寻找，却不见她的踪影。他那焦急不安的目光扫过一张张餐桌，他还来回奔走，问这个又问那个，谁也没有瞧见她。他担心得要命，就这样东找西找，这时，一名伙计对他说：“您是找玛德琳夫人吧？她刚才和波莉娜夫人一道走了。”

就在说话的同时，保罗望见咖啡厅的另一端，站着那个身穿见习水手服的女人和那两个漂亮姑娘，三个人相互搂着腰，一边窥视他，一边交头接耳。他明白了，立刻像疯了似的冲上小岛。他先朝夏图方向跑去，可是看到眼前一片平野，他沿原路返回，开始搜寻灌木丛，狂奔乱走，不时停下来听一听。四面八方都送来铿锵短促的蛙声。从布吉谷方面，还传来几声鸟叫，但是距离远而声音微弱。月亮的清辉洒在宽阔的草地上，仿佛白絮般的尘雾。清辉透过叶丛，沿着白杨的银色树皮流泻，看上去高高震颤的树冠就像被光雨打穿。这仲夏之夜醉人的诗意，也由不得保罗，还是透进他的心胸，穿越他惊慌失措的历程，带着残忍的嘲讽搅动他的心田；在他那颗沉思多情的灵魂上，激起狂热的渴望，要追求理想的爱情，要在一个忠贞可爱的女子怀中倾诉炽烈的情肠。

他柔肠寸断，泣不成声，不得不停下脚步。一阵悲痛过去，他又往前走。猛然，他好像挨了一刀：树丛里有人在拥抱。他跑过去一看，原来是一对情侣，两个身影搂抱在一起吻个没完，见他走近便躲开了。他不敢呼唤，就知道她不会答应。而且，他又深恐突然发现那两个。短号声令人心碎，笛子模仿欢笑，小提琴尖声狂叫，这些组成四对方舞的老调，一下下揪他的心，加剧他的痛苦。疯狂的音乐节奏混乱，在树下流窜，随着阵风时强时弱。

他猛然想到，也许她回去了吧？不错，她肯定回去啦！为什么不会呢？实在愚蠢，这一阵他无缘无故自相惊扰，胡乱猜疑，完全昏了头。痛苦绝望的情绪，也有奇异的间歇的时候，他正好碰到这种情况，又回头朝舞场走去。

他扫视整个大厅，仍然不见她的人影儿。他绕过餐桌，又突然面对那三个女人，他那气急败坏的样子一定很怪，因为她们仨都咯咯笑起来。他赶紧逃开，又跑上小岛，喘着粗气冲进树丛里。——继而，他又谛听——听了许久，因为耳朵嗡嗡鸣响。终于，他仿佛听见不远处有尖细的笑声，是他所熟悉的。于是，他蹑手蹑脚地靠近，拨开树枝朝前爬行，心跳得十分剧烈，连呼吸都感到困难。

两个人在窃窃私语，还听不清楚，随后又不出声了。

他忽然产生一个强烈的愿望，要逃开，不想看见，不想知道，永远逃开，远离这种毁掉他的狂热恋情。他要回到夏图，乘上火车，再也不回来，再也不见她了。可是，她的形象又突然浮现，他又在意念中看见她。早晨她在他们暖烘烘的床上醒来，紧紧贴着他亲昵，双臂搂住他的脖子，蓬乱的头发稍微遮住前额，眼睛还闭着，张开嘴唇接受第一个吻。他蓦然想起这种晨起的亲昵，心中立刻充满肠断魂销的遗憾、炽热狂燃的欲火。

那二人又说话了，他弯着腰靠近，忽听近旁枝叶下轻轻叫了一声。一声叫！那正是他们欢情深烈时他听熟了的叫声。他还继续靠近，仿佛不由自主，无法抵御那种吸引，完全是下意识的……果然看见她们了。

噢！另外一个，哪怕是个男人呢！不料却这样！却这样！他就觉得自己也被扯进她们的无耻行径里了。他愣在原地，神情沮丧，意乱心烦，就好像猛然发现一具被残害的亲人尸体，发现一件伤天害理的罪案、一种亵渎神灵的行为。这时，他不由自主地一闪念，想到他看见拉出肠子的那条小鱼……忽然玛德琳轻声叫道：“波莉娜！”那声调就跟叫“保罗”一样热烈。于是，保罗心如刀绞，立刻奋力逃开了。他撞到两棵树干，摔倒在一条树根上，爬起来又跑，忽然发觉到了河边，面对月光照亮的湍急的水流。激流形成许多巨大的漩涡，舞弄着月影。河岸形同峭壁，高踞于水面，河面如同一条宽宽的黑带，可以听见暗影中的汩汩水声。对岸是克鲁瓦西村，皎洁的月光下是一片农舍。

这一切如同梦境，保罗仿佛重温一件往事。他什么也不想，什么也不明白，自然万物，乃至他自身的存在，都变得恍惚遥远了，都忘却了，完结了。面前就是河流。他明白自己在做什么吗？他要寻死吗？他简直疯了。在这寂静的夜晚，庸俗舞曲的叠句还在微弱固执地回荡，他决然转过身，面向小岛，面向她，惨叫一声：“玛德琳！”那声音绝望、尖厉，迥非人声。

他那声撕肝裂胆的呼叫，穿过寥廓长天的沉寂，传向四面八方。接着，他纵身一跳，像野兽蹿跳那样，投进河中，溅起水花，河面随即又合拢。他消失的地方，泛起一圈圈波纹，映着月光越扩越大，一直扩展到对岸。两个女人听见了。玛德琳站起来，说道：“是保罗。”她心里萌生一丝疑虑：“他跳河了。”她冲向河边，胖波莉娜也随后赶到。

一条笨重的平底船上有两个男人，在那处水面转悠。一人划船，另一人将一根长竿探进水中，似乎在探寻什么。波莉娜嚷道：“你们干什么呢？那儿有什么？”

一个陌生的声音答道：“有个投河自杀的人。”

两个女人惊呆了，紧紧靠在一起，注视着船的移动。远处青蛙滩的音乐还在闹哄，那节拍仿佛给捞尸者的动作伴奏，而河流现在隐藏一具尸体，在月光下打漩流淌。

打捞了好长时间。可怕的等待，玛德琳瑟瑟发抖。至少过了半个钟头，其中一个人终于说道：“我钩住啦！”

他轻轻往上提竿。一样大东西终于浮出水面。另一个船员放下桨，两个人合力，拉那个不动的大坨子，拉到船上。然后，他们挑地势低并有月光的一处上岸。等他们上了岸，两个女人也赶到了。

玛德琳一见尸体，吓得连连后退。在月光下，他仿佛变绿了，嘴巴、眼睛、鼻子、衣服都沾满了污泥，合拢的僵硬的手指十分可怕，全身都糊了一层黑乎乎的泥水。脸好像肿胀了，沾了稀泥的头发上不断往下淌污水。

两个船员察看了尸体，其中一个问道：“你认识他吗？”

另一个是克鲁瓦西的摆渡人，他犹豫一下，答道：“认识，这张脸好像见过，不过你也知道，这是不容易认的。”接着，他突然说道：“嘿，这是保罗先生啊！”

“保罗先生是谁呀？”伙伴问道。

前一个回答：

“就是保罗·巴隆先生啊，参议员的儿子，小伙子太痴情了。”

另一个则达观地补充说：

“是啊，现在他玩到头了。不过，人有钱，走了还是挺可惜的。”

玛德琳失声痛哭，瘫倒在地上。波莉娜走到尸体跟前，问道：“他真死了吗？——救不活了吗？”

那两个人耸耸肩膀：“唉！都这么长时间啦！肯定完了。”

而后，其中一个人问道：“他是住在蟋蟀饭店吗？”

“对，”另一个答道，“该送到那儿去，能给赏钱的。”

他们又上了船，划走了，但是水流太急，船行得很慢。两个女人站在原地，好久还能望见他们，听到船桨有节奏击水的声音。

这时，可怜的玛德琳还在哀痛，波莉娜搂住她，极力爱抚，久久拥抱，安慰她说：“有什么办法，这根本不是你的错，对不对？没法儿阻止男人干傻事。归根结底，他要这么干，这就活该啦！”

接着，她把玛德琳扶起来，又说道：“好啦，宝贝儿，去我那儿睡吧。今晚，你不能回蟋蟀饭店了。”她又拥抱玛德琳，说道：“好啦，我们会治好你的。”

玛德琳站起来，还一直在哭泣，但声势减弱，她的头偎在波莉娜的肩上，仿佛找到了庇护所，是一种更体贴可靠、更亲热信赖的温情，她脚步蹀躞，蹒跚而去。

[1] 法伦斯泰尔是法国空想社会主义者夏尔·傅立叶创造的一种理想城邦概念——自给自足似的乌托邦生活社区。他认为为了更好的生活状态，人们应该打破家庭的概念，用“法郎吉”来替代，这些“法郎吉”住在被称为“法伦斯泰尔”的城中。——编者注

奥托父子

一

这座大庄院，半似农场，半像庄园，是混合型乡居，颇有几分领主庄园的气派，现在则居住着大庄户人家。院落苹果树上拴的几条狗守着院门，瞧见护树人和几个小青年扛着猎袋，便汪汪叫起来。

在厨房兼餐室的厅堂里，老奥托和小奥托父子，收税员贝尔蒙先生和公证人蒙达吕先生，正吃一顿便饭，喝杯红酒，就要出发打猎了，今天是正式开猎的日子。

老奥托拥有这份家产，很是得意，打猎前就先吹嘘客人到他这地盘上，能打到什么猎物。他这个诺曼底人身材高大，面色红润，特别健壮，是个能把苹果车举上肩头的汉子。他是半个农民，半个文化人，家境殷富，受人尊敬，很有影响力，也很专横。他让儿子凯撒上学受教育，念到三年级[1]就辍学，唯恐小奥托变成文化人而忽略田产。

凯撒小奥托，几乎跟父亲一般高，但是真瘦溜儿。他是个好小伙子，听话的儿子，对什么都满意，对老奥托的意愿和见解，满心赞赏，敬重且钦佩。

收税员贝尔蒙先生，则是个矮胖子，红红的面颊上，呈现青色血脉织成的细网，仿佛地图上的红河水道。他问道：“那么，野兔呢——有野兔吗？”

老奥托回答：“您要多少就有多少，特别是到比伊萨蒂埃那片林子深处。”

“我们先从哪儿开始呢？”公证人插言道。他是个胖子，脸色苍白，作为公证人，性格随和而开朗，同样大腹便便，穿一身崭新的猎装，全身箍得紧紧的，还是上周去鲁昂买的。

“喏，就从那里，从里端开始，我们先将山鹑轰到田野里，然后就势扑上去。”

老奥托说罢，就站起身，大家也都跟着站起来，去角落操起各自的猎枪，再检查一下全套装备，又跺跺脚，确定靴子非常跟脚。靴子偏硬一点儿，等走动起来血脉一热就会软和些。接着，他们走出去，猎犬立时扯直了绳索，身子立起来，前爪在半空乱抓，发出尖厉的叫声。

大家上路，走向林子深处。这是一道小山谷，确切点儿说，是一大道土质恶劣的沟壑，因而不能耕种。一条条细谷长满了蕨类植物，正是猎物极好的去处。猎手们拉开了距离，老奥托走右侧，小奥托走左侧，两位客人居中。猎场守护人和扛猎袋的人紧随其后。这是庄严的时刻，大家都等待打响第一枪，心跳不免有点儿加速，而紧张的手指随时准备叩动扳机。

突然，第一枪打响了！是老奥托开的枪。所有人都停下来，只见一只山鹑脱离拍打翅膀逃窜的一群，跌落到一条沟壑茂密的荆丛里。亢奋的猎手开始奔跑，跨越，挣脱挂住他的刺藤，他也消隐在矮树林中了，去寻找他的猎物。几乎紧随其后，第二声枪响了。

“嗬！嗬！这个无赖，”贝尔蒙先生叫起来，“在那下面，他很可能把一只野兔赶出窝了。”

所有人都等待，眼睛注视那片目光透不进去的茂密枝叶。公证人双手合成喊话筒，嚷道：“捉到了吗？”老奥托没有应声，于是凯撒回身对护林人说：“你去帮帮他，约瑟夫。必须一排往前推。我们等着。”

约瑟夫，干干巴巴，长得像根老树桩，疙里疙瘩，各个关节无不突显。他不慌不忙卸下装备，找准容易下脚的穴坑，像狐狸一样谨慎小心。不大工夫，听到他嚷起来，“噢！来人哪！来人哪！出乱子啦！”

所有人都跑下去，冲进荆丛里，老奥托侧身倒在地上，双手捂住肚子，只见鲜血从子弹打穿的帆布衣破洞里流到了荒草上。他在伸手去抓那只打死的山鹑时，丢下的猎枪磕到石头上，撞击走火，打出第二响，打穿了他的腹部。大家急忙上手，把他从沟里拖出来，扒开猎装，看到伤口惨不忍睹，肠子也流出来了。好歹给他包扎住伤口之后，当即抬他回家，等待早已派人请的医生以及一位神父。

医生赶来检查伤势，他神情凝重，摇了摇头，转过身来，对坐在椅子上哽泣的小奥托说道：“我可怜的小伙子，看来情况可不妙。”

不过，等伤口包扎好了，伤者动了动手指，张开嘴，睁开枯槁的双眼，目光焦虑地环顾四周。接着，他仿佛搜寻记忆，似乎想起来，明白过来了，这才咕哝一句：“妈的，这下子栽啦！”

医生拉住他的手，说道：

“哪儿的话，哪儿的话呢，休养几天就行了，没什么事。”

奥托接口道：“这下子栽啦！我肚子破开啦！我完全清楚。”

随即突然说道：“我想跟儿子谈谈，如果还来得及的话。”

小奥托不由得哭哭啼啼，像个小孩子似的反复说道：“爸爸，爸爸，可怜的爸爸！”

然而父亲，语气更加坚定，说道：“好了，别哭了，这不是时候。我有话跟你说。过这儿来，靠近前，很快就能说完，我也就放心了。你们几位，请给我一些时间。”

所有人都出去了，留下儿子面对父亲。只有父子二人了，父亲便说道：“听着，儿子，你已经二十四岁了，事情可以告诉你了。其实，我们说的，也不是什么天大的秘密。你清楚，你母亲过世已有七年了，对不对，我呢，现在不过四十五岁，当年结婚我才十九岁，对不对？”

儿子结结巴巴地回答：“对，是这样。”

“那好，你母亲过世都七年了，我呢，一直独身生活。好嘛！像我这样一个男人，不可能三十七岁就一直做个鳏父吧，对不对？”

儿子回答：“对，是这样。”

父亲喘着气，脸色惨白，面部肌肉抽搐着，他接着说道：

“天哪，疼得真邪乎！喏，你明白。男人天生就不能过独身生活，但是，我又不愿意续弦，替代你母亲，只因我向她许诺过……怎么样……你明白吧？”

“是的，父亲。”

“因此，我在鲁昂找了个小相好的，住在胡瓜鱼街，十八号，四层，二门——我对你说的这些，不要忘了，——那个小相好的很体贴人，对我一心一意，很重感情，很忠贞，是一个实实在在的女人，怎么？你懂了吧，我的孩子？”

“是的，父亲。”

“那好，如果我走了，我还欠她点儿什么，而且至关重要，能保证她生活无忧。你明白吧？”

“是的，父亲。”

“跟你说，她是个贤淑的姑娘，真的，很贤淑，如果不是有你，如果不是怀念你母亲，再说，如果没有我们三人生活过的这个家，那么，我就会带她来这里了，然后娶她，这是肯定的……你听好……听好了……我的孩子……我本可以立一份遗嘱……可我根本没有做！我不愿意……因为事情……这类事情……决不应该写下来……这太损害合法继承人了……况且，这样会全部搅乱了……这样能毁了所有人！你瞧，印花公文纸，不需要，永远呢不要使用。如果说我富有，就因为我一辈子都没有动用过。这你明白，我的儿子！”

“是的，父亲。”

“再听我说说……听好了……就是说，我没有立遗嘱……我不愿意……而且，我了解你，你心肠好，你不吝啬，怎么说呢，不斤斤计较。我心里想好了，等临终时，我就把事情一五一十告诉你，还要恳求你别忘记那个女孩：卡罗莉娜·多奈，胡瓜鱼街十八号，四层，二门，别忘了——再有，听我说，等我一走，你立刻就去那儿——去妥善处理，免得她想起我时产生抱怨情绪。——你有钱财——你办得到……我给你留下的相当多……你挺好……平日找不到她。她在莫罗太太家里干活，博瓦西纳街。星期四你去。这一天她等着我。这是我的日子，已经六年了。可怜的姑娘，她会怎么伤心哭泣啊！……这件事，我全对你讲了，我的儿子，就因为我非常了解你。这类事情，不能当众去讲，也不能告诉公证人和本堂神父。这种事天天发生，众所周知，但是不能讲，除非到了必要的时候。因此，除了家人，外人，谁也不知道这个秘密，就因为家庭，所有人拧成一股绳。你明白了吧？”

“是的，父亲。”

“你答应吗？”

“是的，父亲。”

“你发誓？”

“是的，父亲。”

“是我求你了，恳求你了，儿子，不要忘了，这是我的心事。”

“不会忘的，父亲。”

“你要亲自去。我希望这个事情你能妥善安排。”

“是的，父亲。”

“然后，就看情况吧……你看她怎么向你解释。我呢，不能对你多讲了。发过誓了。”

“是的，父亲。”

“就这样吧，我的儿子，吻吻我。别了。我不行了，确定无疑。告诉他们进来吧。”小奥托呻吟着亲吻了父亲，他也始终顺从，打开了房门。神父进屋，他身穿宽袖白色法袍，手上拿着圣体油。然而，重危的人已经闭上眼睛，再也不肯睁开了，也不肯回答，甚至都不肯做一个他听懂了的暗示。

这个汉子，他说得够多的了，不能再讲了。况且，此刻他心里很平静，就想这样安静地死去。他已经向他的儿子，这个家庭的成员忏悔了，何必还向上帝的代表忏悔呢？

照例为他行了圣事，净除了心中的邪魔。赎了罪过，他的朋友围在身边，仆人们跪了一圈，没见他脸上有一丝征象他还活着。

表明剧痛的抽搐持续了四小时之后，他于午夜时分离世了。

二

星期天开猎，星期二下了葬。凯撒·奥托送父亲到墓地，安葬之后回家，这天余下的时间，他就只顾伤心流泪了，通宵没有怎么睡觉，醒来感到特别凄苦，心想，今后这日子怎么过下去呢？不过，到了傍晚，他还是想到要遵从父亲的遗愿，次日他一定得前往鲁昂看望卡罗莉娜·多奈那个姑娘，记得她住在胡瓜鱼街十八号，四层，二门。他像喃喃祈祷一样，低声重复这个名字和这个地址，不知念叨了多少遍，以免忘记。最后就没完没了地咕哝，停都停不下来，或者无论想什么，他的舌头和他的思维却总被这句话控制着。

第二天，约莫八点钟，他就吩咐下人备车，套上“大麦粒”，那匹诺曼底种的高头大马，他上车起程，马车飞驰在安维尔通往鲁昂的大道上。他穿上他那件黑礼服，头戴丝绸大礼帽，穿一条裤脚松紧带套在脚底的长裤。考虑当时的境况，他不愿意显露他那漂亮的礼服，就套上了蓝罩衫，迎风便鼓起来，能遮挡灰尘和脏点，到达后一跳下车，随手就脱掉。

马车驶进鲁昂城，恰好敲响十点钟。凯撒·奥托还一如既往，到三潭街“好心肠”旅馆落脚，接受老板、老板娘及其五个儿子的拥抱，因为他们得知了办丧事的消息。他还不得不详细讲述是出意外的情况，这又引起他们伤心落泪。这些人都知道他有钱，百般殷勤招待，可是他却谢绝，甚至不吃他们的饭，这又让他们挺生气。

他掸掉帽子上的尘土，刷干净礼服，又擦亮了皮靴，便出去寻找胡瓜鱼街。他不敢向任何人打听，生怕被人认出来，引起怀疑。最终他还是没有找到，看见一名教士，认为教会的人信得过，他们在职业上就谨慎，于是向那人问路。原来，走过去不过百十来步远，就在右侧的第二条街。

这时，他倒犹豫起来。此前，他就像个粗人，一直按照死者的意愿行事。而现在，他却感到心慌意乱，迷惑起来，一想到他，作为儿子，要面对这个曾经是他父亲的姘头女人，就不免觉得丢脸。我们心中的全部道德观，是多少世纪传承教育在我们感情深处的积淀，关于生活中的坏女人，源自教理课本他所学到的一切，以及天性多疑的男人，对这种放荡的女人，哪怕娶了一个，也必然——本人心存的蔑视，再加上他这个农民身上所具备的整个狭隘的正派观念，凡此种种，都在他内心翻腾，令他畏缩不前，令他羞愧而脸红。

不过，他还是想：“我答应了父亲，总不该失信。”于是，他推开挂着十八号牌子的半掩的楼门，发现一座昏暗的楼梯，上到四层，看到一门，又看到二门，找见门铃绳，便拉了两下。丁零丁零的铃声，在里面的房间响起，让他浑身不由得猛一战栗，房门打开了，出现在他面前的是一位年轻太太，穿戴得很好，一头棕发，肤色鲜艳，她眼神惊愕地打量他。

凯撒不知道对她说什么好，而她，还什么都不知道，等待对方开口，并不请他进屋。二人彼此端详，就这样过了将近半分钟，女主人终于问道：“你有什么事吗，先生？”

他讷讷答道：“我是奥托的儿子。”

女人惊抖了一下，脸色刷的白了，她好像早就认识他似的，结结巴巴地说道：“凯撒先生？”

“对。”

“您来有什么事吗？”

“我代表父亲，有话对您说。”

她不由得发出一声：“噢！我的上帝！”随即后退一步，让他进屋。他关上房门，跟着往里走。这时，凯撒瞧见一个四五岁的小男孩，正逗弄一只猫玩。男孩坐在地上，身后一个火炉，火上正热着菜，冒着浊气。

“请坐。”她说道。

他坐了下来。

她问道：“怎么回事呢？”

凯撒再也不敢开口了，他的目光凝视摆在屋子中央的桌子，桌子已经放好三副餐具，一副是儿童的。他看着背对着炉火的椅子，对面摆好餐巾、酒杯、开启的红葡萄酒、未开瓶的白葡萄酒，那是他父亲的座位，背对着炉火还等着他呢。凯撒看到并认出，叉子旁边是为他父亲准备的面包，已经削下硬皮，因为奥托牙口不好。接着，他抬眼，又瞧见墙上挂的大照片，奥托在巴黎世博会那年照的相，而同样一张相片，就挂在安维尔家他卧室床头的上方。

少妇又问道：“怎么回事，凯撒先生？”

凯撒看了她一眼。她惶恐焦虑，面失血色，双手害怕得发抖，还在等待。于是，他鼓足了勇气：“是这样，小姐，星期天开猎，爸爸身亡了。”

少妇受到极大的震撼，一时动弹不得。沉默了半晌，她才喃喃说，声音低得几乎听不见：“噢！这不可能！”

继而，她眼中突然涌出泪水，她抬起双手，捂住脸，开始抽泣起来，这时，小男孩扭头看见他母亲哭了，便叫起来。接着，他看明白母亲突然悲痛，是这个陌生人引起的，便扑向凯撒，一只手揪住他的裤子，另一只手拼力打他的大腿。这对母子，一个是为他父亲痛哭的女人，一个是保卫母亲的孩子，凯撒夹在中间，手足无措又极为感动，他觉得自己也受到这种激动情绪的感染，眼睛因伤悲而肿胀起来，于是振作一下，开始讲述了：“是的，”他说道，“不幸的事件，是星期天早晨八点来钟发生的……”

他讲述，就好像她在听似的，不漏掉任何细节，以农民的那种细心，多么微不足道的情况都要讲到。而小家伙还一直打他，现在是用脚踢他脚踝了。当他说到老奥托谈她情况的时候，她听到自己的名字，双手便从脸上撤下来，请求道：

“对不起，我没有听您讲，我很想了解……如果您不介意，就再从头讲起。”

他又从头讲述，还是原来的话：“不幸的事件，是星期天早晨，八点来钟发生的……”

他全部讲了，讲了很久，中间有停顿，有句号，还时而有他的想法。她贪婪地听着，以女人神经的敏感度，领会他叙述的各种变化的情况，有时感叹一声：“噢，我的上帝！”孩子以为她平静了，就不再打凯撒了，过去拉住母亲的手，也同样倾听，就好像听懂了似的。小奥托叙述完了，又说道：“现在按照他的愿望，我们一起把事情安排一下，您听我说，我很富裕，他给我留下了财产。我不愿意安排不周让您抱怨……”

然而，她急忙打断他的话：“噢！凯撒先生，凯撒先生，今天不说了。我心如刀绞！等下次吧，改天。不，今天别谈了。如果我接受，听我说，也不是为我。不，不，不，我向您发誓。是为了孩子，而且，钱财也要落到他的名头。”

凯撒闻听此言，十分惊恐，他猜测出来，结结巴巴地说道：“这么说……是他的……这孩子？”

“当然了。”少妇回答。

小奥托注视着这个小弟弟，激动的心情很复杂，既强烈又难堪。少妇又哭起来，凯撒沉默了许久，处境十分尴尬，接着说道：“那好吧，多奈小姐，我先走了，什么时候您愿意，我们再谈好吗？”

她高声说：“噢！不，您别走，您别走，不要丢下我一个人跟埃米尔！我会伤心死的。我什么人都没有了，除了我孩子就没人了。噢！多大的苦难，多大的苦难啊，凯撒先生，喏，您请坐，您还要对我讲一讲。您要告诉我，他在那边，平时都做什么？”

凯撒顺从惯了，他又坐下来。她挪过一把椅子给自己，靠近他也坐下来，就在一直热着菜的火炉前面。凯撒还抱起埃米尔放到膝上，女人向凯撒问起有关父亲无数的事儿，全是私生活的小事儿，看得出来，凯撒不用推理就感觉得到，这个可怜的女人，真是全心全意爱奥托。

凯撒的想法并不多，他说着话，自然又回到那个意外的不幸事件。“他肚子崩开一个大洞，能塞进去两个拳头。”凯撒讲出这种情况时，她不由得叫了一声，泪水再次涌出。凯撒受此感染，也哭起来。眼泪总能软化心弦，他俯向埃米尔，嘴唇正巧接近孩子的额头，就势亲吻了他。

母亲缓过一口气，喃喃说道：“可怜的孩子，现在成了孤儿。”

“我也一样。”凯撒说道。

随后，他们又不说话了。

忽然，家庭主妇什么都想到的习惯——这种实践的本能在这少妇心中苏醒了。

“这一上午，也许您还没有吃什么吧，凯撒先生？”

“没有，小姐。”

“唔！您肯定饿了。您还是吃点儿东西吧。”

“谢谢，”他回答，“我不饿，心里太痛苦了。”

“难过归难过，总得活下去。这事儿您不能拒绝！而且，您也可以多留下一会儿。等您一走，真不知道我会成什么样子！”

凯撒还婉拒了两句，终于退让了，他坐下来，背靠着火，面对着她，吃了一盘在炉子上炖得咕咕作响的羊肚，喝了一杯红葡萄酒，但是说什么也不让她开那瓶白葡萄酒。小孩子吃饭，满嘴巴浇汁，凯撒给他擦了好几次。他起身告辞时，问道：“您看什么时候合适，我再来谈事呢，多奈小姐？”

“下星期四吧，凯撒先生，如果对您没妨碍的话。这样我就不用耽误干活时间了。我每逢星期四休息。”

“下星期四，我也方便。”

“您来吃午饭吧，好不好？”

“哦！吃午饭嘛，我还不能应承。”

“一边吃饭一边谈事更好，时间也充裕些。”

“那好吧。还是中午。”

他离去时，又亲了亲小埃米尔，还同多奈小姐握了握手。

三

这一周，凯撒·奥托感到很漫长。他从来没有这样寂寞过，觉得难以忍受这种孤独。此前，他一直如影随形，生活在父亲身边，跟随到田间地头，监督雇工执行命令的情况，即使分开一阵工夫，吃晚饭时又见到了。晚上的时光，爷儿俩就面对面，边抽着烟斗，边谈论马、牛和羊；而早晨醒来，父子就握手问好，洋溢着深厚的亲情。

现在，凯撒独自一人了。他沿着秋天的田地游荡，始终期望从一片平展的地头，立起父亲那挥动臂膀的高大身影。他要消磨时光，就走进邻居家，向所有未听过的人讲述那次意外事件，有时还向听过的人重讲一遍。这种事情忙完了，该想的事也想过了，他就坐到路边，思索这种日子还要持续多久。

他经常想到多奈小姐。他觉得挺喜欢她，确实认为她很像样，正如他父亲所言，是一个温柔的正派姑娘。对，若说一个正派姑娘，她确确实实是一个正派的姑娘。处理这件事，他决心要出手大方：在确保孩子资产的同时，给她买下两千法郎的年金。一想到星期四又要见到她，一起安排这件事，他甚至感到有几分欣喜。再一想到这个弟弟，这个五岁的小家伙，却是他父亲的儿子，又让他忧虑，颇为烦恼，同时也让他心里热乎乎的。这个私生的娃儿，虽然算作家里人，可是永远不能姓奥托，这个家他管不管也随意，但总归令他联想到父亲。

因此，星期四早晨，前往鲁昂的路上，驾车的“大麦粒”嗒嗒的马蹄声非常响亮，他坐在车上的心情，自不幸的事件发生后，还从来没有如此轻松，如此平静。

他走进多奈小姐的套房，看到餐桌已经摆好，同上星期四一样，只有一点不同，面包没有去掉硬皮。

凯撒握了握少妇的手，亲了亲埃米尔的脸蛋，随即坐下，有点儿像到了他的家，不过心情还照样沉重。他觉得多奈小姐廋了一点儿，脸色也苍白了些：她肯定流泪过多。现在她在凯撒面前，神态不自然了，就好像意识到了些什么，而上星期刚受不幸消息的打击时却未曾注意。她对他格外客气起来，表现出一种痛苦的谦恭、体贴的照顾，仿佛要用关心和忠诚来回报凯撒对她的善意。他们午饭吃了好长时间，谈论他此次来要办的事。她不要这么多钱。这太多了，实在太多了。她挣的钱足够生活了，她只是希望埃米尔长大后，还能有点儿钱。凯撒执意这样做，甚至还额外赠送一千法郎，作为抚恤金。等他喝完咖啡，多奈小姐问道，“您抽烟吗？”

“抽啊……我有烟斗。”他说道。

他摸了摸口袋。糟糕，烟斗忘记带了。他正欲气恼，多奈小姐却从杆子里给他取出他父亲的烟斗。他接受了，拿起一看便认出来，还嗅了嗅，夸赞它是最好的烟斗之一，声音中还透着一丝激动。随后他往烟斗里塞满烟丝，吸几口点着了。多奈小姐收拾桌子，将用过的餐具放进橱柜下层，准备等他走后清洗，他将埃米尔放到腿上，让孩子骑马玩，直到该走的时候。

快到三点时，他不免遗憾地站起身，想到该走了心里很烦。

“好啦，多奈小姐，”他说道，“希望您下午过得愉快，我很高兴看到您这种状况。”

多奈小姐伫立在他面前，脸有点儿红，显得挺激动，注视着她心里的另一个人。

“我们就再也不见面了吗？”

他回答得干脆：“可以呀，小姐，如果您愿意的话。”

“当然愿意了，凯撒先生。那好，下星期四，您方便吗？”

“方便啊，多奈小姐。”

“您来吃午饭，没错吧？”

“这，如果您乐意，我不谢绝。”

“当然乐意，凯撒先生，下星期四，中午，像今天这样。”

“星期四中午见，多奈小姐。”

[1] 相当于我国初中毕业。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明的之外，均为译者注。）

公墓妓女

五个朋友一起吃晚饭。这五个上流社会人士，都是成熟男子，富有，三人已有家室，两个仍然单身。他们这样聚会，每月一次，追忆他们的青春岁月，吃完饭便闲聊，直到凌晨两点钟。他们始终是知心密友，而且兴趣相投，也许认为这种聚会是他们一生中最美好的夜晚。他们无所不谈，谈遍了巴黎人喜闻乐见的大事小情，其实他们之间，也像大多数沙龙聚会那样，无非是重复在晨报上看到的那些社会新闻。

最欢快的要数约瑟夫·德·巴尔东。这个单身汉以别出心裁的方式全方位地过着巴黎生活。他绝非放荡之徒，也非堕落分子，而只是一个尚属年轻的好奇者、乐天派，因为他不过四十岁。说他是上流社会人士，是取这个词组最宽泛、最和善的含义。他天资聪慧，却没有多大深度；知识面很宽，又谈不上渊博；理解事物很快速，但不肯认真深入探讨。他从自己的观察、自己的奇遇，从自己所看到的、碰到的和找到的一切，提炼出哲理滑稽小说式的趣闻逸事，以及幽默的见解，从而在全城赢得了智慧的盛誉。他是饭局的演说家。他有自己的故事，每次都讲他的故事，别人也总有所期待。他不用别人请求，就开始讲起自己的故事了。

他抽着烟，两只臂肘支在餐桌上，半杯上等白兰地摆在餐盘前面，沉浸在弥漫热咖啡香味的烟雾中，仿佛就在自己家中，犹如某些生物在某时某处，绝对在自己栖息地的感觉，犹如礼拜堂里的一个虔诚的女信徒，又如鱼缸中的一只金鱼。他在吸烟的间歇，说道：

“不久之前，我有一次非常独特的艳遇。”

所有人几乎异口同声，要求道：“讲来听听。”

他便说下去。

好吧。你们都知道，我在巴黎走的地方很多，就像爱收集小摆设的人，到处探寻摆设的

橱窗那样。我则窥探热闹，窥探人，注视眼前经过的一切、发生的所有事。

且说九月中旬，一天午后我出门，去哪儿还不知道，天气好极了，就像此刻这样。男人总有一种模糊的欲望，不期而遇一位美女，而且在脑子里挨排挑选，比较，酌量她们能引起你多大兴趣，对你能施展多大魅力最终还是决定要看当天的吸引力了。不过，阳光明媚，天气温暖，往往就没什么兴致拜访人了。

阳光真是明媚，天气真是温暖，我点着一支雪茄，糊里糊涂走在环城大道上。我溜达了一会儿，便心生一念，何不一直走到蒙马特公墓，进去瞧瞧呢。我呢，很爱看公墓，能休息，也感受点儿忧伤，这是我所需要的。而且，有些好友，也在那里安息，再也没人去探视了；我呢，时而还去看望。

恰恰在这座蒙马特墓园，有我一段感情史。一个矮小的可爱女子，一个对我非常钟情也让我特别动情的相好。每每想起来，心里就难过到极点，同时也深感痛惜，百感交集的痛

惜。我就去她的墓畔静思，她走完了这一生。

此外，我也喜爱墓园，只因这是一座座大城池，居民异常密集。你们想想看，在这狭小的空间，埋葬了多少死者，世世代代的巴黎人，在这儿找到永久的归宿，关进小小的墓穴里，埋进小土坑，上面盖着一块石板或者立个十字架标志，彻彻底底成为穴居人；反之，活在世上的这些蠢货，却占据了大片地方，大肆喧哗闹腾。

再者，公墓里有些纪念性建筑物，其价值几乎不亚于博物馆的藏品。我得承认，卡芬雅克的坟墓，不用比较，就能让我联想到让·古戎的杰作——鲁昂大教堂地下礼拜堂里路易·德·布雷泽墓的全身浮雕像。先生们，凡是称得上现代和现实主义的艺术均来源于此。路易·德·布雷泽的浮雕像，比起今天在墓中所有受刑折磨的尸体，显得更为真实，更为骇人，更具有临终后痉挛且已无生命的肉体感。

不过，在蒙马特公墓，还能观赏到博丹宏伟的纪念碑，以及戈蒂埃、米尔热的墓碑。而

有一天，我看到米尔热的碑前，仅仅摆放了一个可怜的黄蜡菊花圈，是谁送的呢？也许是最后一个小女工，如今年迈，在附近当看门人时送来的吧？这是米勒制作的一尊小雕像，很精美，但是因为无人照管而肮脏不堪。米尔热哟，歌唱青春吧！

且说我走进蒙马特公墓，忽然一阵感伤袭上心头，倒是一种不太难受的忧伤，是那种能让健康的人思考的忧伤：“这地方嘛，没多大意思，不过，我还没有到迁居这里的时候。”秋色印象，暗淡的枯叶氤氲着温暖的潮湿，微弱的阳光强化了飘浮在这上空的孤独和终结的感受，为这墓园染上了些浪漫色彩。

我漫步在这些故冢的街道上，这里的邻居们绝不往来，再也不同床共枕，再也不看报了。我呢，则开始读起碑文来。读碑文，真的，这是世上最有趣的事。拉比升也好，梅拉克也罢，从来就没有滑稽得像碑文这样能引我如此发笑的文字。啊！这些大理石墓板，这些十字架上的文字，远高于保罗·德·科克的书，更能令

人捧腹大笑：父母倾诉丧失孩子的憾恨，唯愿逝者在另一个世界生活幸福，并且希望日后相聚——开什么玩笑！

不过，在这座墓园中，我尤其喜爱被遗弃的部分，非常凄清，布满紫杨和翠柏。埋葬前人的老区，用不了多久，又会重新变成新区，伐倒那些以死者遗体为养料的绿树，将新近的死者埋进排列整齐的小块大理石板下面。

我游荡了一段时间，头脑清爽了，心下明白就要感到乏味了，得赶紧到我那女友长眠的“床位”，敬献我忠诚的哀思。我走到她的墓前，感到一阵揪心。亲爱的人啊，多么可怜，生前她那么温柔，那么深情，那么白净，那么清新……而现在……如果开棺瞧瞧……隔着铁栅栏，我俯身对她低声讲述我的哀痛，当然她根本听不见了，正要离去，却瞥见旁边墓前跪着一位女子，身穿重孝，一色黑衣裙。她撩起黑纱，露出一副令人惊艳的容貌，那头金发分梳在两鬓，在她头巾的黑夜中仿佛照耀着曙光。我停下来。自不待言，她一定心潮涌动着深深

的痛苦，目光埋藏在双手里，全身僵直不动，俨然一尊沉思的雕像，行进在痛惜之路上，在遮蔽眼睛的阴影里，数着前尘往事折磨人的念珠，她自身仿佛一个死了的女人，可能在思念一个死去的男人。忽然，我看出她要哭了，只见她后背微微颤动，宛如弱风拂柳，我才做此猜想。起初她在饮泣，逐渐哭得厉害，脖颈和肩头急速抖动。猛然，她移开手，露出双眼，漫溢着泪水，很是迷人，惊慌的眼神扫视周围，处于从噩梦中醒来的状态。她瞧见我正注视她，不免有些羞愧，整张脸重又埋在双手中。这时，她的哭泣变得抽噎了，脑袋缓慢俯向大理石墓板，额头贴在上面，纱巾披散开，罩住了爱人坟墓的白衣角，仿佛新戴的孝。我听见她呜咽，继而全身瘫软，脸颊贴着石板，静止不动，失去了知觉。

我急步上前，拍打她的双手，往她眼睑吹气，同时浏览了十分简单的碑文：

“海军陆战队上尉，路易·泰奥道尔·卡雷尔之墓，战死于东京湾。为他的灵魂祈祷吧。”

数月前死去的。我也伤心为之落泪，便加倍努力救护。救护奏了效，她苏醒过来。当时我的神情很激动——我的相貌也不赖，未满四十岁——从她投来的第一眼，我就明白她是个懂礼貌、知感激的人。随后她又流了泪，讲述了身世，证明她确实是这样的人。她抽泣着，断断续续倾吐胸臆，说她是个孤女，父母双亡，这位军官出于爱情才娶她的，因为她的嫁妆勉强说得过去，不料结婚才一年，丈夫便倒在东京湾了。

我劝解，安慰她，扶她立起身，搀她站起来。然后，我对她说。

“不要在这里逗留了。跟我来吧。”

她喃喃答道：

“我走不了路了。”

“别担心，我帮您。”

“谢谢，先生，您真是好人。您来这里，也是祭拜死者吗？”

“是的，夫人。”

“死去的一位女子？”

“是的，夫人。”

“您妻子？”

“一位女友。”

“爱一位女友，也可能像爱妻子那样，爱情并无规范。”

“是的，夫人。”

于是，我们就一道走了，她偎依在我身上，在出墓园这一路，我几乎是抱着她走的。出来之后，她气息微弱，说道：“我觉得自己要病了似的。”

“要不要找个地方，您进去喝点儿什么？”

“好吧，先生。”

我看到一家饭馆，是办完丧事之后，亲友聚一聚的那种馆子。我们进去，我给她要了一杯热茶，她喝下去似乎有了点儿精神，嘴角泛起了一抹微笑，跟我谈起了她本人。要多凄凉有多凄凉啊，生活中孤单一人，在家里，白天黑夜，总是形影相吊，纵使有什么风情，信赖体恤、亲近相处的情意，也没有任何人可给予了。

这种话听来很诚恳，从她口中讲出来，也

讨人喜欢。我动了情感。她非常年轻，或许就二十岁。我恭维她几句，她坦然接受了。看看时间不早了，我提议叫辆车送她回家，她同意了。我们坐上出租马车，肩靠着肩挤在一起，体温透过衣服相交融，这种事最令人心猿意马了。

马车停到她家的楼门口，她低声问道：“我觉得单独上不了楼了，我住在五层。您这么热心，能不能搀扶我送到家呢？”

我赶忙答应了。她缓慢上楼，还气喘吁吁。到了她的家门口，她又说道：“您进屋坐一坐，好让我向您表示感谢。”

没的说，我进去了。

房间不大，甚至有点儿贫寒，但是很简朴，她家里收拾得整整齐齐。我们并排坐到小型长沙发上，她又向我提起她的孤寂。她摇铃唤女仆，要吩咐给我端上什么喝的。女仆没有来。我心下暗喜，想必那个女仆只是上午来干活，即所谓的清洁女工。她已经摘了帽子。她那双明澈的眼睛凝视我，样子确实非常可爱：那么明澈，又那么凝视，激发起我的极大欲念。

我情不自禁，一把将她搂在怀里，亲吻她那忽然闭起的眼睛，吻了又吻，吻个没够。她挣扎着推我，连声说：“行了，行了，行了！”

她这话是什么意思呢？此情此景，“行了”至少可能有两层意思。我要让她住声，就从眼睛移吻到嘴上，从而给“行了”这话赋予我喜爱的定义。她并不过分抗拒。在冒犯了对死于东京湾的上尉的纪念之后，我们重又凝视着对方时，她那样子显得倦怠、温柔、驯顺，这便驱散了我的不安情绪。

于是，我献起殷勤，因感激而更加热情。大约又交谈了一小时之后，我就问她：

“您在哪儿用晚餐？”

“在附近的一家小餐馆。”

“独自一人？”

“当然了。”

“您愿意同我共进晚餐吗？”

“去哪儿？”

“林荫大道一家好餐馆。”

她婉拒了一下，我坚持邀请，她就退让

了，给自己找了个台阶下：“我太烦闷，太烦闷了。”随后又补充一句：“我得换一条衣裙，颜色别这么暗了。”她说着，走进自己的画室。再一出来，她已换成戴半孝了，穿了一条灰色连衣裙，非常朴素，突显苗条的身段更有魅力了。显而易见，她有两套装束：扫墓的孝服，出门的便装。

晚餐很开心。她喝了香槟，兴奋起来，活跃起来。我同她一道回到她家里。在墓畔结缘的这段关系，大约持续三周。可是，人做什么事都有个够，尤其是男女的事儿。我借口一趟远行推不掉，便离开了她。分手时我也出手大方，她也向我千恩万谢。她让我答应她，向她发誓，我一归来就去找她，因为，她对我似乎真的有点儿依依不舍了。

我又另寻新欢去了，大约过了一个月，我也没有多大意愿再去见墓地艳遇的那个小妞。然而，我却忘不掉她……对她的记忆萦绕心头，仿佛一个秘密，仿佛一种心理问题，又像一种困扰我们的无解的疑问。

有一天，也说不清为什么，我想象到蒙马特公墓，就能见到她，于是去了。

我在墓园久久漫步，仅仅遇见那里的常客，还没有完全斩断同死者关系的那些人。至于在东京湾阵亡的那个上尉的墓前，既不见跪在大理石上哭泣的那位女子，也没有祭奠的鲜花、花圈。

不过，在这座亡灵的大城池，我误入另一个街区，忽然发现一条狭窄的十字架林荫路尽头，有一对身穿重孝的男女朝我走过来。噢，好不惊愕！他们渐行渐近，我认出那个女的：正是她！

她看见我，脸一红，与我擦肩而过时，她还向我打了个小暗号，向我丢了个眼色，示意“装作不认识我”，似乎还表明：“来看我呀，心爱的。”

那男人很体面，风度翩翩，佩戴着四级荣誉团勋章，年纪约有五十岁。他搀扶着她，一如我本人曾那样搀扶她走出公墓。

我走开了，不免十分惊诧，心中回味刚看

到的情景。这个墓园女猎手究竟属于哪类人，莫非就是个普通妓女，揽客有了灵感，专门在墓区拉伤心的男人，即心里还装着一个女人，妻子或情妇，还因念念不忘失去的恩爱而魂不守舍的那种男人。她是独此一家吗？抑或还有数人呢？莫非这是一种职业？在墓地也像在街头人行道那样吗？公墓妓女！再不然，唯独她发此奇想，能从哲学的深度发掘，到这种悲凄哀悼的场所，唤醒痛惜的爱情吧？

我真想知道，那天她是哪位墓主的孀妇呢？

Cockcrow

Madame Berthe d’Avancelles had rejected the advances of her admirer Baron Joseph de Croissard to such an extent that he was now in despair. He had pursued her relentlessly throughout the winter in Paris, and now at his château at Carville in Normandy he was holding a series of hunting parties in her honour.

The husband, Monsieur d’Avancelles, turned a blind eye to all this. It was rumoured that they lived separate lives on account of a physical shortcoming of his which Madame could not overlook. He was a fat little man with short arms, short legs, a short neck, short nose, short everything in fact.

Madame d’Avancelles, in contrast, was a tall, chestnuthaired, determined- looking young woman. She laughed openly at old Pipe and Slippers as she called him to his face but looked with tender indulgence on her admirer, the titled Baron Joseph de Croissard, with his broad shoulders, his sturdy neck and his fair, drooping moustache.

Until now, however, she had granted him no favours despite the fact that he was spending a fortune on her, throwing a constant round of receptions, hunting parties, and all kinds of celebrations to which he invited the local aristocracy.

All day long the woods rang to the sound of hounds in full cry after a fox or a wild boar and every night a dazzling display of fireworks spiralled upwards to join the sparkling stars. A tracery of light from the drawing- room windows shone on the huge lawns where shadowy figures occasionally passed.

It was the russet season of autumn when leaves swirled over the gardens like flocks of birds. Wafting on the air came the tang of damp, bare earth, caught as the smell of a woman’s naked flesh as her gown slips down to the floor after the ball.

On an evening during a reception held the previous spring, Madame d’Avancelles had replied to an imploring Monsieur de Croissard with the words: ‘If I am to fall at all, my friend, it will certainly not be before the leaves do likewise. I’ve far too many things to do this summer to give it a thought.’ He had remembered those daring words of hers spoken so provocatively and was now pressing his advantage. Each day he crept closer, gaining more and more of the bold beauty’s heart until by this point her resistance seemed hardly more than symbolic.

Soon there was to be a great hunting party. The night before, Madame Berthe had said laughingly to the Baron:‘Tomorrow, Baron, if you manage to kill the beast I shall have something to give you.’

He was up at dawn reconnoitring where the wild boar was wallowing. He accompanied his whips, setting out the order of the hunt in such a way that he should return from the field in triumph. When the horns sounded for the meet, he appeared in a well- cut hunting costume of scarlet and gold. With his upright, broad- chested figure and flashing eyes he glowed with good health and manly vigour.

The hunt moved off. The boar was raised and ran, followed by the baying hounds rushing through the undergrowth. The horses broke into a gallop, hurtling with their riders along the narrow forest paths while far behind the following carriages drove noiselessly over the softer verges.

Teasingly, Madame d’Avancelles kept the Baron at her side, slowing down to walking pace in an interminably long, straight avenue along which four rows of oaks arched vaultlike towards each other. Trembling with both desire and frustration he listened with one ear to the young woman’s light badinage, the other pricked for the hunting horns and the sound of the hounds growing fainter by the minute.

‘So you love me no longer,’ she was saying.

‘How can you say such a thing?’ he replied.

‘You do seem to be more interested in the hunt than in me,’ she went on. He groaned. ‘You do remember your own orders don’t you? To kill the beast myself.’

‘Indeed I do,’ she added with great seriousness. ‘Before my very eyes.’ At this he quivered impatiently in the saddle, spurred on his eager horse and finally lost his patience.

‘For God’s sake, Madame, not if we stay here a minute longer.’

‘That is how it has to be nevertheless,’ she cried laughingly. ‘Otherwise, you’re out of luck.’

Then she spoke to him gently, leaning her hand on his arm and, as if absentmindedly, stroking his horse’s mane. They had turned right on to a narrow path overhung with trees when, suddenly swerving to avoid one of their low branches, she leaned against him so closely that he felt her hair tickling his neck. He threw his arms around her and pressing his thick moustache to her forehead planted upon it a passionate kiss.

At first she was motionless, stunned by his ardour, then with a start she turned her head and, either by chance or design, her own delicate lips met his beneath their blond cascade. Then, out of either embarrassment or regret for the incident she spurred her horse on the flank and galloped swiftly away. For a long while they rode straight on together, without so much as exchanging a glance.

The hunt in full cry was close and the thickets seemed to shake, when suddenly, covered in blood and shaking off the hounds that clung to him, the boar went rushing past through the bushes. The Baron gave a triumphant laugh, cried ‘Let him who loves me follow me!’ and disappeared, swallowed up by the forest. When Madame d’Avancelles reached an open glade a few minutes later he was just getting up, covered with mud, his jacket torn and his hands bloody, while the animal lay full length on the ground with the Baron’s knife plunged up to the hilt in its shoulder.

The quarry was cut by torchlight on that mild and melancholy night. The moon gilded the red flames of the torches which filled the air with pine smoke. The dogs, yelping and snapping, devoured the stinking innards of the boar while the beaters and the gentlemen, standing in a circle around the spoil, blew their horns with all their might. The flourish of the hunting horns rose into the night air above the woods. Its echoes fell and were lost in the distant valleys beyond, alarming nervous stags, a barking fox and small grey rabbits at play on the edge of the glades. Terrified night birds fluttered above the crazed pack while the women, excited a little by the violence and vulnerability surrounding these events, leaned a little heavily on the men’s arms and, without waiting for the hounds to finish, drifted off with their partners down the many forest paths. Feeling languid after all the exhausting emotion of the day Madame d’Avancelles said to the Baron: ‘Would you care for a turn in the park, my friend?’

He gave no answer, but trembling and unsteady with desire pulled her to him. Instantly they kissed and as they walked very slowly under the almost leafless trees through which moonlight filtered, their love, their desire and their need for each other was so intense that they almost sank down at the foot of a tree.

The horns had fallen silent and the exhausted hounds were sleeping by now in their kennels.

‘Let us go back,’ the young woman said. They returned.

Just as they reached the château and were about to enter, she murmured in a faint voice: ‘I’m so tired, my friend, I’m going straight to bed.’ As he opened his arms for one last kiss she fled, with the parting words: ‘No . . . to sleep . . . but . . . let him who loves me follow me!’

An hour later when the whole sleeping château seemed dead to the world the Baron crept on tiptoe out of his room and scratched at the door of his friend. Receiving no reply he made to open it and found it unbolted.

She was leaning dreamily with her elbows on the window ledge. He threw himself at her knees which he showered with mad kisses through her nightdress. She said nothing, but ran her dainty fingers caressingly through the Baron’s hair. Suddenly, as if coming to a momentous decision, she disengaged herself and whispered provocatively: ‘Wait for me. I shall be back.’ Her finger raised in shadow pointed to the far end of the room where loomed the vague white shape of her bed.

With wildly trembling hands he undressed quickly by feel and slipped between the cool sheets. He stretched out in bliss and almost forgot his friend as his weary body yielded to the linen’s caress. Doubtless enjoying the strain on his patience, still she did not return. He closed his eyes in exquisitely pleasurable anticipation. His most cherished dream was about to come true. Little by little his limbs relaxed, as did his mind, where thoughts drifted, vague and indistinct. He succumbed at last to the power of great fatigue and finally fell asleep.

He slept the heavy, impenetrable sleep of the exhausted huntsman. He slept indeed till dawn. Then from a nearby tree through the still half- open window came the ringing cry of a cock. Startled awake, the Baron’s eyes flew open. Finding himself, to his great surprise, in a strange bed and with a woman’s body lying against his he remembered nothing and stammered as he struggled into consciousness: ‘What? Where am I? What is it?’

At this, she, who had not slept a wink, looked at the puffy, red- eyed and dishevelled man at her side. She answered in the same dismissive tone she took with her husband. ‘Nothing,’ she said, ‘it’s a cock. Go back to sleep, Monsieur. It’s nothing to do with you.’

Femme Fatale

The restaurant, Le Grillon, Mecca of the entire local boating community, was now slowly emptying. At the main entrance a large crowd of people were calling and shouting out to each other. With oars on their shoulders, strapping great fellows in white jerseys waved and gesticulated. Women in light spring frocks were stepping cautiously into the skiffs moored alongside and, having settled themselves in the stern of each, were smoothing out their dresses. The owner of the establishment, a tough- looking, red- bearded man of legendary strength, was helping the pretty young things aboard and with a practised hand was holding steady the gently bobbing craft.

The oarsmen then took their places, playing to the gallery and showing off broad chests and muscular arms in their sleeveless vests. The gallery in this case consisted of a crowd of suburbanites in their Sunday best, as well as a few workmen and some soldiers, all leaning on the parapet of the bridge and watching the scene below with keen interest. One by one the boats cast off from the landing stage. The oarsmen leaned forward and with a regular swing pulled back. At each stroke of the long, slightly curved blades the fast skiffs sped through the water making for La Grenouillère and growing progressively smaller till they disappeared beyond the railway bridge and into the distance.

Only one couple now remained. The slim, pale- faced young man, still a relatively beardless youth, had his arm around the waist of his girl, a skinny little grasshopper of a creature with brown hair. They stopped from time to time to gaze into each other’s eyes.

The owner cried: ‘Come on, Monsieur Paul, get a move on!’

The couple moved down closer. Of all the customers, Monsieur Paul, who paid regularly and in full, was the best liked and most respected. Many of the others ran up bills and frequently absconded without settling them. The son of a senator, he was also an excellent advertisement for the establishment. When some stranger asked, ‘And who’s that young chap over there with his eyes glued to the girl?’ one of the regulars would murmur, in a mysterious, important sort of way, ‘Oh, that’s Paul Baron, you know, the son of the senator.’ Then the stranger would inevitably have to comment,‘Poor young devil, he’s got it bad.’ The proprietress of Le Grillon, a good businesswoman and wise in the ways of the world, called the young man and his companion ‘my two turtle doves’ and looked with tender indulgence on the love affair which brought such glamour to her establishment.

The couple ambled slowly down to where a skiff called the Madeleine was ready. Before embarking, however, they stopped to kiss once more, much to the amusement of the audience gathered on the bridge. Finally, Monsieur Paul took up the oars and set off after the others also making for La Grenouillère.

When they arrived it was getting on for three and here too the vast floating café was swarming with people. It is in effect one huge raft with a tarpaulin roof supported by wooden columns. It is connected to the charming island of Croissy by two narrow footbridges, one of which runs right through to the centre of the café itself. The other connects at the far end with a tiny islet where a single tree grows and which is nicknamed the Pot- de- Fleurs. From there it connects with the land again via a bathing pool.

Monsieur Paul moored his boat alongside the café, climbed up to its balustrade then, holding his girl’s two hands, guided her up also. They entered, found a place for two at the end of a table and sat down opposite each other.

Lining the towpath on the opposite side of the river was a long string of vehicles. Fiacres alternated with the flashy carriages of gay young men- about- town. The first were lumbering great hulks whose bodywork crushed the springs beneath and to which were harnessed broken- down old hacks with drooping necks. The other carriages were streamlined, with light suspension and fine, delicate wheels. These were drawn by horses with slender, straight, strong legs, heads held high and bits snowy with foam. Their solemn, liveried drivers, heads held stiffly inside huge collars, sat ramrod straight with their whips resting on their knees.

The river banks were crowded with people coming and going in different kinds of configurations: family parties, groups of friends, couples and individuals. They idly plucked at blades of grass, wandered down to the water’s edge then climbed back up to the path. Having reached a certain spot they all congregated to wait for the ferryman whose heavy boat plied constantly back and forth, depositing passengers on the island.

The branch of the river, incidentally called the dead branch, which this floating bar dominates, seemed asleep, so slowly did the current move there. Flotillas of gigs, skiffs, canoes, pedaloes and river craft of all kinds streamed over the still water, mingling and intersecting, meeting and parting, running foul of each other, stopping, and with a sudden jerk of their oarsmen’s arms and a tensing of their muscles, taking off again, darting this way and that like shoals of red and yellow fish.

More were arriving all the time; some from Chatou upstream, some from Bougival, downstream. Gales of contagious laughter carried from one boat to another and the air was full of insults, complaints, protestations and howls. The men in the boats exposed their muscular, tanned bodies to the glare of the sun and, like exotic water- plants, the women’s parasols of red, green and yellow silk blossomed in the sterns of their craft.

The July sun blazed in the middle of the sky and the atmosphere was gay and carefree, while in the windless air not a leaf stirred in the poplars and willows lining the banks of the river. In the distance ahead, the conspicuous bulk of Mont- Valérien loomed, rearing the ramparts of its fortifications in the glare of the sun. On the right, the gentle slopes of Louveciennes, following the curve of the river, formed a semi- circle within which could be glimpsed, through the dense and shady greenery of their spacious lawns, the white- painted walls of weekend retreats.

On the land adjoining La Grenouillère strollers were sauntering under the gigantic trees which help to make this part of the island one of the most delightful parks imaginable. Busty women with peroxided hair and nipped- in waists could be seen, made up to the nines with blood red lips and black- kohled eyes. Tightly laced into their garish dresses they trailed in all their vulgar glory over the fresh green grass. They were accompanied by men whose fashion- plate accessories, light gloves, patent- leather boots, canes as slender as threads and absurd monocles made them look like complete idiots.

The part of the island facing La Grenouillère is narrow and between it and the opposite bank where another ferry plies, bringing people over from Croissy, the current is very strong and very fast. Here it swirls and roars, raging like a torrent in a myriad of eddies and foam. A detachment of pontoon- builders wearing the uniform of artillerymen was camped on the bank and some of the soldiers, side by side on a long beam of wood, sat watching the river below.

A noisy, rambunctious crowd filled the floating restaurant. The wooden tables, sticky and awash with streams of spilt drink, were covered with half- empty glasses and surrounded by half- tipsy customers. The crowd sang and shouted and brawled. Red- faced, belligerent men, their hats tipped at the backs of their heads and their eyes glassy with booze, prowled like animals spoiling for a fight. The women, cadging free drinks in the meantime, were seeking their prey for the night. The space between the tables was filled with the usual clientèle – noisy young boating blades and their female companions in short flannel skirts.

One of the men was banging away at the piano using his feet as well as his hands. Four couples were dancing a quadrille and watching them was a group of elegantly dressed young men whose respectable appearance was ruined by the hideous incongruity of the setting.

The place reeked of vice and corruption and the dregs of Parisian society in all its rottenness gathered there: cheats, con men and cheap hacks rubbed shoulders with under- age dandies, old roués and rogues, sleazy underworld types once notorious for things best forgotten mingled with other small- time crooks and speculators, dabblers in dubious ventures, frauds, pimps, and racketeers. Cheap sex, both male and female, was on offer in this tawdry meat- market of a place where petty rivalries were exploited, and quarrels picked over nothing in an atmosphere of fake gallantry where swords or pistols at dawn settled matters of highly questionable honour in the first place.

Every Sunday, out of sheer curiosity some of the people from the surrounding countryside would drop in. Every year would bring a fresh batch of young men, extremely young men at that, keen to make useful contacts. Casual cruisers would amble by and every so often a complete innocent would become embroiled.

La Grenouillère lived up to its name. There was a place for bathing between the tarpaulin- covered raft where drinks were served and the Pot- de- Fleurs. Women with the requisite curves came there to display their wares and their clients. Those less fortunate who required padding and corsetry to pass muster looked disdainfully on as their rivals cavorted and splashed about.

Awaiting their turn to plunge in and thronging around a small diving board were swimmers of every shape and size: some slim and straight as vine- poles, some round as pumpkins, some gnarled as olive- branches, some with bodies curved forward over pot- bellies, some whose vast stomachs threw the body backwards. Each was as ugly as the other as they leapt into the water and splashed the customers drinking at the café next door.

Despite the proximity of the river and the huge trees shading it, the place was suffocatingly hot. Mingling with the fumes of spilt drinks came the smell of flesh and the cheap perfume with which the skin of those trading in sex was drenched. Underlying all these smells was the slight but persistent aroma of talc, which wafted with varying intensity as if an unseen hand were waving some gigantic powder- puff over the entire scene.

All eyes were on the river where the comings and goings of the boats attracted everyone’s attention. Girls sprawled in the stern opposite their strong- wristed menfolk looked with contempt at those still prowling about the island in search of a male to buy them dinner that night. Sometimes when a crew in full swing flashed past their friends ashore would shout and were joined by the crazy, yelling crowd inside the restaurant. At the bend of the river near Chatou boats were constantly coming into view. As they approached and grew more distinct, faces became recognizable and more shouts went up.

A boat with an awning and containing four women came slowly downstream towards them. The woman at the oars was small, lean and past her prime. She wore her hair pinned up inside an oilskin hat. Opposite her a big blonde dressed in a man’s jacket was lying on her back at the bottom of the boat with a foot resting on the thwart on either side of the oarswoman. The blonde was smoking a cigarette and with each jerk of the oars her bosom and her belly quivered. At the very stern of the boat under the awning two beautiful, tall, slender girls, one blonde the other brunette, sat with their arms round each other’s waists watching their two companions.

A shout went up from La Grenouillère: ‘ Aye- aye! Lesbos!’and suddenly a wild clamour broke out. In the terrifying scramble to see, glasses were knocked over and people started climbing on the tables. Everyone began to chant‘Lesbos! Lesbos! Lesbos!’ The words merged into a vague howl before suddenly starting up again, rising into the air, filling the plain beyond, resounding in the dense foliage of the tall surrounding trees and echoing in the distance as if aimed at the sun itself.

During this ovation the oarswoman had calmly come to a halt. The big blonde lying at the bottom of the boat turned her head languorously and raised herself on her elbows. The two in the stern started laughing and waving to the crowd. At this there was even more of a hullabaloo and the place shook with the noise. The men raised their hats and the women waved their handkerchiefs. Every voice, deep and shrill alike, chanted in unison ‘Lesbos!’ This motley collection of undesirables seemed to be saluting a leader, as warships give a gun salute to their passing admiral. From the flotilla of boats also there was wild acclamation for the women’s boat which now continued at its leisurely pace, to land a little further off.

Monsieur Paul’s reaction was unlike that of the others. Pulling a key from his pocket he started using it as a whistle and blew hard. His girl, looking nervous now and even paler than before, pulled his arm to make him stop. This time when she looked into his eyes, it was with fury. But he was beside himself with male jealousy and a deep, instinctive ungovernable rage. His lips trembling with indignation he stammered: ‘Shouldn’t be allowed! They should be drowned like puppies with stones round their necks!’

Madeleine suddenly lost her temper. Her shrill voice became piercing as she lashed out at him: ‘Mind your own business, will you! They’ve got a perfect right to do whatever they want. They’re not doing any harm to anyone. Why don’t you just shut up and leave them alone . . .’

He cut her short. ‘This a matter for the police! If it was up to me I’d have them locked up in Saint- Lazare!’

She gave a start. ‘Oh you would, would you?’

‘Certainly I would. And in the meantime I forbid you to have anything to do with them. I absolutely forbid it, do you understand?’

She shrugged her shoulders at this and said in a suddenly calm voice: ‘Listen, dear, I shall do exactly as I please. If you don’t like it you know what you can do. Get the hell out. Now. I’m not your wife, so shut up.’

He remained silent and they stood staring each other out, breathing rapidly, their mouths set.

At the other end of the café the women were now making their entrance. The two dressed as men led, one gaunt and weatherbeaten, ageing and very mannish. The other, more than amply filling the white flannel outfit with her large bottom and her huge thighs encased in the wide trousers, waddled forward like a fat, bow- legged goose. The two friends followed and the whole boating community surged forward to shake hands.

The four had rented a riverside cottage and lived together there as two couples. Their vice was public, official and perfectly obvious to all. It was referred to quite naturally as something entirely normal. There were rumours about jealous scenes that took place there and about the various actresses and other famous women who frequented the little cottage near the water’s edge. One neighbour, scandalized by the goings- on, alerted the police at one stage and an inspector accompanied by one of his men came to make enquiries. It was a delicate mission: there was nothing the women could be prosecuted for, least of all prostitution. The inspector was deeply puzzled and could not understand what these alleged misdemeanours could possibly be. He asked a whole lot of pointless questions, compiled a lengthy report and dismissed the charges out of hand. The joke spread as far as Saint- Germain.

Like queens they now walked slowly the entire length of La Grenouillère. They seemed happy to be in the limelight and delighted with the attention paid to them by all this riff- raff. Madeleine and her lover watched them, and as they approached the girl’s face lit up.

When the leading couple reached their table Madeleine cried ‘Pauline!’ and the big girl, turning round, stopped, still arm in arm with her midshipwoman.

‘Well good heavens! Madeleine! Darling! Come and join us for a bit. We must catch up!’

Paul tightened his grip on his girl’s wrist but she said, ‘You know what you can do, sweetheart, shove off.’

He kept quiet and let her be. Standing huddled together the women continued their animated conversation sotto voce. Pauline from time to time cast furtive glances at Paul and flashed him an evil, sardonic smile. Finally, unable to bear it a minute longer he suddenly stood up and trembling in every limb leapt towards her. He seized Madeleine by the shoulders and said: ‘Come with me, do you hear? I said you were not to speak to these beastly women!’

Raising her voice, Pauline began to swear at him like a fish wife. People around started laughing. Others stood on tip- toe to get a better look. Under the hail of filthy abuse he was speechless. Feeling contaminated by it and fearing there might be worse to come he retreated, retraced his steps and went to lean on the balustrade overlooking the river, turning his back on the three triumphant women. He stayed there looking at the water and every so often brusquely wiping away the tears that sprang to his eyes.

The fact was that despite himself, without knowing why or how it had happened and very much against his better judgement, he had fallen hopelessly in love. He had fallen as if into some deep and muddy hole. By nature he was a delicate and sensitive soul. He had had ideals and dreamed of an exquisite and passionate affair. And now he had fallen for this little cricket of a creature. She was as stupid as every other woman and not even pretty to make up for it. Skinny and foul- tempered, she had taken possession of him entirely from tip to toe, body and soul. He had fallen under the omnipotent and mysterious spell of the female. He was overwhelmed by this colossal force of unknown origin, the demon in the flesh capable of hurling the most rational man in the world at the feet of a worthless harlot. There was no way he could explain its fatal and total power.

Behind his back now he could feel something evil brewing. Their laughter pierced his heart. What should he do? He knew very well but had not the courage. He stared fixedly at the opposite bank where an angler was fishing, his line perfectly still. All of a sudden the man jerked out of the water a little silver fish which wriggled at the end of his line. Twisting and turning it this way and that he tried to extract his hook, but in vain. Losing patience he started pulling and, as he did so, tore out the entire bloody gullet of the fish with parts of its intestines attached. Paul shuddered, feeling himself equally torn apart. It seemed to him that the hook was like his own love and that if he were to tear it out he too would be gutted by a piece of curved wire hooked deep into his essential self at the end of a line held by Madeleine.

Feeling a hand on his shoulder he started and turned round. Madeleine was standing beside him. Neither spoke. She simply put her elbows on the balustrade beside him and leaned with him, staring out at the river. He tried to think of something to say but failed. He was incapable of analysing what was going on inside him. All he felt now was joy in the very nearness of her and a shameful cowardice on his own part. He wanted to forgive her, to let her do anything in the world she liked provided she never left him again.

After a while in a very gentle voice he asked, ‘Would you like to leave now? We’ll be better off in the boat.’

‘All right my pet,’ she said.

Awash with forgiveness and with tears still in his eyes he held her two hands tightly and helped her on board. Basking in the warmth of the afternoon they rowed upstream again past the willows and the grass- covered banks. When they reached Le Grillon once more it was not yet six, so, leaving their skiff, they set off on foot towards Bezons across the meadows and past the high poplars bordering the banks.

The wide hayfields waiting to be harvested were full of flowers. The sinking sun cast a mantle of russet light over all and in the gentle warmth of the day’s end the fragrance of the grass wafted in on them mingling with the damp smells of the river and filling the air with easy languor and an atmosphere of blessed well- being.

He felt soft and unresistant, in communion with the calm splendour of the evening and with the vague, mysterious thrill of life itself. He felt in tune with the all- embracing poetry of the moment in which plants and all that surrounded him revealed themselves to his senses at this lovely restful and reflective time of day. He was sensitive to it all but she appeared totally unaffected. They were walking side by side when suddenly, bored by the silence, she began to sing. In a squeaky, unmodulated voice she sang one of the catchy tunes of the day which jarred violently with the deeply serene mood of the evening. He looked at her and felt between them an unbridgeable abyss. She was swinging her parasol through the grass with her head down, looking at her feet as she sang, drawing out the notes and adding the odd little trill.

So behind the smooth little brow which he so much adored there was nothing! Absolutely nothing! Its sole concern at the moment was this caterwauling. The thoughts which from time to time passed through it were as vapid as the music. She had no understanding of him. They were as separate and distinct as if they had never met. His kisses had touched her lips only and nothing deeper within.

When, however, she raised her eyes to meet his and smiled, he felt himself melt. Opening his arms out wide to her in a surge of renewed love he clasped her passionately to him. Since he was crushing her dress as he did so, she eventually broke free saying consolingly, ‘Yes, yes, I love you, my pet, now that’s enough.’ In a mad rush of relief he grabbed her round the waist and started to run, dragging her with him. He kissed her on the cheeks, the temples and the neck, all the time dancing with joy. They threw themselves down at the edge of a thicket incandescent in the light of the setting sun. Even before catching their breath they came together. She could not understand the rapture he felt.

Walking back hand in hand they suddenly saw through the trees the river and on it the boat containing the four women. Big Pauline must have caught sight of them at the same time since she straightened up, blew kisses at Madeleine and shouted, ‘See you tonight!’

‘See you tonight!’ shouted Madeleine in reply.

Paul felt his heart turn suddenly to ice. They returned for dinner and settling down in one of the arbours at the side of the water they began to eat in silence. When darkness fell, a candle enclosed in a globe was brought which shed a feeble, glimmering light on the two. All the time they could hear bursts of laughter coming from the large room on the first floor where the boat- trippers were. The couple were just about to order dessert when Paul, taking Madeleine’s hand tenderly in his own, said: ‘Darling, I feel so tired. Shall we make an early night of it?’

But she saw through his little ploy and shot him an enigmatic glance, one of those treacherous looks that so often appear in women’s eyes. She thought for a second, then said,‘You’re perfectly welcome to go to bed if you like but I’ve promised to go to the dance at La Grenouillère.’

Attempting to mask his misery he gave her a pitiful smile and answered in a coaxing, wheedling tone: ‘Be a darling. Let’s both stay here. Please.’

She shook her head without saying a word. He tried again.‘Please, sweetheart . . .’

She cut him off. ‘You know what I said. If you’re not happy, you know where the door is. Nobody’s stopping you. But I’ve promised, and I’m going.’

He put his two elbows on the table, sank his head into his hands and sat brooding. The trippers were coming down the stairs, yelling as usual before setting off for the dance at La Grenouillère. Madeleine said to Paul: ‘Make up your mind. If you’re not coming I’ll ask one of these gentlemen to take me there.’

Paul rose. ‘Come on then,’ he muttered before they too set off. The night was dark and the sky full of stars. Around them the air was still hot and the atmosphere heavy with seething, unseen activity. The warm breeze caressed their faces, its hot breath stifling their own and making them gasp slightly. The skiffs set off, each with a Venetian lantern in the prow. It was too dark to see anything of the boats themselves except for the little patches of colour in the night bobbing and dancing like frenzied glow- worms. Voices sounded from the shadows on all sides as the young couple’s skiff glided gently along. Sometimes when another overtook they would catch the flash of the oarsman’s white- jerseyed back illuminated by his lantern. As they came round the bend of the river, La Grenouillère came into sight in the distance.

In gala mood, the place was decorated with bunting and with strings, clusters and garlands of fairy lights. On the surface of the Seine large barges moved slowly about, representing domes, pyramids and all kinds of monuments picked out in variously coloured lights. Illuminated festoons hung down as far as the water itself, and here and there an enormous red or blue lantern suspended from an invisible rod hung like a huge star in the sky.

All these illuminations shone on the café and floodlit the great trees on the bank whose trunks stood out pale grey and whose leaves were milky green against the deep, pitch black of the fields and of the sky. A band consisting of five local players blared shrill, syncopated music across the water and, hearing it, Madeleine began to sing along. She wanted to go in right away. Paul would have preferred to make a tour of the island first but had to give in. The clientèle had thinned out a little by this time, still consisting mostly of boatmen with the odd sprinkling of middle- class couples and a few young men flanked by girls. The director and organizer of the can- can strutted in his faded black suit and cast round the audience the world- weary, professional eye of a cheap music- hall master of ceremonies. Paul was relieved to see that Big Pauline and her chums were nowhere to be seen.

People were dancing. Couples faced each other and capered about madly, kicking their legs as high as their partners’ noses. The women, who appeared to have double- jointed legs and hips, leapt about in a frou- frou of lifted skirts, flashing their knickers and kicking their legs up over their heads with amazing agility. They wriggled their bellies and shook their bosoms, spreading about them the powerful smell of female flesh in sweat. The males squatted like toads in front of them making faces and obscene gestures. They cavorted and turned cartwheels, posturing meanwhile in hideous parody, as one strapping maid and two waiters served the audience drinks.

Since the café- boat was covered by a roof only and had no side walls to separate it from the outdoors, the whole rumbustious dance was performed against the backdrop of the peaceful night and a firmament dusted with stars. Suddenly Mont- Valérien in the distance lit up as if a fire had started behind it. The glow deepened and spread, describing a wide, luminous circle of pale light. Then a ruby- coloured shape appeared, grew large, and glowed like red- hot metal. The circle widened further still and seemed to be emerging from the earth itself, as the moon, breaking free of the horizon, sailed gently upwards into space. As it rose, its crimson glow dimmed and turned to an increasingly light then bright yellow. As the planet climbed higher it grew smaller and smaller still in the distance.

Paul, lost in long contemplation of this sight, had become oblivious of his girl. When he turned round she had disappeared from view. He looked for her in vain. Having searched anxiously and systematically up and down the rows of tables he started asking people. No one had seen her. He then began to wander about wretchedly until one of the waiters said: ‘If you’re looking for Madame Madeleine, she went off a little while ago with Madame Pauline.’

Simultaneously, he caught sight of the midshipwoman and the two beautiful girls sitting at the opposite end of the café, arms round each other’s waists, watching him and whispering. Realizing what had happened, he ran off like a madman towards the island. Chasing first in the direction of Chatou, he stopped at the edge of the plain, turned and retraced his steps. He began to search the dense coppices, wandering about aimlessly and stopping every so often to listen. All he could hear around him was the short, metallic croak of frogs. Towards Bougival an unfamiliar bird sang a song which reached him faintly from a distance. Over the broad fields the moon shed a soft, filmy light. It filtered through the foliage, silvering the barks of the poplars and casting a shower of brilliant moonbeams on the shimmering tops of the tallest trees. Despite himself Paul was enchanted by the intoxicating loveliness of the night. It penetrated the terrible anguish he was feeling and stirred in his heart a fierce sense of irony. He longed with all his gentle and idealistic soul for a faithful woman to worship – someone in whose arms he could express all his love and tenderness as well as his passion.

Choked by racking sobs, he had to stop in his tracks. Having recovered a little he went on, only to feel a sudden stab in his heart. There, behind that bush . . . a pair of lovers! He ran forward and saw their silhouettes united in a seemingly endless kiss before they quickly ran off at his approach. He dared not call out, knowing full well that his own girl would not respond. He was desperately afraid now of coming upon them all of a sudden. The music of the quadrilles with its piercing solo cornets, the mock gaiety of the flute and the scraping of the fiddles pulled at his own heartstrings and deepened the pain he continued to feel.

Suddenly it occurred to him that she might have gone back in! Yes, that was it! She must have returned. He had lost all sense of proportion, he was stupid, he had been carried away by all the silly suspicions and fears that always haunted him. In one of those periods of strange calm which occur during periods of the blackest despair he turned and began to make for the café again.

He took in the whole room at a single glance. She was not there. He checked all the tables, and once again came face to face with the three women. He must have looked the picture of dejection for the three burst out laughing. Rushing out again, he ran back to the island. He threw himself into the coppices and stopped to listen once more. It was some time before he could hear anything save the roaring in his own ears. Finally, however, he thought he could hear some way ahead a shrill little laugh he knew only too well. Creeping forward he fell to his knees and crawled on, parting the branches cautiously as he went. His heart was beating so wildly in his chest that he could hardly breathe. Two voices were murmuring. He could not make out what they were saying. Then they fell silent again.

He had a sudden furious desire to run away, not to see, not to know and to keep on running to escape from the raging passion with which he was consumed. He would return to Chatou, catch a train and never come back. He would never see her again. Just as suddenly her face appeared in his mind’s eye. He saw her as she was waking up next to him in their warm bed. He saw her snuggle up to him and throw her arms round his neck. Her hair was loose and a little tangled over her brow. Her eyes were still closed and her lips parted, waiting for the first kiss of the day. The thought of this morning’s embrace filled him with unbearable regret and frantic desire.

They were talking again. He approached bent double. Then a cry rose from under the branches close to him. That cry! It was one of those he had come to know from their most tender, their most passionate love- making. He crept even closer, drawn irresistibly, blindly, despite himself . . . and then he saw them.

Oh! If only the other person had been a man! But this! He was transfixed by the loathsome sight before him. He remained there overwhelmed by shock. It was as though he had just stumbled upon the mutilated body of a loved one. It was a crime against nature, a monstrous and wicked desecration. Suddenly flashing into his mind’s eye this time came the image of the little fish whose entrails he had earlier seen ripped out. Madeleine was moaning ‘Pauline’, exactly as she used to moan ‘Paul’ to him. Hearing it, he felt such pain that he turned and fled. He hurtled into one tree and ricocheted into another, fell over a root, picked himself up and ran again until suddenly he found himself at the edge of the river. The raging torrent made whirls and eddies on which the moonbeams now played. On the opposite side the bank loomed over the water like a cliff, leaving a wide band of black at its foot from which the sound of the swirling water rose in the darkness. Clearly visible on the other side were the weekend homes at Croissy.

Paul saw all this as if in a dream or as something remembered. He was no longer thinking. He understood nothing now. Everything including his own existence seemed vague, distant, forgotten and finished. There was the river. Did he know what he was doing? Did he want to die? He had lost his mind. Nevertheless he turned round to face the island where she was. Into the night in which the faint but persistent beat of the dance- band still throbbed back and forth, he shouted, ‘Madeleine!’

His heart- rending call pierced the great silence of the sky and echoed, lost in the distance. Then with a furious animal- like leap he plunged into the river. The water splashed then closed over the spot setting up a series of ever- widening circles which rippled in the moonlight as far as the opposite bank. The two women had heard. Madeleine got up and said,‘That’s Paul.’ A suspicion arose suddenly in her mind. ‘He’s drowned himself,’ she said and rushed towards the bank where Pauline caught up with her.

A heavy punt with two men in it was circling over and over around the same spot. One of the men rowed while the other was plunging a long pole into the water evidently looking for something. Pauline shouted: ‘What’s happened? What are you doing?’

A stranger’s voice cried: ‘A man’s just drowned himself.’

With haggard faces the two women huddled together and watched the boat’s manoeuvres. The music from La Grenouillère pounding in the distance provided a grim counterpoint to the movements of the solemn fishermen. The river, now containing a corpse in its depths, continued to swirl in the moonlight. The search was prolonged and Madeleine, waiting in horrible suspense, shivered. Finally, after a good half- hour, one of the men announced: ‘I’ve got him!’

Very gradually he pulled in the boathook. A large mass appeared at the surface of the water. The other boatman left his oars and between the two, each heaving with all his strength, they managed to haul the inert body and bring it tumbling into the boat. They soon reached the bank and found an open, flat space in the moonlight. As they landed, the women approached.

As soon as she saw him Madeleine recoiled in horror. In the light of the moon’s rays he looked green already and his mouth, his eyes, his nose and his clothes were full of the river’s slime. The stiff fingers of his clenched fist looked hideous. Black, liquid silt covered his entire body. The face looked swollen and from his hair now plastered down with ooze a stream of filthy water ran. The two men examined him.

‘You know him?’ asked one.

The other, the Croissy ferryman, hesitated.

‘Seems to me I know the face . . .,’ he said, ‘but it’s difficult to tell seeing him like this . . .’

Then suddenly: ‘Oh! I know! It’s Monsieur Paul!’

‘Who’s Monsieur Paul?’ his friend asked.

The first went on: ‘You know! Monsieur Paul Baron. Son of that senator. The kid who was so hooked on that girl, you remember?’

The other added philosophically: ‘No more girls for him now, eh? Poor sod. And with all that money too!’

Madeleine, having collapsed on the ground, was sobbing. Pauline approached the body and said, ‘I suppose he really is dead . . . there’s no chance he might . . . ?’

The men shrugged their shoulders.

‘After that length of time no question.’

Then one of them asked: ‘Was he staying at Le Grillon?’

‘Yes,’ said the other. ‘We’d better take him back there. Handsome tip, mate.’ Re- embarking they set off, moving slowly against the rapid current. Long after they had disappeared from the two women’s sight the regular sound of their oars could still be heard.

Pauline took poor, weeping Madeleine in her arms, kissed and rocked her for a long time and then said: ‘Now look. As long as you know it’s not your fault. You can’t stop men doing stupid things. It was his decision so it’s just too bad, that’s all.’

Then lifting her to her feet, she added, ‘Come on darling! Come and sleep at the house. You can’t go back to Le Grillon tonight.’ She kissed her again. ‘Come on, you’ll feel better with us,’ she said.

Madeleine got up, still sobbing, but less violently. She leaned her head on Pauline’s shoulder. Seeming to find there a safer, warmer refuge and a closer, more intimate affection, she walked slowly away from the scene.

Hautot ＆ Son

The house, half farm and half manor, was one of those combinations often found in the country of a property once vaguely seigneurial and now owned by farmers themselves rich in land. In front of it the dogs tied to the farmyard apple trees were barking and yelping as the keeper and some small boys arrived carrying gamebags.

It was the opening day of the season and in the vast kitchen which served as dining room Hautot senior, Hautot junior, Monsieur Bermont the tax- collector and Monsieur Mondaru the lawyer were having a drink and a bite to eat before setting off on the day’s shoot. Hautot senior, very proud of his property, was telling his guests ahead of time what excellent game they would find on his land. He was a big- boned, ruddy- faced Norman, the powerfully built sort of man who can carry a whole barrel of apples on his shoulders. Somewhat authoritarian in manner, he was wealthy, respected and highly influential. He had sent his son César to school up to the fourth form so that he should have some education, then removed him lest he become so much of a gentleman that he no longer cared about his land.

César Hautot was nearly as tall as his father, but leaner. He was an easy- going, happy- go- lucky young man, a good son to his father whom he greatly admired and to whose every wish and opinion he was happy to defer.

Monsieur Bermont, the tax- collector, was a stout little man on whose red cheeks a maze of violet- coloured veins looked like a network of tortuous rivers and tributaries as might be seen on maps in an atlas. He asked, ‘And hare? Will there be . . . hare?’

Hautot senior replied, ‘As much as you like! Specially round Puysatier.’

‘Where shall we start?’ enquired the lawyer, a portly, well- fed man trussed up now in a new shooting jacket bought the previous week in Rouen.

‘Down at the bottom, I think. We’ll get the partridge out on the plain and then put them up from there.’

With this, Hautot senior rose. Following suit they all stood up and stamped their feet to bring warmth and suppleness to the leather of their newly- donned and tight- fitting boots. They collected the guns propped up in various corners of the room, examined the locks, then left the house. Outside, the dogs, still leashed, were now jumping up on their hind legs, yelping shrilly and pawing the air.

They set off towards the lower grounds and a small valley which was no more than a dip of poor- quality land left purposely uncultivated. It was criss- crossed with gullies and covered with fern – an excellent place for game. The guns spread out, with Hautot senior on the far right, Hautot junior on the far left and the two guests in the middle. The keeper and two gamebag carriers followed. Nervously fingering their triggers and with their hearts beating fast they stopped and stood waiting in solemn silence for the first shot of the season to ring out.

There it was! Hautot senior had fired. They saw one partridge fall away from the headlong flight of birds and come down in a gully covered with thick brush. Highly excited, Hautot leapt up and ran off, tearing up everything in his way and finally disappearing into the undergrowth to pick up his quarry. Almost immediately a second shot rang out.

‘The lucky devil!’ cried old Bermont. ‘He’s picked off a hare while he’s at it!’

They all waited, eyes fixed on the dense, impenetrable under growth. Cupping his hands round his mouth, the lawyer yelled: ‘Have you got them?’

Since no answer came from Hautot senior, César, turning to the keeper, said: ‘Go and give him a hand, Joseph, will you? We must spread out in line. We’ll wait for you.’

Joseph, a great gnarled tree- trunk of a man, set off calmly down towards the gully. Like a fox he carefully reconnoitred the easiest way through the brush. Having found it and disappeared, he cried out suddenly: ‘Come quick! Quick! There’s been an accident!’

Each man tore through the bushes towards the scene. When they got there they saw Hautot lying on his side, unconscious, clasping his stomach from which long streams of blood were flowing inside his bullet- torn jacket and into the grass. His fallen partridge within reach, Hautot must have dropped the gun to pick it up and in so doing triggered a second shot which shattered his own entrails. They dragged him from the ditch and on removing some of his clothing found a terrible wound now spilling out his intestines. They ligatured him as best they could and carried him home where the doctor they had sent for was waiting, along with a priest.

When the doctor saw him he shook his head gravely, and turning to Hautot’s son who was sobbing in a chair, said,‘My poor boy, I’m afraid it doesn’t look at all good.’

But when a dressing had been applied, the injured man moved his fingers, opened his mouth, then a pair of haggard eyes, and cast a few anxious glances around him. He seemed to be searching his mind for something and then, when the whole sequence of events came flooding back, murmured:‘Christ almighty! I’ve had it now.’

The doctor took his hand.

‘No! Certainly not! All you need is a few days’ rest and you’ll be absolutely fine.’

Hautot went on: ‘No, I know the score. Shattered stomach. I’ve had it.’

Then suddenly: ‘I want to talk to my son if I’ve got time.’

Young Hautot whimpered like a little boy: ‘Papa! Papa! Oh, poor Papa!’

In a firmer tone his father said: ‘Listen, stop crying. Doesn’t help. I’ve got to talk to you. Come close, it’ll only take a minute. Then I’ll feel much better. You lot, can we have a minute or two if you don’t mind?’

The others went out of the room, leaving father and son together. As soon as they were alone the father spoke:‘Listen, my boy, you’re twenty- four, I can tell you everything now. Not that there’s much to tell. Anyway you know when your mother died seven years ago I was . . . well I’m forty- five now. I was married at nineteen by the way, right?’

‘Yes I know.’

‘So when she died she left me a widower at thirty- seven. Can you imagine? Chap like me. Can’t be a permanent widower at thirty- seven, can you my boy?’

‘No father, of course not.’

The father’s face was pale and contorted with pain.

‘God, I’m in agony here. Anyway, to continue. A chap can’t live entirely on his own yet I couldn’t remarry. I’d promised your mum. So . . . are you following?’

‘Yes father.’

‘So. I took up with this girl in Rouen. Rue de l’Éperlan, number 18, third floor, second door. You are taking all this in I hope? This girl, she’s been so good to me, you know. I couldn’t have wished for a sweeter little wife. Loving, devoted, you get the picture my boy?’

‘Yes father.’

‘Well, anyway, if I should pop off I reckon I owe her. A lot. Enough to set her up. You understand?’

‘Yes, father.’

‘When I say she’s a good kid, I mean really good. If it hadn’t been for you, and out of respect for your mother’s memory, if it hadn’t been for this house, and us having lived here, the three of us, I’d have brought her home here and married her, no question. Listen, listen, my boy. I could have made a will but I didn’t. Didn’t want to. Never put things down in writing. Not that sort of thing anyway. Upsets the family. Makes everything too complicated. Everybody at each other’s throats. Who needs legal documents? Don’t ever use them. That’s how I’ve made my money, such as it is. Understand, my boy?’

‘Yes, father.’

‘Listen again, carefully. So I haven’t made a will. Didn’t need to. Because I know you. You’ve got a good heart, you’re not . . . careful . . . tight- fisted, you know what I mean? So I thought when the end came I’d just tell you how things stood and I’d ask you not to forget the girl: Caroline Donet, rue de l’Éperlan, number 18, third floor, second door, don’t forget. Listen again. Go straight there when I’ve gone . . . and make sure she’s seen all right by me. You’ll have plenty. You can do it. I’m leaving you enough. Listen. She won’t be there most of the week, she works for Madame Moreau, rue Beauvoisine. But go on Thursday. That’s when she expects me. That’s my day, has been for six years now. Oh the poor girl! She’s going to be so upset! I’m telling you all this because I know you, my boy. Not the sort of thing you tell everybody. Not the lawyer and not the curé. It happens, everybody knows that, but you don’t discuss it. Not unless you have to. So, no strangers in on it. Just the family that’s all. You understand?’

‘Yes father.’

‘Promise?’

‘Yes father.’

‘Swear?’

‘Yes, father.’

‘I beg of you, my boy, please. Please don’t forget. You mustn’t.’

‘I won’t father.’

‘Go in person. You’re in charge of everything.’

‘Yes, father.’

‘Then you’ll see what she says. I can’t talk any more. Swear to me.’

‘Yes father.’

‘That’s good, my boy. Come and give me a kiss goodbye. I’m nearly finished. This is it. Tell them they can come in.’

Moaning, the younger Hautot kissed his father and, obedient as always, opened the door. The priest appeared wearing a white surplice and carrying the holy oils. But the dying man had closed his eyes and refused to open them again. He refused to reply and refused to give any sign that he knew what was going on.

He had talked enough and could not say another word. Besides, he felt relieved now. He could die in peace. What need was there for him to confess to this delegate of God since he had already confessed to his own son who really was family?

The last rites were administered, and he was given communion in the midst of his kneeling friends and servants with never a movement of his face to indicate that he was still alive. He died at around midnight after four hours of spasms indicative of appalling pain.

The season had opened on the Sunday and Hautot was buried the following Tuesday. Having returned from taking his father to the cemetery, César Hautot spent the rest of the day in tears. He hardly slept that night and was so miserable the next day that he wondered how he could carry on living. Nevertheless he spent the whole day thinking that, if his father’s last wish was to be carried out, he should go to Rouen the following day and see this Caroline Donet at the rue de l’Éperlan, number 18, third floor, second door. He had repeated this like a mantra so many times so as not to forget it, that now he could think of little else. Both his mind and his ear were hypnotized by the phrase. Accordingly, the next morning around eight o’clock, having ordered Graindorge harnessed to the tilbury, he set off at a brisk pace behind the heavy Norman horse on the main road from Ainville to Rouen. He was wearing his black frock- coat, a tall silk topper and his trousers with the straps under the soles. In the circumstances he decided not to wear over his handsome suit the loose blue smock which, flapping in the wind, protected his better clothes against any dust or spots and which he normally shed as soon as he jumped down on arriving at his destination.

He got to Rouen just as ten o’clock was striking and went as usual to the Hôtel des Bons- Enfants, rue des Trois Mares. There he was embraced by the proprietor, the proprietor’s wife and their five sons, all of whom had heard the sad news. After that he had to tell them exactly how the accident had happened and this set him off crying again. He turned down their offers of comfort, all the more insistent now that he was a man of substance, and even refused their invitation to dinner, which really offended them.

Having dusted off his hat, brushed down his frock- coat and given his boots a quick wipe, he set out to find the rue de l’Éperlan. He dared not ask for directions lest he be recognized and suspicions raised. Finally drawing a complete blank, he spotted a priest and counting on the professional discretion of a clergyman found out from him the way to the address. It was very close. In the next street on the right in fact.

He began to feel a little hesitant. Until this moment he had been blindly following his dead father’s instructions. Now he felt a confusing mixture of sorrow and shame as he thought of himself, a son, soon to be face to face with the woman who had been his father’s mistress. All the old moral strictures lying buried in his unconscious under layer after layer of conventional, received wisdom handed down from generation to generation, everything he had learned from his catechism years and since about loose women and the instinctive mistrust men have of them even if they marry one – all these ignorant, peasant values clamoured inside him, held him back and brought a blush of shame to his cheeks.

Nevertheless, he thought, I promised my father. Mustn’t let him down. The door marked 18 was ajar so he pushed it open and saw beyond it a dark stairway which he climbed as far as the third floor. There he saw first one door, then a second with a bell- pull which he now tugged. The tinkle which he heard echo into the room beyond made his heart sink. The door was opened and he found himself standing opposite a very well- dressed, fresh- faced brunette who was staring at him in astonishment.

He had no idea what to say and she, unaware of anything untoward and expecting his father any minute, did not invite him in. They looked at each other for a full thirty seconds, at the end of which she said: ‘Can I help you, monsieur?’

He murmured, ‘I’m Hautot, the son.’

She started, turned pale and stammered as if she had known him all her life: ‘Oh! Monsieur César?’

‘Yes.’

‘What . . . what’s . . . ?’

‘I have a message for you from my father.’

She said, ‘Oh my God!’ and took a step backwards to let him in. He then saw a little boy playing with a cat on the floor in front of a stove where several dishes were cooking.

‘Sit down,’ she said.

He sat down.

‘Well?’ she asked.

He was struck dumb, his eyes on the table in the middle of the room laid for three including a child. He looked at the chair with its back to the fire, the plate, the napkin, the glasses, one bottle of red wine, already drunk from, and one unopened bottle of white. That must be his father’s usual place with his back to the fire! He was still expected by her! That would have been his father’s bread with all the crust removed because of his poor teeth. Raising his eyes, he saw hanging on the wall a large photograph of his father taken at the Paris Exhibition, the duplicate of one which hung over the bed in the master bedroom at Ainville.

The young woman went on: ‘So? Monsieur César?’

He looked at her. She was pale with dread and her hands were trembling fearfully as she waited for him to speak. Eventually he gathered up enough courage to do so. ‘Well Mam’zelle, I’m afraid Papa died on Sunday on the opening day of the shooting season.’

She was shocked literally rigid. After a few moments’silence she said in a barely audible voice, ‘Oh no! He can’t have!’

Then suddenly her eyes filled with tears. She raised her hands to cover her face and began to sob. The little boy, seeing his mother burst into tears and deducing that this stranger was the cause, hurled himself on César, grabbed him by the trouser- leg with one hand and started smacking him on the thigh as hard as he could with the other. César, frantic with grief himself, his own eyes still swollen with crying, was moved at the sight of this woman weeping for his father and the little boy defending the mother. He felt almost overwhelmed with emotion and, in order to keep from breaking down himself, started to speak: ‘Yes,’ he said,‘the tragedy occurred on Sunday morning at eight o’clock . . .’

He went on, assuming she was hearing it all and forgetting no detail, omitting not the smallest incident in a painstaking, plodding peasant way. The little boy continued to smack him and had now begun to kick him on the ankles. When Hautot junior came to the part where Hautot senior had talked about her, the young woman, hearing her own name, uncovered her face and asked: ‘I’m sorry. Could you start again please? I wasn’t taking it in . . . I really want to know what happened . . .’

He began again, using exactly the same words: ‘The tragedy occurred on Sunday morning at eight o’clock . . .’

Again he told her everything, stopping every now and then to punctuate the story with little asides of his own. She listened attentively. With the sensitive perception of a woman, she seized every implication of each twist and turn of events, shuddering with horror and saying ‘Oh my God’ from time to time. The little boy, seeing his mother had calmed down, stopped hitting César and was now holding her hand, listening too as if he understood every word. When he came to the end Hautot junior said: ‘And now what we must do is make sure his wishes are carried out. I’m in a comfortable position. He’s left me property so . . . I wouldn’t want you to feel in any need . . .’

She broke in abruptly: ‘Oh, please, please, Monsieur César! Not today! My heart’s breaking! Another time, another day, perhaps. But not today. And if I were to accept, I do want you to know it would not be for me, oh no, no, no, I swear I wouldn’t want anything for myself but for the little one. We’ll put any money in his name.’

César was aghast. Then the penny dropped. He stammered, ‘You mean . . . he’s his?’

‘Oh yes,’ she said.

Hautot junior looked at his half- brother with a mixture of emotions, all deeply painful. After a long silence, for she had begun to weep again, César was at a complete loss as to what to do. He said: ‘Well then, Mam’zelle Donet, I’d better be going. When would you like us to meet and talk about arrangements?’

She cried out: ‘Oh don’t go! Please! Please don’t leave me and Émile on our own. I’d die of grief. I’ve got nobody now except my little boy. Oh it’s awful, Monsieur César, it’s terrible! Please, please sit down! Talk to me some more. Tell me about what he used to do when he was away from here, when he was back home with you.’

And so César, obedient as always, sat down again. She drew her chair up close to his in front of the stove where the food was still cooking. She put Émile on her lap and asked César hundreds of little intimate questions about his father from which he could see or rather feel instinctively that this poor young woman had loved Hautot with all her heart.

The conversation naturally kept returning to the accident and he told her all over again what had happened, in the same detail. When he said, ‘The hole in his stomach was so big you could have put both hands in it’, she gave a sort of cry and began sobbing yet again. This time César too broke down with her and started to weep. Softened by his own tears he leaned down towards Émile whose forehead was within reach and kissed it. His mother struggled to get her breath back.

‘Poor little mite,’ she said, ‘he’s fatherless now.’

‘Me too,’ said César.

At this, each stopped talking. Suddenly the young woman became the practical housewife who thinks of everything and everyone.

‘I don’t suppose you’ve eaten a thing all morning, have you, Monsieur César?’

‘No, Mam’zelle.’

‘Oh, you must be hungry! Will you have something to eat?’

‘No thank you,’ he said, ‘I’m not hungry. Too upset.’

‘Oh, but you’ve got to eat in spite of everything, you’ll grant me that. Do stay a bit longer. I don’t know what I’ll do when you leave.’

After a few attempts at resistance, he sat down opposite her, and in the chair with its back to the fire he settled down to a dish of the tripe that had been sizzling in the oven, and to a glass of red wine. Several times he wiped the mouth of the little boy who had dribbled sauce all over his chin. As he rose to leave, he said: ‘When would you like me to come back and talk business, Mam’zelle Donet?’

‘If it’s all the same to you, Monsieur César, next Thursday. It’ll save me taking time off. I’ve always got Thursday off anyway.’

‘That’s fine with me. Next Thursday.’

‘You’ll have lunch, won’t you?’

‘Oh, I don’t know . . . really.’

‘It’s much easier to talk over a meal. Saves time too.’

‘All right then. Let’s say twelve o’clock.’

After giving little Émile another kiss and shaking Mademoiselle Donet’s hand he left.

The week passed very slowly for César Hautot. He had never been on his own before and solitude seemed unbearable to him. Until then, he had shadowed his father all his life, following him into the fields, seeing that his orders were carried out, then, after a little while apart, he would see him again at dinner. In the evenings they would sit opposite each other smoking their pipes and talking about horses, cows and sheep. Their morning handshake was an expression of deep family attachment.

And now César was alone. He wandered about in the ploughed fields of autumn, all the time expecting to see the tall silhouette of his father waving to him from some field or other. To kill time he would drop in on neighbours, describe the accident to anyone who had not heard what had happened, and retell the story to those who had. Sometimes when he had run out of things that needed thinking about or doing he would sit down at the side of a cart track and wonder how much longer he could carry on.

He thought often of Mademoiselle Donet. He had liked her very much. He thought she was a very nice person indeed, a good, kind girl as his father had said. Yes, she was a lovely girl. A really lovely girl. He was determined to do her proud and to give her 2,000 francs in interest on capital to be settled on the child. He was rather pleased that he had to go and see her the following Thursday to sort things out with her. The thought of this brother, this new little fellow was a bit of a worry. It bothered him a little, yet at the same time it gave him a warm sort of feeling. There was a bit of kin for him there. The kid born on the other side of the blanket would never be called Hautot, but he was a bit of family with no pressure attached, a bit of his father after all.

When he found himself once more on the way to Rouen on Thursday morning, with these and similar thoughts in his head and the sound of Graindorge’s rhythmical clip- clop, his heart was lighter and his mind calmer than at any time since the accident. As he entered Mademoiselle Donet’s apartment he saw that everything was laid exactly as it had been the previous Thursday with one single exception – the crust of the bread at his place had not been removed.

He shook hands with the young woman, kissed Émile on both cheeks and sat down feeling both very much at home and extremely emotional. Mademoiselle Donet seemed slightly thinner and slightly paler. She must have cried her little heart out. This time she was a bit awkward in her manner towards him as if she had realized something she had been unable to absorb on that first occasion when she was still taking in the enormity of what had happened. She was extremely attentive to his needs and humble in her approach, as if trying to pay back in devotion and service towards him some of the generosity he was showing her. They took a long time over lunch and discussed the business which had brought him there. She did not want so much money. It was too much, far too much. She earned enough to keep herself; all she wanted was that Émile might have something to look forward to when he reached his majority. César, however, stuck to his guns and even added a present for herself as a token of mourning. As he finished his coffee, she asked, ‘Do you smoke?’

‘Yes, I’ve got my pipe here . . .,’ he began.

He patted his pockets. Damnation. He had left it at home! He was just about to bemoan the fact when she produced one belonging to his father which she had kept tucked away in a cupboard. He took it from her and recognized it. Sniffing it and with emotion in his voice, declaring it to be one of the best, he filled and lit it. Then he put Émile on his knee and played ride- a- cock- horse with him while she cleared the table, stacking the dirty dishes in the sideboard to wash later after he had gone.

At about three, when he rose regretfully, he hated the idea of leaving.

‘Well, Mamz’elle Donet,’ he said, ‘I’ll wish you a very good afternoon. I’m delighted to have made your acquaintance like this.’

She remained standing in front of him, blushing and near to tears. As she looked at him she thought of his father.

‘Are we not to see each other again then?’ she asked.

He replied simply: ‘We can, Mam’zelle, if that’s what you’d like.’

‘It most certainly is, Monsieur César. Shall we say next Thursday, if that’s convenient for you?’

‘Indeed it is, Mam’zelle Donet.’

‘You’ll come for lunch, of course?’

‘Well, if you’re offering I wouldn’t say no.’

‘Very well, Monsieur César. Thursday next it is, at twelve o’clock, like today.’

‘Twelve o’clock on Thursday then, Mam’zelle Donet!’

Laid to Rest

Five friends had been dining together. They were all rich, middle- aged men of the world, two of them bachelors, three married men. These monthly meetings of theirs were some of the happiest evenings of their lives. They had all known each other since their youth, remained close friends, enjoyed one another’s company and often stayed talking till two o’clock in the morning. The conversation was about anything and everything that might interest or amuse a Parisian and, as in most drawing rooms, it was a kind of verbal version of the news in the morning papers.

One of the most footloose and fancy- free among them was Joseph de Bardon, a bachelor who exploited to the full all the attractions Paris has to offer. Though not exactly decadent or debauched in his habits, he managed to satisfy all the natural curiosity of a fun- loving man in his late thirties. A man of the world in the best and widest sense of the word, he was witty rather than profound, knowledgeable rather than wise and possessed a quick rather than a deep understanding of human nature. His experiences and encounters provided him with a fund of anecdotes, some edifying, some frankly hilarious. He had a reputation in society as a bright fellow with a good sense of humour – everyone’s favourite after- dinner speaker whose tales were always the ones most looked forward to. He never needed any urging to begin, as he did on this occasion.

Certain creatures at certain times and places look absolutely in their element, let’s say a goldfish in its bowl, a nun in church, or what have you. Sitting there smoking a cigar, with his elbows on the table, a half- filled glass of liqueur brandy to hand and relaxing in a warm haze of coffee and tobacco, he looked like a man in his ideal milieu. Between a couple of puffs he spoke.

‘The funniest thing happened to me not so long ago . . .’

A near- instantaneous chorus replied, ‘Go on, do!’

And he was off.

‘Thank you, I shall. You know I get around Paris a fair amount. As other people window- shop, I watch what’s going on. I watch the world and his brother pass by, I watch what’s going on around me. Well, some time towards the middle of last September, I left the house one afternoon with no clear idea of where I was going. You know how you always have a vague yen to go and see some pretty woman or other . . . you riffle through your little black book, you do a few mental comparisons, you weigh up the possible delights and you decide more or less on the spur of the moment. But when the sun’s shining and it’s warm outside you don’t always want to be cooped up indoors. On this particular day, it was warm and sunny and I lit a cigar before starting to stroll along the outer boulevard. As I was sauntering along I decided to make for the cemetery in Montmartre and have a little wander about there. I like cemeteries, you know. They sadden and they soothe me and I find I need that from time to time. And of course some of one’s chums are there, people nobody goes to see any more. I drop by every so often still. And as it happens, an old flame of mine is buried in Montmatre Cemetery, a lovely little lady I was very keen on at one point in my life, very attached to. So although it’s painful, I find it does me good. I mean all kinds of memories come flooding back while I’m there, letting my thoughts drift beside her grave. It’s all over for her of course . . .

‘The other reason I like cemeteries is because they’re like cities in themselves, densely populated at that. Just think how many generations of Parisians are packed in there for ever; so many people stuck in their caves, their little holes just covered with a stone or marked with a cross, while the living take up so much room and make such a stupid racket.

‘Then of course you’ve got all the monuments, some of them much more interesting than in a museum. Though I wouldn’t put them in the same league, Cavaignac’s grave reminded me so much of that masterpiece by Jean Goujon, the statue of Louis de Brézé in the underground chapel at Rouen cathedral. That’s actually the root of all so- called modern, realist art, you know. That statue of the dead Louis de Brézé is more convincing, more terrible and more suggestive of inanimate flesh still convulsed in the death- agony than any of the tortured corpses you see sculpted these days on people’s tombs.

‘But in Montmartre Cemetery you can still admire the impressive monument to Baudin, the one to Gautier, and that to Murger, on which incidentally, only the other day I spotted one poor solitary wreath of helichrysums. I wonder who put that there. Perhaps the last of the grisettes, now a very old woman and possibly one of the local concierges. It’s a pretty little statue by Millet, suffering badly from neglect and all the accumulated dirt of the years. Oh for the joys of youth, eh, Murger?

‘Anyway there I was, stepping into Montmartre Cemetery, suddenly filled with sadness of a not entirely disagreeable kind, the sort that makes a healthy fellow think “Not the most cheerful of spots, but thank God I’m not stuck in here just yet.” The feeling of autumn, the warm dampness of dead leaves in pale, weak sunshine heightened and romanticized the sense of solitude and finality surrounding this place of the dead.

‘I wandered slowly along the streets of graves where neighbours no longer call, no longer sleep together and never hear the news. Then I started reading the epitaphs. I tell you gentlemen, they are absolutely killing. Not even Labiche or Meilhac can give me more of a laugh than the language of the headstone. When you read what the nearest and dearest have put on the marble slabs and crosses, pouring out their grief and their best wishes for the happiness of the departed in the next world, and their hopes – the liars! – for a speedy reunion, it’s hilarious! Better than a Paul de Kock any day!

‘But what I love most in that cemetery is the deserted, lonely part planted with all those tall yews and cypresses, the old district where those who died long ago now lie. Soon it will become the new part of town; the green trees nourished by human corpses will be felled to make room for the recently departed to be lined up in turn under their own little marble slabs.

‘After I had wandered about long enough to refresh my mind, I realized I was now getting a little bored and that it was time to go to the last resting place of my old love and pay her my ever- faithful respects. By the time I reached her graveside I was feeling quite upset. Poor darling, she was so sweet, so loving, so fair and rosy . . . and now . . . if this spot were ever opened up . . . Leaning on the iron railings I whispered to her a few sad words which I dare say she is unlikely to have heard. I was just about to leave when I saw a woman in deep mourning on her knees at the next graveside. She had lifted her crêpe veil and under it could be seen a pretty head of fair hair, a crown of bright dawn under the dark night of her head- dress. I lingered. In what was obviously deep distress she had buried her face in her hands and, stiff as a statue, was deep in meditation. Absorbed by her grief and telling the painful beads of memory behind closed and hidden eyes, she seemed herself dead to the world in her loss. Suddenly I saw that she was about to break down. I could tell from the slight movement her back made, like a willow stirring in the wind. She wept gently at first then more and more violently with her neck and shoulders shaking hard and rapidly. All of a sudden she uncovered her eyes. Full of tears they were lovely. She looked wildly about her as if waking from a nightmare. She saw me looking at her, seemed ashamed and buried her whole face once more in her hands. Then she burst into convulsive sobs and her head bent slowly down towards the marble slab. She rested her forehead on it and her veil, spreading about her, covered the white corners of her beloved sepulchre like a new mourning- cloth. I heard her moan before she collapsed with her cheek against the tombstone and lay there motionless and unconscious.

‘I rushed over to her, slapped her hands and breathed on her eyelids while reading the simple epitaph beyond:

HERE LIES LOUIS- THEODORE CARREL

Captain of Marines

Killed by the enemy at Tonkin

PRAY FOR HIS SOUL

The date of death was some months earlier. I was moved to tears and redoubled my efforts to revive her. Finally they succeeded and she came to. I’m not bad- looking, not yet forty, remember, and at that moment I must have been looking extremely solicitous. At any rate, from her first glance I realized she would be both polite and grateful to me. I was not disappointed. Between further tears and sobs she told me about the officer who had been killed at Tonkin after they had been married for just one year. He had married her for love. She had been an orphan and possessed nothing but the smallest dowry.

‘I comforted her, consoled her, lifted her up, then helped her to her feet.

“You can’t stay here like this,” I said, “come on . . .”

“I’m not sure I can manage to walk . . .”

“I’ll help you, don’t worry.”

“Thank you, Monsieur, you’re very kind. Did you have someone here yourself you wanted to mourn?”

“Yes, Madame.”

“A lady?”

“Yes, Madame.”

“Your wife?”

“A . . . friend.”

“One can love a friend as much as a wife. Passion has its own laws.”

“Indeed so, Madame.”

‘We walked away together, she leaning on me so heavily that I was almost carrying her along the paths of the cemetery. As we were leaving it, she said: “I think I’m going to faint.”

“Would you like to go in and sit down somewhere? Let me get you something to . . .”

“Yes thank you, I would.”

‘I noticed a place nearby, one of those restaurants where the friends of the recently buried go when they have completed their grim duties. We went in and I made her drink a cup of hot tea which seemed to restore her strength somewhat. A faint smile came to her lips and she began to tell me a little about herself. How sad, how very sad it was to be all alone in the world, to be alone at home day and night, to have no one with whom to share love, trust and intimacy.

‘It all seemed sincere and so genuine the way she told it. I felt my heart softening. She was very young, twenty at most. I flattered her a little and she responded gracefully. Then, as time was getting on, I offered to take her home by cab. She accepted. In the cab we were so close to each other, shoulder to shoulder, that we could feel the warmth of each other’s bodies through our clothing – one of the most disturbing feelings in the world, as you know. When the cab drew up in front of her house she murmured: “I really don’t think I can get up the stairs on my own. I live on the fourth floor. You’ve been so kind . . . could you possibly give me your arm again, please?”

‘I said of course I could, and she went up slowly, breathing hard all the time. Then at her door she added: “Do come in for a few moments so that I can thank you.”

‘In I went, naturally.

‘It was a modest, not to say poor little apartment furnished in simple but good taste. We sat side by side on a little sofa where she started talking again about how lonely she was. She rang for her maid to bring me something to drink. No one appeared. I was delighted about this and imagined that this maid must work mornings only, in other words, she only had a cleaner. She had taken off her hat. She really was quite a charmer. Her lovely, limpid eyes were fixed on me with such a clear, direct gaze that I suddenly felt an irresistible urge. I succumbed on the spot and clasped her in my arms. On her eyelids, which had instantly closed, I rained kiss after kiss after kiss. She struggled, pushing me away and repeating: “Please . . . please . . . please . . . have done!”

‘What exactly did she mean? In the circumstances there were two ways of interpreting the words. To silence her I moved down from the eyes to the mouth and, putting my preferred interpretation on her request to please have done, complied with it. She put up little resistance and when later we looked at each other again after an insult to the memory of the captain killed at Tonkin she wore a languorous expression of tender resignation which dispelled any misgivings of my own.

‘I showed my gratitude by being gallant and attentive, and after an hour or so’s conversation asked: “Where do you normally dine?”

“At a little restaurant nearby.”

“All on your own?”

“Yes, of course.”

“Will you have dinner with me tonight?”

“Where did you have in mind?”

“Oh, a very good restaurant on the boulevard.”

‘She demurred for a while but I insisted and finally she gave in, reasoning that she would otherwise be terribly lonely again. Then she added, “I’d better change into something less severe,” and disappeared into her bedroom. When she emerged she was in half- mourning and wearing a very simple but elegant grey dress in which she looked slender and charming. She obviously had markedly different outfits for the cemetery and for town.

‘Dinner was very pleasant. She drank champagne, became very animated and excited, after which I went back to her apartment with her. This little liaison begun between the tombstones went on for some three weeks or so. But novelty, particularly with regard to women, eventually palls. I dropped her on the pretext of some unavoidable trip I had to make. I was very generous when we parted and she in turn very grateful. She made me promise, no, swear, to come back on my return and really seemed to care a little for me.

‘I lost no time in forming other attachments, however, and about a month went by without my having felt any particular desire to resume my funereal fling. But nor did I forget her. The memory of her haunted me like some unsolved mystery, a psychological teaser, one of those nagging little puzzles you can’t leave alone. One day, for some inexplicable reason, I wondered whether, if I went back to Montmartre Cemetery again, I might bump into her, and decided to return.

‘I walked around for a long time but there was no one there apart from the usual sort of people who visit the place, mourners who have not yet severed all ties with their dead. At the grave of the captain killed at Tonkin no one mourned over the marble slab, no flowers lay there, no wreaths. However, as I was walking through another district of the city of the departed I suddenly saw a couple, a man and a woman in deep mourning, coming towards me down a narrow avenue lined with crosses. To my amazement as they approached, I recognized the woman. It was she! Seeing me she blushed. As I brushed past her she gave me a tiny signal, the merest glance, but conveying in the clearest possible way both: “Don’t show you know me,” and “Come back and see me, darling.”

‘The man with her was about fifty, distinguished- looking and well- dressed, with the rosette of the Légion d’honneur in his lapel. He was supporting her just as I had done when we both left the cemetery that day.

‘I went off, flabbergasted by what I had just seen and trying to imagine what tribe of creatures she belonged to, hunting as she obviously did on this sepulchral terrain. Was she a single prostitute who had struck on the brilliant idea of frequenting graveyards and picking up unhappy men still haunted by the loss of a wife or a mistress and troubled by the memory of past caresses? Was she unique? Or were there more like her? Was it a professional speciality to work the cemetery like the street? The loved ones of those laid to rest! Or was she alone in having conceived the psychologically sound idea of exploiting the feelings of amorous nostalgia awakened in these mournful venues?

‘I was longing to know whose widow she had chosen to be that day.’

打火匣

大路上一名士兵迈着正步走来：一，二！一，二！他背着军包，挎着军刀，因为他刚打完仗，现在要回家了。然后他在大路上遇到一个老巫婆；她丑恶极了，她的下嘴唇一直垂到胸前。她说：“晚上好，士兵！你的军刀真漂亮，军包真大，你是个不折不扣的士兵！现在你想要多少钱就能有多少钱。”

“谢谢你，老巫婆！”士兵说。

“你看见那棵大树了吗？”巫婆指着他们身边的一棵树说，“里面是空的。你要爬到顶上去，那样你就会看到一个洞，你可以从那儿滑进去，进入树干深处。我会在你的腰上系一根绳子，你喊我的时候，我就可以把你再拉上来。”

“那我到树里去干什么？”士兵问。

“取钱呀！”巫婆说，“你会知道的，你钻到树底下之后，就会进入一条宽大的走廊，那儿很明亮，因为那里点着一百多盏灯。你会看到三扇门，都可以打开，门上插着钥匙。走进第一个房间，你就会看到地板中央放着一口大箱子，上面坐着一条狗，它有一对大如茶杯的眼睛，但你别把它当回事！我把我的蓝格子围裙给你，你可以把它铺在地上；尽快走过去抱住那条狗，把它放到我的围裙上，打开箱子，想拿多少钱就拿多少钱。这些钱都是铜币。但如果你想要银币的话，就得进第二个房间，但那儿也坐着一条狗，它有一对大如水车的眼睛，但你别把它当回事，把它放到我的围裙上，然后拿钱！不过，如果你想要金币的话，你也能拿到，你搬得动多少就能拿多少，进第三个房间就行。但坐在钱箱上的那条狗，有一对眼睛，每只都像‘圆塔’[1]那么大。那条狗可了不得！但你别把它当回事。只要把它放到我的围裙上，它就动不了你，你就从那个箱子里想拿多少金币就拿多少。”

“听上去不错，”士兵说，“但我拿什么东西给你呢，老巫婆？我想你总会要点什么吧。”

“不要，”巫婆说，“我一个铜子儿都不要！你只要替我把那个旧打火匣拿来，那是我祖母上回落在下面的！”

“一言为定！把绳子系到我腰上吧。”士兵说。

“好嘞！”巫婆说，“还有我的蓝格子围裙。”

于是士兵爬上树，跳进洞里，站起身，正如巫婆说的那样，下面的大走廊里点着上百盏灯。

现在他打开第一扇门。啊！那儿坐着那条狗，眼睛大如茶碗，正瞪着他呢。

“你个好家伙!”士兵说，然后把它抱到巫婆的围裙上，往口袋里塞满铜币，锁上箱子，再把狗儿放上去，接着他走进第二个房间。哎呀！那儿坐着的那条狗，眼睛大如水车。

“你不应该老这么看着我，”士兵说，“眼睛会看疼的！”于是他把狗抱到女巫的围裙上，但当他看到箱子里那么多银币的时候，他把他所有的铜币都扔了，然后往口袋和军包里塞满银币。随后他走进第三个房间！哎呀不好，太可怕了！那里的那条狗真有两只大如“圆塔”的眼睛！它们在它脸上打转，就像两个大转盘!

“晚上好！”士兵说，并举了举军帽，因为他从来没见过这样的狗；但瞧了它一会儿之后，他心里想，这下礼数总算够了吧，于是他把它抱到地上，打开箱子，天哪！那么多金币！用这些金币，他可以把整个哥本哈根都买下来，还有全世界所有蛋糕店的甜点，所有的锡兵、皮鞭和木马。没错，就有这么多钱！于是士兵把他口袋里、军包里装满的所有银币都倒了出来，换成了金币，是的，他的口袋、军包、军帽，还有靴子全都装满，他几乎都挪不开步。这下他可有钱了。他把狗放到箱子上，关上门，透过树干朝外喊：“把我拉上去吧，老巫婆!”

“你拿到打火匣了吗？”巫婆问。

“还真是！”士兵说。“这事儿我忘得一干二净。”于是他去拿打火匣。巫婆把他拉了上来，然后他就又回到大路上，口袋、靴子、军包、军帽里全都塞满了钱。

“你要打火匣干什么？”士兵问。

“这不关你的事，”巫婆说，“你不是已经拿到钱了嘛！把打火匣给我就行了。”

“少废话!”士兵说。“快告诉我你要它干什么，不然我就拔出军刀来，砍掉你的头！”

“不行！”巫婆说。

于是士兵就把她的头砍了下来。她倒在地上！而他把他所有的钱都包进她的围裙里，像包袱一样驮在背上，把打火匣放进口袋向城市走去。

这是一座美丽的城市，他进了一家最美丽的酒店，订了最好的房间，点了他最喜欢吃的美食，因为他发财了，有的是钱。

要替他擦皮靴的服务员觉得，像他这样一位有钱的先生，穿这么旧的皮鞋真有些滑稽，但他还没来得及买新的；第二天他买了合适的靴子和漂亮的衣服！现在我们的士兵摇身一变成了尊贵的先生，大家把这座城市里发生的一切都告诉了他，包括他们国王的事，以及国王的女儿是一位多么美丽的公主。

“到哪儿可以看到她？”士兵问。

“她可不是随随便便就能看到的，”大家都说，“她住在一座宏伟的铜城堡里，周围壁垒森严塔楼林立！除了国王没人敢随便出入，因为有预言称，她会嫁给一个很普通的士兵，这让国王难以忍受。”

“我一定得看看她。”士兵想，但国王肯定不会允许！

如今他生活得很愉快，看看喜剧表演，逛逛国王花园，还施舍很多钱给穷人，真是一种善举！他以前深有体会，一文不名有多糟糕！现在他有钱了，有漂亮的衣服穿，交了很多朋友，大家都说他是个善良的人，一位真正的骑士，这话士兵很爱听！但他每天只往外花钱，却一分钱都赚不回来，就这样，最后他只剩下两个铜币，只好从那些华丽的房间里搬出来，搬到顶楼一间小小的阁楼里去住，他只好自己动手擦靴子，自己用织补针补靴子，他的朋友没有一个来找他，因为需要爬那么多楼梯。

有一天晚上天很黑，他连一根蜡烛都买不起，但他想起来，还有一小截蜡烛装在那个打火匣里，就是那回巫婆帮他下到空树底部，他在那里拿到的那个打火匣。他拿出打火匣和那一小截蜡烛来，正当他打着火，火星从火石上冒出来的时候，房门忽然开了，他在树底下见到的那条眼睛大如茶杯的狗出现在他面前，它说：“有什么吩咐，我的主人！”

“怎么回事！”士兵说，“真是个好玩的打火匣，要是这样我就能想要什么就有什么了!给我弄点儿钱来吧。”他对那条狗说。然后“嗖”的一声，狗就不见了！又是“嗖”的一声，狗又回来了，嘴里衔着一大口袋钱。

这下士兵知道这个打火匣有多美妙了！他打一下，那条坐在铜币箱上的狗就会出现，他打两下，来的就是那条有银币的狗，要是他打三下，来的就是那条有金币的狗。现在士兵又搬回了楼下那些华丽的房间，又穿上了好衣服，他的所有朋友马上又把他认了出来，他们都好喜欢他。

有那么一天他心想：说来真是奇怪，谁都见不到那位公主！她肯定非常美丽，大家都这么说！但要是她整天只能坐在塔楼林立的铜城堡里的话，这又有什么用？难道我真的就见不到她吗？我的打火匣在哪儿？他打起火来，“嗖”的一声，那只眼睛大如茶杯的狗就跑了出来。

“现在的确是深更半夜，”士兵说，“但我真心想见见那位公主，哪怕只见那么一小会儿。”

那条狗马上跑出了门，士兵还来不及想一想这件事，就已经看到它带着公主回来了，她躺在那条狗的背上熟睡，美得是个人就能看出来那是个真正的公主；士兵按捺不住吻了她，因为他是个不折不扣的士兵。

然后狗就带着公主回去了，但第二天早上，国王和王后正倒着茶的时候，公主说话了，她说她晚上做了个奇怪的梦，梦见一条狗和一名士兵，她骑在狗背上，那个士兵吻了她。

“这倒是个不错的故事！”王后说。

第二天一个老宫女到公主的床边守夜，来看看这到底真是一场梦还是怎么回事。

士兵迫切地想再见一次那位美丽的公主，于是晚上狗又来了，背上她，竭尽全力飞奔，但那个老宫女穿上雨靴，在后面紧追不舍；当她看到他们跑进一幢大房子之后，她心想，这下我知道这是哪儿了，然后在大门上用一段粉笔画了个大十字。之后她就回去睡觉了，狗也把公主送了回去；但当它看到士兵住处的大门上画着个十字的时候，它也拿了一段粉笔，在全城的所有大门上都画了十字，这件事干得很聪明，因为既然所有的门上都有十字，这下老宫女就找不到正确的大门了。

第二天一大早，国王和王后，还有那个老宫女，以及所有的官员都来了，要看看公主到底去过哪儿！

“就是那儿！”国王说，他看到了第一扇画着十字的门。

“不对，是那儿，我可爱的丈夫！”王后说，她看到另一扇门上有十字。

“那儿有一个，那儿也有一个！”大家都说。不管他们往哪儿看，每扇门上都有十字。于是他们意识到，他们再怎么找也没有用。

但王后毕竟是个非常聪明的女人，她可不是只会坐坐四轮马车那么简单。她取出她的纯金大剪刀，把一大块绸缎剪成几片，缝了一个精致的小袋子，在里面装满了很细很细的荞麦粉，再绑到公主背上。绑好之后，她在袋子上剪了一个小口，这样公主不管走到哪儿，都会在地上撒上粉。

夜里狗又来了，把公主驮到背上，带着她跑到士兵那儿，他已经深深地爱上了她，他多想能成为王子，娶她为妻。

狗背着公主跳上高墙的时候，完全没有注意到，面粉跟着她从城堡一直撒到了士兵的窗口。就这样，第二天早晨，国王和王后马上就看明白他们的女儿去过什么地方，他们抓走了士兵，把他关进了大牢。

他坐在牢里。呜，里面好黑暗好无聊啊，然后大家对他说：明天你就要被绞死了。这话听起来可不好玩，而他把打火匣也忘在了酒店里。第二天早晨，他从小窗的铁栏杆里可以看见人们蜂拥出城，来看他上绞刑架。他听到鼓声，看到士兵们迈着正步。所有人都跑了出来；其中有一个鞋匠的学徒，穿着皮围裙和拖鞋，他跑得太快，一只拖鞋飞了出去，砸在士兵坐着隔着铁栏杆朝外张望的那堵墙上。

“喂，鞋匠小子！你着什么急呀，”士兵对他说，“我到场之前没什么可看的。但你能不能跑到我住的地方，把我的打火匣拿来？这样的话你能得到四个铜币！但你可得撒开腿儿呀。”鞋匠小子很想要那四个铜币，于是撒腿就跑，取来打火匣，交给士兵，这下好戏开场了。

城外架起了一座巨大的绞刑架，周围站满了士兵和成千成万的老百姓。国王和王后坐在华丽的宝座上，面前就是法官和整个议会成员。

那个士兵已经站到了梯子上。但正当他们要把绞索套到他脖子上的时候，他说，总是应该让罪犯在受刑前了却一个无辜的心愿吧。他很想抽一管烟，这将是他在这个世上抽的最后一管烟了。

国王无法拒绝这样的请求，于是士兵拿起他的打火匣，打起火来，一、二、三！三条狗都出现了，眼睛大如茶杯的那条，眼睛大如水车的那条，还有眼睛大如圆塔的那条。

“救救我，别让他们绞死我!”士兵说，于是那几条狗就朝法官和所有议员扑了过去，扯这个人腿，咬那个人鼻子，把他们抛向几丈高的天空，他们掉下来个个摔得粉身碎骨。

“我不要啊！”国王说。但最大的那条狗咬住了他和王后，跟其他所有人一样抛了出去。士兵们都吓坏了，老百姓高喊起来：“小兵，你应该做我们的国王，娶了美丽的公主吧!”

于是他们把这名士兵让进了国王的四轮马车，三条狗一齐在前面欢蹦乱跳，并高呼：“万岁！”男孩们用手指吹起口哨，士兵们上前行礼。公主走出她的铜城堡，成了王后，对此她心满意足！婚礼持续了八天，那几条狗也坐上了饭桌，眼睛瞪得一个比一个大。

[1] 哥本哈根著名历史建筑，三一教堂的一部分。（说明：本书脚注均为译者注。）

小克劳斯和大克劳斯

很久以前，一个村子里有两个人叫同一个名字，他们都叫克劳斯，但其中一个有四匹马，而另一个只有一匹马；为了可以区分他们，人们管有四匹马的那个叫大克劳斯，而只有一匹马的那个就叫小克劳斯。现在让我们来听听他们俩之间发生了什么，因为这是个真实的故事！

整个星期小克劳斯都必须为大克劳斯耕田，并且把自己唯一的马也借给他；而大克劳斯也会把所有四匹马都拿出来帮他，但每星期只有一次，就是星期日。嘚儿驾！小克劳斯挥舞着他的皮鞭同时赶着五匹马，在这一天，它们就像都是他的马一样好使。阳光明媚，所有教堂塔楼的钟一齐敲响，人们都打扮得漂漂亮亮，胳膊下夹着赞美诗集去教堂听神父布道，他们看着小克劳斯赶着五匹马耕地，他看上去那么得意，挥舞鞭子吆喝道：“驾，我的马儿们！”

“你不能这么说，”大克劳斯说，“明明只有一匹是你的！”

但又有人去教堂的路上经过的时候，小克劳斯已经忘了他不能这么说，又吆喝起来：“驾，我的马儿们！”

“好吧，这下我可不能再让你为所欲为了！”大克劳斯说，“你要再这么喊一次，我就砸你马的额头，当场把它砸死，这事儿就算完了！”

“我以后再也不这么说了！”小克劳斯说，但有人经过的时候，他们冲他点头问好，小克劳斯又得意起来，觉得这样有五匹马同时耕自己的地看上去很帅气，于是又挥舞着鞭子吆喝起来：“驾，我的马儿们！”

“就让我来驾你的马吧！”大克劳斯说着，挥起大木槌砸在小克劳斯唯一那匹马的额头上，马应声倒地，奄奄一息。

“啊，我现在一匹马都没有了！”小克劳斯说着哭了起来。之后他剥下了马皮，风干以后装进袋子里，扛在肩上去城里卖马皮。

他要走很长的路，必须穿过一大片黑漆漆的森林，天气非常恶劣；他迷了路，还没等他走上正道，天已经黑了，无论进城还是回家路都太遥远，一会儿就夜深了。

紧挨着路边有一座大农庄，窗户的挡风板掩着，但灯光还是从上面的缝隙里透了出来。应该会让我在这儿过夜吧，小克劳斯心想，于是就走过去敲门。

农妇打开门，但当她听到了他的请求后，她让他还是赶紧上路走吧，她的丈夫不在家，她不能收留陌生人。

“那我就只能睡在门外了。”小克劳斯说，农妇在他面前关上了门。

紧挨着农庄有一大堆干草，干草和房子之间搭着一个茅草顶的小窝棚。

“我可以睡那上面！”小克劳斯看着茅草顶说，“这不就是一张舒服的床吗，希望那只鹳不会飞下来啄我的腿。”屋顶上站着一只活鹳，它在那儿筑了巢。

小克劳斯爬上窝棚，躺下来翻着身，想找个舒服的姿势。窗户的木挡板并没有挡到顶，他可以看进客厅里去。

“谁那么好口福！”小克劳斯说，朝窗户伸直了脑袋。天哪，他看到了什么，多棒的蛋糕呀！真是一桌丰盛的宴席。

这时他听见有人从大路骑着马朝农庄而来，是农妇的丈夫回家来了。

丈夫是个好人，但他有一种奇怪的病，他见不得牧师；只要他一见到牧师就会大发雷霆。正巧牧师来串门，因为他知道丈夫不在家，他来给农妇问个好，农妇因此为他做了一桌美味佳肴；他们听见丈夫来了，害怕起来，农妇求牧师爬进墙脚的一个空箱子里；他照办了，因为他知道那个可怜的丈夫见不得牧师。农妇把一桌好酒好菜都藏进了烤箱里，要是让丈夫看见，他一定会问这是什么意思。

“啊哟！”小克劳斯在窝棚上叹了口气，眼睁睁地看着食物消失。

“上面有人吗？”农夫抬头看着小克劳斯问，“你躺在那儿干吗？快下来进客厅里坐！”

于是小克劳斯就把迷路的事儿都说了，并请求留宿过夜。

“当然可以！”农夫说，“但我们得先弄点东西吃。”

农妇很友好地招待了他们俩，铺了一张长桌子，给他们一大盘粥。农夫饿急了，津津有味地吃起来，但小克劳斯忍不住想起那桌美味的烤肉、肥鱼和蛋糕，他知道它们都藏在烤箱里。

桌下他的脚边放着装马皮的包，我们知道他就是为了进城卖马皮才离家出远门的。他才不要喝什么粥，于是他踩了一脚自己的包，包里干燥的马皮发出的吱嘎声还挺响。

“嘘！”小克劳斯对自己的包说，但同时又踩了一脚，这下吱嘎声比之前更响。

“哟！你袋子里装的是什么？”农夫问。

“哦，里面是个魔法师！”小克劳斯说，“他说我们不用喝粥了，他变了一烤箱的烤肉、肥鱼和蛋糕。”

“什么！”农夫说。然后打开烤箱，看到农妇在里面藏着的所有美味佳肴，但他以为这都是藏在袋子里的魔法师为他们变出来的。农妇一声都不敢吭，赶紧把食物都端上桌，他们把肥鱼、烤肉和蛋糕都吃得一干二净。然后小克劳斯又踩了一脚自己的袋子，马皮吱嘎响。

“他现在说什么？”农夫问。

“他说他还给我们变了三壶酒，放在烤箱旁的角落里！”这下农妇只好端出她藏的酒来，农夫喝得酣畅淋漓，小克劳斯袋子里这样的魔法师他也想要一个。

“他能把魔鬼变出来吗？”农夫问，“我倒想见见他，反正我现在高兴！”

“行啊，”小克劳斯说，“我的魔法师什么都能变，只要我开口，对不对？”他边问边踩袋子，吱嘎吱嘎，“你听见没有，他说没错。但魔鬼长得太难看，实在不值一看！”

“哦，没关系，他长什么样？”

“嗯，他看上去很像个牧师。”

“呼！”农夫说，“那太糟糕了！要知道，我是见不得牧师的！但现在无所谓了，反正我知道那是魔鬼，应该会好一点！现在我还有点勇气！但别让他靠太近。”

“我来问问我的魔法师。”小克劳斯踩踩袋子，把耳朵凑过去。

“他说什么？”

“他说你可以去把那个箱子打开，就在角落里，这样你就可以看到魔鬼了，他就蹲在箱子里，但一定要抓紧盖子，别让他跑了。”

“你能搭把手吗？”农夫说着走到箱子跟前，就是农妇把真正的牧师藏起来的那个箱子，他现在就坐在箱子里害怕得要命。

农夫把箱子盖掀起一条缝，朝里瞥了一眼，“哟！”他喊了一声，向后一闪，“没错，这下我看见他了，他看上去真的挺像我们的牧师！哎呀，太吓人了！”

他不得不喝口酒压压惊，于是他们一直喝到深夜。

“这个魔法师你可得卖给我，”农夫说，“要多少钱尽管开口！对，我可以马上给你一大桶的钱！”

“不行，我可不能卖！”小克劳斯说，“你想想，这个魔法师能给我多少好处！”

“啊，但我太想要他了。”农夫说，开始央求起来。

“好吧，”小克劳斯最后说，“既然你对我这么好，还让我进屋过夜，卖就卖了吧，一大桶钱就一大桶钱，但桶一定要装满。”

“这个没问题，”农夫说，“但那边那个箱子你得带走，我一刻都不想再把它留在房子里，谁知道他是不是还坐在里面。”

小克劳斯于是就把自己那个装着干马皮的袋子给了农夫，换回满满一大桶钱。农夫还给了他一辆手推车，让他装钱和箱子。

“再见！”小克劳斯说，然后就推着他的钱和坐着牧师的大箱子上路了。

树林的另一端有一条水很深的大河，水流湍急，几乎难以逆流游泳。有人在河上造了一座崭新的大桥，小克劳斯停在桥中央，为了让箱子里的牧师听见，他大声说：

“哎呀，我拿这讨厌的箱子怎么办？又那么重，跟装着石头似的！要是再推下去我就快累趴下了，我还是把它扔河里算了，要是它漂回我家就最好，要是不行也无所谓。”

接着他用一只手托住箱子，把它举起来一点点，就想要把它翻到水里去一样。

“不要啊，”箱子里的牧师说，“让我出来吧！”

“咦！”小克劳斯说，假装吃了一惊，“他还坐在里面！我得把他扔到河里去，淹死他再说！”

“哦不，哦不！”牧师喊道，“我给你一整桶的钱，你放了我吧！”

“这就另当别论了!”小克劳斯说着打开箱子。牧师马上爬出来，把空箱子推进了水里，然后回到家里，小克劳斯在那儿又得到一整桶钱，加上他在农夫那儿得到的那桶，这下整辆手推车上都装满了钱。

“看，这匹马还让我赚了不少钱！”回到自家的客厅里后小克劳斯自言自语着，把所有的钱都倒在房间中央堆成一座小钱山，“大克劳斯要是知道我靠一匹马发这么大财该多气恼，但我不会老实告诉他！”

他派了自己的儿子去找大克劳斯借量桶。

“他要量桶干什么！”大克劳斯心想，于是他在量桶底部抹了点焦油，好粘点称的东西回来看看是什么，他还真的得逞了，当他讨回量桶的时候，桶底粘了三枚崭新的银币。

“怎么回事？”大克劳斯立刻飞奔到小克劳斯家，“你从哪儿弄到这么多钱？”

“哦，是我的马皮，我昨天把它卖了！”

“可算卖了大价钱呀！”大克劳斯说着，马上飞奔回家，拿斧子砸开了他所有四匹马的额头，扒下它们的皮来，驾车载着马皮进城去了。

“卖皮啦！卖皮啦！谁要买皮呀！”他沿街吆喝着。

所有鞋匠和皮匠都跑了出来，问他皮怎么卖。

“一桶钱一张。”大克劳斯说。

“你疯了吗？”大家都说，“你真以为我们这么有钱？”

“卖皮啦！卖皮啦！谁要买皮呀！”他继续吆喝，但不管谁问他，马皮多少钱，他都回答：“一桶钱。”

“他是在耍我们。”大家都这么说，于是鞋匠们拿起了皮带，皮匠们拿起了皮围裙，开始抽打大克劳斯。

“卖皮啦！卖皮啦！”他们嘲弄他，“我们把你这一身皮，抽出点猪血来！快滚出城去吧！”他们喊，大克劳斯只好不顾一切地逃，他可从没被谁揍得这么狼狈过。

“哼！”回到家以后他自言自语道，“这笔账得找小克劳斯算，看我不打死他！”

而小克劳斯家里也出了事，他的祖母去世了；虽然她确实一直对小克劳斯很凶很不好，但他还是很难过，他把死去的祖母放到自己温暖的床上，看看她还能不能活过来；她要在那儿躺一整夜，而他自己搬了张椅子坐到角落里，他要在椅子上过夜，以前也这么干过。

那天晚上他就这么在椅子上坐着，门开了，大克劳斯举着斧子闯了进来；他当然知道小克劳斯的床在什么地方，他径直走到床边，用斧子砸了已死的祖母的额头，他还以为躺在那儿的是小克劳斯。

“瞧！”他说，“这下你再也没法儿耍我了！”然后他就回家去了。

“可真是个卑鄙的恶人！”小克劳斯心想，“他竟然想打死我，幸好祖母已经死了，要不然她就死在他手上了！”

然后他给老祖母穿上节日盛装，从邻居那里借了匹马，驾上马车，把祖母放在马车最后排的座位上，这样她就不会倒下来。就这样，他驾着马车穿过森林，太阳升起的时候，他们来到一家大客栈门前，小克劳斯停下马车进去弄点吃的。

客栈老板有许多许多钱，也是个很善良的人，但性情暴躁，就像藏了一肚子胡椒和烟草。

“早上好！”他对小克劳斯说，“你今天来得可真早，穿得也气派！”

“是呀，”小克劳斯说，“我要跟我的老祖母一起进城去，她坐在外面的马车里，我没办法让她进大厅来。你能给她一杯蜜酒吗？但你说话得大声点，因为她耳背听不清。”

“好的，我这就去！”老板说着，倒了一大杯蜜酒，捧去给死去的祖母，马车里一片寂静。

“这儿有您孙子给您的蜜酒一杯！”老板说，但那位已经死了的农妇当然一声不吭，一动不动地坐在那里！

“没听见吗！”老板使出全身力气高喊，“这儿有您孙子给您的蜜酒！”

他把同样的话喊了一遍又一遍，但她还是纹丝不动，这让他火冒三丈，把杯子往她脸上扔过去，蜜酒顺着她的鼻子淌下来，她向后一仰从马车上摔了下来，因为小克劳斯只是把她放在那儿，并没有绑牢。

“天哪！”小克劳斯喊着冲出门来，抓住客栈老板的前襟！“你杀死了我的祖母！你看见没有，她的额头上有个大窟窿！”

“哦，这是个意外！”老板喊道，双手一拍！“都怪我的暴脾气！亲爱的小克劳斯，我给你一整桶钱，还会安葬你的祖母，就像对我自己的祖母一样，但千万别声张，不然的话他们会砍掉我的头，那样就惨了！”

于是小克劳斯得到一整桶钱，客栈老板还亲自安葬了老祖母，就像那是他自己的祖母一样。

小克劳斯又一次满载而归，他马上派自己的儿子去找大克劳斯，向他借量桶。

“怎么回事？”大克劳斯说，“我不是把他打死了吗！我得亲眼看看。”然后亲自给小克劳斯送来了量桶。

“你这又是从哪里弄来的这么多钱？”他问，瞪大了眼睛看着面前的钱堆，好壮观。

“你杀死的是我的祖母，不是我！”小克劳斯说，“我把她卖掉了，赚了一桶钱。”

“这可是卖了大价钱呀！”大克劳斯说着赶回家，拿起斧子立即砸死了自己的老祖母，把她装上马车送进城，到一个药剂师家，问他要不要买死尸。

“死了的是谁，你是怎么得到尸体的？”药剂师问。

“是我的祖母！”大克劳斯说，“我把她打死了，来换一桶钱！”

“上帝饶恕我们吧！”药剂师说，“你说的什么疯话！千万别再说了，你会掉脑袋的！”然后他告诉大克劳斯他干的事多么伤天害理，他是个多邪恶的人，他应该受到惩罚；大克劳斯吓坏了，他从药剂师那儿逃出来，飞奔上了马车，抽打着马匹逃回家，但药剂师和其他人都以为他疯了，就放他走了。

“你要为此付出代价！”大克劳斯跑到大路上以后心想，“没错，你要为此付出代价，小克劳斯！”他回家以后马上拿了一个他能找到的最大的口袋来到小克劳斯家，说：“这次你又耍了我！我先是打死了我的马儿们，然后又打死了我的祖母！这全都是你的错，但你休想再耍我了。”然后他一把抱住小克劳斯的腰，把他塞进口袋里，扛到肩上，对他喊，“我这就出门把你淹死！”

去河边要走的路还挺长，小克劳斯扛着也不轻。路上经过教堂门口，传来里面美妙的风琴声和人们的歌声。于是大克劳斯把装着小克劳斯的口袋紧挨着教堂大门放好，心想，继续赶路之前，先进去听个赞美诗也不错，小克劳斯又跑不了，所有人都在教堂里，于是他就走了进去。

“啊呀！啊呀！”小克劳斯在口袋里叹气。他翻来覆去，但怎么也解不开绑绳。这时来了一个很老很老的牧羊人，满头白发，手里拄着大拐杖，用它赶着一大群牛，它们撞到了装着小克劳斯的口袋，口袋翻倒在地。

“啊呀！”小克劳斯叹息道，“我那么年轻，却马上就要上天堂了！”

“而可怜的我！”牧羊人说，“那么老了却还去不了！”

“把袋子解开！”小克劳斯喊道，“代替我钻进来，这样你很快就能上天堂了！”

“好呀，我非常乐意。”牧羊人说，帮小克劳斯解开口袋，他立刻从里面钻了出来。

“那你帮我照看我的牲口吧。”老人说，钻进袋子里，小克劳斯绑好绑绳然后赶着所有的公牛母牛上路了。

过了一会儿，大克劳斯从教堂走出来，他又把口袋扛到肩上，感觉到口袋肯定是变轻了，因为那个老牧羊人还不到半个小克劳斯那么重！“他变得好轻呀！肯定是因为我听了赞美诗！”于是他来到河边，河又深又宽，他把装着老牧羊人的口袋扔进水里，然后冲他喊道——因为他当然还以为那是小克劳斯：“瞧！这下你没法儿再耍我了吧！”

然后他朝家走，经过岔路的时候他遇到了小克劳斯，赶着牲口迎面走来。

“怎么回事！”大克劳斯说，“我不是把你淹死了吗？”

“没错，”小克劳斯说，“你不到半小时前是把我扔到河里去了！”

“但你这么多漂亮的牲口是哪儿来的？”大克劳斯问。

“它们是海牛！”小克劳斯说，“我来把来龙去脉都讲给你听。还要感谢你，因为你把我扔到了河里，这下我的财产超过你了，而且真的发了大财，你想得到吗！我在口袋里的时候吓坏了，当时你从桥上把我扔向冰冷的河里，风在耳边呼啸。我很快沉到了河底，但我没有磕到自己，因为下面长着美丽的嫩草。我就掉在草地上，很快袋子就开了，这时来了个世界上最美丽的姑娘，穿着洁白的衣服，湿漉漉的头发上戴着绿色的花环，她拉着我的手说：‘你是小克劳斯吗？先带一些海牛去吧！沿着这条路一英里之外还有一大群，是我赠送给你的！’这下我看到了，河底是一条宽阔的大路，专供海洋人使用。他们就这样从海底或走路或驾车一直到岸上，到大河的尽头。那儿的花美极了，还有最新鲜的嫩草，还有鱼，在水底游来游去，它们在我耳边飞快地穿梭，就像这儿空中的鸟。那儿的人都好漂亮，还有那么多的牲口，漫山遍野到处走！”

“那为什么你这么快就回来了，”大克劳斯问，“下面既然那么美，换我就不回来了！”

“没错，”小克劳斯说，“这就是我机智的地方！你不是听我说了嘛：海姑娘说，沿路一英里之外——她说的路其实就是河，因为她去不了别的地方——还有一大群牲口等着我。但我知道河有多蜿蜒曲折，一会儿东一会儿西，这可是绕了大远路呀，能走捷径当然走捷径啦，上岸抄近路到河的另一边可以省掉将近一半的路程，你看我这么快就已经把我的海牛赶回来了！”

“你运气真是太好了！”大克劳斯说，“你觉得如果我也下到河底的话能不能也弄到几头海牛？”

“当然，我觉得没问题，”小克劳斯说，“但我可不能把你装进袋子里扛到河边，你对我来说太重了，你要不自己走到那儿然后钻进袋子里，这样的话我很乐意把你扔下去。”

“谢谢你！”大克劳斯说，“但要是我得不到海牛，等我回来看我怎么收拾你，你信不信！”

“别呀！别那么恶狠狠的！”于是他们来到河边。牲口们口渴难耐，看到水立刻撒开腿奔过去喝水。

“看它们跑得多快！”小克劳斯说，“它们着急想回河底呢！”

“快先帮帮我！”大克劳斯说，“不然我揍你了啊！”说着他钻进一只驮在一头公牛背上的那个大口袋，“放块石头，不然我怕我沉不下去。”大克劳斯说。

“肯定可以！”小克劳斯说，但还是在口袋里放了一块大石头，绑紧绳子，往下一推：扑通！大克劳斯掉进河里，很快就沉到水底。

“恐怕他是找不到海牛咯！”小克劳斯说，然后赶着他的牲口回家去了。

豌豆公主

很久以前有一位王子，他想为自己找一位公主，但必须是一位真正的公主。于是他走遍了全世界，为了寻找这样一位公主，他总是到处碰壁，公主倒不少，但是不是真正的公主，他也无从考证，总是有什么地方不对劲。后来他只好闷闷不乐地回家了，他真的非常渴望得到一位真正的公主。

一天晚上，天气异常恶劣；电闪雷鸣，大雨倾盆，可怕极了！这时，有人敲响了城门，老国王过去开门。

城外站着的是一位公主。但是，老天爷呀，狂风暴雨让她看上去那么狼狈！水从她的头发和衣服上直往下淌，从鞋尖淌进去，又从鞋跟流出来，而她却说，她是一位真正的公主。

“好吧，反正我们早晚都会知道。”老王后心想。但她什么都没说，只是走进卧房，把所有的被褥都拿掉，在床板上放了一颗豌豆，然后她拿来二十张床垫，盖在豌豆上，之后又在这些垫子上盖了二十床羽绒被。

这就是公主晚上睡觉的地方。

第二天早上大家问她睡得怎么样。

“哦，糟糕透了！”公主说，“我几乎整夜都没合眼！天知道，我的床上有什么东西？我睡在什么硬邦邦的东西上面，全身青一块紫一块！吓死人了!”

这样大家就看出来，这是一位真正的公主，隔着二十张床垫和二十床羽绒被，她都能感觉到下面的豌豆。除了真正的公主，还会有谁这么敏锐。

于是王子就娶了她做妻子，因为他知道，他终于得到了一位真正的公主，而豌豆则进了国家美术馆，如果没有被人拿走的话，现在大家还能看到它。

瞧，这可是个真实的故事！

坚定的锡兵

很久以前，有二十五个锡做的士兵，他们都是兄弟，因为他们是同一把旧锡勺生的。他们怀揣步枪、面朝前方。红红蓝蓝的制服还挺美的。他们在这个世界上听到的第一句话是：“锡兵！”他们当时正待在一个盒子里，盒盖掀开，一个农家男孩一边拍着双手一边这么喊；他们是他的礼物，因为那天是他的生日，他现在把他们一个一个摆到桌子上。士兵们个个都长得一模一样，只有一个稍有不同，他只有一条腿，因为他是最后一个铸出来的，锡不够用了；但他用一条腿站得跟别人用两条腿一样稳当，正是他最引人注目。

他们站着的桌子上，还摆着许多其他玩具，但最让人目不转睛的是一座纸糊的美丽城堡。透过那些小窗户可以望到里面的大厅。城堡外面立着几棵小树，围着一面小镜子——可以看成是一面湖。蜡制的天鹅在湖面游弋并欣赏着自己的倒影。一切都很美丽，不过最美丽的是一个小姑娘，她站在敞开的城堡门口。她也是纸剪出来的，但她穿着一条最纯净的棉布裙，肩上有一条窄窄的蓝丝带，就像一条披肩；场景的中央镶着一枚亮晶晶的闪片——几乎跟她整张脸一样大。小姑娘舒展着双臂——因为她是个舞者，一条腿高高举向天空，高得锡兵几乎望不到，以为她跟自己一样，也只有一条腿。

“她可以做我的妻子！”他心想，“但她太高贵了。她住的是城堡，而我只有一个盒子，而且还挤着我们二十五个人，可不是她该住的地方！尽管如此，我还是得想办法认识认识她！”于是他整个人躺平，藏在桌上的一个鼻烟壶背后；这样他正好可以看到这位漂亮的女士，她一直单腿站着，丝毫没有失去平衡。

夜幕降临的时候，其余的锡兵都回到盒子里，家里的人也都上床睡觉去了。这时候玩具们开始玩起了游戏，串门的串门，打仗的打仗，有的还开起了舞会。锡兵们也在盒子里闹腾起来，因为他们也想参加，但他们掀不开盒盖。胡桃夹子翻起了筋斗，石笔在画板上兴风作浪。骚动吵醒了金丝鸟，她说起话来，还抑扬顿挫的。没有挪窝的只有两个人，一个是锡兵，一个是小舞蹈家。她直挺挺地踮着脚尖，展开双臂。锡兵也坚定地用他的一条腿站立着，目不转睛地看着她。

这时钟敲响了十二下，鼻烟壶的盖子“咔”的一声弹开，但里面装的并不是烟草，而是一个黑黑的小妖怪，原来鼻烟壶只是个幌子。

“锡兵！”妖怪说，“管好自己的眼睛行不行！”

但锡兵假装没听见。

“好吧，明天走着瞧！”妖怪说。

第二天早晨，孩子们起床后，把锡兵摆到了窗台上。不是那个妖怪就是一阵劲风，窗一下子就吹开了，锡兵一头从三楼大厅栽了下去。这一跤跌得好险！他高举着腿，军帽顶着地，刺刀插在石铺的地缝隙里。

女佣和那个男孩立刻下楼来找他，尽管他们差点从他身上踩过去，但谁都没有看见他。要是当时锡兵喊一声“我在这儿！”他们就肯定能找到他。但他觉得高声喊叫不合时宜，他还穿着制服呢。

这时下起雨来，雨点越来越密，成了瓢泼大雨；大雨过后，来了两个流浪儿。

“你瞧！”其中一个说，“那儿躺着一个锡兵！他要扬帆远航啦！”

说着他们就用报纸折了一条船，把锡兵放在中央，他就这样沿着排水沟顺流而下；两个男孩都在一旁跟着跑，还边拍着手。哎呀！排水沟里的浪真大，水流真湍急！那可是一场瓢泼大雨呀。纸船上下颠簸，时不时来个急转弯，吓得锡兵心直哆嗦；但他重新振作起来，面不改色，目视前方，紧握步枪。

突然之间，船冲进一条长长的排水管；里面一片漆黑，就像回到了他的盒子里。

“不知道我现在到哪儿了。”他想，“就是，就是，是那个妖怪的错。唉，要是那个姑娘在船里就好了，那样的话再黑一倍也没关系。”

这时突然出现了一只住在水管里的老鼠。

“你有通行证吗？”老鼠问，“交出通行证来！”

但锡兵保持沉默，并把手里的步枪握得更紧。船继续前进，老鼠紧追不舍。哟！瞧它那咬牙切齿还冲着稻草木棍大喊大叫的样子：

“抓住他！抓住他！他没交过路费！他没出示通行证！”

但水流越来越湍急！锡兵已经能看到水管开口处传进来的天光，但他也听到了一阵可怕的声音，足以让再勇敢的人都胆战心惊。想象一下：水管的尽头，水流落入一条大运河里，对他来说，这其中的危险不亚于我们坠入一座大瀑布。

现在他已经近得无法刹车了。船冲了出去，可怜的锡兵尽可能地挺直身体，谁都别想说他眨过一下眼皮子。船旋转了三四圈，里面灌满了水，一直漫到了船沿，船要沉了；锡兵站在没到脖子的水中，船越沉越深，纸也越来越松。此刻水已没过了士兵的头，这时他想起了那个美丽的小舞者，他再也见不到她了；然后锡兵的耳朵里响起了一个声音：

“前进，前进，勇敢的人！

迎接你的是死神！”

就这样，纸破了，锡兵掉了出来，但与此同时，一条大鱼一口把他吞了下去。

哦不，里面好黑啊！比在水管里还要糟糕，而且地方很窄；但锡兵还是很坚定，直挺挺地躺着，紧握着步枪。

鱼游来游去，做着各种各样可怕的动作；后来它终于平静了下来，就像有一道闪电划过它的身躯。光线明亮起来，有人高声喊道：“锡兵！”原来鱼被人捉住，送到了集市口，卖掉之后进了厨房，女仆用一把大刀把它剖开。她用两根手指把锡兵拦腰夹住，带进客厅，大家都想看看这位在鱼肚子里驰骋过的大人物；但锡兵一点都不骄傲。他们把他放到桌子上，天哪！这世界真是无奇不有！锡兵又回到了他之前待过的同一个客厅，他看着同样的孩子，桌上放着同样的玩具；漂亮的城堡和美丽的小舞者；她仍然单腿站立着，另一条腿高高举在空中，她也很坚定；这让锡兵很感动，几乎要流出锡做的眼泪来，但他觉得这么做不合时宜。他看着她，她也看着他，但他们没有说一句话。

正在这时候，其中一个小男孩拿起锡兵，把他扔进了陶瓷壁炉。他也没有给出任何理由；一定是鼻烟壶里的小妖怪，就是他搞的鬼。

锡兵明晃晃地站在那儿，感到一股热浪，这很可怕，但热浪究竟是来自火焰还是爱情，他也不知道。色彩从他身上褪去，究竟是旅途中发生的，还是悲伤造成的，谁也说不上来。他看着那个小姑娘，她也在看着他，他感觉到自己在熔化，但他仍然坚定地站着，紧握步枪。这时忽然开了一扇门，一阵风卷起了舞者，她像风精灵一样飞进陶瓷壁炉，落在锡兵身边，燃起火焰，消失了，然后锡兵也熔成一团。第二天女仆清理炉灰的时候，她发现锡兵已经变成了一颗小小的锡心；而舞者留下的只有那枚闪片，并已经烧成了黑炭。

夜莺

在中国——这你肯定知道——皇帝是个中国人，他周围的人也都是中国人。这是许多年以前的事了，正因为如此才要听听这个故事，趁它还没有被大家忘记！这位皇帝的宫殿是世界上最雄伟壮丽的，一砖一瓦都是用精美的陶瓷制作的，非常昂贵，但也非常易碎，摸起来要非常小心。花园里可以看到各种奇花异草，那些最美艳的花上都系着银铃，铃儿叮当响，为了不让经过的人们错过这些花儿。诚然，御花园里的一切都那么引人注目，花园那么大，连园丁都不知道哪里是尽头；一直走下去，就会进入到最美丽的森林，那里有很高的树和很深的湖；树林一直延伸到大海，海水蔚蓝深邃；巨大的船只可以一直行驶到树枝下，就在这里，住着一只夜莺，它的歌声如此动听，连穷苦的渔夫，哪怕再繁忙劳碌，都会在夜里收网的时候，停下手中的活静静地聆听。“天哪，实在太美了！”他说，然后他不得不继续忙碌，忘掉这只鸟；然而第二天晚上它又唱起了歌，在外劳作的渔夫又会说同样的话：“天哪！实在太美了！”

世界各地的游客来到皇帝的都城，他们叹赏着这座城市，以及宫殿和花园，但当他们听到夜莺歌唱的时候，他们都会说：“这才是最美的！”

旅行家们回家之后，都会分享他们的所见所闻，其中那些学者写了许多关于皇城、宫殿和花园的书，他们也没有忘记那只夜莺，它被放在了第一位；而那些会写诗的人，写出了最美丽的诗篇，每一首写的都是深海边森林里的那只夜莺。

这些书在全世界流传，有几本还传到了皇帝手上。他坐在自己的金龙椅上，孜孜不倦地读着，时不时点点头，因为那些关于皇城、宫殿和花园的壮美描写让他很满意。“但最美的还是那只夜莺！”书上分明写着。

“怎么回事！”皇帝说，“夜莺！朕怎么完全不知道！朕的帝国里还有这么一只鸟，而且居然就在朕的花园里！朕却从来没听到过！朕还是从书上看来的！”

于是他唤来了他的侍臣，那可是个高贵的人，要是有任何比他卑微的人，胆敢跟他说话，或问他问题，他除了“呸！”之外不会多说一个字，而这个字本身也毫无意义。

“这儿应该有一只非常引人注目的鸟，名叫夜莺！”皇帝说，“大家都说它是朕泱泱大国中最美的东西！为什么从来没人跟朕提起过它！”

“微臣以前从没听说过这个名字！”侍臣说，“从来没人带它来上过朝！”

“朕要让它今晚到这儿来为朕唱歌！”皇帝说，“全世界都知道朕有什么，就朕不知道！”

“微臣以前从没听说过这个名字！”侍臣说，“微臣会去找，微臣会找到它！”

但到哪里去找它呢；侍臣上上下下跑遍所有楼梯，穿过大大小小的厅堂和走廊，但他遇到的人中，没有一个听说过关于夜莺的事，侍臣又跑回皇帝那儿，说这一定是写书的人编出来的寓言。“陛下不能相信书上写的东西！那都是虚构的，也就是所谓的‘无稽之谈’！”

“但朕读到它的那本书，”皇帝说，“是日本那位德高望重的天皇送的，不太可能是胡编乱造的。朕要听夜莺唱歌！今晚就要它在这里出现！这是朕的圣旨！假如它今晚不来，满朝文武吃完晚饭都得在肚子上挨板子。”

“遵旨！”侍臣说，然后又上上下下跑了一遍所有的楼梯，穿过大大小小的厅堂和走廊。半个朝廷都跟着他跑，因为他们不想肚子上挨板子。大家都在找这只奇怪的夜莺——举世闻名，但满朝文武却对它一无所知。

最后他们终于在御膳房里遇到一个贫穷的小女孩，她说：“哦，天哪，夜莺！我当然知道！是呀，它多会唱歌呀！每天晚上我都获准带一些饭桌上的剩菜回家，给我那可怜的、生病的母亲，她住在海边，我回家的路上累了，在森林里休息的时候，就会听到夜莺的歌唱！我听得热泪盈眶，感觉就像母亲吻了我一样！”

“小厨娘!”侍臣说，“我会给你御膳房的固定职位，并准你侍奉吾皇用膳，只要你带我们去找夜莺，因为有圣旨传它今晚进宫！”

于是他们一齐走进夜莺平时唱歌的那片森林；跟来半个朝廷。他们走着走着，一头母牛哞哞叫起来。

“呀！”一位年轻的朝臣说，“终于找到了！这么小的动物身上居然有这么神奇的爆发力！我以前肯定听到过这个声音！”

“不对，这是牛叫！”小厨娘说，“我们还有很长的路要走。”

这下是青蛙在池塘里呱呱叫。

“美妙！”国寺方丈说，“现在我算是听到它的声音了——就像小小的寺庙钟声。”

“不对，这是青蛙！”小厨娘说，“但我想我们很快就能听到它的声音了！”

说着夜莺就开始唱了起来。

“就是它！”小女孩说，“听！听！它就在那儿！”然后她指了指树枝上的一只灰色小鸟。

“真没想到！”侍臣说，“它居然长这样！看上去多普通！一定是因为看到自己身边围了这么多高贵的人它才失去了光彩！”

“小夜莺!”小厨娘高声喊道，“吾皇圣恩，宣你进宫唱歌。”

“荣幸之至！”夜莺说着就兴致盎然地唱了起来。

“宛如琉璃编钟！”侍臣说，“看这副小嗓音，运用得多妙！我们居然从来没听见过，真奇怪！它在宫中一定大获成功！”

“我还要为皇上再唱一次吗？”夜莺问，它还以为皇帝在场。

“我非同凡响的小夜莺！”侍臣说，“能请您入宫参加宫廷夜宴，让您为吾皇一展歌喉以悦龙颜，是在下最大的荣幸。”

“歌儿还是在绿荫下最动听！”夜莺说，但当它听说这是皇帝的希望时，还是欣然答应去了。

宫殿里装点得富丽堂皇！墙和地板都是瓷砖铺成的，被成千上万的金灯照得金碧辉煌！那些最美丽的花朵挂着铃摆在走廊上；只要有人奔跑或一阵穿堂风吹过，所有的铃就会一起叮当响起，没人能听见彼此的说话声。

皇帝正襟危坐的大殿中央，竖着一根金杆，这是给夜莺坐的；满朝文武都到齐了，小厨娘也获准在门后侍应，因为她现在已经正式获得“御厨”的封号。每个人都穿上了最华丽的盛装，大家都望着这只灰色的小鸟，皇帝冲它点点头。

夜莺的歌声如此美妙，听得皇帝热泪盈眶，泪珠从脸颊上滚落，夜莺的歌声越来越优美，动人心弦；皇帝那么高兴，他说要把他的金拖鞋挂到夜莺脖子上。但夜莺谢绝了，它已经得到了足够的酬赏。

“我见到了皇上眼里的泪珠，这对我来说是最珍贵的宝藏！皇上的泪珠有一种神奇的力量。神知道我已经得到了足够的酬赏！”然后它又用天赐的甜美歌喉唱起歌来。

“这是我见过最可爱的尤物！”周围的宫女们说，有人跟她们说话的时候，她们就故意喝口水，在嘴里发出“咯咯”声：她们以为自己也是夜莺。太监和侍女们也表了态，说他们也很满意，这很说明问题，因为这些人是最难伺候的。没错，夜莺首演大获成功。

于是它在宫中住了下来，有了自己的笼子，它还有自由出去散步的时间，白天两次，夜晚一次。每次总有十二个随从跟着，每个人手里都攥着一根系在它腿上的丝线，还都拉得紧紧的，这样散步根本谈不上享受。

整座京城的人都在谈论这只出类拔萃的鸟，两个人在路上相遇，其中一个人别的不必多说，只要说：“夜——！”另一个人就会说：“莺！”然后他们就都叹一口气，彼此心领神会了，的确有十一个小贩的孩子都起名为“夜莺”，但其中没有一个唱歌着调的。

有一天皇帝收到一个大包裹，下面写着：“夜莺”。

“又一本写我们这只名鸟的书吧！”皇帝说。但包裹里不是书，而是一件小工艺品，装在一个盒子里，一只手工制造的夜莺，它很像那只活的夜莺，但全身镶满了钻石、红宝石和蓝宝石；只要给它上好发条，它就会唱一首真的夜莺唱过的歌，尾巴上下摆动着，晶莹剔透。它的脖颈上缠着一根小丝带，上面写着：“日本皇帝的夜莺，无法与中国皇帝的夜莺媲美。”

“太美了！”大家都说。而那个送来手工夜莺的人马上受封：首席皇家夜莺使者。

“现在让它们在一起唱歌吧！那会是多动听的二重唱呀！”

就这样，它们不得不一起唱歌，但怎么都不对劲，因为那只真正的夜莺有自己的风格，而人造鸟是上发条的，只会按部就班。“没关系，”乐师说，“节奏很独特，还挺对我口味！”于是人造鸟就要独唱了——它取得了和真鸟不相上下的成功，另外，它的外表要美艳得多：它像手镯和胸针一样闪闪发亮。

同样的曲目，它唱了三十三遍，并且不厌其烦：大家都愿意再听下去，但皇帝却说也该让那只活的夜莺唱点儿什么了——但它去哪儿了？谁都没有注意到，它已经飞出窗外，回它的绿森林里去了。

“这到底是怎么回事！”皇帝说。满朝官员都在咒骂，说那只夜莺是个忘恩负义的畜生。“反正我们有一只最棒的鸟！”他们说，就这样，那只人造鸟不得不又唱了起来，这是他们第三十四次听同一首歌，但他们还是学不会，因为这首歌太难，乐师对这只鸟赞不绝口，可以肯定，它比那只真的夜莺好得多，不仅衣装以及镶有这么多精美钻石的外表，还有它的内在。

“各位大人，特别是皇帝陛下，恕我直言！谁都无法捉摸那只真的夜莺会唱出什么歌来，而这只人造鸟是有定式的！该怎么样就怎么样！大家可以搞清楚它的工作原理，可以把它拆开，看看其中的匠心，发条在哪里，它是怎么转动的，怎么一步接一步工作的——！”

“我差不多也是这么想的！”大家都说。于是乐师获准在下周日向民众展示这只鸟。他们也应该听听它的歌喉，皇帝说。他们听了，也很满意，就像畅饮香茶一般——因为喝茶是件很具中国特色的事，大家都说：“哇！”一边点头一边向天空举起食指。但那些贫穷的渔夫听到过真正夜莺的歌声，他们说：“声音够优美，也很逼真，但就是缺了点什么，我也不知道缺的是什么！”

真正的夜莺已被放逐出这片国土。

人造鸟紧挨着皇帝的床在一个真丝枕头上落了脚：它得到的所有礼品，金玉珠宝，都堆在它的周围，它的封号已经升为“至尊皇家床头歌手”，等级为左手边第一位，因为皇帝认为左边最尊贵，左边是心脏的位置，哪怕是皇帝的心脏。乐师为人造鸟写了长达二十五卷的书，文章渊博而冗长，使用了最繁难的汉字，大家都说他们读过并读懂了这部书，因为不这么说就是愚蠢，肚子上要挨板子的。

就这样过了整整一年；皇帝、群臣，以及所有其余的中国人都能背得出夜莺的歌里每一处细小的转折，但正因为这样大家才觉得最妙；他们可以跟着一起唱了。流浪儿唱着“唧唧唧！咕咕咕！”，皇帝也这么唱！——没错，这样肯定很美妙！

但某天晚上，人造鸟正唱着最拿手的曲目，皇帝躺在床上听着，鸟的身体里突然“噌！”的一声；哪儿断了什么东西，“唰！”，所有轮子都飞转起来，歌声戛然而止。

皇帝立即跳下床，唤来了他的御医，但喊御医有什么用！于是又传了一个钟表匠来，几番口舌和几番检视之后，他总算把鸟修了个八九不离十，但他说这只鸟以后可要省着点用，因为它的机芯已经锈蚀，换新的机芯让音乐恢复正常是不可能的了。这是一件非常悲伤的事！大家只敢让人造鸟一年演唱一次，就这样也已经算是勉为其难了；然而乐师用那些繁难的字眼做了个简短的发言，他说一切都跟过去一样好，于是一切就都算跟过去一样好。

五年过去了，整个国家遭遇了一场最重大的悲伤，因为大家都很喜欢他们的皇帝，而他现在病了，据说不久于人世，新的皇帝已经选好，老百姓都站在大街上，向侍臣打听皇帝的病情。

“唉!”他边说边摇头。

皇帝冰冷苍白地躺在他华丽的大床上。满朝文武都以为他死了，每个人都跑去向新皇帝请安。太监们都跑出来闲言碎语，宫女们开着盛大的茶话会。所有的大厅和走廊里都铺满了布，为了有人经过的时候不发出脚步声，所以到处都很寂静，非常寂静。但皇帝还没有死，他僵硬苍白地躺在华丽的床上，长长的天鹅绒帷幔和沉重的黄金穗饰；高处开着一扇窗，月亮照进来，月光洒在皇帝和人造鸟身上。

可怜的皇帝几乎透不过气来，感觉就像胸口压着什么东西；他勉强睁开眼睛，看到死神坐在他胸口上，头上戴着金冠，一只手握着皇帝的金剑，另一只手举着他那柄华丽的令旗；他的四周，天鹅绒帷幔的褶皱里探出许多奇形怪状的脑袋来，有些很丑陋，有些很祥和：这些都是皇帝的恶业和善行，他们都瞪着他，而死神就坐在他的心坎上。

“你还记得吗？”脑袋一个接一个地低声问，“你还记得吗？”他们对他讲了许多往事，搞得他满头冷汗。

“朕从来都不知道！”皇帝说。“奏乐，奏乐，大鼓敲起来！”他喊道，“别让朕听到他们说的话！”

但他们还是挥之不去，不管说什么，死神都点头。

“奏乐，奏乐！”皇帝大叫，“你这祥瑞的小金鸟！唱呀，唱呀！朕给你穿金戴银，还亲自把朕的金拖鞋挂在你的脖颈上，唱呀，唱呀！”

但那只鸟一声不吭地站在那儿，没人来给它上发条，它也就不会唱歌；但死神仍然用他空洞的大眼睛瞪着皇帝，四周一片寂静，寂静得可怕。

就在这时，紧挨着窗传来了那最美丽的歌声，是那只活着的小夜莺，它站在窗外的树枝上；它听说皇帝病危，所以赶来用歌声送上安慰与希望。随着它的歌声，那些鬼魂越来越苍白，血液在皇帝孱弱的四肢中流淌得越来越快，连死神都在聆听，他说：“唱下去，小夜莺，唱下去吧!”

“好的，但把华丽的金剑交给我吧！把贵重的令旗也给我吧！把皇帝的金冠也给我吧！”

死神用每一件宝物交换一首歌，夜莺就一直唱下去，它唱到寂静的墓园，白色的玫瑰在那儿生长，接骨木树在那儿散发着幽香，嫩草在那儿沐浴着遗属的眼泪；这让死神怀念起自己的花园来，化作一缕冰冷的白雾，飘出窗外。

“谢谢，谢谢！”皇帝说，“你这只天使般的小鸟，朕认得你！是朕把你逐出朕的国土的！而你却用歌唱驱除了朕床边的恶灵，让死神离开朕的心坎！朕该如何酬谢你？”

“你已经酬谢过我了！”夜莺说，“第一次歌唱的时候，我已从你的眼里唱出了泪珠，我将永生不忘！那些泪珠是珍宝，让歌唱的心受益匪浅。但现在快睡吧，变得健康强壮起来！我会为你歌唱！”

于是它唱了起来——而皇帝就这么进入了甜美的梦乡，温柔而祥和！

他醒来时感觉强健而康明，阳光从窗口洒进来，照耀着他；他的侍从一个都还没有来，因为他们以为，他死了。但夜莺仍在那里唱着歌。

“你要永远和朕在一起！”皇帝说，“只有你想唱的时候才需要唱，那只人造鸟朕要把它摔成碎片。”

“别这样！”夜莺说，“它已经尽力了！永远留着它吧！我无法在宫中安家定居，但让我想来的时候就来吧，那样我就会在傍晚停在窗边的树枝上，为你歌唱，这样你就会快乐并格外地深思，我将歌唱那些幸福的人以及那些煎熬的人！我将歌唱善与恶，它们就隐藏在你的周围。我这唱歌的小鸟还要到处飞翔，去找贫穷的渔夫，去农家的屋顶，去每个远离你和你宫殿的地方。我爱你的心远胜于你的皇冠，然而皇冠本身也有某种神圣的气息！——我会前来为你歌唱！——但有一件事你必须向我承诺。”

“任何事！”皇帝说，他亲自穿上自己的龙袍站在那儿，手持沉重而闪耀的金剑抵住自己的心口。

“我只求你一件事！别告诉任何人你有一只会把什么都告诉你的小鸟，这样一切都会变得更美好。”

然后夜莺就飞走了。

侍从们进来想为他们死去的皇帝善后——他们就这么站在那儿，而皇帝却说：“早上好！”

红鞋

有个小女孩，既可爱又漂亮，但一到夏天她就不得不到哪儿都打着赤脚，因为她很穷。冬天她穿一双大木鞋，小脚背都红了，看着挺吓人。

村子的正中央住着年迈的鞋匠姥姥，她坐在那儿穿针引线，竭尽全力，用旧红布条缝出了一双小鞋，很笨拙，但很用心，这双鞋就是给那个小女孩的。小姑娘名叫卡伦。

就在她的母亲下葬的那天，她得到了那双红鞋并第一次穿上了它们；这双鞋哀悼的时候穿的确不合时宜，但她也没有别的鞋子可穿，于是她就光着脚穿着它们，跟在一口简陋的稻草棺材后面走。

这时突然出现了一辆高大的老爷车，里面坐着一位高大的老妇人，她看着这个小姑娘，心里非常地怜惜，于是就对牧师说：“听着，把这个小姑娘给我吧，我会好好待她的！”

卡伦以为这都是因为那双红鞋，但老妇人却说它们太丑了，于是就把鞋烧了。但卡伦自己却穿上了干净得体的衣服；她必须学习读书和缝纫，大家都说她很漂亮。但她的镜子说：“你岂止是漂亮，你美极了！”

有一次王后周游全国，随行的还有她的小女儿，也就是公主，人们蜂拥来到城堡门外，其中就有卡伦，小公主穿一身精致的白衣服，站在窗子里给大家欣赏；她既没有拖着长长的裙摆，也没有戴金冠，但穿着一双美丽的红色萨非皮鞋；它们确实比鞋匠姥姥为小卡伦缝的鞋好看得多。世上没有什么东西能和红鞋相提并论！

现在卡伦长大了，要参加成人礼，她得到了新衣服，还有新鞋子。城里有钱的鞋匠为她的小脚丫量了尺寸，是在他自己家的客厅里量的，厅里立着大玻璃柜，里面摆着迷人的鞋子和光鲜的靴子。那儿看上去很漂亮，但老妇人眼神不好，所以也受用不到。在这些鞋子中间有一双红鞋，像极了公主穿的那双，真是美极了！鞋匠也说这双鞋是为一位伯爵的女儿缝的，但鞋不合脚。

“一定是打光革的！”老妇人说，“好亮！”

“是的，好亮！”卡伦说。鞋子很合脚，于是她们就买了下来；但老妇人并不知道鞋是红色的，不然她决不会让卡伦穿着红鞋参加成人礼，但是她还是这么去了。

所有人都看着她的脚，当她穿过教堂的大厅走向诗班席大门的时候，她觉得就连墓碑上的古画——那些戴着硬邦邦的襞襟穿着黑色长袍的牧师和牧师夫人的肖像，都把目光锁定在她的红鞋上。牧师把手搭在她的头上，讲述神圣的洗礼，对上帝的誓约，说她已经是成年的基督徒，但哪怕这个时候，她想的还是那双鞋；风琴演奏的音乐如此庄严，优美的童声在唱，年迈的领唱也在唱，但卡伦想的只有那双红鞋。

下午连那个老妇人都知道鞋是红色的，她说这太糟糕，太不合时宜，卡伦从此以后去教堂都必须穿黑色的鞋子，哪怕是旧鞋。

下一个星期日是圣餐礼，卡伦看了看那双黑鞋，又看了看那双红鞋——然后她又看了看红鞋，拿起来穿在了脚上。

那天阳光明媚，卡伦和老妇人穿过田间小径，灰尘弥漫。

教堂门口站着一个老兵，拄着一根拐杖，留着一把奇怪的长胡子，胡子的颜色比白色要红，因为它就是红色的；他深深地鞠了个躬，脑袋几乎着了地，并问老妇人他能不能擦擦她的鞋。卡伦也把她的小脚伸了出来。“瞧，多美丽的舞鞋啊！”士兵说，“你跳舞的时候鞋也穿得牢！”说着他用手敲敲鞋底。

老妇人给士兵一个小铜币，然后带着卡伦走进教堂。

教堂里所有人都看着卡伦的红鞋，所有的画像也都在看着它们，当卡伦跪在圣坛前，把圣杯端到嘴边的时候，她想的只有她的红鞋，就像它们在圣杯中为了她游来荡去；她忘了唱赞美诗，她忘了念“亲爱的圣父”。

之后大家都走出教堂，老妇人迈进她的马车。卡伦跟在后面抬起脚，这时那个站在她们身旁的老兵说：“瞧，多美丽的舞鞋啊！”卡伦忍不住想跳几个舞步，她一开始跳起来，双腿就停不下来，就像这双鞋控制了它们；她绕着教堂一角跳了一圈，她忍不住；车夫不得不跟在她身后，跑过来一把抓住她，把她抱进马车里，但她的脚仍在舞蹈，结果她狠狠地踢了那位好心的老妇人。最后他们终于脱下了她的鞋，腿才恢复平静。

回家后，这双鞋放进了柜子里，但卡伦还是忍不住想看看它们。

后来老妇人病倒了，大家都说她将不久于人世！她需要有人照顾护理，她身边没有比卡伦更亲近的人了。但正巧城里举行盛大的舞会，也邀请了卡伦。她看了看那位老妇人，反正她将不久于人世，她又看了看那双红鞋，觉得看看也不算什么罪孽。她穿上这双红鞋，穿穿总可以吧。然而她还是去参加了舞会，并且又开始跳舞。

但她想往右，鞋偏跳向左，她想向前，鞋却偏跳向后，下楼，穿过大街，出城门。她跳着舞，不得不跳着舞，一直跳到黑暗的森林里。

树丛中亮起一束光，她以为那是月亮，因为她看到一张脸，但那是那个红胡子老兵，他坐在那儿点着头说：“瞧，多美丽的舞鞋啊！”

她害怕起来，想把红鞋扔掉，但它们紧紧地箍着她的脚，她扯下了她的袜子，但鞋已经长在了她的脚上。她跳着舞，不得不跳舞，穿过田野和草坪，无论雨淋还是日晒，无论黑夜还是白昼，而黑夜是最可怕的。

她跳进一座开放的墓园，不过那儿的亡灵不跳舞，他们有比跳舞更重要的事要做；她想在一座长满苦涩菊蒿的陋坟上坐一下，但她根本不得安宁，于是她跳到敞开着的教堂门口，在那儿她看到一位身穿白色长袍的天使。他的翅膀一直从肩膀拖到地上，他的表情庄重而严肃，他手中持着一把宽宽的剑。

“你要跳舞！”他说，“穿着你的红鞋跳舞，直到你变得苍白冰冷！直到你的肌肤萎缩，把你变成一具骨架。你要从一户人家跳到另一户人家，那些家里住着傲慢可恶的孩子，你要敲他们的门，让他们听到你的声音并怕你！你要跳舞，跳舞——！”

“宽恕我！”卡伦喊道。但她没有听到天使的回答，因为鞋把她带出了门，带到田野上，穿过大路，穿过小径，她得一直跳舞。

一天早晨她跳过一扇门，她很熟悉的门；里面传出赞美诗来，人们抬出一口棺材，上面装饰着花朵；这时她才知道老妇人死了，她觉得自己已经被所有人遗弃并受到了上帝天使的诅咒。

她跳着舞，不得不跳着舞，在漆黑的夜里跳着舞。鞋带着她穿过满是荆棘和木桩的地方，把她扎出了血；她跳着舞穿过荒地来到一座孤零零的小屋跟前。她知道那个刽子手住在这儿，她用手指敲着玻璃窗上说：“出来！——出来！——我进不来，因为我在跳舞！”

刽子手说：“你难道不知道我是谁？我会砍掉恶人的脑袋，我能感觉到我的斧子已经在颤动了！”

“别砍我的头，”卡伦说，“因为这样我就不能忏悔我的罪过了。但把我的脚砍掉吧，连我的鞋一起！”

于是她坦白了自己所有的罪孽，刽子手砍下了她穿着红鞋的脚，但鞋带着她的小脚跳着舞穿过田野，跳进了茂密的森林深处。

他为她削了一双木脚和一副拐杖，还教给她一首罪人常唱的赞美诗，她吻了那只握斧子的手，然后穿过荒地而去。

“我已经受够了那双红鞋的折磨！”她说，“现在我要去教堂，让大家看看我！”于是她飞快地走向教堂大门，但她到那儿的时候，红鞋就在她面前跳舞，她吓坏了，只得转身离开。

整个星期她都很悲伤，流了许多沉重的眼泪，但星期天到来的时候，她说：“看吧，我已经受尽折磨竭尽全力！我觉得，我已经和那些昂首坐在教堂里的人一样善良了！”于是她勇敢地去了；但她还是只走到门口，她又看到那双红鞋在面前跳舞，她吓坏了，转过身，并打心底忏悔起她的罪过。

她走到牧师家，请求在那里服务，她会勤勤恳恳地工作，做所有力所能及的事，她无所谓报酬，只求有一个安身之处，有好人为伴。牧师夫人可怜她，收留了她。她的确很勤恳也很用心。晚上牧师朗读《圣经》的时候，她就静静地坐下来听。所有孩子都很喜欢她，但他们说起装饰、城市，以及她像皇后一样美丽的时候，她就摇头。

接下来的星期天，一家人都要去教堂，他们问她愿不愿意一起去，但她噙着眼泪，悲伤地看着她的拐杖，于是其他人都去听上帝的训诫，而她独自走进自己的小房间；地方不大，只够放一张床和一把椅子。她坐下拿起自己的赞美诗；无比虔诚地读起来，随风传来教堂的管风琴声，她抬起头，泪流满面地说：“哦，上帝，救救我！”

阳光如此明媚地照耀着，她的面前出现了上帝的白衣天使，就是那天晚上她在教堂门口见到的那位，但他手中拿着的不再是锋利的剑，而是开满玫瑰的绿枝，他用它触碰了一下天花板，天花板就高高地升了起来，凡是他触碰过的地方，都会有一颗金色的星星在闪烁，他触碰了一下墙壁，墙壁就延展开来，她看到了演奏着的管风琴，她看到了画有牧师和牧师夫人的古画；人们坐在装饰过的座位上，唱着他们的赞美诗。要不是教堂为可怜的小女孩来到这逼仄的小房间里，就是她已经进了教堂；她和牧师家的其他人一起坐在座位上，当他们唱完赞美诗抬起头的时候，他们点点头说：“你来对了，卡伦！”

“这是上帝的恩典！”她说。

风琴鸣响，童声合唱如此温柔优美。明媚的阳光温暖地透过窗户洒在卡伦坐着的教堂长椅上；她的心被阳光、平和与欢乐充盈，直至破碎；她的灵魂顺着阳光飞向上帝，在天堂再也没人问起那双红鞋。

The T inderbox

A soldier came marching along the road: left, right! left, right! He had his knapsack on his back and a sword at his side, because he had been off to war, and now he was on his way home. Then he met an old witch on the road. She was so hideous, her lower lip hung all the way down to her breast. She said, ‘Good evening, soldier. What a nice sword and big knapsack you have – you must be a real soldier! Now you shall have all the money you could ask for!’

‘Well, thanks a lot, you old witch,’ said the soldier.

‘Do you see that big tree?’ said the witch, pointing at a tree right next to them. ‘It’s completely hollow inside. Climb up to the top and you’ll find a hole that you can slip into and slide all the way down inside the tree. I’ll tie a rope around your waist so I can hoist you back up when you call me.’

‘Why would I go inside that tree?’ asked the soldier.

‘To get the money!’ said the witch. ‘You see, when you reach the bottom of the tree, you’ll be in a huge passageway that’s very bright because it’s lit by more than a hundred lamps. Then you’ll see three doors, and you’ll be able to open them because the keys are in the locks. If you go inside the first chamber you’ll see a big chest in the middle of the room, and on top of it sits a dog. He has eyes as big as a pair of teacups, but never mind that. I’ll give you my blue- checked apron that you can spread on the floor. Go right over and pick up the dog and set him on my apron. Then open the chest and take as many skillings as you like. They’re all made of copper, but if you’d rather have silver, then go into the next room. In there is a dog with eyes as big as a pair of mill wheels, but never mind that. Set him on my apron and take the money. But if it’s gold you want, you can have that too, and as much as you can carry, if you go into the third chamber. But the dog sitting on the money chest has two eyes that are each as big as the Round Tower. Now that’s a real dog, believe me! But never you mind. Just set him on my apron and he won’t harm you. Then take from the chest as much gold as you like.’

‘Not bad,’ said the soldier. ‘But what do I have to give you in return, you old witch? Because I imagine there must be something you want.’

‘No,’ said the witch, ‘I don’t want a single skilling. All you have to bring me is an old tinderbox that my grandmother left behind when she was down there last.’

‘Fine. Then let’s have that rope around my waist,’ said the soldier.

‘Here it is,’ said the witch. ‘And here is my blue- checked apron.’

So the soldier climbed up the tree, tumbled down the hole, and then, just as the witch had said, he stood inside the huge passageway where hundreds of lamps were burning.

He opened the first door. Ooh! There sat the dog with eyes as big as teacups, staring at him.

‘You’re a handsome fellow!’ said the soldier and set him on the witch’s apron. Then he took as many copper skillings as his pockets would hold, closed the chest, put the dog back, and went into the second room. Eeek! There sat the dog with eyes as big as mill wheels.

‘You shouldn’t look at me so hard,’ said the soldier. ‘You might hurt your eyes!’ And then he set the dog on the witch’s apron, but when he saw all the silver coins inside the chest he threw away the copper coins he was carrying and filled his pockets and his knapsack with nothing but silver. Next he went into the third chamber. Oh, how hideous! The dog in there really did have eyes as big as round towers, and they were spinning around in his head like wheels.

‘Good evening,’ said the soldier and doffed his cap, for he had never seen a dog like that before. But after he’d looked at him for a while, he thought to himself, ‘All right, that’s enough.’ And he lifted him onto the floor and opened the chest. Good Lord, there was a lot of gold! Enough to buy all of Copenhagen and every single sugar- pig sold by the cake- wives, and all the tin soldiers, whips, and rocking horses in the whole world! Yes, there was certainly plenty of money! So the soldier threw away all the silver coins that filled his pockets and knapsack and took the gold instead. Yes, all his pockets, his knapsack, his cap, and his boots were so full that he could hardly walk. Now he had money! He put the dog back on the chest, slammed the door shut, and called up through the tree:

‘Hoist me up now, you old witch!’

‘Do you have the tinderbox?’ asked the witch.

‘Oh, that’s right,’ said the soldier. ‘I forgot all about it.’And he went over and picked it up. The witch hoisted him up and he once again stood on the road, with his pockets, boots, knapsack, and cap full of money.

‘What do you want the tinderbox for?’ asked the soldier.

‘That’s none of your business,’ said the witch. ‘You’ve got the money. Now just give me the tinderbox.’

‘Pish posh!’ said the soldier. ‘Tell me right now what you want it for or I’ll pull out my sword and chop off your head!’

‘No,’ said the witch.

So the soldier chopped off her head. There she lay! But he wrapped up all his money in her apron, slung it in a bundle over his shoulder, stuffed the tinderbox in his pocket, and headed straight for the city.

It was a lovely city, and he went inside the loveliest of inns and demanded the very best rooms and his favorite food, because now he had so much money that he was rich.

The servant who was supposed to polish his boots thought they were rather strange old boots for such a rich gentleman to be wearing, but he hadn’t yet bought himself new ones. By the next day he had a good pair of boots and fine clothes to wear. The soldier was now a distinguished gentleman, and the people told him about all the splendid things to be found in their city, and about their king and what a charming princess his daughter was.

‘Where might I catch a glimpse of her?’ asked the soldier.

‘It’s impossible to catch a glimpse of her,’ they all said.‘She lives in an enormous copper palace surrounded by dozens of walls and towers. No one but the king dares visit her, because it was foretold that she would marry a simple soldier, and that certainly did not please the king.’

‘She’s someone I’d like to see,’ thought the soldier, but that wasn’t possible.

He was now leading a merry life, going to the theater, taking drives in the king’s gardens, and giving away a great deal of money to the poor, which was a very nice gesture. No doubt he remembered from the old days how miserable it was not to have even a skilling. He was now rich and wore fine clothes, and had so many friends who all said that he was a pleasant fellow, a real gentleman, and that certainly pleased the soldier. But since he was spending money each day and not taking any in, he finally had no more than two skillings left and had to move out of the beautiful rooms where he had been living and into a tiny little garret room right under the roof. He had to brush his own boots and mend them with a darning needle, and none of his friends came to see him because there were too many stairs to climb.

It was a very dark evening, and he couldn’t even afford to buy a candle, but then he remembered there was a little stump of one in the tinderbox he had taken from the hollow tree when the witch had helped him inside. He took out the tinderbox and the candle stump, but the minute he struck fire and sparks leaped from the flint, the door flew open and the dog that he had seen inside the tree, the one with eyes as big as two teacups, stood before him and said, ‘What is my master’s command?’

‘What’s this?’ said the soldier. ‘What an amusing tinderbox, if I can wish for whatever I want! Bring me some money,’ he said to the dog, and zip, he was gone; zip, he was back, holding a big sack of skillings in his mouth.

Now the soldier realized what a wonderful tinderbox it was. If he stuck it once, the dog who sat on the chest of copper coins came; if he struck it twice, the one with the silver coins came; and if he struck it three times, the one with the gold came. Now the soldier moved back downstairs to the beautiful rooms, dressed in fine clothing, and all his friends recognized him again, because they were so fond of him.

One day he thought, ‘How odd that no one is allowed to see that princess. Everyone says she’s supposed to be so lovely. But what good is it if she’s always kept inside that enormous copper palace with all the towers? Couldn’t I possibly have a look at her? Where’s my tinderbox?’ And then he struck fire and zip, the dog with eyes as big as teacups appeared.

‘I know it’s the middle of the night,’ said the soldier, ‘but I have such a great desire to see the princess, if only for a moment.’

The dog was out the door at once, and before the soldier knew it, he was back with the princess. She was sitting on the dog’s back, asleep, and she was so lovely that anyone could see she was a real princess. The soldier couldn’t resist, he had to kiss her, because he was a real soldier.

Then the dog ran back with the princess, but when morning came and the king and queen were pouring their tea, the princess said that she’d had a strange dream in the night about a dog and a soldier. She was riding on the dog’s back, and the soldier had kissed her.

‘That’s certainly a fine story!’ said the queen.

One of the old ladies- in- waiting was then ordered to keep watch at the bedside of the princess on the following night, to see if it was really a dream, or what else it might be.

The soldier was longing terribly to see the lovely princess once more, so the dog appeared in the night, picked her up, and ran as fast as he could, but the old lady- in- waiting put on her wading boots and ran just as swiftly right behind. When she saw them disappear inside a large building, she thought to herself: Now I know where it is. And with a piece of chalk she drew a big cross on the door. Then she returned home and went to bed, and the dog came back too, bringing the princess. But when he saw that a cross had been drawn on the door where the soldier lived, he took another piece of chalk and put a cross on all the doors in the whole city. That was a clever thing to do, because now the lady- in- waiting wouldn’t be able to find the right door, since there were crosses on all of them.

Early the next morning the king and queen, the old lady- in- waiting, and all the officers went out to see where the princess had been.

‘There it is!’ said the king when he saw the first door with a cross on it.

‘No, it’s over there, my dear husband,’ said the queen, who saw another door with a cross on it.

‘But there’s one there, and one there!’ they all said. Wherever they looked, there was a cross on every door. Then they realized it was no use to go on searching.

But the queen was a very clever woman who was capable of more than just riding around in a coach. She took her big golden scissors, cut a large piece of silk into pieces, and then stitched together a charming little pouch, which she filled with fine grains of buckwheat. She tied it to the back of the princess, and when that was done, she cut a tiny hole in the pouch so the grains would sprinkle out wherever the princess went.

That night the dog appeared once again, put the princess on his back, and ran off with her to the soldier, who loved her so much and wanted dearly to be a prince so that he could make her his wife.

The dog didn’t notice the grain sprinkling out all the way from the palace to the soldier’s window, as he ran along the wall, carrying the princess. In the morning the king and queen could see quite well where their daughter had been, and they seized the soldier and threw him into jail.

And there he sat. Oh, how dark and dreary it was, and then they told him, ‘Tomorrow you will hang.’ That was not a pleasant thing to hear, and he had left his tinderbox behind at the inn. In the morning he could see through the iron bars on the little window that people were hurrying to the outskirts of the city to watch him hang. He heard the drums and saw the marching soldiers. Everyone was in a great rush, including a shoemaker’s apprentice wearing a leather apron and slippers. He was moving along at such a gallop that one of his slippers flew off and struck the wall right where the soldier was sitting, peering out through the iron bars.

‘Hey, shoemaker’s apprentice! You don’t have to be in such a rush,’ said the soldier. ‘Nothing’s going to happen until I get there. But if you run over to the place where I was staying and bring me my tinderbox, I’ll give you four skillings. But you have to be quick about it!’ The shoemaker’s apprentice wanted those four skillings, so he raced off to get the tinderbox, brought it to the soldier, and . . . well, let’s hear what happened.

Outside the city a huge gallows had been built, and around it stood the soldiers and many hundreds of thousands of people. The king and queen sat on a lovely throne right across from the judge and the entire council.

The soldier was already standing on the ladder, but as they were about to put the rope around his neck, he said that before a sinner faced his punishment he was always allowed one harmless request. He dearly wanted to smoke a pipe of tobacco; it would be the last pipe he had in this world.

Now, that was not something the king could refuse, and so the soldier took out his tinderbox and struck fire, one, two, three! And there stood all three dogs: the one with eyes as big as teacups, the one with eyes like mill wheels, and the one with eyes as big as the Round Tower.

‘Help me now, so I won’t be hanged!’ said the soldier, and then the dogs rushed at the judge and the entire council, seizing one by the leg and one by the nose, and flinging them high into the air so they fell back down and were crushed to bits.

‘Not me!’ said the king, but the biggest dog seized both him and the queen and tossed them after all the others. Then the soldiers were afraid, and all the people shouted, ‘Little soldier, you shall be our king and wed the lovely princess!’

They put the soldier in the king’s coach, and all three dogs danced before it, shouting, ‘Hurrah!’ The boys whistled through their fingers, and the soldiers presented arms. The princess came out of the copper palace and became queen, and that certainly pleased her! The wedding celebration lasted for a week, and the dogs sat at the table too, making big eyes.

Little Claus and Big Claus

There was a town where two men had the very same name. Both of them were named Claus, but one owned four horses while the other had only one. In order to tell them apart, people called the man with four horses Big Claus, and the man with only one horse Little Claus. Now we’re going to hear what happened between those two, because this is a real story!

All week long Little Claus had to do the plowing for Big Claus, lending him his only horse. Then Big Claus would help him in return with all four of his horses, but only once a week, and that was on Sunday. Hee- ya! How Little Claus would crack his whip at all five horses. They might as well have belonged to him on that one day. The sun shone so wondrously, and all the bells in the tower rang, summoning people to church. Everyone was dressed in their best, walking with their hymnals under their arms, on their way to hear the pastor preach. And they looked at Little Claus, who was plowing with five horses, and he was so pleased that he cracked his whip again and shouted, ‘ Giddy- up, all my horses!’

‘You shouldn’t say that,’ said Big Claus. ‘Only one of those horses is yours.’

But when someone else passed by on his way to church, Little Claus forgot that he wasn’t supposed to say that and he shouted, ‘ Giddy- up, all my horses!’

‘All right, now I really must ask you to stop that,’ said Big Claus. ‘Because if you say it one more time, I’m going to strike your horse on the forehead, and he’ll drop dead on the spot, and that will be the end of him.’

‘Well, I certainly won’t say it again,’ said Little Claus, but when people came past and nodded hello, he was so pleased and thought it looked so splendid that he had five horses plowing his field that he cracked his whip and shouted,‘ Giddy- up, all my horses!’

‘I’ll giddy- up your horses!’ said Big Claus, and he seized the tethering mallet and struck Little Claus’s only horse on the forehead so that it fell to the ground, stone dead.

‘Oh no, now I have no horse at all!’ said Little Claus and began to cry. Later he flayed the horse and let the hide dry in the wind. Then he stuffed it in a sack that he hoisted onto his back and set off for town to sell his horsehide.

He had such a long way to go. He had to pass through a big, dark forest, and a terrible storm came up. He completely lost his way, and before he found the right road, dusk had fallen, and it was much too far to reach town or to go back home before night came.

Close to the road stood a large farm. The shutters on all the windows were closed, and yet there was a glimpse of light above. Surely they’ll let me spend the night here, thought Little Claus, and he went over and knocked.

The farmer’s wife opened the door, but when she heard what he wanted, she told him to keep on going. Her husband wasn’t home, and she didn’t take in strangers.

‘Well, then I guess I’ll have to sleep outside,’ said Little Claus, and the farmer’s wife shut the door in his face.

Nearby stood a big haystack, and between the haystack and house a little shed had been built with a flat, thatched roof.

‘I can sleep up there,’ said Little Claus when he saw the roof. ‘That would make a lovely bed, and I’m sure the stork isn’t going to fly down and bite me on the leg.’ A real live stork was standing on the roof, where it had made a nest.

So Little Claus climbed up onto the shed, lay down, and turned onto his side to settle in properly. The wooden shutters on the windows of the house didn’t quite meet at the top, which meant that he could peek into the room.

A great feast had been laid out with wine and a roast and such a lovely fish. The farmer’s wife and the deacon were sitting at the table, all alone. She was pouring wine for him, and he began with the fish, because he was awfully fond of fish.

‘If only I could have a bite too,’ said Little Claus, craning his neck toward the window. Lord, what a lovely cake he could see in there. Oh yes, it was quite a feast.

Then he heard someone come riding along the road toward the house. It was the woman’s husband, on his way home.

Now, it’s true that he was a good man, but he had a strange affliction: He couldn’t stand to see deacons. If he caught sight of a deacon, he would grow quite furious. That was also why the deacon had come to visit the woman when he knew that her husband wasn’t home, and that’s why the good woman had set out for him the best food she could offer. When they heard her husband coming, they were both terrified. The woman told the deacon to climb into a big empty chest that stood in the corner, which he did, because he knew full well that the poor man couldn’t stand the sight of a deacon. The woman quickly hid all the wonderful food and wine inside her baking oven, because if her husband saw it, he was sure to ask what was going on.

‘Oh no!’ sighed Little Claus up on the shed when he saw all the food disappear.

‘Is somebody up there?’ asked the farmer, peering up at Little Claus. ‘Why are you lying up there? Come on into the house!’

Then Little Claus told him how he had lost his way and asked if he might stay the night.

‘Yes, of course,’ said the farmer. ‘But first we’ll have a bite to eat.’

The woman welcomed them both, set dishes on a long table, and brought them a big bowl of porridge. The farmer was hungry and ate with gusto, but Little Claus couldn’t help thinking about the wonderful roast, fish, and cake that he knew were hidden in the oven.

Under the table at his feet he had put the sack with the horsehide in it, because we know, after all, that this was what he had brought from home to sell in town. The porridge was not at all to his liking, and so he stepped on his sack, and the dry horsehide inside creaked quite loudly.

‘Hush!’ said Little Claus to his sack, but at the same instant he stepped on it again, and it creaked even louder than before.

‘Tell me, what do you have in your bag?’ asked the farmer.

‘Oh, it’s a troll,’ said Little Claus. ‘He says we shouldn’t eat the porridge because he has conjured a whole oven full of roast and fish and cake.’

‘Is that right?’ said the farmer and quickly opened the oven. There he saw all the wonderful food that his wife had hidden, but he now thought the troll in the bag had conjured it up. His wife didn’t dare say a word but set the food on the table at once, and so they ate the fish and the roast and the cake. Then Little Claus stepped on his sack again, making the hide creak.

‘What’s he saying now?’ asked the farmer.

‘He says,’ said Little Claus, ‘that he has also conjured up three bottles of wine for us, and they’re standing over in the corner by the oven.’ Then the woman had to bring out the wine she had hidden, and the farmer drank and grew quite merry. A troll like the one that Little Claus had in his bag was something that he would certainly like to own.

‘Can he also conjure up the Devil?’ asked the farmer.‘That’s someone I’d really like to see, now that I’m feeling so merry.’

‘Yes,’ said Little Claus, ‘my troll can do anything I ask. Isn’t that right?’ he said as he stepped on the bag, making it creak. ‘Did you hear him say yes? But the Devil looks so horrid that you wouldn’t want to look at him.’

‘Oh, I’m not the least bit afraid. How bad do you think he could look?’

‘Well, he’s going to look exactly like a deacon.’

‘Whoa!’ said the farmer. ‘That’s ghastly, all right. I must tell you that I can’t stand the sight of deacons. But that doesn’t matter, because I’ll know it’s the Devil, so it won’t bother me as much. I’m feeling brave now. But don’t let him come too close.’

‘Let me ask my troll,’ said Little Claus, and he stepped on the bag, cupping his ear.

‘What does he say?’

‘He says that you can go over and open the chest that’s standing in the corner, and you’ll see the Devil moping inside, but you have to hold on to the lid so he doesn’t get out.’

‘Come and help me hold on to it,’ said the farmer, and he went over to the chest where his wife had hidden the real deacon, who sat there completely terrified.

The farmer lifted the lid slightly and peeked inside.‘Whoa!’ he yelled, jumping back. ‘I saw him all right, and he looks just like our deacon! Oh, that was terrible!’

After that they had to have a drink, and then they kept on drinking until late into the night.

‘You’ve got to sell me that troll,’ said the farmer. ‘Ask whatever price you like. Why, I’d even give you a whole bushelful of money!’

‘No, I can’t do that,’ that Claus. ‘Just think how much I’ll gain from owning this troll.’

‘Oh, but I’d certainly like to have it,’ said the farmer, and he kept on begging.

‘All right,’ said Little Claus at last. ‘Since you’ve been kind enough to give me shelter for the night, I can’t refuse. You can have the troll for a bushel of money, but I want the bushel to be full to the brim.’

‘And that’s what you’ll get,’ said the farmer, ‘but you have to take that chest over there with you. I refuse to have it in the house for even an hour longer. There’s no telling whether he’s still inside.’

Little Claus gave the farmer the sack with the dried horsehide and got in return a whole bushel of money, full to the brim. The farmer even presented him with a big wheelbarrow for carrying the money and the chest.

‘Farewell!’ said Little Claus, and then he set off with his money and the big chest in which the deacon was still sitting.

On the other side of the woods was a big, deep river. The water was running so fast that it was almost impossible to swim against the current. A big new bridge had been built across it. Little Claus stopped in the middle of the bridge and said very loudly so that the deacon inside the chest would hear him:

‘Well, what do I need this stupid chest for? It’s so heavy it feels like it’s full of rocks. I’m getting awfully tired of carting it around, so I think I’ll throw it in the river. If it floats home to me, that’s fine, but if it doesn’t, it won’t matter at all.’

Then he grabbed one handle of the chest and lifted it slightly, as if he were going to shove it into the water.

‘No, stop!’ yelled the deacon inside the chest. ‘Let me out!’

‘Ooh!’ said Little Claus, pretending to be scared. ‘He’s still inside! I’ve got to toss it in the river as quick as I can so he’ll drown.’

‘Oh no, oh no!’ shouted the deacon. ‘I’ll give you a whole bushelful of money if you don’t.’

‘Well, that’s a different story,’ said Little Claus, and opened the chest. The deacon crawled out at once, shoved the empty chest into the water, and went off to his house, where he gave Little Claus a whole bushelful of money. Little Claus already had one bushel from the farmer; now his whole wheelbarrow was full of money.

‘Look at that, I certainly did get a good price for that horse,’ he said to himself when he came back to his own house and dumped all the money in a big heap in the middle of the floor. ‘Big Claus will be annoyed when he finds out how rich I’ve become from my only horse, but I’m not going to come right out and tell him about it.’

Then he sent a boy over to Big Claus to borrow a bushel measure.

‘I wonder what he wants it for,’ thought Big Claus, and smeared tar inside the bottom so that a little of whatever was being weighed would stick to it. And it did, because when he got the bushel measure back, there were three new silver eight- skilling coins stuck to it.

‘What’s this?’ said Big Claus and ran right over to see Little Claus. ‘Where did you get all this money?’

‘Oh, I got it for my horsehide. I sold it last night.’

‘That was certainly a good price!’ said Big Claus, and he raced back home, picked up an ax, and struck every one of his four horses on the forehead. Then he skinned them and drove into town with the hides.

‘Hides! Hides! Who wants to buy hides?’ he shouted through the streets.

All the shoemakers and tanners came running and asked him how much he wanted for the hides.

‘A bushel of money for each of them,’ said Big Claus.

‘Are you crazy?’ they all said. ‘Do you think we have bushels of money?’

‘Hides, hides! Who wants to buy hides?’ he shouted again, but to everyone who asked how much the hides cost, he replied, ‘A bushel of money.’

‘He’s trying to make fools of us,’ they all said. Then the shoemakers picked up their straps and the tanners their leather aprons, and they all started beating Big Claus.

‘Hides, hides!’ they jeered at him. ‘Oh yes, we’ll give you a hide that bleeds like a pig! Now get out of town!’ they shouted, and Big Claus had to rush off as fast as he could. He had never been beaten so badly in his life.

‘Well!’ he said when he got home. ‘Little Claus is going to pay for this. I’m going to murder him for this!’

But back at Little Claus’s house his grandmother had just died. Now, it’s true that she had been terribly ill- tempered and mean toward him, but even so he was quite sad. He took the dead woman and put her in his warm bed to see whether she might come back to life. There she would lie all night long while he slept in the corner, sitting on a chair; that was something he had done before.

As he was sitting there that night, the door opened and Big Claus came in with an ax. He knew where Little Claus’s bed stood, and he went right over a struck the dead grandmother on the forehead, thinking that it was Little Claus.

‘Take that!’ he said. ‘Now you won’t make a fool of me anymore.’ And then he went back home.

‘What a mean and evil man,’ said Little Claus. ‘He wanted to murder me, but it’s a good thing the old lady was already dead, or he would have taken her life.’

Then he dressed his old grandmother in her Sunday best, borrowed a horse from his neighbor, harnessed it to his wagon, and put his old grandmother on the back seat so that she wouldn’t fall out when he started driving. Then they headed off through the woods. When the sun came up, they were outside a big inn, where Little Claus stopped and went inside to get a bite to eat.

The innkeeper was very, very rich, and he was also a good man, but hot- tempered, as if there were pepper and tobacco inside of him.

‘Good morning,’ he said to Little Claus. ‘You’ve put on your fine clothes awfully early today.’

‘Yes,’ said Little Claus, ‘I’m going to town with my old grandmother. She’s sitting outside in the wagon, and I can’t get her to come indoors. Would you mind taking her a glass of mead? But you’ll have to speak up because she doesn’t hear very well.’

‘Why, certainly,’ said the innkeeper. He poured a big glass of mead and took it outside to the dead grandmother, who was propped up in the wagon.

‘Here’s a glass of mead from your grandson,’ said the innkeeper, but the dead woman didn’t say a word, just sat there without moving.

‘Didn’t you hear me?’ shouted the innkeeper as loud as he could. ‘Here’s a glass of mead from your grandson!’

Once again he shouted the same thing, and then one more time, but when she didn’t budge in the slightest, he got angry and tossed the glass of mead right in her face so it ran down her nose. And she toppled over backward into the wagon, because she had merely been propped up but wasn’t tied down.

‘What’s this?’ shouted Little Claus as he came running out the door and grabbed the innkeeper by the shirtfront.‘You’ve gone and killed my grandmother! Just look at that big hole in her forehead!’

‘Oh, what bad luck!’ cried the innkeeper, wringing his hands. ‘It’s all the fault of my bad temper. Dear Little Claus, I’ll give you a whole bushelful of money and pay for your grandmother’s burial as if she were my own, but don’t say a word or they’ll chop off my head, and that would be awful!’

So Little Claus got a whole bushelful of money, and the innkeeper buried the old grandmother as if she were his own.

As soon as Little Claus got back home with all the money, he at once sent his boy over to see Big Claus, to ask if he could borrow a bushel measure.

‘What’s this?’ said Big Claus. ‘I thought I killed him! I’m going to have to see this for myself.’ And so he took the bushel measure over to Little Claus in person.

‘Where on earth did you get all that money?’ he asked, opening his eyes wide when he saw how much more Little Claus had accumulated.

‘It was my grandmother, not me that you killed,’ said Little Claus. ‘But now I’ve sold her for a bushelful of money.’

‘That was certainly a good price,’ said Big Claus, and he rushed home, picked up an ax, and promptly killed his old grandmother. He put her in his wagon, drove into town to the apothecary’s shop, and asked him whether he wanted to buy a dead body.

‘Who is it, and where did you get it?’ asked the apothecary.

‘It’s my grandmother,’ said Big Claus. ‘I’ve killed her for a bushelful of money.’

‘Good Lord!’ said the apothecary. ’You don’t know what you’re saying! Don’t say things like that or you could lose your head.’ And then he told him exactly what a dreadful, evil thing he had done, and what a bad person he was, and that he ought to be punished. Big Claus was so scared that he leaped straight from the apothecary’s shop into his wagon, cracked his whip at the horses, and raced off home. The apothecary and everyone else thought he was mad, and so they let him go where he liked.

‘You’re going to pay for this!’ said Big Claus when he was out on the road. ‘Oh yes, you’re going to pay for this, Little Claus!’ As soon as he got home he took the biggest sack he could find and went over to Little Claus and said, ‘You’ve made a fool of me again. First I killed my horses, and then my old grandmother. It’s all your fault, but you’re never going to trick me again.’ And he grabbed Little Claus around the waist and stuffed him into the sack. Then he slung him over his back and shouted, ‘Now I’m going to take you out and drown you!’

It was a long walk to reach the river, and Little Claus wasn’t easy to carry. The road passed very close to the church, where the organ was playing and people were singing so beautifully inside. Then Big Claus put down the sack holding Little Claus right next to the church door, thinking that it might do him good to go inside and listen to a hymn first, before continuing on his way. Little Claus couldn’t get out, and everyone else was in church, so Big Claus went inside.

‘Oh me, oh my!’ sighted Little Claus from inside the sack. He twisted and turned, but it was impossible for him to loosen the cord. At that moment an old, old cattle- driver with chalk- white hair and a big walking stick in his hand came by. He was driving a big herd of cows and bulls in front of him. They trampled over the sack that Claus was in, tumbling it onto its side.

‘Oh my,’ sighed Little Claus. ‘I’m so young, but I’m already headed for Heaven.’

‘And what a poor man am I,’ said the cattle- driver. ‘Here I am so old but it’s not yet my time to go.’

‘Open the sack!’ shouted Little Claus. ‘Climb in and take my place, and you’ll end up in Heaven at once.’

‘Oh, I’d like that very much,’ said the cattle- driver, untying the sack. And Little Claus jumped right out.

‘Could you take care of the cattle?’ said the old man, and he climbed into the bag, which Little Claus tied up and then went on his way, taking along the cows and bulls.

A little while later Big Claus came out of the church and hoisted the sack onto his back, thinking that it certainly was a lot lighter, because the old cattle- driver was no more than half the weight of Little Claus. ‘How easy it is to carry him now! Well, that’s probably because I’ve been listening to a hymn.’ Then he went over to the river, which was deep and wide, threw the sack with the old cattle- driver into the water, and shouted after him, thinking he was Little Claus, ‘Take that! Now you won’t be making a fool of me anymore!’

Then he headed home, but when he came to the crossroads, he met Little Claus walking along with all his cattle.

‘What’s this?’ said Big Claus. ‘Didn’t I drown you?’

‘Yes, you did,’ said Little Claus. ‘You threw me in the river less than half an hour ago.’

‘But where did you get all these wonderful cattle?’ asked Big Claus.

‘They’re sea cattle,’ said Little Claus. ‘Let me tell you the whole story. And by the way, thanks for drowning me, because now I’m back on my feet and let me tell you, I’m as rich as can be! I was so scared when I was inside that sack, and the wind whistled in my ears when you threw me off the bridge and into the cold water. I sank straight to the bottom, but I didn’t hurt myself because the loveliest soft grass grows down there. That’s where I landed, and the bag was opened at once. The loveliest maiden, wearing chalk- white clothing and with a green wreath on her wet hair, took my hand and said, “Is that you, Little Claus? Well, first let me give you these cattle. Five miles up the road there’s another whole herd that I want you to have.” Then I saw that the river was a great highway for the sea folk. Down on the bottom they were walking and driving all the way from the sea toward land, to the place where the river ends. It was so lovely with flowers and the freshest of grass, and fish swimming in the water; they flitted around my ears like the birds in the air. How handsome the people were and how many cattle there were, ambling along the ditches and fences.’

‘But why did you come back to us so soon?’ asked Big Claus. ‘That’s not what I would have done if it was so charming down there.’

‘Well, you see,’ said Little Claus, ‘it was really very cunning of me. You heard me say that the mermaid told me that five miles up the road – and by road she meant the river, of course, since she can’t travel any other way – there was a whole herd of cattle waiting for me. I happen to know where the river starts to bend, first one way and then the other, making a whole detour. It’s much shorter, if you can do it, to come up here on land and head straight across to the river. That way I saved almost two and a half miles and reached my sea cattle much quicker.’

‘Oh, you certainly are a lucky man!’ said Big Claus. ‘Do you think I could get some sea cattle too, if I went down to the bottom of the river?’

‘Oh yes, I imagine so,’ said Little Claus. ‘But I can’t carry you in a sack to the river; you’re much too heavy for me. But if you walk there yourself and then climb into the bag, I’d be more than happy to throw you in.’

‘Thanks so much,’ said Big Claus. ‘But if I don’t get any sea cattle when I get there, I’m going to give you a beating, believe you me!’

‘Oh no! Don’t be so mean!’ And then they went down to the river. The cattle were so thirsty that when they saw the water, they ran as fast as they could down the slope to drink.

‘Look how fast they’re moving,’ said Little Claus. ‘They’re longing to go back down to the bottom.’

‘Yes, but help me first,’ said Big Claus. ‘Otherwise I’ll give you a beating!’ And then he climbed into the big sack that was lying across the back of one of the bulls. ‘Put a rock inside, because otherwise I’m afraid I won’t sink,’ said Big Claus.

‘Oh, I’m sure you will,’ said Little Claus, but just the same, he put a big rock in the sack, tied the cord tight, and then gave it a shove. Plop! Big Claus landed in the river and promptly sank to the bottom.

‘I’m afraid he’s not going to find any cattle,’ said Little Claus, and then he headed home with all he had.